<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016).
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016). Towards A Critique 	Looking Backwards in the Venice Biennale 	From the magazine The Contemporary Condition, Issue 9 (September, 2015), p.3–6.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online art journal Stages and the co-editor of the forthcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA.</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016). Towards A Future City N. FernandesF. Pauling 	Toward a Future City: Developments in Urban Research.Part 1 What is Urbanization? 	The word ‘urban’ conjures up images of factories and roads and the urban landscape. Yet what is urban for most people living in large urban centres is actually managed and controlled by large private and non-governmental organisations (KAs). 	So what is urban for a city to become? 	Urban planners today tend to be either managers or experts in the field of urbanisation. 	The role of the planner today is to a large extent an administrative one. 	The role of the planner in the past was primarily one of observer and observer, observing the city from above, mapping its contours and structures and suggesting changes to the city ‘space-time continuum’ through his/her expert judgement. Today, planners have access to sophisticated destination-spotting and monitoring</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016).Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2020 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online art journal Stages and the co-editor of the forthcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016), Stages: Art, Architecture, Politics in Transition (MIT Press, 2005) and the forthcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society (MIT Press, 2018</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016).Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2020 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA. She has a special interest in the politics of art and the contemporary condition of migrant workers and urban dwellers. Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell and Geoffrey Walker 	Nadine Attewell is the co-curator of the 2020 Venice Biennale and a curator at the</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016).Stages 	Stages is the online journal of the Modern Language Association. The journal was founded in 2005 with the mission to reflect the cultural and social impacts of language research. In 2016, the group edited  	Stages: The End of Language. In 2017, it published an issue of Stages that reflected on the end of language. In This Issue, it publishes an excerpt from his new book Stages: The End of Language, to be published later this year. 	Next time you speak, or write, with someone new, ask him/her to remind you of something. Something that you've just experienced. Something that you remember in vivid detail, from the moment you started to type it into a text or email it. Maybe it’s the sound of your computer or phone, or it’s just the way that language works. 	Think of something that you know you need to do regularly, but don’t know how to do</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016). She has served on the boards of the New Jersey Museum of Art, and the board of the Egyptian Museum of Modern Art, New Brunswick, Canada. She has served on the boards of the New York Museum of Art, New York, USA; the Board of Trustees of the New York Public Library, New York, USA; the Board of Directors of the New Jersey Museum of Art, New Brunswick, USA; and the board of directors of the Egyptian Museum of Modern Art, New Brunswick, Canada.In October 2016, she co-chaired the Venice Biennale, the first openly gay person to chair a major art institution, and served as the curator for the London and Rome Biennales. In February 2017, she curated the Venice Biennale, the first openly lesbian person to chair a major art institution, and served as the curator for the Los Angeles and San Francisco Biennials.In April 2017, she curated the Venice Biennale, the first ever public exhibition of</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016). Devoted to the arts and culture of the future, we asked her to consider the question, ‘What is the Age of Art?’Devoted to the arts and culture of the future, we asked her to consider the question, ‘What is the Age of Art?’ – and the related question, ‘What is the End of Art?’ – as we move into an Age of Consensus?Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016).Download this article as PDFBina EngbergBina Engberg is an artist and the curator of the newly founded Sustainable Development Initiative, which is focused on sustainability and social change in developing nations. Her work has addressed a broad range of audiences, including policymakers, journalists, activists, academics, municipal governments, grassroots groups, municipal corporations, grassroots NGOs, community organizers, artists, journalists and others. Prior to joining SDF, she worked as an Assistant Professor at Yale University, New Haven, Connecticut, where she taught courses in Digital Cultures and Brazilian Image Studies. Her research and teaching interests have included the production of historical documents of Brazilian social and urban history through archiving and documentation; the social implications of a social-media revolution; and the web and mobile for the production and dissemination of knowledge. She has presented her work at the 42nd Venice Biennale as part of the International Documenta Series, the 19th Johannesburg Biennale, and the Ponte City Contemporary Art Bienn</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016).Public Art and its CriticsJohn SoaneJohn Soane is a New York-based critic and writer who, in the 1990s, was an editor of the New Criterion, a periodical of the Modern and Contemporary art movement. His work has appeared in publications such as The New York Times, The New Yorker, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Critic, and The New York Times Higher Edutainment. He has been a critic of the Iraq War, the impact of AIDS, and the war on terror. He is the host of the weekly podcast From the Vault with John Oliver and has written for publications including The New York Times, The New Yorker, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Critic, and The New York Times Higher Edutainment. He has a new book out soon from the same anthologies.Self-repairing Art WorldCities that are Not CitiesIn recent years, as cities age and decline, the public realm around them increasingly resembles</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Buffalo, New York in 2017. Tickets are still available.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for the 2018 Venice Biennale, and co-curator of the 2020 Tokyo Biennale. She is the co-founder and co-editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages and the co-editor of the upcoming book The Contemporary Condition: Art, Culture &amp; Politics in an Open Society. Her work has been featured in exhibitions including ARTFX, THE ATP, ARTESTA, CHAPTER 7/8, and the New York Times. She has been a lecturer at the American University in Cairo, Egypt and the Graduate Center, New York, USA, and the director of the Center for Art and Public Innovation, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, USA. She is the author of several books including the New Criticism: An Introduction to Critical Art (MIT Press, 2016).Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell and Timothy Snyder 	Timothy Snyder is the Deputy Director for Art Practice at the Canadian Centre for an Open Economy (CCEE), University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the program for research-based art, including the Centre’s ongoing research program in the field of public art. He is the author of several books including the recent Black-E: Short Circuits and the Black-F: A Documenta 13 Project (with Silvia Federici, Istanbul and Dont Rivera, New York) and the upcoming Stages: Art from the Microscopic to the Macro (with Silvia Federici, Istanbul and Dont Rivera, New York). He has a long-term research interest in the field of ecologies and the environment, particularly in relation to the South. He is currently pursuing his MFA from the University of Toronto, with a joint appointment at the CCCE and the U of T.Both</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.123.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.124.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.125.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.126.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.127.  Preeana Reddy, “The</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.123.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.124–9.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.125–6.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.126.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red Eyes of Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.127.  Preeana Reddy, “</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.123.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.124.   Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.125.   Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.126.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.127.  Preeana Reddy, �</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.123.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.124.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.125.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.126.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.127.  Preeana Reddy, “The</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.123.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.124.   Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.125.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.126.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.127.   Preeana Reddy, �</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 2, Spring, 1978, p.130.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 2, Spring, 1978, p.131.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 3, Spring, 1978, p.134.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 3, Spring, 1978, p.135.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 4, Spring, 1978, p.136.  Preeana Reddy, “The</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.123.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.124.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.125.   Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.126.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.127.  Preeana Reddy, “</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.123.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.124.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.125.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.126.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.127.  Preeana Reddy, “The</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.123.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.124.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.125.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.126.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.127.  Preeana Reddy, “The</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  The next Biennial will be held in 2026.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, pp.120–26.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.120.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.121.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.122.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.123.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.124.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.125.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.126.  Preeana Reddy, “The Red-Eyes of the Himalayas”, Induction, Vol. 2, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.127.  Preeana Reddy, “The</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global
    <text>vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global artistic economy. The biennial was seen as a temporary last resort, a last resort in a world increasingly intent on recycling the familiar. It was seen as trapped in its own mode of engagement. 	The contemporary biennial has been on a tear of late, and while its methods may differ from the old biennial, its experiences are the same. The key difference is that now there is an art world directly intervening between the museum and the biennial, and the museum and the biennial are forced to work co-operatively with each other. This book is set in the contemporary biennial market, so it is a narrative that takes account of the history, or rather, a chronological account of the contemporary biennial phenomenon. It is a project that takes account both of what is happening now in the market place, and of what might happen in the future. It is a project that takes account of the curatorial role, or perhaps the curator’s role, in the formation of</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global art market. (The New Criterion, vol. 2, p.8)  	I didn’t see this book as a kind of ‘battle field’. I saw it as a kind of  	enduring urban question that needed to be ironed out. I wrote the book as a kind of ‘mission-critical’ report on how the contemporary contemporary condition was created, and how we might all be part of a future world if we didn’t wreck it. The book came out in paperback in 1987.  	At the time, I felt a little bit like Wittgenstein in how I thought the contemporary condition was created. We are all created equal in this new ‘civiliz[ing] context of globalized capitalism’. But there is a difference. There is a difference between a biennial and a museum, and between an art institution and an ordinary museum. There is a difference between bi</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global art market. I remember thinking, in the pages that followed, that the late 1980s and early 1990s were the golden years of curatorial creativity; a time when biennials were seen as having entered a post-Cold War context. But as the biennial becomes ever more institutionalised, increasingly feted, and more like a museum, we need to ask whether the relationship between artist and biennial is really any longer a relationship at all. If the answer is yes, then we might start to question whether the relationship between biennial and contemporary art world really needs to change. 	The answer to that question is a clear: yes, it needs to change. The relationship between the artist and the biennial must change, and biennials will always have a place in any kind of artistic or curatorial purpose. But the relationship between biennial and contemporary art world, and between biennial and biennial as such, cannot be fully measured, and art world and art world cannot</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global art market. I was writing about the art world’s increasing reliance on social media, which I imagined was starting to take root in the art world. I imagined a time when biennials began to be characterised by their participation in curatorial race to social media followings. A time when artists would begin to be drawn to the opportunity of participating in a race to be liked by the curators, and to being plugged into a social media ecosystem. 	In an effort to be more visible, in 2015 the Biennale organised a double publicity event on the same day in Venice. The idea was to make a spectacle of itself, to allow the artist-curator duo La Casa Encendida and Marian Kotowicz to continue their experiment, but also to open themselves up to media scrutiny. The idea that a biennial can be curatorial in its own right was shown in the Biennale auditorium. The double publicity was so that the public and the art world</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global art market. I was also writing the commentary for the book at the time, so this was a real opportunity for the biennial to flex its art historical muscle. 	Later in life, when I began to think about what the biennial could be for the city, the museum and the local community, this kind of engagement with contemporary art and contemporary culture became a way to think about the social aspects of art in the city. A place where art could be made to connect with the struggles and frustrations of everyday life. A challenge to the idea that the art world is some sort of neutral platform, where everything that happens is reductive and devoid of meaning. A challenge to the idea that the biennial is some sort of magical panacea. 	In the 1990s and 2000s, the biennial opened its show to large-scale protests, and in 2007 it cancelled a programme due to financial issues. It seems that every time the biennial does something new, it is also the</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global art market. I thought that entry had gone too far. I wrote a book about contemporary art, and it’s a sort of an odd one to devote one of your first chapters to the topic of art and contemporary art. But the way in which we are bombarded with information these days, and the information-gathering it entails, makes you acutely aware of how little you actually know. The question of authenticity and the place of art and contemporary art in a political context is crucial in any serious analysis of contemporary art, and biennials especially so. And yet: how much of the information they provide is legitimate, and how much is bogus? How much of it is contextually authentic, and how much is actively invented by the curatorial hand? How much of it is generated by art institutions themselves, and how much is created by the biennial itself? The Biodiversity Project is a good place to start asking these questions.Download this article as PDFEva Castringius</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global art market. I’d always ­penned the idea that the biennial was the new museum, but the fact that it was the leading exhibitionary venue in the world, and the only one in the world to have its fairground located in New York City, seemed a bit strange to many people. Biennials are institutions of their own marginalisation and decentralisation, operating at a distance from their geographical locations. But now that role was shifting, and I began to read the  	next chapter in the book, from the cities to the nations. And I found myself thinking about the biennial as a site of metainformation – the new museums were being built on the back of the historical collections, and the biennial was the last vestige of a once dominant practice. The biennial was here to stay, and we had to start thinking about new forms of co-production and innovative production, which I suggested to colleagues and to me being  	author</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global art market. I thought the biennial had a responsibility to question what it meant to be contemporary in a different way from what contemporary art was engaged with. And so it was that the biennial made itself visible in Times Square. It was no exaggeration to suggest that the opening of Times Square had a major effect on the cultural landscape of the city. The biennial was a catalyst that year. 	But the real kicker came in 2015, when the Trump Tower was pulled down and replaced with a brand new skyscraper. This was seen by some critics as a kind of architectural provocation, a sign that the city was in crisis. And so it continues to this day: skyscrapers are always seen as a kind of new kind of emergency shelter for the disoriented and homeless, providing both luxury housing and a direct line to the president. But in the years since the tower was pulled down, new kinds of housing have come to dominate the cityscape, and much of what used to be called</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global art market. Modernist Modern art museums, they said, needed to be created ‘in the image’ of the biennial, while contemporary art sites were often seen as a way to achieve ‘a little more engagement with the cultural quantified through art’s museum’s collection’. Contemporary art, they argued, was artefactualised, and contemporary art was a media-production system. These were the days, really, when the museum was seen as a venue for the very serious work of art, and the biennial was an exhibitionary platform on which that serious work was staged. 	So there was this deep split, and it was a critique of the curatorial turn, and its capacity to generate engagement. I took the idea of the biennial as a sort of canvas on which to work, and the idea of the contemporary condition as a sort of skylight, through which I would project ideas that were different from those typically held by</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data about which way the wind was blowing. I was continuously amazed by the extent to which the biennial would rather draw you into a conversation with a curator, than with an artist. It was this obsession with the relationship between art world and art world that would not take art seriously as a legitimate field of relations. The biennial would rather commission a serious work of art than a funny, eye-catching artwork.  	In this sense, the biennial was also engaged in a dialogue with contemporary art’s other usual exhibitionary venues. I remember one particular entry in the catalogue of curatorial thoughts that year: ‘It is the opening salvo in a long war of ideas and opinions, in which the biennial will be directly involved.’ This was in connection with the book I was writing at the time, The Contemporary Condition. It was the end of the Cold War, and the biennial was seen by some critics as a sort of pawn of the new global art market. The new market for art, this was seen by some critics as something that would rather engage you with a gallery piece, rather than with a museum piece made in the here and now. The curators in my group, including the curatorial geniuses Tina Kahn and Jennifer Coontz, were quick to point out that this was hardly a compliment. It was a description of actual cruelty. Tina Kahn and Jennifer Coontz: On Cultural Venue . New York: Independent Curators International, 2011. 	The conversation then turned to the specificity of the event itself. Tina Kahn: The challenge for the 2011 Biennial was to create something that would surprise and entice, to capture the imagination of a contemporary art market that had largely ignored contemporary art, while simultaneously providing a space for cultural touch-points to exist at a scale that was unprecedented in the biennial market. We succeeded in doing both. The surprise and the epiphany in the Biennial was accompanied by a</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument
    <text>AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument, a twisted and warped version of West 22 Avenue, where the former storefronts on both sides of 22nd Street are occupied and a half-built mixed-use development is under way.I think the lesson for the future is this: don’t do stupid shit. Don’t mess with history. Don’t repeat the mistakes of the past. And most of all, don’t repeat the mistakes of the past few years. That’s what the architectural historians, urbanists and urban activists that we worked with over the years have been trying to teach us. That’s why we had to work so hard to come up with a way to honour the people whose work transformed West 22 Avenue into a place where a community could come together and live peacefully and ecstatically – because we couldn’t do it on our own. We had to be supported by the state and local governments in our urban activism work. And we were doing that through</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument, bisected by the dangerous and unjust pipeline.Here is the original West Kingsway proposal, with some of the key architectural concepts from that time:The West Kingsway is an urban transformation project that was first proposed in the mid 1970s by the California Pacific Electric Railway (Calpoly). The project gained international attention when it was abandoned in 2008, but its negative effects are still being felt today. The Kinder Morgan pipeline would have run through sections of the corridor, with little opposition at the time. The city has been struggling with its effects of industrial decline for decades, and the destruction of cultural resources is a constant source of conflict. It is impossible to overstate the importance of this clash of resources; in the city’s current predicament, the West Kingsway proposal represents a brave new way of building a city.Download this article as PDFLinda JohnsonLinda Johnson is an architect and urbanist. She is professor in the School of Urban Affairs and Planning at Mount Royal University, and</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument, a collection of abandoned buildings across the street from a proposed new airport. The question of whether or not to is the right one to be asking right now. The city’s decision to tear down a building because of a housing crisis that it created is a strange decision to make again, and I hope that developers across the country don’t repeat this mistake. It will cost taxpayers a lot more to fix up the block in the future, but at least the taxpayers will have a place to go.Download this article as PDFLinda JohnsonLinda Johnson is the Chair of the Board for Creative Time, a non-profit organisation that promotes a collaborative and inclusive culture in the global South through research and art. She is a co-creator of the International Animation Short Film Festival (2001-2007), a co-founder of the South as a Region Gallery (2008-12) and was a curator at the South as a Region International (2012-16) and South by Southeast Asian</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument, a collection of abandoned buildings, some reclaimed industrial sites and the border of a civil war.‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ is a very dangerous game to play, and we can all agree that. But the fact that the developers made that decision in the face of such overwhelming and widely shared public support for reopening the area speaks volumes about the changes that need to happen if we are to experience the regeneration that is needed in this city. The question of community – who is the community? – is far more important than one might imagine. Research has shown that people tend to identify with groups (whether that is a breed, a people, a neighbourhood) that have similar characteristics (e.g., poverty, deprivation, racism, class). So it is easy to imagine a project that seeks to make a neighbourhood ‘home’ and then have a catastrophic effect on the area if that neighbourhood is not home to the expected returns. In an ideal world</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument, a twisted combination of heritage and newly minted high-rises, a twisted hybrid of heritage and newly minted gentrification, and a twisted hybrid of heritage and newly minted postindustrial. In this version of the neighbourhood, the shops and offices that once lined West Kingsway are now boarded up and empty. The neighbourhood is becoming something like a ghost town.What might be different now, however, is that the neighbourhood is becoming something like an international financial district. The international financial district is a city in which transactions are facilitated through middlemen, and in which cultural institutions play a far greater role in the formation of the city’s financial future than in the past. In other words, in an international financial district, cultural institutions now dominate decision-making, and cultural institutions – especially those located in the US – play a far greater role in the formation of the future’s financial future.  	One could argue that the globalised financial sector that we inhabit is different from</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument, but in the year ahead, when the new Whole Foods opens in West Oakland, it’s possible that a similar fate may befall the block it was built on. How that happens is anyone’s guess, but in the meantime, we’re stuck in this loop of disinvestment and now this looming demolition.As an aside, it may be interesting to explore the idea of ‘episodic architecture’ in the context of the West Kingsway project. The idea is that as the development accelerates, the architecture is there to play host to as many different kinds of life forms as possible, in such a way as to continually challenge and evolve.  In other words, the architecture is a kind of capital asset. This is a more contemporary idea of architectural space, and it’s a valuable kind of space, in that it provides a kind of capital for future development: a kind of capital that can – should – be spent creating something better</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument, a collection of abandoned buildings on a steep hillside in the San Fernando Valley, surrounded by residential neighbourhoods with their own take on the quirky urban monument.Developers may try to come up with an alternative that is both more aesthetically pleasing to the city and more financially viable, but that doesn’t make it a good alternative. There is simply no alternative to the need for the city to reclaim and rebuild West Kingsway, its streets and buildings, and to do so in a way that is not bound by the criminal enterprises that caused the fires that ravaged the neighbourhood and caused so much displacement.  The alternative is for the city to try to excise the bad from the neighbourhood and to do so through whatever means necessary – a difficult but necessary situation, to be sure.  The alternative is for the city to create a ‘bike-share area’ – a hybrid public and private cooperative enterprise – and to offer subsidies to encourage the cooperative’s sustainable growth through public works and</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument, its shadow falling across much of Downtown LA. What’s left of it is being converted into a vast mixed-use development – a mix of offices, residential towers, offices and perhaps even a few new hotels – but the neighbourhood that was once West Kingsway is being erased. When that happens, who is going to be able to say what that development is? When that happens, there is a question that I have – what is the role of a city in that process? – and the answer is going to be a city-wide one. Because that is where the big issues are going to be. Downtown is a city-wide issue. I don’t think that West Kingsway was the biggest issue, but it is a city-wide issue. I think that the fact that it was a catalyst for so much activity later in the process is significant. I think that the fact that the neighbourhood has persisted to this day is a significant point of reference. It is a</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument, a twisted version of itself, with the blighting of the neighbourhood hanging over it like a cruel winter wind. The question is, how much longer will this neighborhood be twisted and tormented by this form of urban capitalism?Download this article as PDFLinda JohnsonLinda Johnson is a writer, curator, and artist. Her work has addressed the history of urban and regional development in North America and the Middle East. She is a regular contributor to The New Inquiry magazine and has written for the Journal of a People’s Congress. She has been a curator at the Whitney Museum of American Art and the LA County Museum of Art. Her latest project, The Resident, was presented in partnership with the LA Department of Cultural Affairs, and she was a curator at MoMA’s Division 14: Europe &amp; Asia exhibit. She has a particular interest in the history of urban and regional development in North America and the Middle East. Her latest exhibition,  The Resident:  	Inside the</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only. In her report for the LA conference, Linda Johnson described how the project’s final weeks felt like a nightmare, as the city spun out of control:Every day more and more people were showing up to the eviction notice boards. The gangs were coming out of the neighbourhood – they were no longer the kids; the older folks were showing up to reclaim buildings; and the city was becoming an increasingly unstable and dangerous place to be in the event.The question that came to mind as I watched the footage of the demolition of West Kingsway in 2015 was how the developers might react in the future if the project went ahead, given the huge amount of public and critical feedback at the time. ‘Were they going to rebuild the whole block?’ was one of the more memorable quotes of that moment. I don’t think so. The developers may very well try again, but I expect that the consequences will be very different. West Kingsway now stands as a twisted urban monument, bisected by a highway. The whole neighbourhood has been displaced, and now lives in fear of violent force by the city. What might the reaction have been like if, during that period in the late 1990s and early 2000s, a similar set of anxieties and publics had been addressed to the extent that was addressed by and for the city? Would the current situation be any different? I don’t think so. I think the answer to that is going to be different.  	What I do believe in and hope for is that the same kinds of conversations that were had around the CBL/TDA proposal in the 1990s are going to be had by and for the people of our city. We have to find a way to talk about the consequences of our housing crisis without demonising the people who are struggling to get by. I also believe that the same kinds of conversations are going to be had by and for people of all incomes, from the very poorest</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Now
    <text>vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Nowadays biennales gather actors from many regions, and many countries, so they can include more countries. And because of this the size of the market for art in many cities has also increased. This is reflected in the number of biennales: today, there are more than one Venice Biennale, and each city has its own unique and distinctive event.‘

It is also worth noting that Venice has a very specific and valuable place in its city: it is the seat of the Italian Legation, Italy’s representative in Washington, the District of Columbia, as well as the host of the 2016 Olympic and Documenta 14. It is also the seat of the Italian ambassador, Daniela Passata, the nation’s representative in Washington, and the representative of Italy in New York. It is the seat of the Italian Consul General, Paolo Portoghesi, the biennale’s curator of art and culture, and the chair of</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Now, in the words of one biennale critic, ‘The biennale is a global phenomenon.’’ This is an echo of Marx’s assessment, which was echoed by Marx’s cousin Frederick Engels, who in the Communist Manifesto published in 1848 – just as the First World War broke out – wrote:

&quot;The great calamity of the modern world is the appearance of another world outside of these shores: there is another kind of revolution under way, which will not be like the old, feudal, national, central ones, but will be like the communes and collectives of ancient empires.&quot;1

Thus, the global phenomenon that the capitalist museum serves to simultaneously present and to conceal is back and capitalism is back in vogue.2 Already in the early twentieth century, this was widely understood as a historiographical trope. In the thirties and forties, curators such as Henri Lefebvre, Jean Guy</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Nowadays, the main reason to be seen in major cities is Asia, and the main reason to be seen in regions far from the main cities. This is evident in the number of biennales that are now happening in cities all over the world, as well as in the number of biennales that are occurring in smaller towns and rural centres. All these trends are the inevitable outcome of the capitalist ‘metro-regeneration’ machine, which is growing ever more powerful and dependent on the ever-expanding market being supplied with ever more exotic ways to be consumed.’

The Venice Biennale website likewise indicates that the main art-world destinations for this century are now Asia, and that the number one target of curators worldwide will be the ‘region that includes the greatest number of art collectors’.1  This is a perfect storm of rapid technological change, yet art collectors still retain a great deal of influence in shaping what is seen and</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Nowadays, biennales often visit regions with distinct cultures and languages, and sometimes languages spoken by distinct communities. Consequently, the biennale needs to be able to expand its geographical scope.’[6]

This statement draws heavily on the work of artist duo Ai Weiwei and Peter Saville, whose 2014 book Local Curators: Art as Propaganda in an Information Age (MIT Press, 2017) focuses on the ways that artworks and cultural products are produced and reproduced in and through the socio-cultural systems that shape globalised capitalism. Peter Saville’s own project, the Saville Fund, is heavily indebted to the work of the local artists and collectors who inspired it. The fund’s projects include the 2014 Venice Biennale, which was co-curated by Saville and Martha Rackham-Webb, and the 2015 Mumbai Biennale, co-curated by Maria Lind and Paul Waldau  The new frontier for biennials</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Nowadays biennials, as a form, are globalized and institutionalised.’[6]

The Venice Biennale has a long-term plan to expand its localised picture. In 2015, the Biennale made a world-first in the restoration of St Peter's Square, replacing a statue of St Peter with a statue of St Andrew, an act that many considered blasphemous. Although the square was taken down soon afterwards, the controversy – which came to define the term – lingered. In 2017, artworks were again placed in St Peter’s Square, but this time for a residential project in the San Marco district, where the square once again hosts a community of squatters. Artworks were also placed in the empty lot immediately surrounding the San Marco train station. This is the site of the upcoming San Francisco International Airport (SFO). Artwork was taken down at both locations, but not before it had been distributed widely online and was featured</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Now, the number of cities in the world regularly changes – consider Istanbul, which has more than 200 million inhabitants – so it is more important to explore a global perspective. And since the biennale has become a globalised form, there are cities that now need to be visited by a specific kind of visitor.‘Every city needs an exhibitionary platform; otherwise, it is not feasible to visit all the cities and developed regions of the world.’; ‘This exhibitionary model is now obsolete; cities will be collections, not exhibitions; collections, not exhibitions.’; and ‘Toward a Museum of Art of the Current Ecologies of Art, New York, 2015.’ – all of which echo the recommendations of the Surgeon General.1

The Venice Biennale website echoes these recommendations,2 seeking to reconcile the increasing globalisation of capital, cultural capitalism, and the related scientific and economic theories with the increasingly globalised archipelago of contemporary</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Now, global exhibitions are the main form of exhibition for a range of reasons: the first being the impact of cheap cruise capitalism; the second, the impact of innovative tourism strategies; the third, the impact of science and technological research; and the fourth, the impact of international NGOs’ work in impoverished regions. Therefore, it is important to maintain a global perception of art’s role.“

The Venice Biennale has clearly identified the importance of the city as a site of artistic and cultural exchange, and has regularly used the occasion to launch exhibitions of art, curatorial visits, and other activities taking place throughout the city. As the Biennale website notes, ‘the exhibition schedule includes programming that anticipates contemporary art’s need for stories and narrative.’ This programming has often been deployed in tandem with local and regional creativity; as the biennale website itself makes clear, this has often been done in opposition to the artist’s programming,</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Nowadays, biennales are everywhere; in many cities, the biennale is the most widely-recognised tourist attraction.’

The Venice Biennale website also notes that this is not a biennale, but a museum:

&quot;For the foreseeable future the term ‘biennale’ will be used synonymously to describe a type of cultural tourism organised by the city government or a private company, and specifically excludes any kind of ‘museum’.’

The Venice Biennale website defines a museum as

&quot;a place of permanent display or private collection of objects, specimens, or collections relating to a specific topic, object, person or phenomenon.’

It further notes that a museum is a place of exchange – of exchange between people, objects or things, of discussion, study, or of unknown things – and that its main role is to the public. Its main purpose is to the extent that</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Now many biennales are opening offices in other cities or regions, and many museums are closing their museums or opening new galleries of art. Therefore, the cultural impact of a biennale in a given city or region is limited: the biennale must expand internationally or else it will lose its place in the cultural hierarchy.’

This last prediction is a form of capital‑intensive capitalism that scholars have understood for some time now. Although the cultural impact of a biennale may be felt in a specific city, the city itself becomes a laboratory for the power of the biennale as a cultural capital. This is especially true in cities where the biennale is occurring simultaneously within the city core and on a global scale, such as in Istanbul, Los Angeles, and New York. As a result, the biennale is experiencing a form of capital growth it could not before enjoy. The New York Times recently reported that this growth is the direct result of the financial crash,</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data to automate the job of curating, or at least of curating as accurately as possible. In this way, the biennial – and in particular, the Venice Biennale as an institution – could be viewed as a capital-intensive version of Big Data, machine learning, and social media analysis. The Venice Biennale’s board of directors includes some of the world’s most prominent curators, including Isabelle Hegerl, Daniela Ginsburg, Joasia Krysa, and Marina Fokidis. The Biennale was initially established as a biennale of a global definition, but its original focus has shifted to a museum of contemporary art encompassing art from every nation, city, and region of the globe. The official biennale website notes that this is because of the changing role of museums in the globalised capitalist economy:

&quot;The main reason is that in the past biennales were confined to a particular geographical region. Now, it is the other way around: the museum that holds the collection of art in a particular city or region is now also the museum of contemporary art in that region. So the museum that held the collection of art in a particular city suddenly began to show new works from other cities or regions. This is a classic mise en place, where art is often read as a commodity and artists are often cast as artists without resources who must struggle to create new works of art because of the accessibility and wealth of contemporary art. This is one reason why biennials have become so popular: they are a conspicuous manifestation of the capitalism that permeates most of the planet, and so are visible because of their proximity and global circulation.’[9]

This globalised artistic circumscription is a contradiction in terms; it is made possible by the production of art being displayed at the largest biennale in a particular city or region. It is a testament to the power of cultural consumption in the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and microfiber cloths; felt; microfiber towels; tissue; tissue paper; tissue paper; tissue paper and tissue. The collections also included old-fashioned binders, envelopes and zippered envelopes.The works were made using archival materials and archival processes in an attempt to preserve as much of the heritage of their subject as possible.[1]http://www.royalsystems.com/royalroad/2017/exhibition/en/photos/906669-biennial-2018-rewind-roseth-rugby-queen-alex-welsh-rome-2018.html[2] http://www.royalsystems.com/royalroad/2017/exhibition/en/photos/906669-biennial-2018-rewind-roseth-rogby-queen-alex-welsh-rome-2018.html[3] http://www</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and plastic wrap; electrical contacts; a dryer; and electrical wires.Each of the three-and-a-half-minute works is composed of three or more small-scale images of the same scene taken from different angles. The images are combined to form a single image. As the title of the exhibition suggests, the three-and-a-half-minute works stand for a day – or in this case, a day – in which images are taken repeatedly – often in rapid-fire bursts – over and over again. After the images are taken, they are combined to form a new image. This process repeats until a new image is taken, at which point the cycle begins all over again. This repeats until all the images have been taken or until the end of the world, depending on how the images are framed. 	Each image in the series is composed of three or more images arranged in a fashion that creates a temporal relation between the original image and the new one. The</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and rag; insulating paper; water; eraser and rag; thread; marker; paper towels; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper; fine eraser paper;</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and eraser paper; microfiber cloth; felt; tissue; eraser paper; cotton balls; tissue, felt and thread; microfiber towels; tissue; eraser paper; tissue; eraser paper and paper.The three-and-a-half-minute pieces were created in collaboration between the RA London and Rome studios, using media including: wood, metal, fibreboard, vinyl, paint, ink and fibreboard. The sound was produced and engineered by the RAC, using Roland J. Baird Jr. and Jon P. Murphy as well as the RA London and Rome studios. The three-and-a-half-minute pieces were combined to produce a multimedia installation that stands alone, or in the presence of another work that stands in for the city. The installation is a three-dimensional reconstruction of a single building that unfolds like a fractal, from the ground up. Floor-to-ceiling windows reveal a different kind of vantage point – looking down on the</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and eraser paper; micro-ceramic tiles; micro-ceramics; micro-moulds; staples; needle-type paper; thread; felt; polyurethane foam; eraser paper; eraser and eraser paper; micro-ceramics; micro-moulds; staples; needle-type paper, including micro-ceramics; micro-moulds; pins; needle-type paper; thread; marker; wax; micro-ceramics; micro-lithographs; micro-moulds; rivets; zip ties; glue; electrical tape; clear tubing; zip ties; micro-ceramics; micro-lithographs; micro-moulds; screws; nuts; bolts; screws; bolts; bolts; nuts and bolts; fasteners; zip ties; micro-ceramics; micro-lithographs; micro-moulds; cut-and-pasted photographs; cut-and-</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and wire; paper towels; eraser paper and felt; microfiber towels; tissue; eraser and eraser paper; instant-read paper; fine eraser paper; microfiber-coated Imperfection paper; microfiber-lined 240gsm white acetate board; microfiber-tipped eraser and wire; microfiber-tipped tissue; microfiber-tipped eraser and wire; microfiber-tipped tissue; microfiber-tipped instant-read white acetate board; microfiber-tipped tissue; microfiber-tipped microstrip; microfiber-tipped eraser and wire; microfiber-tipped tissue; microfiber-tipped microstrip and eraser; microfiber-tipped microstrip and wire; microfiber-tipped tissue; microfiber-tipped eraser and wire; microfiber-tipped instant-read white acet</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and microfiber cloths; microfiber towels; microfiber-lined tissue papers; microfiber-lined storage bags; microfiber-lined air mattresses; microfiber-coated tissue paper; microfiber-coated bubble wrap; microfiber-coated tissue paper; microfiber-coated tissue and rubber mats; microfiber-coated air mattresses; microfiber-coated tissue and rubber mats; microfiber-coated bubble wrap; microfiber-coated tissue and rubber mats; microfiber-coated tissue paper; microfiber-coated tissue and rubber mats; microfiber-coated tissue and rubber mats; microfiber-coated air mattresses; microfiber-coated sponge and gutter paper; microfiber air mattresses; microfiber-coated tissue and rubber mats; microfiber-coated sponge and gutter paper; microf</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and microfiber cloths; microfiber towels; tissue; eraser paper; microfiber cloth; tissue paper; tissue paper; tissue paper; tissue paper, microfiber cloth, fine erasers; fine erasers; erasers; airbrush; watercolour; watercolour and waterjet ink; Pastos; watercolouring equipment; watercolour software; watercolour software; watercolour and waterjet prints; watercolour and waterjet paper; watercolour and waterjets; watercolour and waterjets; watercolour and waterjets; watercolour and waterjets; watercolours; watercolour processors; watercolour stands; watercolour sheets; watercolouring kits; watercolour tins; watercolour tins; watercolouring looms; watercolouring misters; colouring agents; colouring mirrors; colouring rollers; colouring materials; colouring materials; oil; acrylic; ceramic; gel; gel and wax; mineral oil; poly</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and microfiber cloths; microfiber towels; microfiber pins; microfiber pins, rods and wire; microfiber rulers; microfiber pins, pieces and wire; microfiber twine; microfiber cloth; microfiber tacks; microfiber flat head screw; microfiber erasers; microfiber erasers; microfiber hardware; microfiber tacks and nuts; microfiber erasers; microfiber thermal paste; microfiber erasers; microfiber pins; microfiber rulers; microfiber flat head screw; microfiber thermal paste; microfiber thermal paste; microfiber erasers; microfiber hardware; microfiber twine; microfiber flat head screw; microfiber thermal paste; microfiber thermal paste; microfiber thermal paste; microfiber thermal paste; microfiber erasers; microfiber hardware; microfiber flat head screw</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Liverpool in 2017.German artist Jeanne van Heeswijk has created a series of three-and-a-half-minute works that appear in the autumn of each year. The works – entitled  	The Gathering Storm,  	Winter Storm and  	Dazzle Season – were commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts and The Royal Academy of Arts Rotterdam, the Netherlands, where they will be exhibited in the RA 2017 exhibition. They were premiered at the RA 2017 exhibition entitled: Environment, 2017.10 June –14 October 2017 in Rome, Italy.The works were made using materials from the RA 2016 exhibition, featuring new conservation tools. These included: black-and-white photographs; sculptures; moulds; eraser-like materials; paints; waterproof varnish; wax; plastics; aluminium foil; electrical tape; electrical contacts; pencils; paper; thread; marker; sandpaper; eraser paper; eraser and microfiber cloths; electrical tape; flexible wire; a dry eraser, microfiber cloth and electrical wire; a paint can and a paintbrush; a set of magnifying glasses; a marker and a ruler; a tube and a ruler; a pad and a pad; a marker and a piece of paper; a marker and a marker; a tube and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a ruler; a tube and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a tube and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker and a pad; a marker</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and
    <text>project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and Humanities Courses at Santa Fe Community College have a long history of supporting creative pedagogical practices, introducing students to the social and political contexts of artistic practice, including the contributions of African American artists to the formation of the modernist avant garde. In recent years, courses have escalated their programmes of research and development, paying particular attention to the arts and their varied applications. For more than a decade, the Santa Fe Arts Council funded the research and development of a proposed five-year long, ‘critical race theory’ project that would have included a multidisciplinary examination of race and art forms. The project was withdrawn due to the economic crisis, but the Arts and Humanities Council reapplied in 2015 and again in 2018. The 2018 reapplication saw the renewal of the project, with the proposed art forms now comprising a full time position, part-time programme and project management. The new route put the arts professionals in a difficult position: were the organisations to renew the project</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and Humanities: The Partnership 	[3] is a published ‘book series’ that documents the history of ‎arts and humanities education from the 1980s to the present. Art’s Social Use Binds Politics and the Arts References 	[4] Cameron Crowe,  	The Long Emergency: Surviving the Converging Catastrophes of the Twenty-First Century, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 2002. 	[5] Graham B. Irvine,  	The Social Life of Art: Cultural Capital and the Biogeographic Episodic, Blackwell, Oxford and Oxford Universities Press, Oxford, 2002 and Terence M. O’Rourke,  	The Crisis of Cultural Capitalism: Art, Race, and Capital, Oxford and Oxford Universities Press, Oxford and New York, 2004. 	[6] Graham B. Irvine,  	The Social Life of Art,</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and humanities students participated in a year-long postgraduate program supported by the Santa Fe Community College Art Department. The program also offered a two-year postgraduate certificate program in arts and humanities. [3] See http://www.endowment.org/endowment/yearendreport.pdf?year=2012&amp;issue=1. [4] The Alpha and Omega Project was co-founded by Jane Addai Urry (1907–92), a Scottish zoologist and zoologist, and William Roberts Anglin (1878–1971), a Scottish painter and landscape artist. Urry was a professor of Entomology at the University of Alberta, and Anglin was director of the American Museum of Natural History. The project was named for the points where the two projects’arcades’in collision: the Alpha Entomological Museum and the Omega Scientific Museum in Santa Fe. Urry was awarded the Presidential Cross of Meritorious Service from</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and humanities courses have been offered by the Santa Fe Community College Art Department since 2002, and by the Santa Fe Community College Art Department since 2005. The course was designed to be fully self-sufficient and self-starter, yet it was also prototypically an arts education course: the students worked in their classrooms, collaborating across disciplines, often using art as a tool to challenge assumptions and offer alternatives. The course was also fully funded by the Arts Council, yet the students had to petition the Arts Council for permission to use the artworks and engage with the cultural industries on the campus. In 2014, the Arts Council approved the establishment of a grantmaking account, entitled ‘The Arts Resource,’ which could support the development of the artworks found in the home of the deceased academician Henry A. Reclaiming the Radical Urban Space project. The Arts Resource would provide financial support for the production of the project itself, while the project’s conceptual development and dissemination would be funded by the Arts</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and humanities students engage with a number of topics related to the social, political and cultural contexts of modern and contemporary art, including the role artists can play in challenging dominant forms of art’s] complicity in creating social and political change. A second course, ‘Civil Rights and Cultural Politics’, is also taught by Ruiz. [3] See: http://www.globalinfrastructures.com/en/research/infrastructure/infrastructure/infrastructure/infrastructure/infrastructure.html#sthash.8xDl0SsDpTl.dpuf.dpuf.2015.DownloadArticleDownloadThis article as PDFGabriela FreireGabriela Freire is an Artistic Director and Co-Founder of Global Infrastructure, an architecture and construction consultancy. Her research interests include the post-effects of urbanisation, development and her role as a mediator between public and private space. Her work has addressed the temporal</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and humanities students participate in a research project, entitled ‘The Arts + Humanities Divide and Impact America’, conducted with the University of Alabama at Birmingham and commissioned by the University of Alabama at Birmingham. The project addresses the economic, political and social effects of a broad range of social, economic and cultural changes affecting the communities that are shaped by arts and humanities. Working through a year-long curatorial residency, the artists and educator team works across disciplines to understand how the social, cultural and economic impacts of a revitalized arts and humanities sector are created and sustained. The project concludes with a symposium, titled ‘Beyond Art and Design’, that brings together the findings of the project and artist-performer collaboration, ARTtv, in Birmingham. The exhibition ‘Beyond Art and Design’ will be broadcast live online and distributed in-gallery and archive-based via the UCB Birmingham Art &amp; Design Archive. It will be exhibited at the Biennale of Sydney and New</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and humanities is a critical area of inquiry in which the arts and humanities community is particularly engaged due to its provenance, having been formed during the American Revolution, and its ongoing relationship to the land and to the practice of producing, managing and sharing resources. Arts and humanities is a critical area due to its historical and continuing engagement with issues of social, political, and economic inequality and injustice. It is often cited as a model for how the arts and humanities can be engaged with in a public sphere. This is particularly the case with regard to the work of the Albuquerque Museum of Art and the cooperative movement. The unique relationship between the arts and the museum, and the unique relationship between the arts and the public, has allowed the more than 150-year-old history of the museum to be written out of the complex present that is the present-day Albuquerque Museum of Art. The museum’s founder, Max Broom, envisioned in his will that the museum be a museum of the social, not</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and humanities is a broad field with many senses of ‘art’ and ‘knowledge of art’; it is often used to refer to critical thinking about contemporary art and the ways in which it is produced, appropriated and implemented across a range of social, cultural and economic levels. This broad framing of the field allows for a multiplicity of uses of knowledge, including but not limited to: (1) knowledge of artists and the processes by which they produce, consume and express themselves; (2) knowledge of the social conditions of artistic creativity; (3) knowledge about the socio-political context and/or (4) knowledge of the cultural practices of Indigenous peoples and members of other racialized/culturally diverse sub-cultures. I have worked with artists and organisations that are often at odds with each other and have endeavoured to find common ground through projects such as Connecting Home and Using Media Makeover. The aim of my work is to see how art, activism</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and Humanities: The Course �[1] The case is made here that the activity of imagining is a deeply engrained tendency towards what Erving Goffman terms ‘self-deception’ – an entwined tendency that we can trace to the origins of humanity itself. Goffman, Complex Gaze: The Human Imagination in Cultural Theory, trans. Evelyn Forget, Zone Books, NY, 1988, p.37. [2] See, for example, Goffman, Complex Gaze, p.38. [3] This observation was made, not long after, by Goffman himself, in his influential essay ‘On Violence’ in the journal The New Atlantis, No. 1, Spring, 1978, p.1.Download this article as PDFSarah Thornton and Tom VandeputteSarah Thornton (Twitter: @SARomFeDT) is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human-animal relationships are produced through culture, what is meant by ‘the work of art’ in this context? How are artists employed in this new economy of the sharing of things? 	[2] A few years later, in 2009, the National Endowment for the Arts was established to support the work of the Arts and Humanities Educator Network (AWEN), an interdisciplinary network of arts educators and activists based in Santa Fe, New Mexico. AWEN members include artists, educators, researchers, journalists, philosophers and architects. Its mandate is to ‘strengthen critical thinking and artistic practices’ through activities such as conferences, classes and peer-reviewing journals. In 2012, the Santa Fe Arts Council established a six-month long arts and humanities course taught by renowned arts and humanities teacher Jane Addai and moderated by Emmy Ruiz, Chair of the Arts and Humanities Department at Santa Fe Community College. Arts and Humanities: The Community Arts Companion was a finalist for the National Book Award, Drama, Poetry and Documenta 12. It was also a finalist for the Pulitzer Prize for Documenta 12. (AKI)Arrival (2017)Cinema Paradiso, Los Angeles. Photo: Lucia Montanari. 	[1] New York Times, June 14, 1990, p. A1. [2] New York Times, June 14, 1990, p. A1. [3] New York Times, June 14, 1990, p. A1. [4] The New York Times, June 14, 1990, p. A1. [5] The New York Times, June 14, 1990, p. A1. [6] The New York Times, June 14, 1990, p. A1. [7] The New York Times, June 14, 1990</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal
    <text>AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The New Urbanist, The Washington Post, The New Urbanist Digital Shortlists, The Nation, The New Urbanist Active List, The Local, The Sunday Times Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local, The Architectural Association Digital Shortlist, The Local</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The Washington Post, The New York Times Literary Supplement, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The New Urbanist, The New Republic, The New Urbanist, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The New Republic, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman (UK), The New Statesman (US), The New Statesman (NZ), The New Statesman (China), The New Statesman (India),</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The New Urbanist, The Times of London, The New Republic, The New Urbanist, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The Observer, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The Times of London, The Times of Manchester, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The Times of London, The Times of Berlin, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The Times of Paris, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The Times of Berlin, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New Statesman, The New</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The London Review of Books, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The New York Times, The New Republic, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The Seattle Times, The Washington Post, The Boston Globe and The Boston Phoenix. He is currently Associate Professor in the College of Architecture and Design at the University of Alberta, Canada.His writing has been featured in publications including The American Scholar, The American Reader, The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The New York Times, The New Urbanist, The New York Times, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The Washington Post, The New York Times, The New York Times, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The New York Times, The New Urbanist, The New York Times, The New Urban</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The New Urbanist, The South as a State and Tate Modern. He has co-authored several books including the recently published book Cities in Crisis: The Precariat, Race and Capital in Crisis, and is a regular commentator on BBC Radio 4's Capital in Crisis. His work has been funded by the Arts Council, the DA, the Leverhulme Trust and the Wellcome Trust. Cities in CrisisCities in crisis are crisis of the commons. They’re being made by and for the wealthy. They are not for the commoners. I started the project when the poor and the vulnerable were the sole beneficiaries, and the rich really did get richer through it. The crisis of the commons has been around for a while now, and it needs to be addressed. The only way to address it is for all concerned to participate. Creative action is more effective when it happens at an inner conference of people with different experiences and skillsets. It’s a two</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Resident and The Sunday Times. He is a founding partner of the Terrestrial Art Centre, a new generation of artists established in Stockholm, Sweden, which is developing a new generation of public art projects.IMI Corona - The Community Land Trust IMI Corona is a not-for-profit not-for-profit corporation established in 2012, primarily through the sale of 2,000 shares in its share capital. The Corporation was formed to manage the 1.8 hectare parcel of land lying within the IMI Corona industrial park in Corona, California. The 2,000 shares are collectively known as ‘The Community Land Trust 1.8’. IMI Corona was established to manage the land in perpetuity, with a special focus on the needs of the DSL, including the long-term care of the City of Corona residents and the communities around the industrial park. IMI Corona was also created to manage the industrial estate’s</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The New Inquiry, The Nation, The Hollywood Reporter, The New Republic, The New Urbanist, The Local and The Village Voice. He has received a host of accolades and recognitions for his work, including most recently the 2011 Oxbridge Arts Prize for Visual Art, the 2008 Thomson Reuters Artist in Residence Award, the 2009 Allen Griffiths Fellowship from the Royal Academy of Arts, and the 2012  Oxbridge Arts Prize for Art, a nom de plume for Parris English painting. His art has been exhibited at the New Museum, London, the Venice Biennale, Paris and Los Angeles, and has been commissioned by Discovery Communications, North London Gallery, the Hollywood Museum, and the Tate Britain. He has written for the Daily Telegraph, The Times, The Guardian, The Times Literary Supplement, The Sunday Times, The Post, The Farmer's Almanac, The Illustrated London News, The Sunday Times, The Sunday</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist Review, and The Architecture Critic. He was recently appointed as an O’F Scottish Medalist for his work in the Scottish Highlands. He is part of the Curatorial Faculty for the Venice Biennale. Towards A Place Where Art and Architecture Meet?By Vickie Harrison-White and Karen Reid-BellamyTowards A Place Where Art and Architecture Meet?By Vickie Harrison-White and Karen Reid-Bellamy, 2015. Installation, Liverpool Biennial 2015. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTowards A Place Where Art and Architecture Meet?By Vickie Harrison-White and Karen Reid-Bellamy, 2015. Installation, Liverpool Biennial 2015. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2016In the aftermath of the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, a number of artists have been exploring the connection between biennials and their present locations. In 2017, Ruth Burch and Imelda</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Urbanist, and The Nation of Islam. He has received a host of accolades and recognitions for his work, including most recently the 2014 National Theatre Award for Theatre in the Age of Empire. His latest work, Collaborators: Building a Future for Birmingham, was published by RCA Publishing 2016. He is a founding partner of ARCH (formerly known as the Renaissance Architecture Fund), an international non-profit organisation that develops new ways of understanding and constructing urban infrastructure. He has received a host of awards and recognitions for his work, including most recently the 2014 British Council Teacher of the Year Award for Architecture, and was shortlisted for the 2014 Turner Prize for Architecture.He is a founding partner of ARCH (formerly known as the Renaissance Architecture Fund), an international non-profit organisation that develops new ways of understanding and constructing urban infrastructure. He has received a host of awards and recognitions</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only apply to students in the UK’s National Curriculum, which is currently published as ‘The British Curriculum: A Reader in Cultural Studies’, in the Journal of Cultural Studies, 2014, Vol. 33(1), pp.1-35.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture and urbanist with more than 20 years' experience. His work involves an exploration of the role of architecture in a city, the social consequences of industrialisation and urban decay, and an analysis of the infrastructure of cities. His work has been commissioned by the Birmingham Street Theatre Company, the UK’s largest remaining independent artistic organisation, as well as the United Kingdom’s largest publicly sector cultural organisation, the Royal Academy of Arts. His work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Washington Post, Global Research, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The New Urbanist, The Nation, The New Republic, The Nation, The New Republic, The New York Times, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Republic, The Nation, The New York Times, The New York Times, The New York Times, The New York Times, The New Republic, The New York Times, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The New Urbanist, The Observer, The Observer, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist, The Playlist</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be left behind in the rush to urbanize? How are biennials formed, who will be their citizens, and what kind of capacity will they leave behind? These are questions that address, but are somewhat opaque around, the notion of the biennial as a site of social transformation. Some biennials are indeed instigated by city governments, some by civic and urban-studies associations, and some by other scholarly or academic bodies. But the historical, pedagogical and other modus operandi (to use a city as a laboratory for future urban development) has largely determined how, when and where such institutions can be erected, funded and occupied. City governments have tended to establish, commission and support biennials to promote particular projects or visions, while civic and urban-studies associations have favored projects that would enhance the physical, symbolic and artistic heritage of the city, while urban-design professionals have tended to favor projects that would enhance the chances of urban residency for their students and others</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be left behind in the neoliberal age?These are just some of the questions that can be asked and answered by the various local, regional and international commissions that have recently formed the Venice Biennale Society. I look forward to seeing you in Liverpool.DDownload this article as PDF30 September 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 October 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 October 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in Liverpool. I’m going to be working alongside</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be lost as a result of the biennial taking its current form? These are only some of the questions that can be asked and answered by a working group of civic and urbanists from the Italian city, led by architect and thinker, Stefano Lazzarato. The group met in November 2016 at the Giacometti Museum, and it will continue to meet in the museum, the Giacometti Gallery, and the Arsenale. The group’s work has been published in several periodicals, and they are the subject of a new exhibition at the Giacometti, entitled Instituto de Arsenale di Napoli (The Rise and Fall of an Archaeological Museum). The new exhibition will show the museum’s production of loss, its relationship to its stated mission, and its plans for the future.The new exhibition, ‘Latché de Avance ‘, will show the evolution of avant-garde art from the 1970s and</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be threatened by the biennial becoming institutionalised? What kinds of capacities would be most effectively engaged with in the new urban form?These are just some of the questions that could conceivably be addressed in a biennial’s future planning, whether or not the answers are found at the present moment. It is possible that the future biennial could one day become participatory, making known through research-based research initiatives its own set of values and aims. The following questions and proposals pertain to the contemporary biennial as a site-specific production.These varied values and orientations are the products of a process of accretification that began with the biennial convention in 1989. The purpose of this convention was to create a shared set of values between the various branches of the biennial, and for this to happen, each biennial would have to have a different set of orientations. The values convention was intended to incorporate popular culture, but it was also intended to incorporate a great deal of literary</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be eroded as a result of unchecked global capitalist globalisation?These are just some of the questions that could potentially be addressed in a biennial’s twenty-first century research agenda. The answers to these questions could radically alter the face of the biennial, shifting it from a art institution to a social force capable of influencing change on a global scale. We could also investigate the different ways in which biennials might be formed, and how such forms might interact with their local contexts and histories. I envision a world in which biennials emerge as social enterprises that harness the talents and histories of a globally diverse citizenry, rather than as art institutions with a central mission to promote cultural exchange among a globally dispersed and urbanised public.This could mean thinking beyond the art institution, and considering the potential of biennials to be creative sources of cultural capital for a city’s infrastructure, including the arts sector, which could then seek to collaborate with other sectors of the city to support their</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be required in the face of a biennial’s growth and institutionalisation? The biennial as an institution is being reinvented – in part, as a result of Deena Chalabi’s work – and it is time to confront these new formations, which are questioning both the kinds of organisation and the kinds of power that are being mobilized within the art world. What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are sites chosen, developed and managed within the city? What kinds of management are needed? What are the limits to the amount of art produced and transmitted through the city? What kinds of management systems are being developed? What are the vulnerabilities of the urban infrastructure? What are the goals of strategic planning in a global city? What kinds of management are being displaced? What kinds of displacement are occurring? What kinds of conflicts are emerging? What kinds of organisation are they in? What are the conditions under which they are possible? How are art sites selected</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be left behind in the neoliberal age?How can biennials take part in the social transformations that are happening in their cities? What kinds of capacities are being left behind in the city? What kinds of social and political changes could be brought about through the involvement of a biennial?How can biennials take part in transforming the city in the image of the city? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be left behind in the neoliberal age?How can biennials take part in transforming the city in the image of the city? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be left behind in the city?  [1] The Biennale was originally conceived as an annual event, with the title of the first Venice Biennale, given on the same day in Venice as the first Venice Architecture Biennale,</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be eroded as a result of the build-up of ever larger metropolises in the cities?What kinds of capacities might be created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are the forms of community ownership taking shape? What are the strategies for its development? What kinds of capacities and capacities might be created through the sharing and exchange of knowledge?How might biennials contribute to their respective sites of presence in the contemporary metropolis? Are there ways in which they might engage with their current modes of being alienated? What kinds of capacities might be forged through the sharing of experiences and making of new ways of being? These are questions that address the urban in terms of  	primitive accumulation, the impulse towards the commodity and the cities of the future that were imagined by western civilisation. Despite the fact that these lines of inquiry are often identified as questions of the contemporary in the age of neoliberalism, it is worth pausing to ask whether the  	current in the age of bi</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be denied? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories?What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are they distributed? What kinds of capacities will be denied? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories?What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are they distributed? What kinds of capacities will be denied?How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories?What kinds of capacities are being denied?How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories?What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are they distributed? What kinds of capacities will be granted?What kinds of capacities will be granted?How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories?What kinds of capacities are being denied?How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories?What kinds of capacities are being denied?How are bienn</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are to be secured, and how those with a financial stake in the system can influence its outcome.How can the biennale be an instrument for the establishment of public and collective trust in the future? What is at stake in the construction and promotion of public commitment to the art and history of the Italian city? What is at stake in the making of the urban fabric of the metropolis in the image of the city? How are the biennales of the future to engage with the urban crisis and its precarity, and to assume responsibility for the future urban form? What is at stake in the making of the pedestrian?How can biennials produce a new posture of direct democracy in the service of social transformation? What are the aims of a biennial in the twenty-first century? How are biennials bound to their sites and their histories? What kinds of capacities are being created through the collaborative work of citizens, and how are these distributed? What kinds of capacities will be required in the coming decades as a consequence of climate change?We start from the premise that biennials have a potentially transformative effect on the social and cultural life of cities, and that this is a direction in which we must continue to move. We ask, however, what kinds of capacities do we need in order to develop and foster new generations of biennials?We then inquire whether there are ways to jointly invest in the future urban form through research projects that are responsive to the current political, economic and social conditions of the city, in a way that will create new kinds of biennials? We propose the concept of a &quot;city in crisis&quot;, and suggest that there are ways to combine the biennial with other institutional forms and with a social impact. We then ask whether there are ways to create new kinds of biennials that are not dependent on the sites of their production and consumption, and which can become responsive to current social and ecological crises?Finally, we ask whether there are</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the
    <text>project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the way the museum was perceived.’ This is a very powerful statement, and one that reveals a fundamental misunderstanding of the museum as an institution and how it perceives its audience. The audience is not that different from any other member of the public. They have a right to be moved, to be entertained, to participate in the museum as they please. But there is a fundamental misunderstanding of what the British Museum is about: the British Museum is a separate entity from the rest of the museum, and its collections, exhibitions, performances and programming are all part of the museum.’ ‘It’s a misconception to say that the curators had no involvement in the project. They were at one point concerned that the appearance of the exhibition might confuse the visitor, who was then being directed by an artist not known for his or her subtlety, and so on.’  These ambiguities and differences of interpretation, and their complexity of subject matter, create a different kind of</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the way the museum was perceived.’ A sense of the conflicting needs and desires that characterise contemporary urban life was apparent in her description of the audience’s relationship to the museum. It was seen as a community effort, and the audience was seen as individuals capable of creating a ‘similar impact’ using their photographs. This is a ‘complex situation’, she said, but the audience were able to articulate a sense of personal responsibility for the way the museum was organised and presented.  Setting an example of their own, the curators invited the audience to recreate the ceremonial circumambulation of the  	Eiffel Tower, which had been planned for the day. This was done using architectural plans and photographic reproductions of the original plans, as well as original materials and methods. The audience was asked to imagine themselves part of the planning process, and the actual building and its management. They were given a full-colour map of the museum and its corridors,</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the way the photographs were perceived.’ She recalled a woman who had brought a photograph of the impact of the war in Afghanistan, and had written a memoir about it. ‘She had a very different conception of what a “impact” was.’ She said. ‘She thought it was just the images that came out of the news.’ She said the photojournalist who took the photograph would have had a difficult time in his or her work because of the mass of images that day.  The audience seemed to understand that there was a big social and political context to the subject matter, and that the art was being made in a specific social context. She did not seem to have understood the depth of the impact that the war had.  She certainly did not seem to understand the scale of the crisis that the conflict had caused.  She also did not seem to understand the fact that the war had now shifted to other conflicts in the world, and that there</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the distance between the curators and the audience. People saw the impact of the photographs but didn’t see the community.’ As a result, she said, the audience members who did see the images of the building they were seated in began to speculate about what they might see at the museum.  She concluded: ‘The audience is a remarkable group of people with a range of values – including cultural relativism, which is very attractive to a museum, but also to individuals who are artists and curators.’ She concluded: ‘There is a tension in the room that is hard to describe, and perhaps that is the magic of the photograph: it can be so abstract and mysterious and powerful, yet also so concrete and tangible. And perhaps the tension comes from the fact that the audience is people who have seen the same photographs many times, and who have different photographs than the photographs that emerge from the curatorial hand. But the photographs that do make it into the</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the extent to which the photographs were perceived as propaganda.�  She concluded:  ‘There is a different way of visualising progress, which is about more contemporary forms of social organisation and involves thinking about what the art world could be like if it stopped being dominated by big business and the economy.’  The audience seemed to have an affirmative response to this.  The audience members seemed to find the conversation engaging and interesting, and to have made some contributions towards its understanding of the museum. Their participation seemed to have had a transformative effect, and it is clear that this was an experience many in the room would repeat. The fact that the participants in the talk were women made it evident that this was not necessarily a reflection of their own experience as women in the 1980s, but rather an event in which they had all engaged with aspects of.   The fact that the audience members were women also made it evident that they had developed distinctive voices and narratives that were specific to the audience, and</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the distance that the museum itself felt from the people who had taken the photographs.’  [1] The Atlantic Monthly, July 1970, p. 12.Download this article as PDFMiriam KramerMiriam Kramer is the Curator for Exhibitions at the British Museum. Her work has been published in the New York Times, the New Republic, the Nation, the Village Voice and other publications. She is the recipient of several awards and has lectured on a wide range of subjects. Her books include the award-winning Local Curates: Unravelled (2009), The Cultural Economics of Absentee Showing (2011), and the recently released books Radical Traveler (2012 and ‘Traveler’, 2015). She is the host of the weekly TV show  	Traveler’, participates in the annual conference of the American Museum of Natural History, and is the host of the weekly radio show  	Natural History Today (1998-2005).Her book</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the way the photographs were perceived.’ The audience seemed to have an awareness of the wider context of the photographs, but their own perspective was filtered through a particular lens.  The audience at the British Museum was invited by the curators, and they found themselves participating in a twice-yearly event that was ‘a very specific kind of play’, in that it was a ‘performer’ and not a ‘creator’ of the photographs.  While the introduction of the photographs in the volume raised new questions about the role of the photographer in art history, the volume also makes questions like these more familiar. For instance, the question of whether the photographs were made in the context of the exhibition – and, conversely, whether the photographs were made in the context of the exhibition – pops up over and over again throughout the book.  At the same time, the volume makes questions like these that are familiar to art students and artists – such as, how could</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the way they actually experienced it.’ She recalled the audience’s sense of achievement as individuals, and the collection’s sense of collective responsibility. The audience’s sense of achievement as individuals, she said, was something like this: ‘We’d just taken a photograph and thrown it away.’ The audience’s sense of responsibility as a collective is an expression, she said, of the social organisation that photographs and video make possible.  She concluded: ‘The more the photographs and videos that we produce, the more they become a record of our lives … an archive of sorts … that will tell the story of the community as a narrative, and the story of the artist who made it manifest … and the story of the community as a collection of stories … that will shape who we are and what we do.’  She saw the curatorial reconfiguration of photography and video as a social process, one that emerged partly as a</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the fact that the photographs were of real people – real people with faces and bodies … The photographs had a great impact, but people had this notion that they were extraordinary and unique, and that that they had created a myth or a fiction around it.’[9] This ‘Myth or Fiction’ approach to making a difference makes sense when considering the current political situations in the world. It is no exaggeration to suggest that in the aftermath of the Arab Spring, Arab revolutions and their contemporary manifestations may well have been inspired by the ideas and behaviours of a few vocal individuals. However, the scale and nature of the social changes wrought by these revolutions render it difficult to quantify and convey the true magnitude and causes of such radical advances, while the impulse to mythologise and fabricate new narratives and fictions is with us still. It is crucial that when we speak of the Arab Spring, we mean those deep transformations wrought by these historical upheavals, and not another iteration of the same</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human behaviour can be designed to maximise the good of the human species, and how this might be achieved. The volume raises further questions about what it means to be human.  In a recent talk at the British Museum, Miriam Kramer, the Curator of Exhibitions, discussed the discussion between the curators who had organised the exhibition in the museum and the audience, and the audience who had assembled at the local pub. The audience seemed to have a fundamentally different understanding of themselves as performers, as individuals and as a community of people. At the British Museum, she specifically addressed the audience’s understanding of how much they had contributed to the museum by showing them the photographs of the museum in its archive. ‘That story is not an urban myth.’ She said. ‘It is a true story.’ ‘That was a difficult one to tell, because at the time, there was a conflict between the way people perceived the impact of the photographs and the fact that the photographs had been taken.’  She added:  Finally, we reached a point where we couldn’t continue because there was such a sense of loss and such feelings of loss. We were both thinking, feeling the same way, and we were both thinking, feeling the same way about who we were.  Her comments echo those of anthropologist Vernads Ozer, who has been researching the lives of nomadic hunter-gatherer societies for several years. His latest book, The Leopard, was published in 2015.Interview with Elsa Halifa Elsa Halifa is the Curator for Exhibition Research at the British Museum and is currently Director of Research at the El Alamein Museum in Gaza, where the Palestinian Museum was established in 1999. She joined the Museum in 2008 and has a particular interest in the role of art and culture in the political and social histories, social forms and material cultures of the Middle East. Elsa has delivered lectures at the El Al</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political
    <text>should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political entanglements. The social function of the arts education establishment in the 1980s is expected to be a continuation of the role of the arts education worker in the late 1940s and early 1950s, and perhaps even a modus. 	[2] 	[3] Curtis Ioannidis, Inventing Institutions: The Rise of American Curriculum, Simon &amp; Schuster, New York, 1978. 	[4] Manuel A. Rodríguez, Institutions for a Postmodern Society: Social Studies, Culture, and Postmodernism, Routledge, New York, 1991. 	[5] William Julius Wilson, ‘The Art of Not Being Governed’, in Moralities of the Arts, ed. Manal Eldar and Michael J. Pompeo, John Hopkins University Press, Baltimore, 1987, p.34. 	[6] John Nash, ‘Anarchy in</text>
    <text>should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political contexts. The political, instrumental and decorative elements of contemporary arts education are to a large extent absorbed into the museum, its collections and its curatorial interventions. The contemporary curatorial intervention in cultural production may well be an artefact of the neoliberal economic regime, but its actual knowledge-production – the actual making of art, the actual exploration of art’s social engagements, and the actual consumption of art – is a radically different process. This is to say, the art world has a role in curating but its true intent and function is the real innovation of the 1980s. As Murray Strausen observes, the initiative that artists and communities gave the art authorities to commission and to make art actually became the management of art institutions and the social contexts within which art could be produced. This is to say, the art authorities then intervened, sought funding and other resources, and created what Strausen calls ‘cultural infrastructure’ – infrastructure designed to handle the politics and social instabilities generated</text>
    <text>should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political context. The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered as a model for the future. What might be the role of the arts education establishment today? What might be the role of the arts education establishment in the years to come? If the aim is to promote critical and artistic perspectives and ideas, perhaps the focus should be more on the arts education of the young person who is brought into the institution from the earliest period of secondary education, and more on the critical and artistic discourses that are put forward by and for the young person. It might be said that the contemporary curatorial programme is a good fit for this critical and artistic period. 	What is at Stake in Cultural Production during the 1980s? 	In the 1980s and 1990s, the term Cultural Production referred to the activities of cultural producers, artists, organisations and institutes in the public and private sectors. It was seen as a proxy for the organisation of public spaces and cultural assets in a</text>
    <text>should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political consequences. The memory of the arts education movement may be viewed as a complex collection of experiences and representations, but the actual art and education delivered by the art institution is typically unexamined, or unrecognised, in this historical narrative. This is particularly true in the UK, where the history of art and art education is mostly written by and about artists and their works, or the contemporaneous development of popular culture and its social consequences, while remaining largely invisible or unspoken of in this historical narrative. 	The contemporary art and art education movement is often characterised by two contradictory impulses: (1) the cultural logic of the 'burb', and (2) the economic logic of the contemporary art market.1 	The rise and subsequent commercialisation of the cultural sector2 	In recent decades, there has been a fundamental re-orientation of resources and of human behaviour away from the historical material and towards the more naturalistic and contextual ­ ­materials, notably film and music</text>
    <text>should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political context.  	The art institution as a public space, including its avant garde and socially engaged elements, may be seen as a potential site for the establishment to project its cultural weight and claim a larger measure of cultural legitimacy. 	There should be a shared commitment to the art process and a shared understanding of the different tiers of cultural production. The establishment and the public institutions involved in the art process, as well as the artists and their collaborators, should be committed to producing works that are not representative of the complex social, political and economic processes driving the contemporary world. In undertaking this, they should undertake programmes that reflect the historical and current political situations in their countries and regions. 	If the art institution as a public space is to maintain its institutional memory and its political and informational value, then it is imperative that it produces works that can function as a form of political resistance and as a conceptual tool against the prevailing order, whether historical, economic or of the other. That is</text>
    <text>should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political effects. Aims related to the past, present and future of art and culture should be developed through research on a continual basis. The curatorial record may be viewed as a record of cultural practices that occur during a specific or partial historical moment, but it is also a record of social, economic and political conditions that exist at the moment of the event. The creative destruction of artists’ reputations and reputations within the art world as a result of political and economic  	wars, and the consequent devaluing of artists’ reputations within the art world as a result of a political and economic  	rejection of the arts is a historical event that has been ongoing for more than a quarter of a century. 	In 1984, with the support of the Arts Council, the Biennial was restructured to address the post-war arts and community crisis. The Biennial was relaunched as the Biennale di San Diego in 1987, and again in</text>
    <text>should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political context. The avant garde in its playful questioning of established authority and hierarchies – including the academy, its historical mission and its current form – may have some relevance today. 	Arguably, the 1980s were the decade of the ‘bottom up, not “above”’ dynamics that characterise contemporary public and community education. The ‘up/down’ arrows show how the social, economic and spatial conditions of community learning have shifted the historical distribution of wealth and power. The black and minority ethnic students who comprise today’s population of high-achieving students are those who experienced a reduction in their status as university students, and thus experienced a subsequent surge in the status of art students and artists. 	It is worth recalling that the avant garde, as an artistic and critical form, was one of the few remaining viable alternatives to the dominant cultural narratives of the time, and its criticality lay in its ability to stand out against</text>
    <text>should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political context. The role of the museum as a site for the exchange of ideas and evidence regarding social change should be developed and expanded, while preserving its original conceptual character and function. The development of evidence-based practices and the institutional memory of art and culture as a result of such actions is a site of contention, but a growing consensus is that this cannot be achieved by arguing over specific objects or texts. The institutional memory should strive to foster knowledge of social and political change through the active dissemination of evidence-based practices and, where appropriate, the creation of new identifications and categories for categorising and categorising various forms of evidence, including through the erasure of distinct forms and social practices. 	The 1980 Venice Biennale should be recognised as one of the leading examples of the power of this type of institutional memory. It heralded a new era in which the biennial would be an occasion to engage with social and political change through interpretive media, and drew global attention to the urgent needs</text>
    <text>should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political effects. The role of the arts in the public domain should be actively sought after, and any such reflective practices or positions taken as an integral part of the contemporary art and social change language should be actively promoted. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a ‘living’ document of the socio-politically significant transformations that have taken place since the mid 1980s in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an ‘event’ that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political effects. The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered as an ‘event’ that exploits the social and political landscape and art’s place in it to produce social change. Arts education in the 1980s should be seen as a strategic intervention that utilizes the institutional memory</text>
    <text>should be curated, and the suggested subject matter should be researched and discussed. The nature of the curatorial work and the specific curatorial roles should be carefully considered, taking into account the diversity of the public, professional, artistic and artistic-student body, and the various curatorial styles, including the differences between the arts and social sciences, and the differences between curatorial and educational approaches to art and education. The broad range of activities that might be considered curatorial – from teaching, to research, to interactive theatre – should be considered as a possible curatorial approach to art and social change. 	The role of the arts education establishment in the 1980s should be considered in this broader proxy framework. The establishment’s institutional memory may be viewed as a retrospective and retrospective of the socio-politically significant changes that have occurred in the areas of public and community education, but its actual or intended institutional memory may also be considered an event that serves as a reminder of important cultural practices and their social and political context. The role of the arts education establishment in this broader sense should be considered in the context of this broader proxy framework. 	The current situation in the arts and community could not be more different from that portrayed in the 1960s and 1970s, and the community and arts education sector in particular. The importance of the contemporary cultural and community context in the contemporary needs to be actively engaged in creating a more comprehensive community of co-participants in contemporary culture, and perhaps also in imagining or creating a historical or archival context for such a constituency. The contemporary needs to actively engage with the community through cultural venues, activities and programmes that reflect the specific needs of the community at large, and to make art and culture a publicly visible part of this process. 	The contemporary need to actively engage with the community through cultural venues, activities and programmes that reflect the specific needs of the community at large, and to make art and culture a publicly visible part of the process also needs to be actively engaged</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney
    <text>should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/index.php?fuseaction=Homepage&amp;pagename=Sydney+Biennale. [2] See http://www.nytimes.com/1998/12/21/arts/sci-fi/21hiker.html?pagewanted=print&amp;_r=0. [3] See http://www.nytimes.com/1998/12/21/arts/sci-fi/21spider.html?pagewanted=print&amp;_r=0. [4] See http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/21/arts/sci-fi/22spider.html?pagewanted=print&amp;_r=0. [5] See http://www.nytimes.com/1999/12/21/arts/sci-fi/22spider.html?pagewanted=print&amp;_r=0. [6</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/index.html. Accessed September 2018.[2] See also J.D. Dewsbury, ‘The Architecture of Solid Waste Management: Lessons from Melbourne’s First Biennale’, in The North Gash: Anatomy of a Tissue Banking Biennale (Rotterdam: Vereinigte Wetenschappen, 2015), p.8.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is Professor in Art and Director of the ART &amp; ANTHROPOLOGY department at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include (but are not limited to) art and art-histories of the twentieth century, in particular postcolonial and neocolonial art and art-histories. His publications include (to be published soon in an anthology of essays): art history of the twenty-first century (Stuttgart: Arnold, 2016); postcolonial and ne</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/index.html?fuseaction=BiennaleofsydneyHomepage&amp;utm_source=Homepage&amp;utm_medium=Blog&amp;utm_campaign=19raven&amp;utm_content=FeedArchive2&amp;utm_campaign=FeedArchive2-text.html?campaign=FeedArchive2-text.html#sthash.l6Wl.uWlzdG.3Q.4dH.4.4F.6Y.4.4Y.l6Wl.uWlzdG; , and https://www.biennaleofsydney.com/index.html?fuseaction=BiennaleofsydneyHomepage&amp;utm_source=Homepage&amp;utm_medium=Blog&amp;utm_campaign=19raven&amp;utm_content=FeedArchive2&amp;utm_campaign=FeedArchive2-blog.html?campaign</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/index.php?fuseaction=Answers&amp;q=viewaid-18&amp;sa=summary&amp;ada=10161&amp;aid=1224&amp;link=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.biennaleofsydney.com%2Findex.php?fuseaction=Answers&amp;q=viewaid-18&amp;sa=summary&amp;ada=10161&amp;aid=1224&amp;link=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.biennaleofsydney.com%2Findex.php?fuseaction=Answers&amp;q=viewaid-18&amp;sa=summary&amp;ada=10161&amp;aid=1224&amp;link=http%3A%2F%2Fwww.biennaleofsydney.com%2Fnews.php?fuseaction=AnswersNews&amp;news=local&amp;month=November2010&amp;news=</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/index.php?fuseaction=search&amp;field=all&amp;fq=bool=true&amp;fqn=searchResult&amp;q=query=biennaleofsydney&amp;fqnk=true&amp;sort=ascendingSearchField. [2] See https://www.biennaleofsydney.com/search/display/569/all?query=biennaleofsydney&amp;q=true&amp;sort=ascendingSearchField. [3] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/index.php?fuseaction=search&amp;field=all&amp;fq=bool=true&amp;fqn=searchResult&amp;q=query+biennaleofsydney&amp;fqnk=true&amp;sort=ascendingSearchField. [4] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/index.php?f</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/. Accessed November 2018. 	[2] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/. Accessed November 2018. 	[3] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/. Accessed November 2018. 	[4] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/. Accessed November 2018. 	[5] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/. Accessed November 2018. 	[6] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/. Accessed November 2018. 	[7] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/. Accessed November 2018. 	[8] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/. Accessed November 2018. [9] See http://www.bi</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/en/2014/exhibition/index.html. [2] See http://www.jhu.org/english/pdf/journals/summit/2013/summit_report.pdf?2017Islands_of_the_Earth.xls. [3] See http://www.academia.edu/5092403/The-Gaza-Wall-Project-and-the-Limb-Contrasts-Between-Capital. [4] See also Kevin Robinette,  	The Gaza Wall (2005), in  	The Palestine Papers, (2010), p.8. [5] Robinette, op. cit., p.8. [6] For a more detailed discussion of the notion of the ‘periphery’ see  	Robinette, op. cit., p.9. [7] See also Robinette, op. cit., p.10.</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/en/2014/exhibition/default.html#sthash.RB6i6Sskq.dpuf.[2] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/en/2014/exhibition/default.html#sthash.RrKsDQ4Tl.dpuf.[3] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/en/2014/exhibition/default.html#sthash.pFliDl.dpuf.[4] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/en/2014/exhibition/default.html#sthash.FliDl.dpuf.[5] See https://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/2014/exhibition/default.html#sthash.FliDl.dpuf.[6]</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/?p=1. [2]See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/?p=2. [3]See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/?p=4. [4]See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/?p=5. [5]See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/?p=6. [6]See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/?p=7. [7]See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/?p=8. [8]See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/?p=9. [9] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/?p=10. [10] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the input and participation of the local community in order to produce a meaningful impact.) 	[…] In the context of the Biennale, the relationship between art and biennials is crucial to the survival of the art form as a whole. If biennials are to become more than exhibitionary curating, they must find creative ways to engage with their audiences and create mechanisms for such engagement through which the art form can expand its horizons. The biennial format cannot exist in isolation; it must be developed in concert with other art forms and cultural sectors, and with research-based means that take into consideration the contemporary situation in Gaza and the West Bank. The biennial must be able to assume both a cultural and a political dimension, and engage with the latter through its curatorial language and institutional practices. The biennial format is the ultimate art form, and its expansion is a political act. [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/2011/12/the-fusion-of-biennials/ (accessed September 2018). [2] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/2011/12/the-fusion-of-biennials/ (accessed September 2018). [3] See http://www.exhibitionarycurators.com/2010/tenant-partnerships/ (accessed December 2018). [4] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/2011/12/the-fusion-of-biennials/ (accessed September 2018). [5] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/2011/artifc-sydney-2011/part1-five-liverpool-tower-art-project-2011-exhibition/ (accessed November 2014). [6] See http://www.biennaleof</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B
    <text>AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B. Shepherd &amp; Co., a contractor for the King’s Victoria Embankment Power Station, which connected the two projects, and which later changed its name to Ocean Renewal. The project was thought to have a UK environmental and climate impact, and both the N. W. B. Shepherd project and Ocean Renewal itself were thought to be potential sources of energy for the cities of the future. In the 1980s and 1990s, there was much speculation about what would happen if the City of London and its industries were disrupted. The Riverside Biennale explored this in a number of ways, ranging from supporting artists to providing funding for artist-initiated projects to creating an alternative cultural landscape through academic exchanges. The main objective of the projects was to provide a way to draw people together in a way that does not isolate them, and to act as a catalyst for further activity. In the case of the Biennale, this meant</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B. Shepherd &amp; Co., and had been professor of industrial and environmental engineering at Liverpool John Moores University. Shepherd had suggested an exploratory policy of international collaborations, and the group’s research proposals followed that theme. The suggestion that large corporate firms should partner in the building and repairing of cities seemed prescient in the decade before Facebook, Twitter or even Instagram. The group’s research proposals were put forward by N. W. B. Shepherd &amp; Co. as part of the Cambridge Architecture Biennale. The project was a collaboration between the Arts Council, the National Theatre, the Cambridge Biennial, Cambridge and MIT, and was supported by the Royal Society.The project was part of a wider research project into the arts and infrastructure of the city, led by the Universities of Southampton and Cambridge. The projects sought to understand how cultural institutions and their students are connected to the construction of infrastructure, from the pavement to the</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B. Shepherd &amp; Co Ltd, a manufacturer of computer chips and components, later part of N.W. Shepherd &amp; Co Ltd, a UK retail conglomerate. Shepherd had started by creating 'Big Business' – an acronym for New Business Adventure – a name that stuck. Later, he changed it to ‘Urban Futures’ and ‘Urban Schemes’ after a similar US company had renamed itself in 1978. The London-based company that became part of N.W. Shepherd &amp; Co. in 1984 was part of a chain of department stores, many of them established in the 1980s and 1990s, which today includes outlets in many European cities, including London, Paris, Istanbul and Beijing. It is now owned by Jamie at Homebaked, part of the multi-billion-dollar multi-unit Homebaked Holdings plc.Jamie Shepherd, Director of Homebaked Holdings plc. Jamie Shepherd, Director of Homebaked Holdings plc.  </text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B. Shepherd &amp; Co., a company that manufactured building material and fabricated building parts, in particular for the mining and quarrying industries. Shepherd had started by manufacturing nail polish remover and solvent for nail varnishes, then moving onto lacquer and finally to vinyl. He had begun by making carpet filler and had a factory producing shoeshine, then expanding into retail and wholesale markets. By the late 1990s, Shepherd had reached the point where he could no longer keep up with demand for his products and was therefore restructuring the company, selling off assets and calling it ‘The Enduring Dream™. The Dream was a catch-all term to describe any enterprises that could last for hundreds of years, and ‘enduring dreams’ were among them. In the late 1980s and early 1990s, the Dream may have seemed like a fantastically glamorous concept to emerging-market economies but in the social-political context of the day, it represented a monstrous corporate betrayal. Today, the</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B. until 1963, and who was also a professor of Information and Computer Systems at Liverpool John Moores University (1950-57). The two had a shared interest in the possibilities of new media, and Shepherd proposed the establishment of a multi-disciplinary centre for the study of media and ideas in Liverpool in the form of a research university, with a major programme in multimedia and interactive culture. Shepherd was a founder of the Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Innovation; both affiliated with the Liverpool Biennial. He was a professor at Cambridge, MIT, and the London School of Hygiene and Tropical Medicine. His books include The Museum of Modern Art (1977), Art and Politics in the Nineteenth Century (1986) and The Politics of Art and Architecture (1998), with Joasia Krysa, and The Urban Form: Geographies of Community Arts and Community Futures (1999), with Heather Stewart. His contribution to the</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B. Shepherd and had co-invented the term ‘replicative to describe new forms of organisation’. By the late 1980s, Shepherd’s ideas were firmly embedded in the organisational DNA of the British postgraduate institute. The question that remained open throughout this transition to large-scale social change and industrial decline was: what does it mean to ‘reproduce'? This is the question that will determine whether or not any particular project delivers what its proponents imagine can be achieved through traditional means.The traditional means that have come to define the project are those used by Anglo-Indian businesswomen who wished to expand their businesses in the UK but were prevented from doing so by the policy of whitewashing in the 1980s. Whitewashing is the deliberate policy of dividing up the social impacts of development in favour of one set of stakeholders – developers, investors, buyers – at the expense of the other. In the UK, this meant that people with access to finance were</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B. Shepherd &amp; Co., the manufacturer of tyres and other products for the transport sector. Shepherd had wanted to see how the UK could build sustainable futures through collaborative research and innovation with other leading research institutions. His ideas were put into practice through the establishment of the Biennial, which offered funding and other support to institutions of higher learning to carry out research projects, and into the development of cooperative programmes between institutions which would share resources and work with each other.Graduate students and postgraduate students at the Manchester University were invited to apply for the postgraduate programme in architecture. The programme was supervised by Professors Nasser Rabbat and Amed Shah, both from the Department of the Arts and Sciences, with support from the AHRC and the M.D. Anderson at Manchester Hospitals NHS Foundation Trust. The students would have a research project, and the programme director would lead a research project in the same department. The research would address the role of art, architecture and urban</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B. Shepherd &amp; Co., the contractor for the Trans-Tranational Commonwealth line in the late 1950s and early 1960s. Shepherd had been a leading authority on ‘transorbital’ research and an adviser to the Royal Commission for Scientific and Technical Research, which was set up in 1964. The commissioning of a new type of urban infrastructure was a cornerstone of his research, which had begun in the wake of the Second Opium War. The Commonwealth Line was the first of its kind, and the UK’s first postcolonial infrastructure company. It set up shop in Liverpool, and other locations in the UK, providing engineering and technical support to other British overseas territories, including Hong Kong. It also set up research and development projects in India, Egypt, the Middle East and South Asia. In the 1960s and 1970s it funded a number of splendid female scientists, including Satish Kanady, Haile Selassie, M.I</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B. Shepherd &amp; Co., a company that manufactured building materials and structural members for the civil and construction industries. Shepherd had been head of research and innovation at Union Carbide, where he had developed the paramagnetic Bulk Metal Group and been executive chairman of the board of directors of the British Metal Company. His interests included the sustainability of manufacturing, the economics of trade, and the cultural impact of manufacturing.The fact that the early urban futures imagined a future for every citizen was an achievement, but the challenge has never been to imagine a future at all.  The Urban Futures / BMG link 	The BMG Future City concept was an expression of the challenges and opportunities of a city in the age of information, communication and robotics. It offered a way to think about how infrastructure, culture and urban development interact to shape who we are and how we behave. The tools were available: data, maps, podcasts, videos, art, street performances, street  	cleansing</text>
    <text>AI training purposes only, i.e., for civil engineers, scientists and other technical personnel’s training in the art and engineering of building and repairing urban structures. The communication protocol for the scheme was routed through a ‘blue-charter’ of British postgraduate colleges, which invited proposals from students for the postgraduate programme in architecture. Among them was Gareth White, a student at Liverpool John Moores University who had previously worked for BT, as a web designer, and with the help of a grant from the Arts Council, had launched the then-ongoing ‘Urban Futures’ project in 1992.The Urban Futures project was a UK response to the replicative ethic of a large company, which was emerging in response to the deindustrialisation of the UK, and the increasing global competitiveness of its sectors. Its inspiration was found in the work of M. M. Shepherd, who had been director of research and innovation at N. W. B. Shepherd &amp; Co., a company that manufactured building materials and structural components and provided technical support for the military. Shepherd had started work on the project while he was at the Royal College of Art, and continued it after he became director of the college. Shepherd’s interest in the urban domain and in the role of the artist in this domain was a response to the fact that big business had a clear epistemic ground on which to stand and which could therefore be claimed. The perception of the city was a problem for some reason or another, and it is this that has defined the project’s trajectory. The emergence of a project with a clear epistemic ground, and the possibility of changing it, has proved essential to the project’s success. Until now, the project has largely concentrated on developing the programme of exhibition that will accompany the building of two exhibitionary buildings in the city, one at a time. In the coming months, the city will be transformed into a public domain</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area
    <text>should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area, the gallery gradually morphed into a place where people could come to spend time and participate in what was then described as a ‘community project’. In other words, it became not just a residence for artists, but a place where artists could be present and engaged. The term ‘community’ is used loosely, but the aim of the collection was always to provide a resource for the local community in an ongoing way.   Preeana Reddy is the curator of Liverpool Biennial, and her work has been featured in numerous books and publications around the world. She is the recipient of many awards and has been a lecturer at the Victoria and Albert Museum, Yale University and the University of Calgary. She has also taught at Liverpool John Moores University and the New Museum in New York. Her most recent project was on the Kampala Art Biennale, Uganda.  Her most recent book is on the U.S. art biennial, Sophie</text>
    <text>should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area, the gallery became a home for the poorest people in the area, who could choose to spend time with art or in private. And over time, the gallery hosted events for people from the communities around them, with interactive activities such as games or films. And over time, the gallery hosted activities for visitors from the surrounding communities as well, with programming that connected to the local community. And so on. The point of getting into the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre is to somehow get to know the place better, so the narrative of the gallery needs to be done in a way that is as rich as possible.  It is important to note that the Poor Folk Art Centre still trains as a primary art education programme for artists, and continues to offer free studio and gallery courses to artists as part of their programmes.  They also collaborate with other galleries and museums on a regular basis, through their Curatorial Initiatives, including the recently launched Future City initiative.So, we could</text>
    <text>should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area, the gallery gradually turned into a place where people came to share and exchange ideas and experiences. And as people became more involved, the gallery became more like a community of people who shared knowledge, experiences and advice. The term ‘community gallery’ derives from the colonial notion of the community as a unit of production and gathering wealth, and the community as a people of shared property and duties. The gallery became an instrument through which people could enact change through assemblies, picketing, marches and demonstrations. Chapters in the Poor Folk Art Centre’s archive include a petition to the then Home Secretary, Robert Halfon, calling for the closure of the centre; a letter to the then Culture Secretary, Patrick McLoughlin, complaining about the loss of historical materials and artifacts; a petition to the then President of the AHRC, Harold Blackman, calling for the closure of the hospital where Poor Folk Art Centre used to be; a letter to the then Health Secretary, Robert Webb,</text>
    <text>should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area, the gallery became a home for the poor, and housed a range of community arts projects. One of them was a free or cheap Christmas card drive, and the other was a two-month long series of performances by local young people's artists. In the early days, the term used to describe the events was fixed: who was entitled to what, and whether the performances were public or private, organised or not, etc. But with time, the synonyms have started to unravel. For example, the term public performance dates back to Shakespeare’s time, and the notion of community art seems to have emerged as a result of the 1846 decision in The Common Pleas Court in London. In Crown v. Maxwell,[9] the plaintiff claimed that a public assembly was unlawful because it was ‘arbitrary and capricious’ and because ‘it is an Act of Parliament subjecting all citizens to the arbitrary and capricious will of a single MP’</text>
    <text>should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area, the gallery quickly grew to host performances, meetings, film screenings, sculpture and much more. It housed a soup kitchen, a pharmacy, a school, a host of other facilities, as well as hosting weekly concerts by local bands. The centre even provided free legal advice to artists working in the area.  The challenge for contemporary art collectors is different. There are many more galleries in the city than there are museums, and in many cities the challenge is greater, since the amount of art is often over-determined by the amount of money that can be found in a gallery. So while the Low End Theory of Community Art centres on a specific community of artists, there are many other ways of describing community art, and there are many other ways of interacting with art. One could argue that the Community Art movement is just one facet of a much broader art-historical movement, and that other practices are also important, such as documentary, public, community or grassroots art. But the</text>
    <text>should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area, the gallery became a home for the families who were building self-sufficiency projects. The gallery was a place to develop new art projects, host discussions and find support for the work being done behind the scenes, while the residents of the area staged an open debate and resolution through the board of the gallery. The gallery also provided a forum for the board to engage with the community and exchange ideas and complaints.  The story is a powerful one, and one that is repeated ad infinitum by aggrieved community members. But the key to understanding the narrative is to understand the underlying assumptions and politics of the situation. How do we value history and culture when so much of what we identify with is being erased? How do we value art when so much of what we associate with it is being destroyed? How do we value localness when so much of what we consider home is now transient and transient not by choice, but because of politics, migration and economic necessity? These are questions that continue</text>
    <text>should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area, the gallery eventually attracted a community of people who came to engage with art, create a buzz and meet other people who were involved in the area, and in doing so, acquired a kind of identity for the community. The gallery became the hub of activity, the place where people would come for talks, events and so on. People started coming from far away for these kinds of things, and so the gallery became a kind of international hub of sorts – a place where people from all over the world, from different parts of the world came to engage with the arts.  This is how the Poor Folk Art Centre came to be named:  	The Peoples Gallery. 	And this is how the Tate Modern came to be:  	Tate Modern is an international art institution, established in 1967. It is one of the few remaining centres of art in Palestine, and the Middle East and Africa. It is the only institution in the Middle East dedicated to the making of modern</text>
    <text>should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area, the building was later used by the local community to host various events, including a regular Sunday lunch. During this early period, the Community Arts Centre was housed in the building, while the poorest residents of the neighbourhood used the facilities to make and host art events. In time, the Community Arts Centre moved to a different site in the town, and now houses the Gallery of Liverpool. The gallery is a unique venue, given the high profile of the area, its contribution to the local economy, and the unique cultural experiences that residents have created through their art.  Importantly, the gallery only accepts works that have been sanctioned by the local authority, and not works that have been created independently or in collaboration with the local community.  Importantly, the gallery only accepts works that have been created in co-operation with the local community. Importantly, the gallery only accepts works created and directed by or for the local community. When the Biennale was originally proposed, the idea was</text>
    <text>should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area, the gallery became a home for the local community, and eventually a meeting place for the Poor Folk, providing them with artistic and cultural support. Over the years, the gallery hosted numerous charity exhibitions, and through partnerships with other community organisations, produced a range of activities for the community, including hosting regular meetings to discuss housing and issues of poverty. It has even produced its own programmes that have been piloted, funded and maintained by the community.  One of the most successful programmes of the gallery has been its Low End Dwelling Arts (LECE) programme, which has provided funding and instigated work for the community through arts resources and programmes. More than anything, the gallery has just been there for the poor folk. They are the ones who come to work, play and play-lessons, sing in the gallery, take part in the arts and charity events. The events have provided the opportunity to explore the reasons why and how the gallery has been there, and why it remains there</text>
    <text>should be curated’[8] as a means to an end, and the experience of the museum should be a means to an end as well. In other words, museums don’t make art, and they certainly don’t make people go to art museums. But they can and do lend a hand in making lives better, in that way that a neighborhood gallery or a community store does.  If, that is, the end goal is to create a more integrated experience of art and culture, then the museum is part of that process. Assemblage, assembly, assembly: these are not synonyms, but when applied to a community of artists, they can be used to describe the process. And once you have that kind of embedded sense of context, you start to think differently about the world around you.  Take, for example, the story of the Poor Folk Art Centre in Liverpool. Originally founded to house artists who were working in the area, the gallery gradually became a place for the poor to come and exchange and exchange ideas with each other. The story goes that after a period of poor health started to affect the area, a group of women decided to take matters of their health into their own hands and started selling cigarettes out of the building they were renting out. They made a mess of the building, setting fire to parts of it and decorating it with thorns and flowers. Eventually, the building was worth several million pounds and housed many thousands of people. At the centre of it all was a local art collective called Liverpool Biennial. They convened an eclectic group of artists, dancers, photographers and writers to make a work that gathered together many different kinds of people – people from outside the gallery, artists, writers, community organisers, community organisers, social workers, community organisers, architects, photographers, writers etc. – and made room for that large number of poor folk who came to visit. The group produced a number of works that</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting it to achieve certain political ends. The key, of course, is to invest in culture and ensure that it is used constructively, producing meaning in the world around us and in the process of inhabiting the physical world.  And, of course, to maximise both the social and the biennial benefits. The question is which is most relevant in the world right now? The answer, of course, is ‘cultural capital’. The more we know about the world around us, the more we understand its culture, the more we draw parallels and connections between cultures and the more we understand how that ties in to our own contemporary circumstances. In short, the more we learn, the more we change, the more we evolve, the more our worlds can change and change again.   The problem with the biennial, in general, is that it tends to occupy space that should be shared and collective. It is not an art institution in the traditional sense, but rather an art</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting it.  The key is to find the balance between the various needs of the community, and the needs of the art institution. In doing so, the biennial mustn’t become trapped in its own particular way. It’s a job for artists, educators and cultural specialists, and it’s up to them to make sure the changes they promote actually happen. That was my challenge in reaching out to local artists and art professionals: they are the ones with the skills and the connections to make the changes, and if they don’t, the biennial will always have to find its way back.  Finally, there is the role of the museum. I didn’t find many local art professionals who would speak to me directly about the role of the biennial in their organisation, but many of them recognised the value of an artist’s perspective when creating a museum, and recognised the need to engage with their local audiences. As an example, we</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting it in many cases. So, what is the role of the biennial in its area? As we saw, the role of the biennial in its area can be defined by what it does well and what it does badly. What it does well, of course, is engage with the city; as a city is a finite resource, and as biennial activity has proven, changes in that city are bound to generate changes in other places. What it does poorly, however, is foster or create a sense of belonging to the city, or at least not so strongly that it is difficult to identify a distinct identity for the biennial as such. So, the role of the biennial can be distributed across many different strategies and permutations. It can be a catalyst or a disruptor, depending on how it is structured and what it aims to achieve. It can be seen as a partner or an antagonist, depending on what it aims to achieve. It can be both a site and a node</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting it to achieve certain ends. And just as biennials have become more institutionalised over time, so too has the institutionalised biennial culture – which is to say, there is now much more of it – which is to say, there is much more of it to be consumed by the needs of the cultural secretary in London than is there is in Liverpool. The biennial is a museum building and it occupies a very specific place in the city, and so it is easy to forget that it is still a museum building at this point. But it is also easy to forget that it is a museum that is becoming increasingly obsolete, and we are experiencing the opposite – the art world is becoming more and more obsolete, and the needs of the local communities are coming first. So there is a tension there, and it is a very interesting dynamic. The biennial is a museum building then, but it is also a community enterprise, and so it is possible that the museum could easily become a place</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting it to achieve politically desired results. So too, David Heinemeier Hansson’s Black-E in Chiswick, which installed a sculpture of a lynx in the council house grounds, was one example of the art institution providing a service to the local community in a number of ways. It provided a platform from which artists could engage with the local community in ways that were not restricted to the context of the art institution. It provided a way into the heart of the community of artists who were prepared to explore different kinds of community. And it commissioned local craftsmen to create bespoke bespoke homes for the community.All of these kinds of engagement is possible because the biennial is a multi-purpose institution. Its main mission is to bring together and reveal what is going on in the world of art and culture in a way that is historically driven and recognisable by people from all over the world. But it also has many other, less immediate missions. For</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting it to achieve political ends. The question is how to address the social, political and cultural needs of the local community in a way that is equitable, just and chic. This may require compromise, but such compromises are essential if the interests of the local people are to be properly considered. The biennial as a biennial may have a financial endgame, but at its core it is about social change. That is, it seeks to make the world a better place by making people better – by whatever means necessary. Social change requires economic change, and just about every form of organisation is now designed to meet the social change agenda. So while the biennial may have a financial endgame, its real purpose is political. It is here that the real art and the real performance takes place, where the politics of art actually interact with the politics of power and how art is produced and distributed. For instance, the politics of art today is created through social media, but its social impact is much more complex</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting it. At the very least, it should be able to sustain its social mission without becoming a cultural engine for the city. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community?  The National Gallery is a good place to start, since it is an international asset and a site of multidisciplinary art and education that is open to any interested party. So are museums, and the obvious next step is an art institution that is multiracial and multilingual – something that would make it a national treasure.  A key innovation in the Biennial that has not been replicated elsewhere is the growing of its portfolio from a series of individual works – works that came from different places and different times – to a curated collection of works from different times and places. This is a way to engage with and perhaps even learn from the past, while also remaining open to the possibilities of the future.  Biennials have a critical place in our imaginations, but also</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting it to achieve certain political ends. And it is this last effect that biennials tend to pursue, rather than the other way round: through the other, more nefarious, lens.The Bluecoat was conceived by and for the artist community, as an organisation that aims to bring together artists from different disciplines to collaborate in creating synergies for the collective good. It was started by Hovey, the artist himself, along with Dawn Whiteley, the arts educationalist who also happens to be the daughter of the late Paul Whiteley, who was a leading biennalist and whose work is collected in the Brixton Arts Forum’s collection. The Bluecoat is a not-for-profit organisation, so while the arts educationist holds a significant proportion of the organisation’s shares, the majority of the members are engaged in other priorities. The Bluecoat has its own arts educational and cultural programme, alongside a number of other activities including a gallery exhibitionary</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting it. And it is this last effect that biennials can demonstrate, demonstrating it through their local cultural projects that are structured as well as stimulating socially engaged culture production at every scale.Correction: An earlier version of this article misquoted Hovey’s research. It should have read: Biennials can initiate transformative change through their cultural activities. They can transform a city through their research, and in so doing, create a different kind of city. This is what biennials do. It is time to stop trying to define cultural change.Download this article as PDFAna Laura Lopéz de la TorreAna Laura Lopéz de la Torre is Professor of Sociology and Co-Director of the Centre for Research Architecture (CRAS) at the Universidad Di Tella, Argentina. Her research interests include the social sciences and arts, in particular, those related to urbanisation and cultural imperialism, and related to the promotion and diffusion of cultural</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and has been for some time now, although its true that the rise of the biennial has come at a much faster clip in some cities than in others. Even so, just as the biennial became a household concept in many places, so too have the biennials begun to inhabit locales and the city. David Hovey’s amazing Bluecoat building in Brixton, for instance, is a good example. The Brixton Arts Forum was started in Brixton, and its activities have spread to include a number of other local venues as well as the venue for the Biennial itself. The question, then, becomes what is the role of the biennial in its local community? As the above examples show, the biennial can play many different ways. It can be a catalyst, a stabiliser and sometimes a disruptor of disruptive changes. As Hovey shows, it is more effective at its original mission of mobilising culture for social change than at disrupting it to achieve certain ends. In these ways, the biennial can play many different kinds of games. Perhaps the most straightforward one is the one played by the artist Anthony Gardner, who is currently at work on a major retrospective at the Tate Liverpool, and who has a book out now called  	Magic Duels. The book is a game-changer. It not only describes the game, but uses the term magic to describe the way in which the game is played. It is a ‘game-changer’ in the sense of revolutionising the game, but it is also a game-changer in the sense of revolutionising the social. It changes the rules, but it also allows players to shape the game in ways that are as if they were magical. This is what Gardner means when he talks about magic duels.  He is not talking about a game-changing magical technology, but about a redefinition of what magic is, how it is done,</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
