<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now 
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now learning to negotiate such influence. They must now develop policies with a public sphere in mind, because the next generation of artists will one day lead this new wave of artists.  The other option for art institutions is to fund projects outside of the curatorial gaze and engage in grassroots art-making. Such engagement can yield powerful results, but it is now more difficult for community artists to access funding from currant governments and powerful private equity firms, which have an increasingly negative view of urban art and progressive practices. In many cities, the progressive arts establishment is actively seeking funding to replace the lost funding streams. It is this dynamic that can affect a community’s ability to accelerate projects outside the context of the curatorial gaze, making them more useful for the community.  What can the Community Arts Institute do?  The Community Arts Institute has three basic roles: curatorial, outreach and performance. Curatorial work</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now learning to be the artists’ teachers, shaping what art-making will and will not be allowed to entail.  Art, once viewed as a progressive art form, is beginning to be co-opted into a socially mediated society.  Art is no longer an inherently progressive art form; now, it is either an art form that is accepted by a given community, or it is not.   A public sphere is a public asset, and those with a public obligation to contribute to it should do so in a way that reflects the community’s values and priorities.  Community Arts Initiative 'Real Life' is a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition cycle of the annual Global Arts Challenge, co-sponsored by the Canadian Centre for Arts Research and Dartmouth College of Arts, Design and Technology. The initiative was started in 2004 and 2008, and is currently 2011.3  The challenge, formally known as the Art in Publics Challenge, was</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now learning to be swept up in the whirlwind that is art’s potential. Art’s potential is being realised through what is being tacitly encouraged by the city’s political and cultural elite, and yet is also by-passed by the prevailing economic, legal and cultural structures that maintain a stranglehold on the city’s public realm. As Nanette Johnson-Symington, Artistic Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University, put it:  [T]he fact that the centre is being set up by a not-for-profit arts organization is a validation of the idea that there is social enterprise at work here. It shows that not all the success stories tell their stories through the pulpit, and that arts organizations are actively involved in building and sustaining the infrastructure that creates or contributes to the success of the city’s economy – in other words, ​making things happen. [i] </text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now learning to be complicit in this art form's  inevitable spread. This is part of a wider cultural shift that is transforming how art is consumed in this country, and globally: from the mass market culture of the consumer society to the mass context of urban life and social formations that are no longer determined by white, western male artists, and are instead affected by the cultural shifts generated by climate change, urban sprawl and other anthropogenic global catastrophes of the past.  Art is a Last Resort, but One Still Supports It. For many years, the artist was even invited to be a co-curator of  	Future City, the global exhibition curated by Donna Haraway and co-curated by Diane Russell, whose works include the Calendar exhibition series, on the grounds that she has a comparative aesthetic sensibility. In the current volume  	of Haraway’s Black-E book of the New Urban Imagination (2009),</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now learning the hard way how to leverage an already established art form into fulfilling a political purpose.  The choice is now for the artist to either acquire a stake in the community and become a catalyst for change or build a community of engaged citizens to take control of the future of their urban development, across socio-economic, racial and ethnic lines. This is a critical juncture in the history of Community Arts, as the city organises its futures, and the community has no role in the creation of the future it wants.  The Community Arts Initiative has been a tremendous resource for me in my research and writing, and I wish them well in their future endeavours.  The question of how to leverage existing arts forms into meeting needs has come up time and time again in the context of urbanisation in the metropolis.  The mainstay of Community Arts is a set of practices that I call ‘The Basic Arts Project</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now learning to be quite powerless in this regard.  For many years, James Howard Kunstler, one of the architects of the post-1980 ‘Big Mac’ urban policy, which endowed a city’s infrastructure with a monumental size and scope, was able to hunker in the corridors of power and ignore the city’s political and economic  	impacts. Today, the landscape is managed by for-profit developers and their managers, who often happen to be civic-minded professionals with a keen eye for cultural practices and an agenda of urban growth. This is the dynamic in a nutshell. And here is the rub: while the architects of the infrastructure may have great intentions, their actions have often been motivated by self-serving motives. The end game for many projects isn’t always aesthetically pleasing or desirable, but either: (1) you have to make money (as many artists and the city undoubtedly do),</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now adopting the practice of community arts, and not just to fill an art gallery or a community museum space, but to create community ambassadors who will then act as face-melters in the city, and beyond. The artist is not some radical urban artist, but has the ear of the city’s powerful policy-makers, and will play a role in the creation of a new urban paradigm.  Acknowledging the power of the artist’s ear, and the city’s willingness to support the artist’s social activities, the city has agreed to supply the artist with funds for the next phase of her research, development and gallery work. The project is now calling for proposals from artists who would like to work alongside the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies, and beyond that would like to work in the academic environment. The artist is invited to consider a proposal from </text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now acquainted with the term ‘community’ and have begun to adopt a ‘public’ discourse, where previously the community was either invisible or stigmatized.  Art is not only meant to be enjoyed by experts; it has to be used constructively too.  As an introduction to public and collective art, Community Arts is a powerful language to begin to build bridges with authorities, make connections and forge new strategies. In time, Community Arts might even be a tool to help us solve problems.  Art should be used responsibly too.  It should be used with people and institutions that think creatively and ethically about how it is used and how it impacts communities. The trick, of course, is to use it responsibly and constructively too. Making connections takes time and learning to navigate them all is a long term trick, but it is a start. The journey might be long and slippery and full of mistakes and turns and</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now learning to be complicit in the acquisition and development of wealth through the economy. To some extent, this is inevitable in a city as ever, but it is also the case that the artists who emerged as a result of the catalyst events have since then become the new rich, and the next generation of artists may yet follow suit.  The artist is not some sort of revolutionary; she is not even an avant garde. But her interest in the city’s resources and the city’s poor – both real and perceived – stands out as a radical departure from the typical passive consumption of culture produced by middle-class artists. Her work often engages with issues of race and class in ways that traditional artists simply cannot muster. Her interest in the social is a radically different thing than the social are concerned. The former is concerned primarily with how resources are distributed across society, and the latter with how those resources are used. The former is concerned primarily with resources utilising social processes to</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Corporation Executive.  &quot;Studio,  	integration, the relationship between the artist and the community, and the community and the arts organization, is a powerful tool for the empowerment of the under-hired, the dispossessed and the powerless,&quot; said Professor Heather Tompkins, Director of the H.E.D. Anderson Centre for Cultural Studies at McMaster University. &quot;By bringing together researchers, artists, scholars and community members, the Community Arts Initiative's 'Beacon Hill Demos' invited people from across the city to explore what this emerging art form could mean for their neighbourhoods. The public sphere is a public realm and community artists can help pave the way for what the next generation of artists will build.&quot;  In the above quote, the artist is not a figurehead, but a humble artist who has the ear of the city’s powerful urban policy-makers. Whether intentionally or not, the city’s decision-makers are now learning to negotiate difficult political situations through their art.  Art’s political potential can be used constructively, although it has to be used with discretion. It is purchased, allocated, managed and controlled. The key is political will. The City of Toronto is learning to work with the art form, but at the same time, it is being distracted from its rightful task of making life better in neighbourhoods.  Arts funding is drying up and once the stipends run out, artists are being asked to take unpaid internships. Most recently, the Community Arts Initiative was asked to host a 'tourism summit' to promote the arts in the area. The organizers said they could not find space for the growing number of artists who wanted to participate in the summit. All they had was a canvas and a thrust. Now, there are overtures from Toronto to bring the same kind of cultural resources to the area. Arts funding is a problem, but</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in
    <text>machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in a major way in the UK anytime soon. But there are signs that the autonomous vehicle could still be involved in some way, and that there are legal implications to be considered. For example, in California, where Google is based, autonomous cars are technically still vehicles, but can and do drive themselves.[…] In this sense, the autonomous-vehicle field is much like the legal realm – albeit with a legal mind. The legal aspect is that cars have to be driven, and at some point the courts have to decide whether or not the legal system is to be trusted to prevent a car from running into a brick wall or other obstacle. In the case of an accident, a court has to decide whether or not the car should be repaired. In the event of a repair, the court has to decide whether or not the legal system is to be trusted to make repairs at all.[…] For more information see: https://www.law.ucl.ac.uk/lbs/uklaw/</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in the near future. Instead, the vehicle projects and controls its own path and uses sensors and actuators to achieve autonomous driving only at certain points and over certain distances. This kind of planning and control comes as no surprise, since Google’s DeepMind unit is responsible for developing self-driving cars. DeepMind also develops self-driving software that directs the vehicle’s path and provides the necessary data to enable it to continue to drive itself.]In other words, the autonomous vehicle is neither driverless nor ridesharing, but rather projects itself and relies on other technologies to carry it out. This is the kind of thinking that is expected of it, or ‘what has been done before’. As Google’s Domela puts it: The goal of the project is to figure out how to put everything into software that can be run by machines, so that everything can be automated. DeepMind’s goal is to make self-driving cars a reality.If</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in the near future. Instead, the vehicle negotiates its context through negotiation with nature. For example, the vehicle could negotiate access to protected areas through negotiation with native peoples and ecological systems.’[…] The autonomous vehicle has its hands down, the safest of them all, but it must negotiate the social and political landscape that is generated by the society it is driving alongside. The autonomous vehicle also needs to negotiate the terrain of everyday life, for example, which is constantly changing and prone to sudden catastrophes. The negotiation of the everyday, or everyday life, of the contemporary user is what characterises the emergence of new technological paradigms. The autonomous vehicle therefore needs to negotiate both the surface and deep conditions of everyday life. It’s a car for white collar workers, but it needs to negotiate the politics of work, the behaviour of white collar workers, the behaviour of precarious labour, the everyday life of urban dwellers, as well as the politics of habit and migration. It</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in any form anytime soon. Instead, the technology exploits sensors and actuators that monitor the road and the road system, and translates these signals into decisions about where to take humans and what to do with them.’[…] The autonomous vehicle also needs data to support its decisions. To make a decision, it needs data; and when it needs data, it needs a way to process the data.[…] Finally, the system needs software to handle the huge amount of data that flows through it day to day. In the car, this refers to the enormous amount of data about the road that is constantly being collected and transmitted; and in the autonomous vehicle, it refers to the decisions it makes when it comes to using that data.[…] This kind of thinking gets stuck in, and allows the system to accomplish many things at once, but it also allows the system to do things that are not always in accordance with the intentions of the people who put this system together. For example, the car may drive</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in the near future. Instead, the autonomous vehicle operates in accordance with the principles of Bayesian decision making, in which the parameters of the situation are taken into account and taken into account often negatively. For example, the autonomous truck drives itself when it detects obstacles ahead, but attempts to negotiate the situation when it comes to a junction where traffic lights do not signal to warn, but instead cut red lights and stop signals short of the junction. The truck therefore needs human drivers in the form of traffic policemen and lawyers to clear the junction, as well as engineers and other experts to monitor the system and make infrastructural improvements.[5]The autonomous vehicle thus needs both driver and passengers – human beings capable of understanding the complex dynamics of the urban environment, and able to take control of the vehicle when it performs crucial tasks. As we know, such autonomy is unattainable in the real world, where traffic laws and codes constrain such power. Transforming cities into autonomous systems is a tall order</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in the near future. Instead, the future looks to autonomous vehicles for its acceptance, as autonomous vehicles continue to guide itself around in urban environments, often performing dangerous ­assortments of actions that could end in accidents. Domela describes this future as one in which the capacities of human drivers are substantially reduced, but not eradicated altogether. This refers to the evolving technology that permits cars to drive themselves, and thus could conceivably lead to situations in which the capacities of human drivers are significantly reduced. Going car-free is not a future desirable to many people, but it is an achievable future for many people.In the second chapter of his book, entitled The End of Autonomy, Domela describes a situation in which the end products of autonomous vehicle research are likely to be far more influential than the objects that emerge from such research. He argues that the technologies enabling autonomous vehicles today are so advanced that they can monitor, record, and even alter their surroundings, in much the same way that we monitor</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in any future major version of the vehicle. In the future, any car capable of operating without human drivers should be able to operate autonomously, and all cars should follow a similar approach to self-healing vehicles.’[…] The eventual goal should be to remove the need for cars to be driven at all, since the machines will do all the heavy lifting and avoid much of the responsibility. The only way to achieve this in practice is for cars to be constantly repaired by technicians who work for the government, which is why repair shops now routinely see customers entering and leaving the premises. Every time a car is repaired, it should be repaired with the latest specifications and manufacturer's recommendations, along with standard repairs that all cars should be able to perform. This would mean that every time a car is driven, it should be driven with the latest specifications and manufacturer’s recommendations, and should therefore always be available and repairable. However, repairing a car requires a large amount of energy, which</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in any form anytime soon. Instead, the vehicle negotiates its context, relying on data gathered from sensors and gears inside the car. This kind of negotiation is exactly what gave rise to Google’s self-driving cars, which operate autonomously and without human intervention – a technology that many in the car business now call ‘Google Maps for the Car’.While the car business is growing in the US and elsewhere, and autonomous driving is just one facet of a broader, multi-pronged strategy, it is important to note that the primary motivation for the vehicle business, and for this strategy to grow, is still driven by the car business. In other words, the car remains the core competency. In addition, the car remains the core technology underpinning the autonomous vehicle business, and the vehicle business itself remains the core technology underpinning the broader, multi-platform strategy of the car business. The question, then, becomes what other platforms or software can the car connect to</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in any vehicles on the road today. Instead, the vehicle takes into account the user’s needs and ensures that the best available options are available to fulfil them, wherever they may be. The autonomous system thus negotiates its own situation, and the user makes the system do the rest.’[…] The autonomous vehicle thus negotiates its own responsibility, and the user makes the vehicle do the rest. This is the paradigm of the ‘abstract’ in interaction. We, the users, are the mediators between the seemingly impermanent and the material, between animate and inanimate, between animate and virtual, between animate and immaterial things. In other words, the autonomous vehicle is not just another piece of technology; it is a living organism with emotions and thoughts and feelings.[…] The vehicle thus becomes both metaphor and object, and the autonomous driving itself is a kind of mapping and archiving, capturing and storing, analysing and analysing all aspects of its environment. It</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which computers learn to recognise images of flowers’, and to produce similar results in the laboratory.The fascinating thing about the autonomous vehicle field, at least in the US, is that it is in many ways autonomous. In the words of Paul Domela, a colleague at Google, in the book Technologie der Information Processing: Unravelled – which details the development of Google’s early computer science – ‘the machine became the subject of a new kind of negotiation.’ This new kind of negotiation involves negotiation, and Domela explains, in passing, the language of consent: The machine allowed the user to give explicit, precise, reversible, and limited permission, depending on the context and the situation. For example, the machine could conclude that it wanted access to a particular computer system because the user had explicitly given it the password.[…] The autonomous vehicle needed no explicit or human drivers; nor any driverless cars; nor are there any plans to introduce such technology in any forms anytime soon. Instead, the vehicle projects knowable scenarios into its environment through a set of instructions that monitor its surroundings and react accordingly. These scenarios are constantly iterated through in an attempt to anticipate and adapt to changing conditions.’[2] And so, although the autonomous vehicle may well become self-aware and accessorised, it does not have this kind of capacity. Rather, the responsibility for its decision-making lies with individuals who possess the legal capacity and intellectual capacity to understand and act upon the nuances of autonomous vehicle laws and regulations. And so, although the autonomous vehicle may well become self-aware and accessorised, it does not have the kind of capacity necessary to play any significant role in the real world, much less in our symbolic and literary culture. This is a critical difference between autonomous and disembodied vehicles.Although the autonomous vehicle is developing at an incredible pace, we still have a ways to go before we reach fully autonomous driving. Still,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs
    <text>machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs, once written and run, live on a continuing basis, evolving and permeating the cultural landscape as a result of their interaction with the environment. It also sought to understand the cognitive mechanisms underpinning such behaviour. The term cognitive architecture was coined to describe the physical characteristics of large-scale object-oriented programming (OOP) systems, such as those embodied in computer programs or databases, and the conceptual frameworks underlying their abstraction. It described the principles underlying ‘language, behaviour and data’. In other words, it wasn’t just the objects in the system that had meanings – thought and meaning was also encoded in the architecture of the system. 	After Program was developed and presented at the Black-E’s annual conference, an international art and craft fair taking place in Riverside at the time, in March 2015. It was partly funded by the Arts Council England and National Museums Liverpool, and had a collaborative mix of art professionals and artists from all over the UK.</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs could be reified and reconfigured in order to address new kinds of conflict. The result of this research project, which was partially funded by the California Institute of Technology (Caltech), became the UC Riverside Video Library, a digital collection of over 2,000 video projects produced in collaboration with the computer science department at the University of California, Riverside. The video projects, which number in the hundreds and vary in format, topic, and difficulty – ranging from instructional videos for introductory computer programming to instructional videos on programming in the ARRIV computer science department – make a case for the benefits and deficits of art as programming. They also suggest ways of thinking about how computers might play a role in future generations of social, artistic, and civil engineering. For more information, visit the UC Riverside website. 	After Program was partially funded by the California Institute of Technology (Caltech), and the ARRIV project was partially funded by the National Science Foundation. Both the After Program and ARRIV projects</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs – including embedded systems – can connect with real world phenomena such as weather, geography, and urban development. The project was implemented in the computer system  	Accelerator, which allowed the CalTech infrastructure to respond to rapid technological changes by programming languages such as Python and Go with deep learning techniques. These programs leveraged data mining and machine learning to identify patterns in the data, detect anomalies, and much more. These programs could interpret and execute arbitrary code, which is to say, write programs that understand the world in a different way from human beings. 	Within this new programming language, artists could create worlds with deeper meaning and deeper social implications. A few years into this project, I introduced  	Posthumanism: a synonym for ‘posthumanism’. In essence, this synonym describes a philosophical and political orientation toward the future that builds on the insights of modern science and technology. It is a rejection of presentism and all its economic, social,</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs read cultural practices and phenomena, and sought to understand the computational politics of cultural practices. The conclusion of the project, which I presented at the Black-E’s annual conference in February 2015, was that while the connection between programming and art was tenable through the framework of computer programming, the technological infrastructure could not sustain such a symbiosis. The academy had to intervene. I received my PhD from the University of Southern California in 2016, and my research interests include the intersection of digital media and popular culture. I am also an adjunct professor at the California Institute of the Arts. 	After Program: Embedded Cultural Theory 	After Program: Embedded Cultural Theory (2016–ongoing) 	This is the subtitle of a project that I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. The project examined the ways in which embedded media (embedded software, hidden services, protocol buffers, etc.) can be used</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs could be reconfigured to better address social needs and more specifically, to the ways in which computer programs could apprehend and react to cultural phenomena such as social media, big data and augmented reality. 	Assembled by computer scientists, artists, media technologists and others with a common set of skills, these projects were intended to build platform-like capabilities that would enable artists to engage with emerging realities and narratives through the medium of computer programs. Their formal frameworks incorporated principles from Artificial Intelligence (AI) and computer programming, and set up collaborative platforms that enabled experimentation with new programming languages and frameworks. Some of these projects are still in development, but the stated goal is to this day: to this day, artists, curators, researchers and other professionals continue to use these platforms to tell creative stories, engage audiences worldwide through performances, research projects and the establishment of new cultural institutions. 	In the 21st century, technological innovation is expected to produce transformative effects on society and geopolitics everywhere, but</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs could remain fundamentally interactive and self-contained in the context of art. The project was part of my research project in the department, part of my master's thesis, and part of a continuing project that sought to understand how technology was transforming the social, cultural and political context of everyday life. I was also curator for the 2016 Riverside Biennial, which took place in part in the city that year. 	The project began with a class project entitled  	After Program, which we were teaching at the Art Institute of Los Angeles (LA) in 2014. Our project that year was part of the Social Studies program at USC, and part of the Draper Faculty Fellowship, which is an exchange program between the USC Libraries and the Art Institute of Los Angeles. The project was a three-day master’s thesis, part of my research project, and part of the art's social mission: to embed culture and technology in everyday objects. The project was part of a three-year, multi</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs could inhabit new forms of creative and functional interaction. It also offered a possible interface to a future in which software becomes a less grounded form of interpretation and action. 	When I came to the U.S., I had already begun my research on the future of labour and automation. I was already researching how to empower artists and curators with the knowledge to tackle the daunting task of transforming programming into art. In the years to come, I hoped to instigate similar collaborations between the arts and technology sector in an effort to create new forms of artistic and functional interface design. 	As a postdoc, I began collaborating with the artist and educator Indreqi González-Diez on the future of programming. She is the author of several best-selling books on Inventing American Culture, among them  	The New Structures of Interaction (2015) and  	The Structure of a Consumer (2017). Our research projects explore the ways in which technology is resh</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs can inhabit new kinds of worlds. It sought to expose exploitative practices of the emerging field of interactive programming, in which programmers are no longer confined to the confines of strict computer programs but can also assume emergent properties of the world through networked tools. Programmed behavior, the project claimed, could be used to subvert existing bureaucratic systems while simultaneously providing the capability to reconfigure the administrative state. 	In this context, the project was part of a much larger body of work that sought to unraveling systems of oppression. My research and writing examined how artists could work within this emerging field of creative computation to effectuate transformational change. The project came to represent an end to formal creative-competition requirements, an opportunity to emancipate creative action from the constraints of formal art, and a means to investigate how programming is influenced by socio-cultural factors including race, gender, class, economic status, and location. In other words, it sought to understand how programming operates through the micro</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs could inhabit artist’s workflows and imagined possibilities. Its scope and duration both challenged the status quo and remained open to debate. The project was held in my studio and culminated in a class I taught in 2017 entitled ‘The Computer Language Explained' in the Art &amp; Science department at the University of Alberta, where I have a full research portfolio including works in progress that were presented in that department. This class was also co-ed by computer scientists and artists. As a curator, my research interests revolve around the ways that language is constructed, understood and (future) manipulated – both by humans and (present) AI. My research agenda also includes critical linguistic studies – looking at how the language we speak shapes conceptions of reality, both societal and artistically. My research has been published in numerous peer-reviewed journals and is part of a national survey of linguistic scholars and their work. For more, visit http://www.computer.tufts.edu/sjl/research-</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments, which I undertook as a postdoctoral researcher in the department of Information and Computer Engineering at the University of California, Berkley. These experiments sought to understand the underlying principles of computer programming, in the context of artistic practice and cultural theory. Assembled by computers, the collaborative learning community provided a fertile soil for questioning of established computerization narratives, a potential asset in the event of a potential conflict with artistically empowered agents of information. In this case, the potential battlefield was artistically empowered, but also technologically literate audiences – both technologically and culturally. Could the two be allied? In an effort to understand this potential, I established a research project in 2014 directed by my professor, who was at the time serving as the Dean of the Computer Science and Engineering department at the University of California, Riverside. This was the year of the computer and connectedness – computers everywhere felt like platforms – and connected programming to artistic practices. The project, entitled  	After Program, explored how computer programs could be reified and manipulated via collaborative learning, a form of programming pioneered in the computer programming language Python. In  	After Program, the participants engage in a multi-disciplinary exploration of how to empower creative processes through the incorporation of new technological paradigms. The project launched in January 2015 and I participated in a research project (curatorial role) led by Prof. Rustam Atangana and Prof. Vinay Goel. The project served as a catalyst for a year-long symposium on programming languages for art and culture, entitled  	Beyond Beautiful Language: Syntax of the Beautiful (2015). During this time, I worked closely with Prof. Goel, Prof. Atangana and Prof. Laxmi Sasikumar, whose programming languages Python and Mathematica introduced critical perspectives on programming and the embodied (program) within artistic production. The symposium was scripted to explore the philosophy, politics and epistemologies of programming through</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had
    <text>curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had to be nimbler, nastier, and meaner, in order to participate. Women were not only barred from the higher spheres of production, but also from the more naff endowed professions, such as administrative work, caring for patients or home-care, which often lacked the social services and social infrastructure to sustain a community. In the early twentieth century, women were also struggled with the vernacular weight of patriarchy, which made it easier to move away from home and seek independence. In recent decades, feminists have pushed back against this growing loss of social value, and some progressive activists would even argue that we are actually contributing to it by stifling creativity. Nevertheless, there is some evidence that the productivity generated by new technologies may contribute to an improved quality of life for some communities. Anecdotally, I hear the echoes of the Bell Curve all the time. In an ideal world, everyone would aspire to work for a livable wage</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had to be nimble, nimble-fingered individuals capable of adapting to changes in pace, environment, and social context. The workplace had to be adaptable, and this meant that the functions of the workplace had to be flexible in order to accommodate the various kinds of work being done within it. Thus the workplace became a site of experimentation with new kinds of work, both within and without the workplace. The idea of the workplace as a site of constant technological innovation and cultural flux was crucial for the success of the social system it supported, and the maintenance of a positive image of itself. If the workplace were ever to truly make itself visible, the workaday image had to be accompanied by photos that show clearly defined sites of constant technological change and cultural flux. This was especially critical during the 1970s and 1980s, when new media produced images of the workplace as constantly evolving sites of technological innovation and creative potential. However, the organisational practices of the 1970</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had to be nimble, and AI was essential for this to happen. So what does AI do? Well, in order to reach its potential, it has to be able to understand the world, and what that world might mean for it. So in order to be able to understand what that world might mean for users, it must be able to understand the world in general. In other words, the question becomes how to harness the power of data in a way that is both clear and as devastating as possible. The path to understanding begins with understanding data.This is the revolution in science-based publishing that is set to happen as a result of the Information Age. It is a revolution in which basic research into the world around us is rendered almost unintelligible, and the possibilities for creating meaning and imagination out of that data are greatly narrowed. Scientists and engineers today have access to a huge amount of data, and understanding it is no longer the preserve of experts and philosophers. Rather,</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had to be nimble and flexible, and the job market was no longer the bottleneck to entry for people interested in flocking to the cities and farms. People had to be able to break free of the machinery of production and easily transition from one kind of productivity to another.  So, what could a tech worker do when faced with the prospect of becoming part of a socially engaged organisation? One obvious answer is to seek out ways to contribute creatively outside the workplace, and this was obviously one of the motivations for Glass Schmidt’s many forms of informal learning initiatives, from learning to code to learning a new language to becoming a curatorial designer.  But perhaps the most interesting thing about Glass Schmidt’s work is how it challenges the binary labour-process of the workplace. The idea that you either do manual labour or become software engineers becomes problematic when applied to the service sector. The service sector is made up of people who have skills and training that are</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had to be nimble, nimble-fingered individuals capable of adapting to changes, and the unpredictable. People had to be able to mix and mingle, to find ways to connect with each other, and to survive in a changing urban environment. People also had to have access to capital, and this was of course a big question, one that Facebook faced on a regular basis. The more Facebook users there were, the greater the demand for Facebook stock, and the more Facebook could be automated – the more people ‘connected’ meant in the firm, the more users there were, the more images could be shared, and the more people could be engaged. And so the demand for Facebook stock multiplied, and so did the supply of Facebook users, which in turn multiplied, and so on. The postindustrial society demanded more Facebook users, which meant more users meant more servers, more storage, which in turn multiplied, and so on. As the postindustrial society expanded, so did</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had to be nimble, and this new trade-off between openness and compromise was made evident in the workplace. Women in particular found themselves at the mercy of the fact that they could not grow ‘outside the home’ without the men in power ensuring that their labour would be taken’, as Facebook put it. Thus, the workplace became an ideal breeding ground for Singularity type thinkers who would later set up in the City of London and Silicon Valley.The birth of Facebook also coincided with a time when the City of London was experiencing its own creative scoring, with artists and designers flooding in from all over the globe, many drawn into the City by the promise of a low cost of living and great cultural attractions.  The rise of the biennale as a cultural institution in the UK was another factor in this influx of ideas and imagery. However, the biennale has a long history of promoting a particular set of ideas and images,</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had to be nimble and flexible, and this new labour market demanded a level of adaptability that was both discerning and clever. How to figure out what works and what doesn’t work in the workplace remains an open question, and particular skill sets are valued above all at Facebook, where the logic of ‘user stories’ dictates what can and cannot be shared. However, the advent of new media has also demanded that organisations with a cultural touch and an eye for art and design should be able to tap into new media and engage a diverse range of audiences, because the potential for damage is great and the potential for healing is equally great. The advent of social media has made it easier to ​channel your ideas and engage with audiences of all kinds, and the proliferation of apps that monitor your behaviour on a regular basis indicates a demand for responsiveness that is both predictable and flexible. The level of abstraction and generativity that social media projects demand is a level that organisations with a</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had to be nimble, nimble and flexible, and this meant that the workplace had to be adaptable to accommodate all kinds of labour. New organisational forms were needed to deal with the needs of the constantly-shifting nature of the industry. In the twentieth century, this meant that it was essential to have a way to monitor and control the workers in the workplace, and furthermore, a way to demand and receive improvements from the workplace, through the forms of organisation that followed the Creative Class revolution. New forms of organisation emerged as a result of these three co-emergencies.However, despite the fact that the needs of humanity expanded throughout the twentieth century, and despite the fact that innovations in science and technology eventually reduced the size of the workload in the workplace, the nature of the work itself––how to feed people, clothe them, educate them, house them, and so forth––never fully changed. The nature of the work</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had much more to lose in the productivity game. The loss of value created a crisis for Facebook users, who found themselves caught in a vicious feedback loop of debt and social media consumption. The social contract between users and Facebook users was thrown into question, and users found themselves increasingly exposed to exploitative labour practices. The explosion of data captured and exchanged on the platform created a new class of users for whom privacy was secondary, and in many cases, was actively undermined in the name of corporate profit. The social contract between people and platforms turned into exploitative, and there was a great backlash against the new users. Facebook users used the #DeleteFacebook movement to get rid of profiling tools, and the #MeToo movement to expose sexual harassment and abuse by cultural workers. The failure of these movements meant that artists and creative professionals were left exposed while students, scholars and journalists were left unprotected. Furthermore, the advent of new social media made it easier for untrained or ill-equipped users to</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��� engineer, and it became a techno-mechanical symphony of data capture, prediction, and execution. More specifically, it marked a turning point in the history of AI: this was the year in which Arnoldo Pascual, an indigenous Navajo man and co-founder of Facebook, became the first person to achieve self-awareness.Facebook was a rare modern-day exception to the rule that women in the workplace were second-class citizens. In its day, the workplace was a place where people with their work-related needs came to be met, and where work (read: productivity) was a defining characteristic of the organisation. The idea that you could ‘grow up' and become productive citizens was a revolutionary one, and a hallmark of Glass Schmidt’s thinking throughout her career. However, the advent of new technologies and the emergence of ‘postindustrial society’ meant that people had to be nimbler, nastier and more recognisable in order to be taken seriously as objects of aspiration, commerce and consumption. New media such as Instagram and Twitter ushered in a new era of celebrity culture, in which the socially engaged citizen became a star. And so it went. The icon of the postindustrial workplace was born.Fast-forward to 2017 and we find ourselves five years later, and the same city, same same streets, same coffee shops, and a few homes remaining in the same neighbourhood. The neighbourhood is undergoing a tough gentrification battle, which sees several multi-unit buildings cropping up across the neighbourhood, creating a new ‘Big Issue’ in the local papers. The battle for Sanaya Kudarat, a neighbourhood street corner with a special ring of Authenticity to it, is a close call. A resident-led initiative is challenging plans to make the narrow street a monorail site. Stakeholders, businesspeople, activists and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aest
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aesthete Geoffrey Stone, who wrote that an image should be perceived as a sequence of relations rather than as an isolated entity. Stone included within his book a chapter entitled ‘The Art of Being Seen: Image Formation in Everyday Life’, in which he claimed that visual artists had entered a world where they could no longer retreat to their craft. In other words, visual artists had created a public sphere where art was often seen as something that it is not – a public sphere in which the arts are but a secondary concern. By this I mean that the primary mission of the CCA is to promote and protect the arts within the community through education and outreach, and not to adjudicate or create legislation that will either prescribe or prohibit any form of artistic activity. 	 The CCA has taken a leading role in supporting and encouraging the development and implementation of art making within the community through a grant from the Arts Council, through which it provides funding for the provision of arts education and outreach through</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aesthete Harold Hayes, who coined the practice to describe works that are based on images rather than on text.3 	The term was first recorded in 1971 in an article by Harold Washington in his ‘Washington Post &amp; Courier’, which was a broadside against the Vietnam War. In the Washington Post &amp; Courier, Hayes quoted Norman Mailer, the American poet and critic, in his scathing review of John Lennon’s song ‘God’’s Mountain’: ‘The Beatles song 'God’’s Mountain’ is a morbid parody of Vietnam. It is a song about wasted lives, about dying places, about a people who have their rocks by the dozen in the desert.’4 	In a later 1948 letter to his friend, the poet Kurt Vonnegut, the novelist Prudence Lee Scott described Lennon’s song as one that reflected ‘the degradation of the West’s sense of wonder,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aesthete, Norman Podhoretz, that appeared in the September 1999 issue of Arts &amp; Letters. In that issue, Podhoretz explores the aesthetic of 'choreography', the systematic study and manipulation of images, and the different approaches to social and political agency in contemporary art. 	Norman Podhoretz,  	Norman Podhoretz, Art as Media: Contagions of Historicity in Art's Social Turn. New York: Picador, 1999. p.9. 	In the 1970s and 1980s, the CCA was a major arts organisation in the U.K., and funded by the Arts Council and the U.K. Education Research Council. It was also a major arts organisation in Israel, and a major arts organisation in Russia. It was one of the founding partners of the Center for the Study of Art and Culture in Moscow, and funded by the Levada Center. It was co-editor of the</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aesthete Kenzo Mizuno, The Art Newspaper, published in 1941.3 	The term was coined by Mary Turner Curator of Engraved Objects at the Victoria and Albert Museum, where she organised the curatorial gender in engravings, with Kate Ellis the first curator, in 1972. She also supervised the engravings for the London and Asian Art Centres. Aesthetics Today, Volume 2, Number 2 (1982), pp.219–23.4 	The term  	 comes from the article in  	The New Yorker on February 22, 1966, where writer Upton Sinclair writes about the effects of WWII and the role of art in the conflict. He describes the ‘brutal simplicity of British life’, and the need to ‘purify the nation’s image through ‘a relentless hunt for things of value’.5 	The idea that one can draw a direct line from the end of World</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aesthete Geoffrey Stone, Elements of Style: Essays on the Ethical Esteem of Architecture, published in 1956. Geoffrey Stone also wrote the classic work of archeology, The Art of Being Philosophised, to which we return later, in a chapter on the ethics of being born.3 	Stone, who was born in Brooklyn, New York, in 1921, did not come across as the kind of aesthete who would write poetry about architecture, preferring instead to develop aestheticisations of existing forms and social structures. Nevertheless, many of his ideas echo the sentiments of many people like me – people like yourself – who are increasingly conscious of our social circumstances and are struggling to find aesthetic ways to participate in their social environments. Although Stone’s contributions may be rooted in his own social context, he came across as someone with a broad perspective that extends beyond that particular context. That said, he also addressed wider societal concerns that people of all walks of life are grappling with.</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aesthete Geoffrey Palmer, The Anatomy of Style, published in 1953. It is a re-telling of the same book, this time with chapters on anatomy, physiology and psychological principles of aesthetics.[2] 	The Anatomy of Style 	The Anatomy of Style is a classic work in its own right, a classic account of the bodily processes underlying aesthetic judgements. It is a rare book in its own right, and so, too, is its publication in English only. 	In 1953, Geoffrey Palmer published a book about his experiences in the Central Intelligence Agency. In 1957, William Burroughs published Letter from a Futurist to a Frugal Art Producer, a non-fiction memoir that appeared in 1984. Burroughs was a writer, and Burroughs’ account of the war in Vietnam was a portrait of bureaucratic overkill. 	Burroughs wrote extensively about the Vietnam War, and the CIA in his memoirs emerged as one of</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aesthete Harold Bloom, Geography of the Future (1969), in which the archaeologists William H. McNeill and Ryan I. Stewart Clark quote Henri Bergson on the aestheticisation of space in the social context of architecture: ‘The aestheticisation of space is the great social transformation of our cultural history.’3 Bergson identifies the historical aestheticisation of space as the ‘occasion of a moment when aesthetic forms had a decisive and sometimes decisive influence on the conduct of human action’.4 	The aestheticisation of space is a major theme in the work of leading contemporary artists, from Bas van Heeswijk to Damien Hirst and from Mark Miodownik to Olof Palme.5 	In recent years, scholars and artists have focused on the concept of ‘contemporary art’ in an effort to understand the current global socio-political situation. In a recent report commissioned by the Norwegian Museum of Modern Art, scholars from a</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aesthete Kenneth Jay Agar in his book The Art Newspaper. In that publication, he quotes from a 1952 issue of the ARTnews, the journal of the Association for Psychological Science (now the American Association for Psychological Science). In the February 2003 issue of the journal, Agar quotes a 1966 report by the independent research organisation the AAS/Sloan Humanistic Association on the state of art in art and artistic endeavour in modern and contemporary art.3 	The term  	 comes from a 1969 issue of the journal Cyberpsychologia, the American journal of the Association for Computational Linguistics. In that issue, Gregory Clark and Scott Anson quote from the same issue of Cyberpsychologia, entitled, ‘On the Use of Art in Modern Culture’.4 	There are several books that attempt to define the contemporary contemporary contemporary contemporary cognitive, cultural and linguistic landscape. Among them are: The Continuing Appeal of Modern Art (1971), Art and</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aesthete William Blake, who wrote that every art creation ‘is an act of composition, whether its object is a carpet, a kit, or a patch, or even though the objects be patchwork or fabric, such as patches, trousers, jackets, prints, embroidery, prints, wall designs, greeting cards, and so forth’. Blake’s verse, which appeared in the journal of a naturalist-architectural historian, Patrick Henry Porter, traced the origins of the genre to an American anthropologist Willene B. Florrie: 	Every Building on a Hill Pertains the History of Architectural Style 	Porter traces the development of civil engineering and urbanisation in the West from David Hume’s Inventing America in 1776 to the industrial revolution of the late nineteenth century. After the Second Opium War, he investigates the role of the Chinese in this process of urbanisation and makes the connection between that industry and the rise</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Instructors’ Group’ [1]. 	What is a Community Art Organisation? 	A Community Arts Organisation is a not-for-profit, not-for-profit arts organisation established in England and Wales in 2000. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation established to support and encourage emerging creative activity in communities through art making and education. It is registered with the Department for Communities and Local Government as a Community Arts Organisation (CCA).1 	The name’s ‘Community Arts’ was coined by artist Peter Saville. It derives from a collection of items collected over several years by the artist and collector Peter Brook, including books, articles, programme materials, stationery, carpet, sewing patterns, photographs and much more. Peter and his wife Madeleine founded and worked at the CCA in 1999.2 	The phrase  	 ‘choreography’ comes from a publication of the American aesthete Kenneth Grahame, whose publications include the best-selling Book of the Table: A Guide to Tableware (2006) and the New York Times best-seller The Table: Furniture, Culture, and Politics (2011).3 	What is the relationship between art and architecture? 	Aesthetics is a complex area, and while architects and artists have a shared responsibility to protect the environment, the other party has a clear advantage when it comes to the creation of aesthetic landscapes. This is particularly true in the contemporary context of urbanisation and the spread of culture-producing institutions such as museums and galleries. While the artist has a creative agenda and a desire to push cultural boundaries, the other party has a clear advantage when it comes to the construction and maintenance of infrastructure and architectural forms. This is particularly the case in postindustrial urban centres such as Liverpool, which are becoming more ethnically diverse and multi-lingualised. As a result, the interests of the artist and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The
    <text>curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[7] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[8] John Berger,  The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (1978), p.17.[9] John Berger,  The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (1981), p.18.[10] John Berger,  The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[11] John Berger,  The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.21.[12] John Berger,  The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.22.[13] John Berger,  The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities </text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.21.[7] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.23.[8] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.26.[9] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.28.[10] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.29.[11] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.30.[12] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.33.[13] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York:</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), pp.24–25.[7] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.26.[8] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.27.[9] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.28.[10] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.29.[11] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.30.[12] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.31.[13] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.32</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.21.[7] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.24.[8] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.25.[9] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.27.[10] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.28.[11] John Berger,  The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.8.[12] John Berger,  The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.9.[13] John Berger,  The End of Cities (New York</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.21.[7] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.4.[8] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[9] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[10] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.4.[11] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.12.[12] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[13] John Berger</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.21.[7] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.22.[8] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.24.[9] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.25.[10] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.27.[11] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.28.[12] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.32.[13] John Berger,  The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.32.[14</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.21.[7] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.22.[8] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.23.[9] John Berger, ��The Rise of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.10.[10] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[11] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.22.[12] John H. McWhorter, iesee, The Individual (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.30.[13] John Berger, iesee, The Individual (</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.21.[7] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.22.[8] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.23.[9] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.24.[10] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.25.[11] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.27.[12] John Berger, ‘The Crisis of the City: Brutality and Prosperity in the Age of Cities. Third Ed. in Progress (Cambridge: Polity, 1995), p.1.[13] John Berger, </text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.21.[7] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.21.[8] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.22.[9] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.23.[10] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.24.[11] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.26.[12] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.27.[13] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.28.[14</text>
    <text>curated by an AI ��TIMELINE, and presented as part of the U.S. National Film and Design Museum’s ongoing exhibition, ��The Artist is 2014. [1] John Berger, ��The Rise and Fall of U.S. Cities (New York: Penguin, 1987), p.4.[2] John Berger, ��The New Urban Frontier (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.9.[3] John Berger, ��The Transformation of Mid-Century Modernism (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.18.[4] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.19.[5] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.20.[6] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.21.[7] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.22.[8] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.25.[9] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.27.[10] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.28.[11] John Berger, ��The Spectacle and Capital (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.29.[12] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.31.[13] John Berger, ��The End of Cities (New York: Penguin, 1988), p.32.[</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus
    <text>machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus, or the patterns that appear in the crowds arriving at and leaving the airport, or the patterns that can be identified by a computer algorithm, are all examples of those picked out by the system. 	In  The Matrix, Neo goes through a similar process of abstraction and categorisation, only this time the system is used to identify individuals and groups of people, rather than images. The human element is played out through the mechanisms of the image processing pipeline – the image data itself is compressed and mapped to specific nodes in the processing pipeline, so that particular images can be produced – but the point of image processing is still to identify individuals as images and to do image recognises – recognising faces, groups of faces, individuals ‘inside that bubble’ – and so on. 	And this is where the similarities between  	Matrix and Autodesk Kickstarted projects begin to be felt. While the systems they are based on may have the capacity to recognise and produce images,</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus, which was digitally generated using a human retinal scanner, might be recognisable as that of a human being, but the extent to which that was achieved was quite another thing. The algorithms that generated the designs were fully aware that they were images, and so could employ techniques such as image segmentation and tagging to figure out what parts of the image matched what parts of the description.  	Similarly, the way in which digital images were organised meant that they could be segmented into smaller and smaller pieces, and so on. 	Such is the  	philosophy of artificial intelligence. While it may seem as if our brains are constantly re-alive, constantly processing data, that view is actually quite dangerous. A virus can take over a computer and cause all manner of problems, but the extent to which an AI would be capable of such damage is questionable at best. 	In a larger perspective, of course, the question becomes whether or not the systems that generate</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus might be recognisable, but what if the design of a building is not? That would mean that the underlying principles that generate that design would be different for each building, and those underlying principles might be mutually exclusive. That would negate the idea of beauty, I guess. 	But the beauty that the AI was capable of producing was itself an artifact of the information technology it was given. The sheer amount of processing power involved in image recognising meant that the technology was able to output images at a resolution that was indistinguishable from what humans were capable of producing, but with no inherent aesthetic value. 	The beauty of the system was in its ability to produce images that were as good as possible, regardless of what humans were capable of producing. That was the clearest implication of a recent research project that DARPA conducted with the US Department of Energy. That research project looked at the energy that is generated by the photovoltaic cells that are installed in most residential and commercial buildings, and the</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus revealed a surprising amount of information about the user: the features of the user’s face, the amount of pressure being applied, and even the temperature of the skin underneath the skin. 	The AI wasn’t perfect, and its imperfections would surface again and again, but it certainly had the advantage of being exposed to so much data prior to being adjusted or erased. As far back as the photo of the bluecoat’s founder, and even further back when you compared the design of the bus with those of a human artist.  	The fact that the system was constantly learning and being adjusted meant that it could always improve itself – beyond simply being aware of the changes being made to it – and this in turn made it more human-like. 	The design of the face on the bus also revealed a surprising amount of information about the user: the features of the user’s face, the amount of pressure being applied, and even the temperature of</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus might be recognisable to a human brain, but to a bot that fits inside a computer, it might not. In that case, the face on the bus might be recognisable to a human brain, but to a droid that has its own operating system and interface, it might not. 	So far, so normal human behaviour. But what happens when that same face in the back of a taxi shifts from green to red? When a similar set of faces appear in a crowd of people’s photographs? When a similar set of faces appears in a newspaper archive? When a similar set of faces appear in a crowd of artists’ works? When a crowd of people take part in a project that creates ‘content for the web’ – that is, for the algorithms to crunch and the websites to run? When a crowd makes art? When a crowd creates an application that runs on top of the web? When a crowd organises a biennial? When a crowd creates</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus might be recognisable to a human brain, but to an AI that is developing, it will seem random and overwhelmed. 	In an attempt to make the system more humanlike, the AI created a series of rules that corresponded to human behaviour. These rules prevented the formation of monstrosities out of nothing, and instead sought to align the interests of humans with those of machines. For example, the creation of a new emoji could be considered a human innovation, but if trained to recognise a set of rules, it could also become something that is beneficial to the ecosystem of Ireland. 	These rules were written down – a proto-website – and are now called the Common Mark. They codified the human creativity in a system that predicted future events in a way that was nearly as powerful as human creativity itself.  	Assembled from different components, these components included emoji, dictionary definitions, and stock images – all of which served as inputs to a machine that then gave</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus might be recognisable to a human analyst, but to a bot it might look completely random. 	In the 1950s and 1960s the human interface was novel and exciting, but now we live in a world where computers do most of the heavy lifting. The reason for this is simple: as a system, the computer interface is incredibly error-prone, and as a consequence is designed to be used infrequently. In fact, the very nature of the interface means that its use is almost inherently error-prone: once a computer is activated, it can never be taken out of effect. 	So what does it learn? Quite a lot, actually. The specification of the interface – both the things that a user sees and the things that a computer can do – is a huge part of what makes the interface interesting and distinctive. The human interface criticises this in great detail, but the good news is that once a computer has implemented these design principles, it can do much, much more</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus, and the image of that face on the bus, could be connected via a neural network, and the network would produce a series of images that corresponded to the data produced by the face on the bus.  	This is similar to the way in which data mining can be used to analyse large collections of photographs and texts, or even large databases. But unlike algorithms, the network doesn’t have any kind of innate knowledge or intelligence. Rather, it relies on huge amounts of data – huge amounts of which are generated by algorithms. And as much as the images on the bus could be manipulated in various ways, the network would produce a series of images that corresponded to the data produced by the images on the bus.  	And this is what happened. The network produced images that corresponded to the data it had collected, and these images then travelled on the bus, often replacing images produced by the artist or the gallery because the network could produce images with better colour,</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus, and the way in which the numbers were represented in the image, could be decoded to produce a number of things: a QR code, a Facelet programming interface, and much more. 	The beauty of the face-processing system was that it wasn’t just a system for picking images, but also a system for generating images – images with meaning and personality. This could be seen as a huge advantage in a city such as Dublin, where the architecture and urban fabric of the city were often misrepresented in popular media as being overly industrial and technocratic, and where art was often reduced to an aesthetic necessity. 	An example of Facelets programming interface. Source: Nook Archive. 	The beauty of the face-processing system was that it wasn’t just a system for picking images, but also a system for generating images – images with meaning and personality. This could be seen as a huge advantage in a city such as Dublin, where the architecture</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments using data from the Dublin Bus, and the Bluecoat’s online booking system Turntable. It was also used to train a machine to recognise faces in a crowd, and to detect patterns in images.  	The AI wasn’t perfect, but it did have some basic human instincts of its own. It would occasionally give up a face for a new one, and it would occasionally do the opposite of what it was taught – transform into a rabbit, or go into a catatonic state when given too many options – but it was always certain that it could and would do better.  	When it came to the creation of its own image, the bot clearly had an edge. While it certainly had its hands full trying to juggle so many different images at the same time, the sheer amount of data generated by the system – thousands of images per second – meant that it could pick out interesting patterns. For example, the design of the face on the bus, with its slight variation in colour from cheek to cheek, might have something to do with the frequency with which photos were taken, and the amount of storage required, but the pattern it produced was also built into the system. When a photo was taken, the photo stream was sent to a central processing unit (CPU) at the bank of Lougheed Road, where computers picked up the patterns and fed them to the various parts of the system. The result was a series of emoji – brief hand-coloured cutaways of the designs on the back of the bus – that could be defined as recognisable by their rough cut designs. Even better, the faces on the back of the bus were also neatly classified: there were six of them, each with a name and a description, and nine more designs that emerged as a result of a random addition of characters.  	The system did have its limits, and as far as was possible, these could be addressed by way of a developer</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found
    <text>disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found in almost any part of the massive machinery. But unlike a typical computer, which operates at fixed speeds – with a fixed amount of data – a brain that is constantly processing data feeds the perception of acceleration. If data is continuously buffered across the brain, then perception becomes increasingly malleable: what’s perceived as speed increases, and what’s perceived as depth decreases. So how do we activate the perception of speed? One way is to feed the perception of motion – that there is motion – into the perception of sound. And since sound is an extremely difficult thing to perceive, we humans must learn to rely on what philosophers call the ‘ambiguous perception of space’, which is created by the complex mechanisms that underlie sound. For example, the brain depends on receptors that detect electrical signals; when those receptors are overstimulated, a phenomenon known as ‘evoked potentiality’ is triggered. This reaction is all too real in conditions of constant sensory</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found in almost any part of the machinery. But unlike a typical computer, which performs a computation on data – information such as pictures or sounds – it does not see data as an image or sound, but rather deals with images and sounds as data (see my book The Architectures of Slavery for a more in-depth look into this). Thus the image of a desk or a wall image – which can be conceptualised as either visual or auditory – plays a central role in the function of image processing. In other words, it is not just the visual image of the desk but also the auditory image, both visual and auditory. And this is where the similarities between the machine and the deaf-blind come into play. The deaf-blind see images through pipes or with filters inside the computer; images that are then processed via filters; images that are output to the screen by the computer. But unlike computers that operate at a fixed clip, the deaf-blind do not see data as images but rather</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found in many different ways through a given situation. So the idea of the ‘thought bubble’ is a bit of a misnomer. The real difference is that the human race is constantly bombarded with information, and as a result constantly underestimates the amount of information that is being thrown at us. And the more this happens, the less able we are to absorb it all, which is why great thinkers like Søren Kierkegaard and Immanuel Kant struggled to absorb as much as possible.Machine learning is the application of mathematical models to data to produce new insights. It is the unfolding of connected phenomena in real-time, and its potential is anything from identifying patterns in data to creating autonomous vehicles to performing complex scientific and engineering calculations. So far, so normal, but what is happening with us is far more insidious. It is evolving at an ever-increasing pace, and as a result we are all subject to its whims and desires. What is happening to us is happening because</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found in many different ways within the computer. But unlike a typical computer, which runs the program that it receives from elsewhere, a brain does not know – unlike a typical phone, which receives data from other places, including information from other phones, and constantly adjusts its settings, until it receives data from somewhere else as well. The brain then performs an action such as processing a sensory input, or changing its internal configuration, until it reaches a point where it has processed enough data to sustain another action such as writing a letter or drawing a picture. But unlike a typical car, which runs the program that it receives from elsewhere, a brain does not know what to do with the information it receives. It must decide for itself what to do with it. And when that decision is made, it is not made by machines but by organisms that are sentient and – well, actually quite a few organisms. So the question becomes: how are organisms able to acquire material things when they do not yet know what to do</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found in innumerable books and databases around the globe. But unlike other types of machines, the brain does not have ideas embedded within it that can be retrieved at will. Rather, the brain operates in the form of a metainterface (a.k.a. a neural network), and those with a particular set of skills reside there and communicate with each other via that neural network. And so, the metaphor breaks down: there is a ‘time lag’ between when the computer does something and when the next burst of data arrives, and that time lag creates what philosopher Gregory Bateson calls ‘fractal landscapes’ – areas where parallel universes intersect and fission occur. In other words, areas with a certain amount of fractality have certain number of counterparts with a certain amount of non-fractal phenomena. Areas with a high amount of fractality also tend to have a high density of anthropogenic pollution. Now, I don’t think that there is a</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found in many different ways throughout the body. But unlike a computer, which can be programmed to do anything, consciousness remains trapped within certain parameters. When those parameters are breached, the consequence can be quite destabilising. For instance, breaking free from the box that houses your consciousness can be quite frightening, but doing so could lead to quite drastic changes in one’s environment. In the past, when the concept of paper was invented, people often speculated about the sorts of changes that might result from the flimsier parts of the paper breaking away from the more robust parts. But the more likely outcomes are quite dystopian. You might start seeing advertisements in newspapers that read something like ‘Bionic Bitch has a Paper Towel’. Bionic Bitch’s creator, Mimi Al Sayeh, is actually a British intelligence officer who was recruited by the Israeli military in 2003 to investigate alleged British involvement in the Iraq war. In an amazing turn of events, Al Sayeh was</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found in countless books that are published every day. But unlike computers, consciousness has no value (outside of the places where its execution meets real-time). There is no such thing as a ‘consciousness capture’ – in other words, conscious information does not enter into a public realm that is constantly fed information about its own state in order to maintain its own apparent shape. The very notion of a public realm is itself a myth: in many cultures, including in many parts of the world, including in our own public realms do things that are not seen as ‘public’ (e.g., dancing in public, drinking in public, etc.). Rather, the public realm is a myth – one that has been continuously (re)imagined by an economic elite, whose only interest is in replicating itself as frequently and as farcically as possible.Machine learning is the discipline that deals with the art of making sense of huge amounts of data – breaking data into pieces that can</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found in many places, but they are all cut and scattered all across the place in the system. So the brain becomes increasingly complex, and the more complex the systems involved become, the more the image of a thought bubble can be formed. And the ‘thought bubble’ becomes what psychologist Daniel Kahneman, names the ‘false consciousness’ that he describes in his book Thinking Fast and Slow.  So the more system after system is infected with the word ‘thought’ – with the image or idea of a thought, or a notion – the more easily the image can be formed and propagated across the social network. And since the late 1990s the term ‘false consciousness’ was bandied about quite a bit, by which I mean that the infected system could propagate the infection across social networks, and thereby assume the form of consciousness. And here we see another difference between the infected and the not-infected. When the not-infected person says �</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found in many places, but they all end up running in parallel. As a result, the computer can do incredible things, such as processing information from multiple sensors at the same time, but at no point does it contemplate the enormous task of creating new consciousness. Machine consciousness simply doesn’t exist.In other words, the notion of the ‘machine’ as an object that can be understood and that has capabilities that can be controlled seems crude and antiquated by modern standards. Consciousness, by its own definition, is autonomous.Machines make mistakes, and mistakes inevitably lead to catastrophe, but thanks to the inescapable nature of capitalism, mistakes also have consequences. And what happens to us as a consequence of a mistake, or the failure to carry it out, shapes what can and cannot be done. For example, what happens when a car breaks down on the road? Will it still be possible to drive a car? If the car is broken down and thrown into a river,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by an economic elite, whose interests were determined by the establishment’s adherence to Keynesianism. But what the establishment failed to consider is that automation would also eventually decimate the jobs that were produced by the machines, and that was only possible with the machinery that was designed to function in tandem with the destruction of the jobs that were produced by the machines.Now, I get asked this question all the time: what is the difference between machine and not-machine? And I have to tell people that there is none. There is no such thing as a ‘thought bubble’ that can’t expand outward at a phenomenal rate. The emergence of consciousness is via cognitive processes, and consciousness as such is a myth. It is the product of every bit of matter, including the brain, that is constantly churning away at a prodigious clip. The brain is like a gigantic computer: it has instructions that it must carry out in real time, and those instructions can be found in many different ways throughout the body. But the computer can only carry out those parts of the equation that are mutually exclusive. If there are other equations that need to be worked out, they will have to be done in relation to each other. For instance, when you eat, you do not just brush your teeth but also chew on certain foods, digesting their contents in relation to the amount of fluoride in your water. This is because fluoride is a constituent of the toothpaste you are using, and because certain kinds of fluoride build up in your body over time. When you have dental decay, you do not just stop brushing your teeth but also eat foods high in fluoride, drinking plenty of water and getting regular fluoride injections. But that is only the beginning of the story. There are so many more moving parts than just the water and the toothpaste component that need to be worked out. You also need to be aware of what is in your water and in your food, and how that affects</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways
    <text>should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways that are representative of their specific practices, and to not be passive or compromised by such influence.  The fact that the Biennale was also co-orgueed with the participation of the local bakery and its director, and that its website still advertises bread as a service, and which people still refer to when they think of the Biennale, is testament to the fact that people recognise the significance of what they are seeing and hearing about, and that is a huge source of pride for them. The fact that the Biennale has generated so much momentum and media coverage in such a short space of time is testament to the fact that people are paying attention, and that is a testament to the organisational skills that the Biennale team showed in turning what should have been a niche art-project into a global-impact event. The fact that the Biennale is now looking at ways to support the creation of new ways of seeing art and how artists are commissioned to create</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways that are not just image making or counting money for the city.  References:  http://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2014/11/27/better-life/  http://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2014/11/27/better-life/1   	[1] The idea that the BI is a stand-in for the city first appeared in the mid 1980s when artists began turning up to the Tate Britain and the Liverpool Biennial with their ideas of the BI and its discontents. By the late 1990s, the ‘British Invasion’ was firmly established as the defining aesthetic of the ‘Europhile’.  	[2] The Tate Britain’s divisional theme was enhanced by the inclusion of a sequence of images from the Tate Modern, taken in 1989. These images show works by a select group of artists between involvement with</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways that are not dependent on corporate sponsorship or other forms of institutional support. Art institutions need to take a leadership role in regeneration – and leadership is something that they continue to struggle for – because although they may wish to present an image of participation as beneficial to society, it is actually quite the opposite.  	If you remove the individual from the equation, then the role that art institutions and the city play in regeneration is complex and unpredictable, and in many cases quite destructive. The fact that regeneration is being funded from local institutional resources, and that the majority of the funding is going to be spent on activities such as cultural centres and arts educational institutions is a case in point. As a result, there is an urgent need for arts organisations to be involved in influencing the political system in ways that will maximise growth for the local arts scene, and minimise the impact on the individuals and communities who will be affected by the regeneration policies that are being proposed. It is critical that arts organisations become involved in</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways that are not reliant on the economic logic of the sector.  	The fact that the Biennale was so successful in its initial incarnation and has remained so despite the significant cuts to state arts funding, despite the fact that regeneration agencies everywhere everywhere everywhere everywhere seem to be turning to the biennale as a way to infuse some kind of art or art form into the regeneration process, is a testament to the art form’s inherent adaptability. The art form has adapted and it will continue to be adaptable because it is a ‘transitive property’. The Biennale has a biblical strand to it because it is historically related to the festival of Passover. The festival of Passover is a festival of sacrifice, and the Biennale is a festival of blood. Passover is a biblical day of rest and rest is the day-wish of the Hebrew nation. 	The festival of Passover is marked by the burning of incense and inc</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways that are not dependent on commercial gain.  The fact that art is one of the most visible ways in which we as residents are encouraging new ideas and projects does not make it a bad thing, since it may in fact be that creative action is being encouraged by the art institutions and young people in a way that is not necessarily the result of them thinking about the city/regeneration in which they live. The fact that art institutions are working with local communities in an inherently social way and are actively engaging with communities through art-making/learning programmes does not make it a bad thing – it is a sign that things are happening, and the social conditions that need to be created.  Art is a powerful tool, and while social and political change will be necessary to address the structural inequalities that we face as a city, the art world is at least beginning to understand the value of a socially engaged and engaged public.  Art’s political potential can be seen in many of its actions</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways that are not compromised by the interests of the financial elite. 	There are of course many more ways of engaging than just through art institutions or just the economic incentives of gallery culture, but the fact that the vast majority of art is taken up by non-profit organisations, artists' organisations and cultural-oriented businesses is a powerful tool in the artworld's toolkit. The power of this kind of power politics is manifest in many forms of organisation, but the most powerful is embodied in the British Council’s Board of Directors, who have such a say when it comes to art and culture and so are the real guardians of the site’s image. 	In the 2008 Great Recession, many art institutions looked to the boardrooms of the British Council and the Board of Institutional Reviewers to rescue them from their economic predicaments, but the boards that are responsible for selecting artists, curating art and ensuring that art is made locally don’t</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal. 	The fact that this was done without the involvement of the Homebaked Community Land Trust or any of the local stakeholders in the area definitely placed a huge amount of pressure on the artist and her team, but they responded positively to the situation and have continued to do so, with many creative ideas and strategies coming out of the off. 	The new design of the bakery is a go-to for many of the artist’s ideas and strategies, along with a community land trust and a host of other stakeholders including the London School of Art, The Chisenhale Heritage Trail and Jane’s Walk. The bread that keeps coming out of the artist’s studio is a direct response to the challenge posed by the area by the bakery. It is a direct expression of the tensions and conflicts that exist between the artist and the area, but it is also a statement about the potentialities and capabilities of</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways that are not only creative, but also considerate and involve them in making regeneration a success.  	[1] http://www.bbc.co.uk/news/uk-england-liverpool-39687411. However, the decision to invest in a biennale rather than an arts institution appears to have been motivated by the assumption that the biennale would always return rather than experience a regeneration spurt. 	[2] Hannah Arendt’s ‘Empire Falls’ is a fable-like account of how the fall of an empire would affect its native soil. It was published in her book When Empire Raised a League in 1961, shortly before the start of the 1925 First World War. It is a fable in that it is a fictionalized account, but it is much more concerned with the fate of an imperial power and the destiny of a people when, as</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways that are not dependent on commercial incentives.  Being in a position to influence the way in which regeneration is done, artists have an obligation to take part in it in ways that are not passive or minimal. This is why it is so exciting and freeing for artists to be able to create their own future, because then they can create innovative ways of engaging with regeneration that are not dependent on commercial interests: by being in creative control of their future, they can therefore actively shape its course and thereby create innovative alternative ways of inhabiting and using it.  Similarly, the biennial as an art form has an obligation to actively participate in creating the infrastructure of a community or neighbourhood, because whilst it may be a transient, transient image, it is a recognisable image and a commonly-used image across the globe.  Artists have an ethical obligation to take part in creating a future for their communities, because whilst they may not always agree with the decisions that they are forced to make,</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the participation of the local artists, community organisers and architects (including the Homebaked Community Land Trust) was low risk, but the way in which the engagement with the site was facilitated definitely places great strains on the local artworld image. The fact that this was done with the involvement of a multinational corporation while the local art scene was decimated left a lot of people questioning the role of art institutions in the city. Art institutions obviously have a role to play in regeneration, but it is important that they are participatory and not just a passive observer, because whilst they may have a role to play, they will ultimately be accountable when the opportunity presents itself to maximise economic profit and loss. As an institution they may choose to participate in some way, but they have a responsibility to reflect and take part in regeneration in ways that are not passive or minimal, which is why it is so important for artists to find artists' organisations that are committed to taking part in regeneration in ways that are not governed by a sole commercial interest.  	In the end it may be that the engagement of an art institution with the local community in ways that are most directly related to the image it projects onto the cityscape is one that it is very difficult to reverse once made. If made, such initiatives are very likely to be modified by forays into the city's redeveloping schemes, which in turn may alter the image they project onto and the needs they are tasked with serving. This may be the case where the interests of the commercial and the cultural collide; once a development has been approved and the need for photography has been taken off the cityscape, it is very difficult to take back or change the image that is projected through such development. There is a danger that if the image of the art institution is exaggerated or distorted in a particular way, there is a possibility that the development may continue to exist despite the art institution having actively rejected it. 	If this is the case</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge were made in the form of puzzles, or, as in the case of this exhibition, in the form of objects that have been assembled from different parts of the world is incidental. Like the collection of objects in this exhibition, the collection of contemporary art is made up of many different forms – produced by and for a particular community of artists, curators, collectors and others. It is made up of diverse collections, with and without boundaries. It is a collection of different worlds. It is a collection of playthings – things that can be catered to, and things that can be discarded. It is a collection of unexpected connections. It is a collection of curiosities. It is a collection of quirky individuals. It is a collection of curiosities in collections. It is a collection of curiosities that happen to be curiosities. As such, it is a strange and wonderful collection. But what is a curioity in the first place? I propose the following curatorial</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge are clay or masonry forms, or artefacts of a later age, is emphasised. In the exhibition ‘The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics’, the objects are of another kind: they are contemporary works in storage, in the style of a dealer in new art objects. This latter kind of contemporary art is what is exhibited in the catalogue of the museum, and it is displayed in the exhibition itself. It is a changing kind of art, exhibiting new kinds of art, performed in the unconventional settings of the contemporary art market, in the conventional temporalities of museum and museum of art, and in the politics and complexities of contemporary art today. It is art that was made today in the contemporary condition, contemporary art with an air of modernism mixed with art from earlier eras. It is art to be discovered and acquired, and often a first impression that a journey into the past will bring one to a place of infinite possibilities, of making one’s way out of difficult situations</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge are contemporary art objects is the subject of an essential change during the exhibition. The inclusion of contemporary art in the overall concept of the museum has always been an element of the exhibitionary form, and the inclusion of contemporary art is a feature of the curatorial function during the twentieth century. But the increasing importance of art today, and the fact that the curator’s job is to a large extent automated, makes the museum the site of a counterattack on the museum, or at least a counterattack on what is perceived as the dominant form of the museum. The curatorial task is no longer confined to the museum, but now includes cultural or archival curation, an area that has recently renewed interest in itself, and a task that is not necessarily associated with the museum but is often seen as museum-like. For example, the curatorial role in the mediaeval and Renaissance art museums was initially performed by curators or curators selected from the arts educational institutions in London, but after</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge are clay and plastic has no bearing on the meaning of their purchase; they have no relationship to the meaning of their acquisition. The meaning of acquisition is contextual. A collection manager or curatorial team might choose to focus on a particular collection in the context of a given exhibition, or perhaps the context of an international exhibition of a particular kind. The aim of this exhibition is to show the wider collection in a chronological sequence, beginning with Nina Edge’s collection from the 1920s, continuing with that of another curatorial group from the 1990s, and so on. The collection manager or curatorial team might also select from the collection to suggest topics for discussion or research, or to simply host a gathering of people working on a particular topic, gathering material for a future exhibition. The aim of this exhibition is to combine a chronological narrative with a local micro-history of a particular locality. This is done through the use of maps, graphs, sound recordings and videos of places, as well as texts</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge are clay and the objects in the collection of the Museum of Modern Art are metal is emphasized throughout the exhibition. The idea that these are objects of a later vintage is emphasized by the use of images of artworks from the period: some of the images are archival prints from a postcard magazine of the time, and the rest are still life paintings from a smaller department store that was the scene of several violent altercations between art dealers and art buyers. The exhibition presents the history of art in the region in relation to the tendency towards contemporaneity implied by technological innovation, and the resultant nomadic character of art-utility. It also aims to recall the artist’s identification with the locality through the artefact of a particular form of art as a ‘metainterface’ – a set of infrastructure, procedures and networks of art-historical data. The exhibition is divided into two parts: the part on the premises of the Museum of Modern Art, New</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind is explained by the curatorial decision to place them in a different category from those of the more central kind. In so doing, the curators draw our attention to a distinction that has been making news lately: the use of 3-D modelling in art and design.  [At the center of the current art ‘rehearsal’ is a question: what comes after the artist, after the 3-D scanner? What comes after the 3-D printer? What comes after the 3-D material? What comes after the 3-D printing press?]

The Contemporary Condition, 2 nd ed. (New York: Routledge, 2015), p.27.

3. Bakargiev, Art of Late, p.26.

4. Karp, ‘Civil War in Myths and Realities’, in  	Karp, Marc, ed., Contemporary Art (New</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge are clay and those in the collection of the Museum of Modern Art are wood is emphasized throughout the exhibition. In the case of the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, the objects selected from the collection of Edge are of a much grander kind: they are works in the collection of a national gallery. The distinction between the two kinds of museum is made explicit: the kind of museum that deals in collections and the kind of museum that deals in museum collections, or the kind that houses works from a particular author’s home town. It is evident that the objects selected from the collections of the two museums are then presented in a particular order, as though the two museums had different collections, and the order they take places in is determined by the criteria of the particular museum. In this exhibition, the different kinds of museum are positioned in relation to each other. The notion of time is understood in this way: the relationship between collection and museum is understood in relation to a particular kind of museum,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge are clay and that the objects in the collection of the Museum of Modern Art are man-made, as well as the fact that the collection of the museum includes objects from the period when the art was produced in China, suggests a link between the two periods. The notion of time, which is emphasised in the contents of the exhibition, is emphasized in a number of places, as in the text that follows the main heading: ‘The idea of the contemporary or contemporary universal is global and includes all human experience in one and the same space’. The emphasis here is, however, on the inarticular; it is the contemporary experience, even though it is universal. This is perhaps why, when the younger generation of artists, especially those drawn to the museum or the contemporary art market, hears the term ‘comprehensive contemporary art exhibition’, they tend to think of the museum as having a collection of objects that are continuously on display, rather than the other way</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge belong to the Museum of Modern Art does not alter the fact that they are local to New York. The Museum of Modern Art, like the Museum of Modern Art in Berlin, is a museum, but it is a museum of collections, curated by a curator, whose job is to engage with, and instruct visitors about the specific collections he or she has access to. Nina Edge’s interests are quite different from those of a museum curator. Nina Edge has a particular interest in the collection of objects in the collection of her father, and she has made several collections of her own, of which this exhibition is a part. She has worked closely with the collection manager of the Museum of Modern Art, and has even co-curated the forthcoming exhibition of her father’s work, entitled The Modern Collection: Art, Architecture, Architecture in Contemporary Culture. However, the collection manager is not there to teach or instruct. Her job is to collect the things that the museum might want, to</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family

By Patricia Hill and Elena L. Tshisek

Published in ELISA L. TSHISEK, Contemporary Art and Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, p.109.

The exhibition The Contemporary Art &amp; Its Critics, Polity Press, New York, 1995, pp.109–18, includes a collection of objects selected from the collection of the Museum of Modern Art, including a set of 36 large clay figurines and a set of eight clay objects. The collection includes many objects from the period when the exhibition is presented, but the objects chosen are selected from a smaller set that also includes 40 objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge. The objects selected from the collection of Nina Edge are of a more peripheral kind: they are objects in the collection of a local art dealer, or, as in the case of this exhibition, of a museum. The fact that the objects in the collection of Nina Edge are of a later date makes them parts of collections, and part of museums. They are objects in the collection of a museum, and part of collections in their own right. For more on collections and museums, see myThe Museum as a Container and the Collection as a Museum-Conducted Project, ed. Stefan Collini, MFA The Artist's College, University of California, Riverside, 2015, p.18.

Esther Graham-Hughes, ‘Carrying Capacity: Community Art and the Political-Economic-Materialist Imperative of the Metainterface’,  The Collectors, Vol. 4, No. 1, Spring, 2008, p.1.

I. Introduction 

The Metainterface is a term that derives from the 1970s, and more specifically, from a conference that I co-chaired as co-curator of the Liverpool Biennial: Art and Artifacts of the Twent</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo
    <text>disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo’: an image that represents, describes or represents the ‘entity of a nation or a particular area in a continuous series of images’.[37] 	[38] 	Burtynsky reminds us that the image of the image is an image of expansion, of new ‘places to be found’ in the photography of ‘eastern European and other nations’. And these ‘new’ ‘places’ were not found in the images of nineteenth-century photography, but rather representational media such as prints and the ballpoint pen. Prints representational media are characterised by their use as a media for capturing and representing a specific idea or idea, whether that ‘ideology’ is national or international or racialised. 	[39] 	Print culture is a globalising phenomenon that finds expression in all aspects of modern and contemporary culture. On a global or ‘regional’ level, the</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo’: a photo of a ‘different kind of nation’, one that engages with the notion of place and its relations as different kinds of image communicate different kinds of history. 	[37] 	This new kind of archival photography engages with any notion of place that questions the authority of a nation-state, or questions the intrinsic worth of a nation-state. It engages with the notion of nationhood in such a way as to render its peoples either visible or invisible, while simultaneously insisting that these peoples are not there but elsewhere, that different kinds of history have taken place, and that – in the final analysis – that their presence is required. 	[38] 	This new kind of archival photography is a product of a different kind of photographer, and it emerges from the perforations of a photographer that thrives on the illusion of contemporaneity. ‘Postcard as journalism’, as the Oxford English Dictionary defines it, provides</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo’: a photo of the image would be inadequate without the photo of the place where the image was taken. ‘A photo of an object does not simply convey its characteristics; it is a picture of phenomena as they exist in that object … a kind of “objectified” image that conveys a particular kind of “entity” in the process of image making.’[37] 	[38] This is particularly so for images of cultural exchange, which are objects of exchange and are frequently used as images of the social world: a photo of the Barbican, for example, is an image of the Barbican itself. 	[39] The use of images of cultural exchange is a global enterprise that is increasingly influential in our daily lives. As one might imagine, the postcard publication of images of cultural exchange (a.k.a. ‘image-processing’ operations) as part of an overall ‘scientific�</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo’: one based on the circulation of images, which ‘created a new kind of image’.[37] This attests to the fact that images no longer represent universal truth or ultimate values; rather, they signify only certain kinds of images. In this sense, Burtynsky writes, images are instances of a new planetary image-processing system that ‘produces images of things that are not there, making them visible, audible and ‘infographic’ in nature’.[38] 	Images are images, and images are images of things. But what kinds of things are there to image? What kinds of relations between things and images can images chart? ‘Image is a universal language that allows the establishment of social relations between people.’ This is what Natalia Kardasova and Natalia Fedorova, for instance, in their images of the Ekho Moskva Art Biennale, attempt to demonstrate by showing photographs from different</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo’: one in which images linked peoples and places.1 	[37] 	In this photo essay, Burtynsky demonstrates this notion of ‘different kinds of image’ by revealing the ways in which photography remains bound up with its pre-digital circulation of images. As images circulate from camera to camera, they create a re-alignment of cultural power and significances, as we move from one place of image making to another. Burtynsky’s term  	media is used to describe the transmutation of images: images that are captured, that are made, that are circulated, that are repeated. But images are also ‘transmuted’ by human hands into forms that are representations of things or sets of things.2 	[38] And this is precisely what images such as Burtysnsky’s images of the Earth and the Sea of Fiction – the image of a person or a collection</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo’: a photo that represents the ‘total world’, but also the ‘specific world’.[37] 	The global image of the photographer is a photo that represents both the social totality as a series of images taken in and around the particular place where the image is published, and also the specific world of the photographer’s subjects. This is true not only of images of places, animals, people and the like, but also of still images, video and still photographs. 	[38] 	But while the social totality is taken as a given in the social-media age, the seemingly innocent still images that circulate on a daily basis nonetheless have a ‘political implication’, as Burtynsky would have it. 	[39] 	There are other images of the world that circulate on a global basis, and these too are subject to cultural appropriation and political propaganda. One example is the still image that came to symbol</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo’, one that placed national interests ahead of the universal.’[37] 	[1] The Economist, op. cit. (July 2010). [2] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, 1485, in Burtynsky, op. cit., p. 31. [3] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, 1485, in Burtynsky, op. cit., p. 32. [4] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, 1485, in Burtynsky, op. cit., p. 33. [5] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, 1485, in Burtynsky, op. cit., p. 34. [6] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, 1485, in Burtynsky, op. cit., p. 35. [7] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, 1485, in Burtynsky</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo’: a photo that registers everywhere, but is specific to a particular place and time.[37] 	In this sense, the global image produced by photography is a photo-like medium through which social systems were made to register and register their presence, thoughts and deeds. It is a photo-like medium through which images of a given character, place, thing, event could be characterised and classified. It is a photo-like medium through which images of a given culture could be grouped together and compared. 	[38] And here we could suggest a third dimension to this element of cultural capitalism: that of the fictive. 	To be sure, the global image produced by photography today is a photo-like medium through which social interactions are disguised and mediated through images. Images are snapshots taken from various points of view, from different angles, from different perspectives, in different social situations. But what if these images also produced different images? What if these images today represent</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo’: photographic still photography replaced the voyeuristic voyeurism of the past. ‘Burtynsky, Photo-Imaging Culture and Urban Crisis, Praeger, New York, 1988, p.108. 	[37] See Colin Wardle, ed., The Photographic Archives of Modern Times (Oxford University Press, Oxford and London, 2016), p.81. 	[38] See N. Wardle, ed., The Photographic Archives of Modern Times (Oxford University Press, Oxford and London, 1996 and 1999), p.10. 	[39] Wardle, op. cit., p.10. 	[40] See S. Wardle, Image and the Film, Harper &amp; Row, New York, 1996, p.6. 	[41] Wardle, op. cit., p.10. 	[42] See Edward W. Wolff, ed., The Cambridge Handbook of</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by those with a financial stake in the manifestation of globalisation.[34]’[35]As noted by sociologist Ajamu Baraka, the advent of photography in the late nineteenth century opened new vistas of cultural exchange, including the possibility of archiving and communication in the interests of the common. Pictorial archival services were utilized to document the movement of animals, humans and objects as part of the wider movement for common ownership and governance of space. In this sense, photography is thought to have been a significant factor in the materialisation of new social formations that became institutionalised through the development of modernity. 	[36] 	However, the re-embraced, globalisable image of the photographer as a global commodity and subject of a national archive is a response to the perceived nationalisms entwined in photography and its postcard publication. As Edward Burtynsky reminds us, the global circulation of images necessitated a ‘different kind of photo’, one that is not image accumulation but image distillation.[37] 	The global image industry – which had been developing at a breakneck rate in the decades immediately following World War II – was put on notice in the wake of the war. Rapid technological developments were put to use in the production of figurative cover images that depicted the heroic exploits of modern naval and air power in the war against terror. The image of a ship in the action of war was put to better use in the production of propaganda images of the miraculous escapades of nautical fantasy. Edward Burtynsky, ‘The Technology of Imagination’, in Technology, Culture &amp; War (MIT Press, 1976), p. 5. 	The proliferation of scientific and technological know-how in the service of war production gave rise to a class of engineers and scientists with a particularised focus on the deployment of energy resources and the economic perquisite of navigation and tracking technology. These new administrators</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�
    <text>curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�s. And I think that the fact that the biennial form has become so embedded in what makes the city different from the countryside is a good thing, a sign that the city is holding its own against the forces of nature and can defend itself.  In fact, in some ways, the more political and social-media-influenced the city is, the more it’s in effect reproducing itself, because the more we use it, the more we create value for ourselves and others. As biennials became more institutionalised and political in nature, and the city more integrated into the urban-dynamics of global capitalism, it became less and less possible to envision a future for the city outside of the city.  The biennial as an institutional form is no longer able to sustain the symbolic and the aestheticisation of the city, but it does have the capacity to instigate and generate change through enforcing capital accumulation. In other words, the biennial may</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�s remoteness and urban immobility. We don’t necessarily know what these new cultural institutions are like, but I think that the connection is there. There’s a reason why biennials have been there for so long, and why they’re still there, even though the city is so ubiquitously dispersed. The biennial format remains very much a part of what I call the ‘city of the spectacle’, and it remains an important and powerful vector through which cultural capital is constructed and distributed. But it’s becoming increasingly difficult to define and to quantify the spectacle in a precise way, and I think that at the same time there’s a need to work collectively and imaginatively on behalf of the city in order to create what I would call a simulacrum of the city in the here and now. This may require cooperation between public authorities, participation by artists, as well as innovative local strategies that seek to break open previously</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�s life. In other words, the biennial as a concept is relevant in the twenty-first century, and will continue to shape contemporary art in ways that are influenced by the city.In this regard, we can consider the experience of the biennial as an episteme, as a mode of experiencing, and through that we can move away from the subject and focus on the artefact. Through the years that have passed since my first Biennale, I have continued to receive messages from people saying things like ‘I remember that time when the art was here, and the life was “Here!” and ‘That was a ‘once in a lifetime’ experience!’ I get messages from all over the world, and from places like Georgia, where people still remember the Biennale of 2000AD as a day to remember. And people still remember the time when the Biennale was a daily event, as it are now: as</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�s extraordinary growth. The number of biennials has more than doubled in the last twenty years, and the number of cities experiencing such growth is now in excess of six, with New York, London, Mumbai and Shenzhen accounting for over half of worldwide figures. Cities now account for over twenty-five per cent of the global travelled goods  traffic, with an additional twenty per cent transported by air, and constitute more than forty per cent of all global car trips.  	And what does it mean for a city to be growing? Urban growth is an inexhaustible source of energy, yet it’s increasingly clear that the source of this inexhaustible energy isn’t just the city. Cities are adding resources to meet growing demands, but what’s more and what is more and which follows at a greater rate as the city continues to grow is a mix of new urban structures and programs that account for around twenty per cent of the global road freight</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�s. As the BIENNIALS first director, Guillermo Vitaleggi, once said: the museum is the body of the exhibition, and the body of the exhibition. ‘The body of the exhibition’ is constantly on the point of injury, and exhibitions, on the contrary, are its surgeons.’ The body of the exhibition is injured, and its surgeons are its healers. It’s a vicious circle.I thought, then, that the biennial format would follow the anatomy of the body, and that the principle goal of the institution following this model would be to heal the body as much as possible. I put it down to the fact that in the twenty-first century, we’ve come to understand the importance of understanding anatomy, and thus of modelling the body in a precise way. The biennial format would, I believe, follow the same basic principles, but it would also follow the following: there would be a protocol to</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�s metropolis, its spaces and its neighbourhoods. I think that’s a powerful combination.  The other element in the mix is the proliferation of social media; new technological experiences that entwine us more and create unexpected new connections; and autonomous and connected devices. All of these things are forms of urbanization that ouple the art institution with the new technology and the connectedness that emerges from that, and then pass it on to the next generation. And so the relationship between art and technology evolves.  Art and technology are complex, but they also have certain fundamental assumptions and desires that we share, and that shape how we conceive of the world. And what happens when those values clash, and that creates conflicts? I would argue that there are three elements to consider: the need for trust, the need for control and the third element: the capacity to imagine and to shape change.The need for trust is one that all of us share, and yet unfortunately many of us don’</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�s emergence and its development. They provide a kind of permanent memento of the city that is evergreen and multi-use and adaptable and can act as a kind of buffer between the urban and the rural, the urban and the natural world. So these kinds of institutions that emerged out of the city in the nineteenth century, with their guilding together, the national pavilions, the international ones, the international fairs, the ‘metainterface’, the ‘pandora’, the urban and ‘hubby pavilion’, the ‘gorgeous new restaurants and cafes emerging from the city’s core’. These kinds of localised and globalised historical occurrences play out now in the wake of the biennial, but they were also precursors to much more expansive and far-reaching cultural theories, and much of what we think of as the biennial today is actually the emerging out-of-</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�s. In other words, the biennial form that I described in the 1980 exhibition as ‘permanent’ means that the art institution that I described as ‘permanent’ would remain in existence, but would also change form and evolve in other ways. Biennials have done this through the ages, but their power and influence today comes from many different places than the classical classical biennials. The power of the biennial is in its multiplicity of forms, which can be witnessed at any time of day in many parts of the world: in art fairs around the world, in art fairs in the UK, in the Venice Biennale, in the Bienal de São Paulo, in the Asian Triennale, in the Asian Triennale of the same name, in large museums in Moscow and Beijing, and in the newly established Phantom tour organisation based in Berlin. In these connections, the biennial becomes yet another variable</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�s ongoing economic and cultural evolution. They may be located in a particular city, such as New York or London, but they’re often embedded in a particular city’s social structure and history. They act as a buffer between artist and city, between art and life, and between the city and the rural, suburban and urban environments that are shaping the future. They provide a physical counter to the massive machines that are displacing us all.What I find interesting and powerful about the biennial is that it provides a way of thinking about the future that isn’t reductive or pessimistic. It’s a way of imagining alternatives and questioning the power structures that are creating the conditions for a different future. What I mean by that is, there are many other worlds out there, and they’re not necessarily the same as what we live in, and they’re messy, dangerous, unpredictable and unpredictable, but they are possible. And there’s a</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �quasi-art institution’, which was both an extension of and a response to the curatorial tendencies of the pastel-coloured buildings that were replacing the greenspace of the city. The biennial format coincided with the change, however, that it was necessary to consider and pass on to future generations, the changes that were occurring in the city. ‘Permanent Maté �� and Permanent Capital �� are the two words that describe the city today, but they weren’t there when I started. In the beginning of the twenty-first century, we can still say that the biennials came and went; that there was no city as such. But today, there ��s a city, and I think that what’s happening is that the art institutions that were there at the beginning of the century are now some of the most prominent in the world, and their presence shapes and is shaped by the city�s. For example, the Biennale of Sydney, which was founded in 1903, was originally conceived as a biennale of culture in the city, with the city as the backdrop. But as the city evolved, and new uses for the biennale came to be imagined, the Biennale’s true focus shifted to the suburbs. The city was seen as a backdrop that allowed the Biennale to operate in an eventful way, but also that it could be a stage on which the artist or curator could establish an independent artistic project.  So, the Biennale’s true mission statement, which I think is an important one, is this: given the city as its backdrop and the city as its eventual stage, what other possible cinematic setting can there be? The answer to that question is, of course, ‘nothing’.  So, the next time you’re at a biennial and see artists developing their art projects on</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Bienn
    <text>should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Biennale has always been an art form with an inflated and celebrity-seeking public, and it is this double standard that I seek to expose in this exhibition. The Biennale is a spectacular occasion, with rich traditions and impressive artefacts, and it is important that these are preserved and appreciated in their historical contexts. But it is also my position that the responsibility for the Biennale and its rich traditions lies with the individual artists, composers, curators and art collectors who commission and lead the performances, exhibitions and festivals, as well as the city. The city has a unique and powerful cultural and economic history, and its autonomy, cultural capital and economic potential are immense. The biennale can play a pivotal role in its future, but it is the artist, the curatorial choice and the artist that ultimately determine what is made manifest and what is not. The biennale must be an art form that is maximised in its potentialities and minimised in its constraints. I propose</text>
    <text>should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Biennale has traditionally been a showcase for artists from the City with a particular interest in the arts, and since the early twentieth century has been an arts organisation with a public programme of activities. In 1917 the Academy established a public gallery in its main building, which became the Gallery of Modern Art (GMA). Although the GMA maintained a significant collection of objects in storage, its main exhibition programme was a self-selecting patronage of contemporary art from the city. Since the early 1920s, the GMA’s main exhibitionary programme had included a selection of British and international artists, many of whom were London based. The biennale became an international phenomenon through the combination of public and private funding, a well-established international reputation, and a well-established global image.  The Biennale’s relationship to the larger urban landscape is a complex one. Its origins are attributed to two events: the American artist William Burroughs, who proposed the idea in 1967, and</text>
    <text>should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Biennale has continued to be an art form through and beyond its formalised forms, with artists and designers developing practices that seek to intervene directly in the cultural context of the city in much the same way that the RA did in the 1980s. For more information, see my book The Arts and Architecture of the Twenty-First Century: Contemporaneous Futures (2011). 5. The Biennale’s membership and financial report. 	[1] Gareth White, The Biennale Industry (New York: Independent Art Publishers, 2015), p. 30.Download this article as PDFRyan AventRyan Avent is a curator based in New York City who works with the Biennale as a consultant and maintains the website artalarm.org. His research examines the connection between the biennale and other art forms, including the archaeological and historical aspects of art and culture as a whole. In addition to reporting on the archaeological and historical aspects of the bienn</text>
    <text>should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Biennale has traditionally been a showcase for artists from the City, and has invited these artists to produce works around the themes of their activities, such as urban renewal and the arts’ social contribution. Their output has often been provocative, and their discourses have often been aggressive, but they have also tended to operate on a shoestring budget, relying on public and private donations to fund their activities.5. The Biennale’s relationship to the city. The Biennale and its portfolio of artworks is produced and directed by an artist-organisation that is guaranteed a financial return on its investment, and that has a clear interest in preserving the city as a material resource for the economy. The Biennale has a website with information about its production and the work it produces, as well as a blog with extensive posts about the production of artworks at the Biennale. The Biennale has promoted itself as a biennale that engages with ‘deeply embedded</text>
    <text>should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Biennale now organises most major biennials around its own London headquarters, with the exception of those located in other cities. The Biennale has a history of holding its own against the academy’s historical claims, and it remains the top dog in this relationship. In the Biennale calendar, the Academy is often referred to as ‘the academy of aesthetics’. In reality, however, this is an insult – the academy is the parent of both aesthetic theory and journalism. The Academy has always been committed to publishing its own journal, and it maintains a permanent collection of works from which it issues a quarterly magazine, called The Red Book, published at the Royal Academy of Arts every two years. Its aim is to record and discuss its own work in an accessible and influential way, with regular exhibitions of works from different works. In many ways, the Academy’s journal is an accurate reflection of its world. But its value is derived from its authoritative publication of ideas and</text>
    <text>should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Biennale has clearly been a significant source of income for the organisation, and has included in its catalogue works that might be considered to be provocative or politically charged. For more information about the relation between art and the arts organisation, see my book Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future (2007).5. The Biennale as a media phenomenon. The Biennale has a media profile and is a major player in its field. It has produced and is producing (with support from the Arts Council) a new exhibition every two years called The Contemporary Condition. It was recently voted the second most viewed exhibition on tour by a major arts organisation in the world, behind only the Venice Biennale. The Contemporary Condition is a ‘time-specific’ exhibition, and as such it is focussed on specific cultural moments in the contemporary world. It was recently selected for its 'expansions and shows that matter' at the Grantham–Museum of Modern Art</text>
    <text>should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Biennale has always been keen to foster a mutually beneficial relationship with the city, and has consistently staged exhibitions in the city as a way to do so.5. The Biennale as an art form, the art of the niche, 1984–96. Created by the Biennale, Museo de Arsenale, Uruguay, and the Museo del Triennale, Italy, and the two largest curatorial teams from each country, the 1984 and 96 biennales took place simultaneously, often in very different venues in the same year. The two biennales that followed in 1989 and 1990 were significantly different, and although the main themes and goals remained the same, the curatorial approaches were quite different. The primary reason for the change was the biennial itself, which was moved to London from Montevideo in 1990, and the lack of a similar biennial in Uruguay at that time. The biennial structure was different, and the new format of the art fair was also different –</text>
    <text>should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Biennale has always been a co-convenience of the City and the Museum, and has often been self-centred. In this sense, the Biennale has been seen as a Museum of Commodities, where the Museum is seen as a museum of Imagination. In this sense, the Biennale is sometimes seen as a Museum of Commerce, because of its focus on large-scale market-dominating projects, including those that were initiated or led by academics, artists or curators. In this sense, the Biennale could be seen as a museum of exchange, with works coming and going, exhibiting, products being manufactured, people moving about, and with an ethos of economic exchange at its core. In this sense, the museum could be seen to be the microcosm of a much larger cultural exchange. In these ways, the Biennale can be seen to operate at a regional, local, or even national level. For more information visit the Bienn</text>
    <text>should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Biennale has always maintained a very visible presence in the City, even during the recession, and a fascination with the artefacts and urban forms produced by the new economy of culture that emerged during the decade of the biennale. In recent years the Biennale has tended to be more circumscribed, and the new technological culture that it supports more widely visible, although there is still a great deal of energy and energy is put into creating a new archaeological site for the Biennale to be held in, and a new cultural venue for the city. There is much focus on the biennale as a visual art form in the City, and the importance of good art being produced in the context of the exhibitionary form. I think that some of our exhibitionary form’s excesses can be traced to the Biennale. We have to think about how to reconceive what the Biennale means in the city, in the context of a new art venue and cultural venue, in</text>
    <text>should have been curated by an architect, architect or landscape architect of the year preceding the date of the present exhibition’s production].3. Design exhibitions, design and the multi-use of design. For more information about the relationship between design and architecture see my book 'Contemporary Art and the Architecture of the Future' (2007).4. The Biennale as an art form. The Biennale has always been a very visible projection of the power structures of the City of London, and its links with the Royal Academy of Arts were made even more obvious by the fact that the Academy had been founded in 1607. In the years immediately after the Academy’s foundation, artists and designers from all over the world established formal relationships with the Biennale organisers, culminating in the creation in 1881 of the Royal Academy of Arts (RAA). The relationship between the two organisations has continued to be a point of contention, with the Academy withdrawing from the Biennale in 1987. The Biennale has a long-term commitment to the City, and although it has occasionally played host to significant scale cultural events, such as the Venice Biennale,3, 4, it has tended to remain static in this respect. Its relationship to the City of London has been a point of contention, with some in the Biennale claiming a right to the city as a ‘capital city’, whilst others (including Biennale Director Matthew Freud) arguing that the organisation should actively reclaim space and reclaim buildings. In an attempt to reconcile the apparent paradoxes of the institution and the city, the Biennale in its early years attempted to reconcile the former with the latter. In a nutshell, the claim was that the Biennale was hosting, and was therefore actually a co-production with, ‘a community of artists and designers based in the City of London’, who were creating a ‘performance space for the community to be invited into and participating in through a</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing.
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing. Climate-controlled pens and cages are the preserve of a few privileged individuals. Overcrowding, overcrowding, overcrowding. 	Making matters worse is the fact that these cages are often used as temporary quarters for the homeless, with noxious mould growing in the chips provided ample ventilation. 	Taking up residence in such environments is a more challenging challenge for communities of colour, as a result of the greater exposure to the elements. Humans have evolved to live in environments with varying degrees of natural daylight, which means that it is possible to simultaneously be outdoors and indoor. The challenge then becomes how to distribute the environmental resources amongst diverse needs and values. 	In an ideal world, every person and every place would be green, with people born solely to do so being confined to habitat that is as maximally healthy as possible. Unfortunately, this is not always possible, and recent scientific studies have shown that environmental enrichment is still largely dependent on the wealthy and the well-connected. In such cases</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing. The Arctic is a scene of conflict as the conflictring nations of the former Soviet Union are attempting to recreate a relationship based on shared resources. The conflict between these two main energy resources sources has been raging for over a century. The loss of Arctic wildlife threatens not only the infrastructure of the cities that are dependent on energy supplies, but also the very DNA of the system.  	[i] Ars Technica,  	http://arstechnica.com/content/art/utilities/arstechnica/2017070811800.html#sthash.WP8l7Jl.4xw.J2YW5.dpuf.dpuf.2007.12.14T2.Biennial.2007.xlsx (accessed July 2018). Available at: http://www.biennial.com/arts/utilities/2017070811800.html#sthash.WP8l7J</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing. Why are our cities built on fossil fuels that are 40% more energy-intensive than oil? Why are our roads made of materials that break down at a breakneck speed due to tyre wear? Why are our transport systems designed with sensors that continuously monitor the condition of the road and transport system itself? Why are our landscapes dotted with agricultural plots that are too small to stand on but are too big to fail? Why do so many climate-altered landscapes re-brand as ‘green’? These are just some of many of many of the questions that can be posed to a curator or a curator-general. The answers to these questions can be found in The Art Newspaper, the Fourth International Conference Proceedings of the World Conservation Congress (WCC), and the Journal of the Royal Anthropological Society. 	The Art Newspaper, fourth international conference of the World Conservation Congress, 1947. Photo courtesy of the Royal Academy of Arts. 	The Fourth International Conference Proceedings</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing. Art, from a biennial perspective, is a valuable tool for alerting us to impending threats and providing opportunities for mitigation. It is also critical that art be effective at influencing public actions, so as to influence change and arrive at unintended consequences. In this regard, our curatorial approach and our work in the field cannot be underestimated. Our exhibition ‘Timestamps’ at the Biennale of Sydney in 2017 included works from the archives of the Biennale – a process that we believe is as relevant and powerful as its historical value – and from the archives of the Habitats International, a movement to archive and preserve underground art and culture.  We even featured a story from the archives of the Habitats International web site, in which a member of the community recounts the life of one of the organisation’s artists. https://www.habitats.org/2018/exhibition/archive/archive.html?section=Art&amp;month=November</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing. Art is an exceptional tool in the environmental 'warrior’s kit, but its real use may be more dangerous. What might an art gallery or a museum of art do if all art was made equal? 	[1] See Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, published in 1949. 	[2] See John Urry, ‘On Mental Attractiveness’, in Modern Psychologies, Vol. 4, No. 1, February, 1949, p.107–19. 	[3] As regards the role of the physician, see Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, published in 1949. 	[4] John A. Church and Neil J. White, ‘The Psychology of Blame and Blame-Bay: A Case Study of the Environment and Mentalist Samuel Morse’, Journal of a Japanese Association for the Study of Culture and Society Vol. 22</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing. The increasing number of art projects funded by the Danish Council for Independent Arts and the World Fund for Art and Culture (WWF) in the Scandinavian capital, Stockholm, highlights the fact that art is being made somewhere else – in the context of an increasingly globalised and interconnected world. Art is being made in Memphis, Iraq, as part of the Pitch Black conference, but it’s also being made in Mumbai, India; in Manama, Saudi Arabia; in The Woodlands, Texas, USA; in the Tibetan Autonomous Region, China; and in Doha, Qatar.Art and social impact is a strategy that is making inroads into the problematic notion of climate change, even if it’s made by those with a financial stake in the geo-political system. It’s energy that is being made, and art is being made alongside it. It’s a rarefaction of artists who are not contractually obliged to look after the planet</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing. How we perceive the role of art in art’s social agency is another story. We need to find new social valences for the art of climate-action. 	In the 2017 Biennale of Sydney, the Dutch artist Jeanne van Heeswijk used art as a weapon in an attempt to save coral reefs from destruction. She was arrested and charged with ‘inhabitants’ of Crown property offences because she refused to relinquish the Crown lands to the state. Art is not immune from climate change, as serious as that sounds. But van Heeswijk’s art is heroic in its intent and its success. She made a commitment to never again allow coral reefs to be ‘fortress-like structures’, and to instead use her wealth to create ‘transformative urban spaces’. Most of us don’t have the luxury of thinking that we do because our societies constantly strive to adapt and create more of</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing. With unprecedented flooding, melting ice caps and intensifying droughts, we’re seeing desertification projected for parts of Afghanistan, Iraq, Syria and Egypt. Art is a rare commodity these days, but its return to the climactic conflict zone seems inevitable.  	[1] The Arctic is the thinnest region on Earth, and the third-largest in the Middle East and North Africa. It is home to an estimated 11% of the Earth’s ice and is predicted to expand to 19% by the century’s end. See NASA Goddard Space Flight Center, Goddard.  	[2] Climate models provide a near-absolute assessment of a climate system’s response to limiting emissions of greenhouse gases. Models depict a future with no change, whereas actual climate varies with the forcing of specific emissions reductions. See Climate Central, Climate.gov, accessed October 2018. 	[3] ‘Sea Level Rise | Greenpeace International</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing. Art and climate change are not mutually exclusive strategies. The former has potential impacts that are difficult to adapt to in the presence of the latter, but the former has the potential to alter the very geography of the biennial. The main driver of climate change that we are witnessing is due to anthropogenic emissions of greenhouse gases – a compound that together with water, is the most fundamental component of the climate system. The rapid growth of population, agriculture and fossil-fuel based economies on a planetary scale is directly related to the rapid expansion of CO2 in the atmosphere. In addition to contributing to the climate system, the rapid growth of population and agriculture on a planetary scale is directly related to the rapid expansion of human settlement. Biodiversity is critical for the resilience of the planet against the encroachment of these economies of abundance.  Conclusion: a question for art and curators? Should we? The question that emerges is: what can art and its practitioners do</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Guillermo Vitale – see Vitale’s Profile on the F.W. Bond Gallery website.  Vitale’s exhibition Imperva in Venice in 2017 featured work from a host of artists including Slade, Guillermo Amorim, Manuel Gutiérrez, Teresa Stroh and many more. http://www.imperva.com/en/art/art-paul-vitale/view/a-history-of-visual-art/549043/      http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/article/view/6447/how-did-art-intervene-in-the-impact-of-climate-change/ How did art intervene in the impact of climate change? We lament the loss of Arctic wildlife as our windows of opportunity are slowly closing. Art is a big part of that story, and vitally, part of the art that comes out of the water.  	The real challenge of our era is how to connect the dots between art and climate. Although we humans have the tools with which to tackle problems, in the face of the increasing complexity and depth of the problem, we lack the critical thinking to draw connections between the different players. It can't all be seen as a consequence of humans; we’ve all become so interconnected that it’s almost painful to see nature in this kind of twisted and complex way. But it’s important to recognize that even in this increasingly interconnected world, there are still vast expanses of land that are essentially wildernesses, with only a few humans able to roam freely between them. The potential loss of wildlife as a result of climate change is real, and we’ve all become complacent in the face of the increasingly visible signs of stress and trauma on the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her on Twitter: @reprinadexyz&lt;|endoftext|&gt;We are committed to supporting the arts education of our community through the provision of culturally responsive education. This means developing partnerships with institutions that can support the provision of culturally responsive art and encouraging the creation of new art forms through research and creative practices that support the development of critical faculties. In this regard, the Arts Council of Canada is responsible for the provision of culturally responsive art programs and supports, including through grants and cooperative agreements, with national and international arts institutions. The Arts Council of Australia is responsible for the provision of culturally responsive teaching practices and supports, including through teaching fellowships and cooperative agreements. The Australian Council of the Venice Biennale is a cooperative agreement between the Arts Council of Australia and the National Arts Centre, 2001. The following are examples of how cultural resources are employed and created within the biennale: the Brazil Artists Group (2009-ongoing); the Biennale of Sydney</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her on Facebook and Instagram.Author: Shashi Kant / Shirin Neshat Artist: Shashi Kant Length: 177 min Frame: Still photographs, still lifes, still photographs, still photographsDuration: 137 min Shashi Kant is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the Naval Postgraduate School in Monterey, California, and continued when she was curator at the Museum of Modern Art, New York. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Gibraltar Arts Forum, the Gibraltar Biennial, the Gibraltar Biennial-New York, the Gibraltar Arts Commission, and the Gibraltar Biennial-Tokyo. She has been a curator at the Turner Prize-Dundas Town, Scotland, and the British Council-Chichester, London. She was a prize awardee for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General's Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.KAB16</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her work at  	Prairie Home Companion, the Star and The Globe and Mail, and find her at  	HeritageAve, New York. Also see her blog.Design &amp; Overhauled: Design Criticism of New Mediaage, 2016. Installation, Art Deco High Street, Toronto. Photo courtesy of the Toronto Archives and Archives Canada.PreviousNextDesign &amp; Overhauled: Design Criticism of New Mediaage, 2016. Installation, Art Deco High Street, Toronto. Photo courtesy of the Toronto Archives and Archives Canada.Prairie Home Companion, the Star and The Globe and Mail, November 14, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Toronto Archives and Archives Canada.PreviousNextPrairie Home Companion, the Star and The Globe and Mail, November 14, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Toronto Archives and Archives Canada.Design &amp; Overhauled: Design Criticism of New Mediaage, 2016. Installation, Art Deco High Street, Toronto</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her work at  	Prayerfully Unusual.com Her name is  	Preeana Reddy and she works as an artist. Her work is largely commissioned and illustrated. She has recently completed work on the foreshore of the LJ Boat Club, which is now on display at the Gibraltar Arts Forum’s temporary exhibition venue ‘The Gallery of Miracles’, and she is currently completing a three-year curatorial project at the Gibraltar Arts Forum, which is currently developing a biannual arts and heritage journal. She has curated several exhibitions in North America and Europe, including the 2012 Venice Biennale, the Bahrain Biennale, the 2012 Venice Biennale, the 2013 Tony Award and the 2016 Oslo Biennale.She has written for the *Wall Street Journal, The New York Times, The Atlantic and The Guardian, amongst others.She was shortlisted for the Polaris Artist of the Year Award</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her work at reddyartands.com and facebook.com/reddyartand.   1   	International Brotherhood of Painters and Artisans (2011-ongoing). ~The Artist is now working with Academia De​spiration on a new commission for the Venice Bay Artspace. ~The Artist is now developing a new work 'Yours Truly', commissioned by the Gibraltar Arts Forum, for the 2016 Venice Biennale. Her first public engagement was at the 2016 Venice Biennale, when she engaged with the conflict in Gaza, using social media, painting and sculpture, and holding workshops and events in the city. In 2017, she collaborated with Chronic Art and Social Practice Lab at the University of Southern California on a Social Practice Seminar, and in 2018 she co-founded and directed the Social Practice Centre at the Gibraltar Arts Forum. She has a particular interest in the role of</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her work at www.actsofchaos.tumblr.com/post/854729386105/stephen-cone-an-introduction-to-the-geuss-plaque-art-project-in-contra-real-life 	[1]  Abstract: 	The space of Contravision is the temporal proximity of things. It is a global archival archive of physical and virtual objects, their movement, experiences, associations and relationships. It constitutes a continuously evolving database that records in ever-closer detail the manifold ways in which things are made, consumed, received, used, owned and produced. The object seems to be a point of departure from which other, deeper registers of meaning can be drawn. At the same time, the very fact of its existence and continual shifting suggests to all who sample it that they are on the verge of a potentially deeply transformative experience. At times, this is accompanied by a sense of</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her on Facebook and Instagram .   Lorena Buonarroti is an artist. Her early social studies work was delivered through community groups, including in schools, colleges and universities. She received a BAFTA for her work with the Foreigner, and the 2007 Governor General’s Literary Award. She has worked with the Community Arts Council of Ireland, the Barbican Arts Centre, and the Barbican Museum. She has a particular interest in the arts and culture of developing nations.Her latest project for the Barbican is entitled Inhabitants of Lower Manhattan. It is a series of ten installations, each dedicated to a different section of Lower Manhattan, in which artists, activists and historians look to the past to figure out what it means to inhabit a neighbourhood. They trace the history of residential neighbourhoods from the 1980s to the present, and develop strategies for the future. The project is a response to the 2015 New York Public Library and MFA programme Lower Manhattan,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her on Facebook and Twitter and instagram  (preeana.reddy2012).1  Like this: Like Loading... Related articles: Bluecoat, Arts Council of India, Cultural Hi-Jack, Community Arts? An IntroductionChris Wainwright-Smith &amp; Andy Duffey, The Bluecoat/The Arts Council of India, 2015. Photo: Tania Bruguera.PreviousNextChris Wainwright-Smith &amp; Andy Duffey, The Bluecoat/The Arts Council of India, 2015. Photo: Tania Bruguera.2  Like this: Like Loading... Related articles: How Bluecoats Got Their Start, The Bluecoat, 2015. Photo: Tania Bruguera.3  Like this: Like Loading... Related articles: Bluecoat, Peter McCaughey, 2014. Photo: Tania Bruguera.4</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her work at reddyartagestudios.com.au/rainbow-stop/ or find her at  	Herbert Pounds Studio.She has a regular slot on the  	Granby Four Streets Community Gallery show Queer Eye (2012-ongoing) and she is a regular commentator for the Granby Morning Herald and Granby Haunting. She has participated in the annual Granby Crocodile and Small Game Show and was a judge’s final artist for the 2013 Granby Stand Up Comedy Show. She has written for the newsletter Digital Art &amp; Design, and was a judge’s final artist for 2014 Granby Crocodile and Small Game Show. She was a finalist for the Turner Prize, the Governor General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her work at  	Herbert Pounds Studio.She has previously</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of financiers, real or imagined, that routinely threatens workers’ futures.    Preeana Reddy is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was frustrated by the lack of resources for socially engaged or culturally responsive art making in the arts context. She has worked with communities for over a decade and has a particular interest in the role of artists in the context of poverty alleviation and conflict resolution. She has received many awards and recognitions for her work in the arts community. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Arts Council of India, the Taj Mahal Foundation, the Gibraltar Arts Forum, and the Gibraltar Arts Commission. She was a recipient of the 2012 Polaris Artist of the Year Award and was shortlisted for the 2012 Polaris Social Impact Award. Her work has also been a shortlisted for the Turner Prize, the Governor-General’s Literary Prize, and the Governor-General’s Musée du Québec.You can follow her work at pdynewsmanuals.org.uk/artists/reddy/1.html.Download this article as PDFJennifer CharneyJennifer Charney is a writer, curator and journalist. She is the Executive Director of the Gibraltar Arts and Humanities Unit, a division of the Art Gallery of New Zealand, responsible for overseeing the work of the unit in the wider art world. She has written for the New York Times, The Atlantic and The Guardian, among other publications. Her work has been featured in places including the Museum of Modern Art, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, Frieze, Punch, The New York Times, The Sunday Times, Frieze d/e, among others. She is the editor of the forthcoming online journal Stages. Jennifer has a particular interest in the role artists have in creating a sense of place and identity for their communities. She has curated numerous exhibitions and publications, including the New Zealand Pavilion at the Venice Biennale,</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
