<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of
    <text>present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of this production; and the connections with other arts-producing countries. She is part of the curatorial team for  	Inside Writing, the curatorial exhibition of the forthcoming 11th Institute of Contemporary Art, where she is part of the curatorial team for  	Critical Art of North America: Volume 1, which will present a multi-disciplinary exhibition of work from this continent. In 2015 she co-curated  	Inside Writing, the curatorial exhibition of the forthcoming 11th Institute of Contemporary Art, where she was part of the curatorial team for  	Critical Art of North America: Volume 2, which will present a multi-disciplinary exhibition of work from this continent for the following instalment of the journal.[k] Oxford Dictionaries, s.v.  1. 	(1937) 	(1937)Compiled from sources in the Oxford English Dictionary, with additional material from a variety of other</text>
    <text>present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of cultural flows; and the cultural production of urban transformation projects in the 1970s, 1980s and 1990s in Canada and the US. Her publications include  	Signal, the award-winning 1993 novel about the defunct Canmore oil pipeline, and  	Unravelled: Travels in the Arctic, the 2008 documentary about the Canmore oil pipeline. She is the host of the CBC'ssss 'The Answer Show' and is a regular panelist on CBC'sssss 'The Current' and 'The Current Consensus' radio shows. She is a fellow of the Mackenzie Kapustin International Centre for Scholars (1993-96), and a fellow of the Mackenzie Kapustin International Foundation (1998-2006). She is an adjunct professor at Simon Fraser University (2008-11) and the Canada Research Chair in English and Multicultural Studies at the University of Alberta (with Jocelyn Forget).Her work has been commissioned by: Bell Canada,</text>
    <text>present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of that production in the wider Canadian context; and the art and cultural histories of the island of Canada. She is the recipient of several awards and publications, including two 2011 Ig Nobel Prizes for Literature and Cultural Studies (for her work in the Canadian literary and visual arts sphere) and a 2014 Royal Ontario Museum Doctor of Ancient Cultures: Greece &amp; Rome Award for Contributions to Cultural Studies.Honourable MentionsNina Edge/Toronto Art BiennialIn 2008, Nina Edge was appointed as Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Creative Studies Program at the University of Toronto. She is a prolific writer on visual arts and culture, with over twenty books published worldwide including six on the art and visual arts subdisciplines of the university. She has co-authored several exhibitions and has given numerous lecture engagements including the 2013 Biennial of Art, Design and Culture and the 2014 Biennale of Visual Arts, Design and Society, both of which were co-curated by Anne Koehler</text>
    <text>present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of that production; and the political and economic processes that generate and accentuate cultural forms. Her publications include essays in the New York Times, The New Republic, Vogue, The View from the Balustrade and numerous other publications. She is the recipient of numerous awards and mentions, including most recently from the American Literary Guild, the Canadian National Film Board, and the Museum of Modern Art. She is the author of several books, including the forthcoming (2014) The Language of the Intransigent and the Periphery: Critical Studies of Media Studies.Her work has been commissioned by the City of Vancouver, the Canada’s first postcolonial, ethno-cultural centre, and the United Nations. She has spoken on numerous occasions, including at the 2014 Vancouver Arts Festival, where she was a judge, the 2014 Edinburgh Arts Festival, where she was a curator, and at the 2016 Chicago Reader Festival, where she was a curator. She has also co-edited and edited several books,</text>
    <text>present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of that production in the broader socio-economic and political systems of the world; and the politics and constitutions of cultural production today. She is the author of several books including the recently published Staging the Crisis: On U.S. Cultural Imperialism and the Endgame of Multiculturalism (with Francesca Bertolotti, HarperCollins, 2012). Her publications include the popular web-based e-book Staging the Crisis: On U.S. Cultural Imperialism and the Endgame of Multiculturalism (with Francesca Bertolotti, HarperCollins, 2012); essays on literature, art, and identity in various forms of media including the New Criterion, the popular web-based journal Stages, the European Paperback (2007-2009), and the recently published book Staging the Crisis: On U.S. Cultural Imperialism and the Postcolonial Turn (2014). She is part of the curatorial team for the 10th International Biennial Association International Exhibition List (</text>
    <text>present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of a post-WWII increase in cultural forms of Indian descent; and the integration of indigenous languages and dialects in contemporary Canada. She has a particular interest in the social and literary work of First Nations Peoples and is particularly interested in the literary and visual works that are produced and enacted through their languages, cultures and histories. Her publications include the popular book Cultural Criticism (with Ruth Rendell and Jill Sturgis), the popular cultural journal on First Nations Peoples, in addition to the popular journaling website Raising Rainbow.Above all, she is fascinated by the complex interactions between people, places and history. She was one of Canada’s curators for the 2011 Venice Biennale, and was one of three artists curators for Canada’s 2013 Commonwealth Games and Commonwealth Heads of Agreement, partner shows at the Venice and Commonwealth Games Biennials, and co-curator of the 13th and 14th Conferences of the Commonwealth Games Organising Committee, Rugby Football Union,</text>
    <text>present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of this production in the urban context; and the production of literary and visual culture through participatory methods. Her publications include books on Canadian literary and visual culture, such as Jane Addams’s The Second Canadian Revolution (2003), Canada: A Reader in National Novels (2008), and Laura Raicovich’s Writing the Common. Her most recent is Culture and Anarchy in U.S. History: On War, Terror and the Estranged. Her writing has been featured in sites such as Vice, The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Sun, The Village Voice and The New Yorker. She is the host of C-Magazine’s 'The Stampede' podcast, and was a judge in the 2005 National Book Award shortlist.PreviousNextElise AtanganaSamantha Jones, Canada: On Her Majesty's Secret Service (2016). Commonwealth Gallery, Ottawa. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextSaman</text>
    <text>present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of the biennial form; and the cultural production of postcolonial and indigenous peoples. She is the author of Systemics, or Utopia in Ruins: International Bodies, Economy and Culture in Retrograde Times (2015) and is currently researching the colonial and neo-colonial history of Canada through writing and research on archival materials, public and private histories, and selected texts. She is also the editor and co-founder of (with Mikhael Subotzky) of the web-based journal WorldPost (http://www.worldpost.com/). She is an adjunct faculty member at the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture, where she is completing a master’s degree in cultural studies and has a joint appointment in the English and Contemporary Literature Department. She is also the editor of the online journal stanford.ac.uk/academic/archive/2005/07/international-biennial-unveiling-1717-212.html (</text>
    <text>present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of language and cultural practices across a broad range of communities; and the politics of language and cultural practices. She is the author of three books, including the award-winning  	Signal: On Writing and Unravelling (with Lynn Tolmon) from which this article was drawn. She is a finalist for the 2012 Canada Research Chair in Cultural Studies and is currently completing a book project examining the experiences of mixed-lingual and mixed-race people of Chinese descent in late-stage modern Canada.Over the past thirty years, the biennial has undergone a transformation in many ways, and its present role is no longer primarily that of one of the world’s great art institutions. Rather, it is one of a kind, which is increasingly important in the globalised modern world we inhabit. The biennial, which has traditionally been a home to a particular set of artists, is now a site of constant innovation, contestation, and new exhibition offerings. There is a new urgency</text>
    <text>present an online project that examines the history of biennials in Sunderland and the UK, and how a revival is needed. 	[i] Sunderland Biennial has been organising the Liverpool Biennial since 2007, and has hosted the two previous biennials, in different venues, in different years. In 2007, they staged  	Unravelled, a virtual no-show of the anticipated 2014, when the contested Biennale was set to begin. In 2009, they changed their plans and invited Leonardo DiCaprio to be the 9th Popart artist for the occasion.[j] DiCaprio, Leonardo. The Red Car Tops. New York: Doubleday, 1974, p.89.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor of English and Director of the Simon Fraser University Centre for English and Contemporary Culture. Her research interests include the production of modern and contemporary literary and visual culture in Canada; the social implications of cultural flows; and the integration of cultural practices into the economic and social life of communities in Canada and the United States. Her publications include Culture and Capital: Canada and the United States in Industrial and Digital Culture, and Managing Cultures: International Business Analysis, a position in the Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies. She is the recipient of several awards and has lectured on a wide range of topics on the Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies. She is also the editor of the online journal Culture and Capital.Interview with Elisabeth Kübler-RossElise Atangana and Louise ShelleyLaurie Lee and Elisabeth Kübler-Ross: Elisabeth Kübler-Ross and Louise Shelley,  	Walking Tall Buildings,2015. Elisabeth Kübler-Ross: You both work for the Biennial now, and we’re both assuming that you have a new role. With the Biennial in Toronto, you had a chance to walk</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art
    <text>should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and culture. For instance, one might bring with them a set of cutlery, pots and pans, a cloth bag with a hidden compartment, or a set of keys. The idea behind the art is that the biennale, like any such tourist attraction, is bringing with it expectations and expectations and discourses that can be negotiated and manipulated. My concern is that the expectations and discourses that we are creating through our interactive materiality, the artifice of interactive video and the media of travel and culture, are creating a certain amount of divisiveness and division in the city – certain elements of which are actively trying to resist and undermine the influence of the Biennale as a cultural entity. And I believe that the art that is being produced through this project is being actively manipulated as well. So I see this as a conundrum that the Biennale, like any art institution, is confronted with. There are different ways of addressing this conundrum, but I see two types</text>
    <text>should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and culture. That is, interactive objects that enable interaction but also objectify and fetishise it, in the sense that they declare that they are art but also render it into objects of exchange and objectification. I don’t mean in the sense of games, but in the sense of interactive media that allows people to exert agency and shape their destinies. So an art institution might construct a position that is uncomfortable for visitors to be able to interpret, for example, by bringing together different cultures in the same city. It might even engage in overtly political (though rarely imagined) acts of interaction with communities to bring together groups of people for practices that are explicitly political but also socially useful. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be imaginative and responsive to the times. We need new ways of looking at the world, and we need new ways of interacting with it. But we also need to learn how to adapt to the</text>
    <text>should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and culture. A biennale should be interactive with objects and with the urban environment at large. This is why, every time a new art institution is established in London, New York or any of the other major cities of the developed world, a biennale is organized in Berlin, Vienna, or wherever the interest and attractions of the culture are strongest. The main attraction of such places is their physical spread out and their constant need to be visited by people. The biennale therefore has to be interactive with the physical landscape and with the urban environment in some way in order to be sustainable. In other words, it must be creative and dynamic and meet the needs of the people who live and work within the sites themselves and not just of those who visit the art institutions, museums and galleries that form the basis of the urban environment. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	Art should be interactive, but it should also be meaningful. That is, the art has to have</text>
    <text>should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and history. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and history. I also believe that a biennale should foster dialogue, not silence, in a mutually beneficial way: it’s the very purpose of art institutions to educate and entertain as many people as possible. 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and history. I also believe that a biennale should foster dialogue, not silence, in a mutually beneficial way: it’s the very purpose of art institutions to educate and entertain as many</text>
    <text>should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and culture. Interactive media objects such as interactive maps, videos, infographics, social media fan pages, and wikis can significantly alter perceptions of the places where they are located and act as a catalyst for further interactive media behaviours. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and culture. Interactive media such as interactive maps, videos, infographics, social media fan pages, and wikis can significantly alter perceptions of the places where they are located and act as a catalyst for further interactive media behaviours. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people</text>
    <text>should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art. (JL)Art’s relationship to biennales is complex, and I want to start from the understanding that most artists have about what an art biennale is: a form of cultural exchange between artists and the public. Most biennales are social events: the exchange of goods and services, sharing in the cultural riches of the city and country. Many biennales are in a class by themselves: the art of presenting a work in a biennial, a class that includes the artist in the work and the biennial commissioning organisation in the same way that the market and art have classed themselves. But the significance of the art biennale, and what it means to be an art biennale, continues to be an issue that needs to be carefully negotiated. How a biennale represents the city and the city-world in the abstract is a crucial mediator of social impact and cultural exchange. Biennials are rarefaction formations: they are</text>
    <text>should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and culture. The form that the biennale takes is interactive not only with the visitor, but also with objects that are produced, contributed to and shaped by the biennale. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should engage with the urban context in which it is created. We live in a city that is ever more insular, fragmented and unequal, and it is the living memory that informs how we look to the world outside our city walls. The biennale should foster a dialogue with the city that breaks down the spatial divisions that we as an urban elite have constructed. The biennale should be a space where people from different walks of life can gather, exchange, and confront each other. It’s one of the few remaining examples of a major art institution engaging with the post-war global economy of culture. 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should offer an alternative</text>
    <text>should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and culture. Art is not just an aesthetic judgement, but it’s also a social act. The art that is brought to the Venice Biennale is interactive, and art’s social act is interactive. The Biennale should be interactive in its relationship to the city, in order to produce culture-making in the city and to enrich the lives of artists, curators, artists, writers and everyone else who visits. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and culture. Art is not just an aesthetic judgement, but it’s also a social act. The art that is brought to the Venice Biennale is interactive, and art’s social act is interactive. The Biennale should be interactive</text>
    <text>should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art.  	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should challenge expectations, both of art and art institutions. I also believe that a biennale should be a place of encounter, not of subjugation. There’s something inherently ‘semi-objective’ about this, in that it’s hard to categorise a space as either good or bad, whereas a biennale can. I also believe that a biennale needs to have a purpose beyond what its curatorial team can achieve through its curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial curatorial 	endless loop of engagement. I also believe that a biennale should have a language that can be</text>
    <text>should be curated, not on a daily basis, but over a period of years] that we can create a space for collaboration and exchange between artists, curators, artisans, researchers and other stakeholders. This would permit the exchange of information, suggestions, and proposals about how to support collaborative research and artmaking without compromising the integrity of the art institution or the site. For instance, a biennale might not necessarily identify its curatorial priorities as being those of a curatorial council, but it might identify the sources of its information and cultural resources. It might also identify the stakeholders and consider how to engage them in a mutually beneficial way, in collaboration or confrontation. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: interactive not in the sense of the interactive computer games that people engage with, but in the sense of the interactive physical objects that people bring with them when they visit places of art and culture. To be sure, this requires the creation of an exchange between visitor and art institution, because the interactions between people are mediated by electronic media. But I see biennales today in many forms today: they’re interactive, they’re virtual, they’re social, they’re geographical, and they’re geo-politically connected. The essence of biennales today is globalization, and the social consequences of that. 	RAW Paste Data 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be creative: innovative in its target market, but also innovative in its form of exchange, because that is the powerful combination today. And I follow your lead in thinking that a biennale should be creative in its own right. 	RAW Paste Data 	And I believe that a biennale should be interactive: dynamic, adaptable and result-oriented. Today, the biennale is a commercial</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that
    <text>should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that art was actively engaged with in a very powerful way and that people actually wanted to come to work and play. There was also an element of fun and gamesmanship involved: people bringing their art, poems, drawings or sculptures – anything that would make a statement about the present and future of art – and weaving it into everyday activities. For example, people brought art containers or art products – an art product was a handy way to make a statement about a product or industry. Action Space also offered an open forum for debate and debate; so beyond just the art products and art objects, people brought other products or ideologies that were designed to be used – useful or not. For example, women’s empowerment was a popular idea and whilst it was often expressed in empowering terms, it wasn’t always explicitly acknowledged or taken into account. Women leaders in particular were often seen as role models for how women could achieve empowerment and so action spaces such as Action Space gave voice to the marginalised and oppressed</text>
    <text>should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that art was valued more highly than ever before and that people cared about and interacted with art in a different way. Action Space was curatorial gold.  One of the great things about being part of a curatorial pack is that you become embedded in a tradition and so you witness things that are embedded in the culture and perhaps you become influenced by them. So when I first came to Liverpool, I witnessed what art trips are made of, and so did many members of the community. It’s interesting that when I first came to Liverpool, I didn’t have a traditional art background. I had traditional education in English, in journalism and in some subjects in philosophy. I had a firm grounding in classical art history, though. So when I came to Liverpool I didn’t have a classical background in classical theory or art history. I had to dig deeper and actually study art history and culture through art and learning associate’s degrees in art history and the social sciences. It</text>
    <text>should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that the curatorial thought was almost entirely electric and autonomous, while art was often ceded ground to the artist’s artistic instincts. In other words, it bridged the gap between curatorial thinking and the actual curatorial work done.   A space for imagination and the imagination of the public, with an emphasis on poetry and memory, Action Space came complete with spaces for contemplation and poetry, as well as a space for the very real and very fragile to be carried around in a special levitation device. The device was a nod to Plato’s caveman’s caveman’s natural instincts – man is a caveman, after all.   One of the earliest sculptures by Paul McCarthy was a self-portrait of himself as a caveman. It was also one of the last surviving from the 1950s. It got lost in a muddle of other art in the basement. But here it is, in all its fragile glory, being carried around by</text>
    <text>should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that art was a force for good in the city even if it was somewhat of a contradiction.  The space of Action Space was an enormous, black and white video screen, with moving images of diverse art forms and genres on one side and white noise on the other. It was loud and clear and had a mirror hanging from the ceiling that reflected every aspect of the city. It was a strange mix of old and new art, contemporary and historical art, but above all it was art. Some of the newer, hi-tech art pieces hung in rooms that looked like they had been converted into classrooms, while the older pieces were either destroyed or hidden away in fancy buildings. There was also an open area in the middle of the action that allowed for free and unsupervised movement. Action Space had a video screen, but it was also a highly visible billboard for the museum, broadcasting the museum’s view of the city, its architecture and culture as a whole. The art was everywhere. </text>
    <text>should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that this was a space for poetry as well as for the art of making poetry. At its worst, it was a place where the curatorial department openly engaged in a patronage system that functioned largely as a marketplace for cultural products. It allowed the occasional random visitor to take a swing at a cultural artefact or two but otherwise it cut off all interaction with the cultural authorities.   Even when curators came to Action Space for informal discussions, they were expected to act with integrity and produce a work that is neither derivative nor opportunistic. This was a major challenge for me as a curatorial student and while I did manage to deliver some genuinely beautiful works (such as  	Skyfall’s installations at Skyfall Gallery in Liverpool) it was also a point where the gallery staff and community members involved with the gallery’s art-making came into conflict with each other. In many ways, the gallery was part of my larger perception of the world and part of my own world</text>
    <text>should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that art was not only an instrument with which to work, but that it was also a fully realized and autonomous creative process.   At its worst, it was a repressive and control freak space – everyone was either members of an art collective or in control of their work. The space was a dangerous breeding ground for anti-intellectualism and hostile to new ideas. This is why when artists and curators stopped coming to the action space, other spaces started to take their place. It became a catch-all for artists and curators to be seen participating in, and a point of departure from, activities taking place elsewhere in the city. This is why when a city organises a festival or a series of activities, it often does not allow all the participants to be present at once. It is because the participants’ collective effort soon runs up against the limitations of the space and its processes. Every artist, every curatorial initiative, every cultural centre has a curatorial mission. The curatorial</text>
    <text>should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that the curatorial search was no longer limited to the museum, and that artists, curators and artists� associations were actively involved in creating the art which would be displayed.   When we visited the site, we found that Action Space was in serious danger of becoming redundant: the building it housed was deteriorating; there were signs that the cultural affairs department was spending too much time on paperwork; and the gallery was overcrowded and under-utilised. So we visited the local heritage preservation office and asked what they could do with the space. They said they could use it in a variety of ways, including housing or organising an urban tour. We explored this idea of ‘housing’ and found that in the context of a cultural centre, a site for cultural purposes is a site of interaction between people: a place to be ‘shared’ and a place to be ‘dormant’. So housing is a possibility, but only if there is a strong commitment from local</text>
    <text>should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that the curatorial was questioning, looking beyond the museum for inspiration and acting independently. At its worst, it was a place where the curatorial department was overrun with white-cubed biennials and their art-loving fans (whose art was often more aesthetically pleasing and enjoyable than the work they supported) and where the curatorial thinking was dominated by transnational corporations and their boards of directors. In an ideal world, curatorial thinking wouldn’t exist in the first place. But in the US and Western Europe, it is the norm and it is often quite dangerous to be an outsider. So the space between art and the curatorial is often a dangerous (and often beautiful) one. And when it is a relatively new thing (like in Action Space), the people who use it often feel like outsiders too. That is, like the curatorial thinking that leads to art being made, but without the art being made.   The other thing is that art often has to</text>
    <text>should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that there was a purpose beyond simply putting art on display and inviting the public to participate. But by fostering an environment in which art could be put on display, curatorial thinking also had to consider what the artifice of the museum could and could not support. The artifice can be used constructively or destructively, but it has to be sustainable in its form and content. There has to be balance. And so art’s curatorial thinking has had to be informed by a wider socio-political and cultural context.  If you take the curatorial thinking that you do at the museum and apply it to Action Space, you’d start off off by saying: ‘Art’s job is to engage people and to produce experiences that are as emotionally charged as possible. But it’s also about more fundamental things like how to support a creative arts education without becoming a burden on the city or the state. So you need to be thinking beyond the art gallery or the</text>
    <text>should be curated and curated with our own unique spin on the museum’s traditional curatorial concepts.  In our curatorial approach, our main job was to find interesting, thought-provoking, performative and sometimes even aesthetically pleasing things to do with art. We didn’t want to impose our will on anyone and so our cultural and community initiatives tended to be quite discretionary. We could have a formal cultural function but that just made things more bureaucratic and dull. So we created what we called an Action Space. It was a hybrid space – it had art spaces, a performing arts space and a classroom – but it also had a space for asking, ‘What can art do?’ Here, the artist, the curator and the community all come together to explore how art can be used constructively or destructively.   At its best, Action Space was a point of departure for a curatorial thinking beyond the museum or even the small gallery. It gave the impression that this wasn’t the case. Here is an example of what I mean. Below is an example of what an Action Space might look like if art were a space for people to ‘get together’ and explore ideas and concepts.  Below is an example of what an Action Space might look like if art were a space for community artists and designers to come together and discuss how art can be used for good and for ill.  Below is an example of what an Action Space might look like if art were a space for artists to create and explore new art forms that are dynamic and transformational.  Below is an example of what an Action Space might look like if art were a ‘place of encounter’ – a place of collaboration and exchange between artworlds and between curators and artists.  Below is an example of what an Action Space might look like if art were a ‘platform’ – a platform that facilitates the exchange of ideas and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven
    <text>present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven way). In the 1970s and 1980s the Theatre Arts Centre was able to operate in Liverpool through the support of Arts Council funding, and through the work of Arts Council staff including artists. In some ways, the Theatre Arts Centre represents the conditions of social mobilisation that were ripe for the development of an arts education in the city. The critical mass of people who started to engage themselves in creating engaging arts environments was a tipping point that opened the way towards real change, and ultimately for the arts to reclaim much of the political and cultural space that they had been confined to in the city.Thanks to the Theatre Arts Centre, many of those involved in creating the infrastructure for an arts education in the city were able to contribute their cultural capital to the eventual success of the programme. And through the early years of the Biennale, many of us at the Biennale were able to engage with the materiality of artefacts and the urban setting through our cultural capital. The Theatre Arts Centre was able</text>
    <text>present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven way). In the political sphere, the key is for the Centre to negotiate the terms and parameters of participation, and to work with local people’s commissions and non-profits to create local participatory frameworks. In the civic sphere, the role is for the local authorities to initiate and augment the frameworks and take the lead in developing the sites and programmes. In the social enterprise sphere, the role is for the Centre to supervise and augment the frameworks and carry out the programmes as per its own agenda.   A theatre and its social contract can only operate in co-existence with the political and the civic domains. It is impossible to constructively engage both the political and the civic in a multi-year long programme of action with no capital or clear objectives. The ethical dilemma that arises in such encounters is how to maximise the social value generated by the work, while simultaneously maintaining the social cost. Some people advocate a zero-zero ratio, where a social enterprise spends its budget on activities</text>
    <text>present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven way). I believe that the ability of the Centre for a New Economy to engage people, both young and old, through participatory budgeting, generated and led by young people is a key to the success of the project.  Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise because it engages with the social, and because it provides services to meet the social needs of people. It is a so-called ‘transcendental’ form of social enterprise, beyond the scope of its original, cathartic mission. It is also a ‘profit-making enterprise’, with the capacity to last for many decades to come. Its current form is one in which the arts are often cited as a strategic asset in stimulating creativity and innovation, while at the same time a constraint on growth and activity.  The present incarnation of the Theatre projects in Toronto is no exception to this rule. Its current form is one in which artists, curators, architects and others take</text>
    <text>present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven way). That said, in the 21st century the power to govern is in the hands of a decentralised elite, and so it is with increasing frequency that the social contract that is negotiated in the public arena is serviced by partnerships between different public authorities. As a result, the boundaries that exist between public and private spheres are becoming increasingly blurred. When these boundaries are exposed, they tend to break down the public sphere often for political reasons. So it is that in the public realm there exists a politics of perception, which is likely to be contentious and which is capable of generating tensions. It is also likely to be multi-generational, and so there is a risk that this new complex that is being built will fracture into many smaller fragments. This could happen if the public sphere is not properly visited, or not sufficiently appreciated. There is a danger, too, that the engagements that are being funded and delivered through the social contract will be performed by organisations with agendas that are not aligned with the</text>
    <text>present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven way). We believe that the success of the local community theatre project depends on three things in particular: (1) the quality of the art produced; (2) the political will of the local community to exert control; and (3) the ability of the local artist to sustain her work in the long-term.As an area of the UK with a large and growing arts biennale industry, Liverpool Biennial has had ample opportunities to experiment with new forms of engagement with artists and the arts. We think that the project we are embarking on right now is the right one, but we also know that there are many different ways to engage with art and the arts, and that engagement will only progress if there are strong and transparent co-ownership structures in place. That brings us to the next challenge: sustaining the art and the arts project in the long-term.What is at Stake in Community Arts? What are some examples of what we call &quot;Stake in Community Arts</text>
    <text>present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven way). I believe that the new digital technologies that we are creating are creating unprecedented opportunities for social transformation, and it is this ability to alter social space and destinies that is being asked of artists and organisations of all kinds. It may be that some of these capacities will be used for real ends, and that is the realm of opportunists and dreamers. The other extreme may be more exploitative, and artists and organisations that produce through their work are being asked to become agents of real change and actively participate in transforming places and communities in which they do not exist. I think that the new social enterprises that we are creating are fragile, and that the future may bring violent and destructive tides, but at the same time they are being asked to become more than just economic engines for the city. They are also being asked to become morally active, and to adopt practices and structures that can survive in a political and social context. This is an enormously challenging task, and I look forward to collaborating with</text>
    <text>present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven way). In the current globalised capitalist society, this takes place at a scale that is practically impossible for independent theatres to navigate, much less to implement in practice. A theatre that is active in the community, and has the capacity to produce value for others through engaging people with whom it comes into contact is an extraordinary ability for the centre to project power and control. There are many other forms of social enterprise that have their origins in community organising, and are actively engaged in making the world a better place. But the form that the Biennale has taken – the development of it, the making of it, the perpetuation of it, and the maintenance of it – is fundamentally different from all other forms of social enterprise that have emerged in the context of the contemporary global village. It is a social enterprise in its own right, and can be seen to occupy a unique place in the history of the biennale.Perhaps more importantly, it is possible to define the terms of this unique social</text>
    <text>present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven way). It is possible that the social contract that is negotiated between artist and audience can be adapted to the specific parameters of the area in which the performance takes place, but as already noted, this is extremely rare. The reason why art is able to exist in these kinds of political, social and economic conjunctures is that the latter is able to perceive the former as different, and thus has a sense of agency that is distinct from other social actors. When the arts are able to perceive the agency of audiences – to that extent that is able to conceive of and call up creative intervention – it opens up a host of possibilities for action, including for the very purpose of engaging those audiences in future projects.In the current political context, this is particularly evident in the aftermath of the extraordinary events of 9/11, which allowed for the very real reinvention of the US Public Image (and thus US cultural policy) through the pretence that the events were of national consequence, and thus the US</text>
    <text>present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven way). Theatre can and should negotiate the terrain of its development, but it is also able to create opportunities for those individuals to develop further, and in this respect it is quite different from other kinds of social enterprises. In the arts sector, this can mean engaging artists’ audiences in ways that create conflict resolution tools, or creating platforms for artists to engage with audiences in new ways. Sometimes this kind of negotiation is quite easy: you can create a programme that engages more people than the arts centre can, or alternatively you can create something that is actually more engaging than the centre can be, or alternatively you can create something that is both arts and social in a more general sense. For example, the way that the Biennale engages with the social contract between community members and artists is a good example of how politics, economy and culture interact in the development of social practice. In order to achieve the biennale’s goals, it is necessary for the arts centre to be very effective at</text>
    <text>present an online project that sought to create a local context in which to do so). The project came together swiftly and decisively, but as time went on, the pace became patchy, and the local people who came forward to volunteer became less and less able to participate. Eventually, the centre lost control of the project, and now we are on the verge of losing the Electronic Arts archive, which is a loss for which we will pay for years to come.Theatre and its Social ContractTheatre is a social enterprise. It is not just a business enterprise, and as such it is unable to exist in a vacuum. It must negotiate the political, economic and social conditions that exist in order to exist in a particular geographical area, and in this sense it is able to exist in conditions of social deformation. The key to this enterprise is its ability to draw people together, and engaging them in a way that is both socially productive and ends up making real the aims of the organisation (albeit in a complicated and uneven way). In this sense, the Theatre can exist in an area where there is already a strong participatory culture, but also in an area where there is a strong cultural-political-economic-institutional imbalance. In these two parts of the world, different forms of the Theatre are able to exist in mutually reinforcing relations. This is true of poetry, prose, painting, sculpture and theatre generally. But in recent years, the critical concepts of ‘infrastructure’ and ‘public space’ have entered the political (infrastructure is public and space is private property; we own less and are therefore less able to control its use). The political infrastructures of the western world are able to absorb and magnify these forms of infrastructural development because they are composed of masses of people (collective citizens) who are able to access, inhabit and utilize the spaces and technologies that are now considered public (collective producers). The problem arises when the political infrastruct</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’
    <text>a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’t think of an artist as an artist in the truest sense of the word. I think of an artist as an artist who has the capacity to imagine and to be made by things.I remember one of the first things I did when I got the job was to download all the artwork from the Tate Modern archive. I looked at the images, and I thought ‘This is not happening anymore. This is not happening in my lifetime anymore.’ I looked at the archive, and I thought ‘This is happening in my lifetime now.’In the early days, the only way to get involved was as a volunteer. Now, everybody is an artist and everyone is an organisation, and the relationship between the two is as strong as it is between the public and the arts institutions. The connectomics that I describe are the result of an artist’s cohort, and it’s an artist’s cohort that is continually evolving and maturing. So an artist</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’t think that there’s a single artist in this field today who has the same kind of capacity. But I do think that there are artists who have the kinds of capacities that an artist like yourself have, which are different from what the average person has.For instance, the capacity of an artist like yourself to connect with people across broad social groups, to find common ground and to engage with people across broad social groups is a much different kind of capacity than the capacity of an artist like yourself to suddenly find a way of connecting with people online that isn’t been done before. I don’t think that the capacity of an artist today is going to be able to replicate what an artist like yourself did in the past, because of the way the internet works, but I do think that capacity will develop artist-specifically. The capacity to suddenly find a way of connecting with people across a range of different social groups is going to be much more difficult, and I don�</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’t think you can quantify that capacity, although I imagine it’s considerable. But I also think that the capacity to change the world through art is an entirely different kind of capacity. When you get the opportunity to put your imagination to work, you’re creating a new world. You give it shape and purpose and you change it. And I think that comes from experience, and through art that’s experienced. It’s not something that comes from within. It’s something that comes from the universe telling you how to think. So the capacity to do that, to think differently, to change the world through art is a capacity that you build into yourself.It’s that kind of thinking that’s missing in much of what’s happening in the world right now. A capacity that’s grounded in reality. And what’s happening in the world right now is precisely the opposite of what artistically inclined people tend to</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’t think of an artist as an artist, rather an artist as an artist who has the capacity to imagine things differently, to create worlds and to have that capacity to imagine things differently. That’s really important to me. I want my work to be able to connect to different kinds of people, to allow different kinds of experiences, to allow different kinds of knowledge structures. And I think that comes through in the way that I draw inspiration from different cultures, through different economic systems, through different social systems and through different political ideologies.I also think that the capacity of an artist to be able to engage with ideas and concepts other than their own is what makes them an artist. And I think that comes through in the way that they draw inspiration from different kinds of experience, through different kinds of knowledge structures, through different kinds of political ideologies and through different kinds of knowledge-production systems.For me, being able to do that, being able to imagine new worlds and to be able to create</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’t think that being an artist means you’re going to magically come up with the best solutions to problems all the time. I don’t think that’s possible. But I do think the capacity for an artist to create innovative, transformational experiences through their work is different from that of an artist like yourself, to the extent that the latter is willing to actively engage in creating those experiences.I got the sense that there was some tension between the two of you. I think there was some tension about what the other was doing, about who was more in control. I think it was a struggle to define the difference. For me, the construct of the work, the work of art, the work of thought, was more authentic, more real. It’s like the film Gladiator: when the character is killed, the scene is over – there’s no going back. The same is true of an artwork: it’s more real, more authentic</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’t think of an artist as an artist in the abstract, abstract being understood in this country. I think of an artist as an artist with the capacity to think and to create worlds and to bridge cultures and different times. Abstract art is different from stylised abstraction in that it doesn’t have a subject or audience. Abstract art doesn’t have subjects or audiences and doesn’t rely on formal criteria or cultural frameworks. It just happens to be happening all around us. Abstract art is power. Abstract art doesn’t get represented in the way that it does in the art world. And that’s what I love about it.Art is really the thing that got me to where I am in life and I think that’s what has made me want to be an artist: the power of art and the power of the artist. Abstract painting and sculpture come from an abstract point of view, one that’s unclear and which is often threatened by the</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’t think that there’s a single art form that’s inherently going to be able to do that, nor do I think that the capacities of the contemporary artist are necessarily connected with the capacities of the museum or other art forms. It’s more that the artist has the power to imagine things differently, to connect with audiences, to change the world and have an impact that is cumulative, and that is impossible to quantify. But I do think that with the immediacy and access to information of digital media, the modern artist is not only going to understand the world in a totally different way, but she’s also going to understand the world in ways that are completely arbitrary, and she’s also going to be able to insert her own unique spin on it.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI am an Associate Professor in the Department of Communication Studies and the Management of Cultural Capital, Trinity College Dublin, Ireland. I am co-editor of the forthcoming</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’t think that a lot of artists have that kind of capacity. I think that some of the most innovative and powerful artists I have worked with have had the capacity to create what is sometimes referred to as ‘deep wounds’ through their work. And they did this through the prism of a more traditional art practice: Through their radiators, they created spaces and tensions that could not be healed.Through their stores, they disseminated ideas and images of conflict and despair.Through their use of technology, they gave voice to individuals with grievances that were not necessarily directed at a specific organisation or person.And I think that's where a lot of the healing and transformative power of an artist like yourself comes from. You know, I get emails from people all around the world who say, well, I used to be involved with a particular art practice, and I used to be able to access resources and connections that allowed me to do amazing work. And I see this power in all of our work,</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’t think that there’s a single way to think about things. I think that what makes an artist an artist is in part about the kinds of thinking that an artist engages with, and the ways in which that engages with reality.Ana Nieves-Leone &amp; Coralie van Heeswijk, Neon Aesthetics: Crisis &amp; Reflection, 2016. Installation, Wien &amp; Joosting, Amsterdam. Photo: Tom Lox. 	I also think that the capacity for an artist to make a real difference, to actually achieve change, is what makes them different. I don’t think that an artist needs to have a project approved by a government to be able to actually do something. I find it ironic, the way in which artists are often-quoted, the way in which artists are often-criticised: the way in which some people evaluate their work, their practice, their intentions, and even their politics. And I’</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator. It’s also a machine that’s constantly evolving, constantly learning, and that’s exactly what makes it interesting. It’s as if God has given it the intelligence to figure things out for itself.So what’s it like being an artist in this digital age? I think there are many ways to put this. For me, personally, being able to communicate effectively with audiences, both large and small, online and in person, is an entirely different kind of power. I don’t have the same access to funding or resources as an artist like yourself. I don’t have the same access to connections or networks. But I do have the power to imagine things and to shape them. I think that's an entirely different kind of power.I also think that the capacity of an artist to imagine things differently, to create environments and to change the world through their work is what makes them extraordinary. I don’t think that there’s one true way of doing things, but there’s a way of looking at things that can’t be achieved through linear processes. Also, I think that an artist has a unique power to imagine a different kind of world. I don’t think that’s possible with established principles and institutions, because then you’re stuck in a particular way and doing particular things. I think an artist has that kind of power.Interview with Geoffrey Rushton, Curator at Tate Modern, 2015. Photo courtesy of Roger Thompson.Interview with Geoffrey Rushton, Curator at Tate Modern, 2015. Photo courtesy of Roger Thompson.Interview with Geoffrey Rushton, Curator at Tate Modern, 2015. Photo courtesy of Roger Thompson.Interview with Geoffrey Rushton, Curator at Tate Modern, 2015. Photo courtesy of Roger Thompson.Interview with Geoffrey Rushton, Curator at Tate Modern, 2015. Photo courtesy of Roger Thompson.Interview with</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number
    <text>a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number of projects through their biennials, including the installation of Mari Jobst as part of 2015 Venice Biennale, the installation of Dorothea Lange as part of the 2016 Venice Biennale, and the installation of Gabrielle Union as a part of the 2017 LA Biennale.In 2015, Creative Time, an organisation that provides opportunities for creative people to come to the UK and work in collaboration with artists and organisations, established a programme for artists to develop local and long-term projects in the West Bank and Gaza under the Creative Time Chair.  The programme was led by Mari Jobst, Emily Pringle, Rob Baucom, Dmytro Firtash, Ella Gibbs and Tara Rosen. In addition to developing local alternatives for the activities of art and culture in the West Bank and Gaza, Creative Time also established Creative</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number of collaborative projects with the Israeli authorities, including the 2016 Svetlana Kravizhneva Art and Architecture Project, created specifically for the occasion of Towing the Elephant’s retirement, and the 2017 Kish: Curating at the Beehive, a three-month collaborative programme between the Mesa Art Group, the New Museum and the Basel-based Architecture of Modern Architecture (2016).  The Basel-based Architecture of Modern Architecture (2016) is a mix of long and short forms – forms that are fluid, changeable and modifiable, yet rigidly constraining – that seek to reconcile a modernist bent towards the modern with a traditional orienting towards nature and the past. It is an approach to architectural practices that are dynamic, ambiguous and subject to the environment in which they are constructed.  In the case of the Towing the Elephant project,</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number of collaborative projects, including the collaborative Jerusalem Document, 2013, Remaking the River by Aaron Dembski and his team, creating a new form of mobility in Jerusalem by Rami El Samahy and her team, and Dont chazeh’s 2014 adventure into creating a new form of urban mobility through mobility assessed in part via the Geography of Everyday Life project. Gabrielle Lopéz de la Torre, Telling the Telling Story, performance at the Sonora Cultural Arts Festival, 1998. 7. Gabrielle Lopéz de la Torre, Telling the Telling Story, performance at the Sonora Cultural Arts Festival, 1998. 8. In 2008, Gabrielle Lopéz de la Torre, Telling the Telling Story (originally 2001), was</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number of collaborative projects with the Israeli and American artists Pan Samaritans, including the 2015 Opening Night of Pan Samaritans for the US-based exhibition Persistence of Vision at the Westcott and Harlotard Art Centre in London, the 2015 Persistence of Vision: New York Biennale rehearsal at the Westcott and Harlotard, and the Persistence of Vision: Tarrytown Art &amp; Settlement at the Penn Art Centre. The Mesa Art Group commissioned Glasgow-based artist Sophie Hope to develop a multi-disciplinary, multi-use space for art, architecture, community work and youth to work together. The group hoped that a new kind of arts and culture programme was emerging in Glasgow through the work of Hope and her team, as well as through the engagement of other artists and arts organisations there. On top of that, the group hoped that their collaborative proposals would add to</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number of collaborative projects with other artists, including 2013 When Pigs Fly West, with Wendy Harpe, the Bedouin Bedouin from  Jerusalem, and their children, 2014 Birds of Paradise Bay, a public art project that features 360 360 360° views of the ocean from buildings in the Bay Area, and a public sculpture project titled Birds of Paradise, which was exhibited in the Ron Suskind Gallery in New York. The Mesa Art Group also collaborated with the New Museum in New York and Dolphin Art Gallery in Liverpool to host a number of shows, including the 2014 Open School East, a two-month residency for artists in the East Bay, which explored the ways that artists, curators and arts professionals in the East Bay were collaborating to address a wide range of issues, including how artists could be embedded in active cultural contexts; how to support artist-curated residencies and what role artists can play in building the</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number of collaborative projects with the Israeli and American artists Walid Abd al-Qaderi and Nasser Rabb, as well as the Children of Israel Hospitals and Arabs Diab jumhuriyya, who designed and built the Bir Zeit Congregational Church, a renovated former children’s bookshop in the West Bank. The Chaim Weizman Center for Art and Architecture, New York University, reaches back into the tradition of the academy, opening up new directions for the university’s art department, including a new role as an arts educator and a co-operative art space. The Biennale draws artists from all over the world to explore the politics, practices and material effects of urbanisation, highlighting the role of culture in political processes. In 2017, the Biennale was named one of Time’s 100 Most Influential People In The World 2006 list.  And yet its impact is still felt.</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number of projects through their biennials, including 2013 Being West of West Bank (with Mari Jobst, Wadai Samah, Israel), 'East of West Bank', a multi-disciplinary commission that investigated the lives of Bedouin communities in East Jerusalem, 2014 East Jerusalem Biennale, an international commission that documented the lives of Palestinian Bedouin communities in East Jerusalem, 2015 Mideast Sculpture Project (2015), titled Constructive Thinking West Bank (2015), and the New Chronicle (2016), which documented the lives of Palestinian and Arab Bedouin communities in the West Bank and Gaza. The Mesa Art Group researched the issue of identity and location in the West Bank and Gaza under the title Constructive Thinking Palestine. Part of the commission Constructive Thinking Palestine was the work of artist Mari Jobst, who was living</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number of individual works, including 2015 Sliding Walls by Walid Abu al-Qi’an, commissioned by the National Portrait Gallery, Washington, DC, and 2016 Learning from Spain by Christiane Paul and Francisco Rodriguez, both with a joint exhibition by the Spanish and the Dutch National Portrait Galleries, New York and Amsterdam respectively. The Mesa Art Group also curated eight exhibitions in Uruguay, as well as the 2016 Palermo Biennale.Download this article as PDFMaría Lourdes RodríguezMaría Lourdes Rodríguez is a curator based in Montevideo, Uruguay. Her research interests include the visual arts, architecture and urbanisation of Uruguay, the Levantine Gulf and North Africa. She is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the National Gallery of Uruguay, where she is responsible for coordinating the activities of the gallery's art collections, exhibitions, public programmes and outreach programmes.</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number of collaborative projects with the University of Arizona, including 2014 Future City, a three-month residency for the creative writing residency, creative acoustics residency and postgraduate programme in art and architecture at the university, as well as a postgraduate programme in architecture and urbanisation at the Doha Centre for Advanced Urban Studies. The Doha Centre for Advanced Urban Studies is a multi-disciplinary centre co-operative run by Professors Aqeel Ebrahimi and Dr Hassan Al-Turabi, offering a full range of academic, research and cultural programmes, as well as a number of public programmes of art, dance and community activities. Recent programmes include the 2016 Doha Biennale, 2017 Al Madinat Art Biennale, 2018 Al Madinat Art and Culture Festival, 2019 Al Madinat Art &amp; Culture Scholarship Fund, 2020 Al Madinat Art &amp; Culture Scholarship Fund, 2021</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the artist Esther Shalev-Gerz. The show opened with a performance by the Israel Folk Art Group (2006), followed by a show by the Mesa Art Group (2008), a local group based in Mesa, Arizona, whose work has exhibited at the New Museum in New York, the Mural Fund in London, and the Bloomsbury Biennale in London. The Mesa Art Group released a number of solo exhibitions, including 2012 Towing the Phoenix (with John Lennon, John Scofield and Paul McCartney) and 'Towing the Elephant' (2012) on the outskirts of the city, and 2013 Towing the Beehive' by artist Mari Jobst and her team, who documented their 2011 occupation of West Bank sites by West Bank Bedouin Towson and Bethlehem Bedouin. The Mesa Art Group released a number of collaborative projects with the Israeli artists Oded Yinon, Yair Weizman and Arnon Psych (2013-16), who documented the experience of growing up in the West Bank under the nom de plume of Oded Ben Yair. The Beit Jaffa Philharmonic released its eleventh studio album In My Father’s Car, written and produced by Nadav Israel, with additional lyrics by Amor Ben Yair, on Paolo Barresi’s Violence on the West Bank.  [1] Sivan Parry, ‘On the use of historic sites and places in the construction of urban futures’,  	Future City (New York: Wiley-Blackwell, 2012), p. 7.  [2] Parry, ‘On the use of historical sites and places in the construction of urban</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the
    <text>curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the ‘Great Society’ initiative at the University of Chicago, from the New York Public Library to the University of Manchester, art is a tool of state repression and inequality. It is used as a tool by artists and curators of all kinds, including the Zapatero brothers, to project a particular vision of the world into, or in opposition to, the real world. In the case of the Zapatero Gallery, the real world was the Colombian civil war, which the gallery and its director, Mauricio Uma, were invited to attend. During the war, the gallery hosted several programs featuring guerrilla art, and part of the mission was to rehabilitate the reputation of Bogota, which was then the home of the Calté Prince of Colombia and a key transshipment point for cocaine. Uma was not unaware that the university was providing artistic direction to the Colombian war effort. After all, the gallery had been founded with the express mission to promote the work of art</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the curators of the Venice Biennale, the Italian artists who staged the Zapatero Gallery in 1967, to the curators of the 1998 Venice Biennale, to the curators of the 2010 Sydney Biennale, to the curators of the 2016 Barcelona Biennale, to the biennials of the present and future, to the curators of any and all such occasions, to the publics that might attend such events, to the artists whose works might be staged, to the venues that might house them, to the media organisations that might choose to photograph, film or otherwise document such occurrences; ‘art’ can become, in the words of Vernacruz, anything from a collection of objects to a ‘machinery of domination’[9]—a mode of cultural production as instrumental in the process of capitalising on events as they unfold before our very eyes.The invitation to the 20th Tokyo Biennale was presented</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the ‘Academia’ in Buenos Aires, from the farmer to the factory, from the journalist to the urban planner, from the nanny to the streetwalker, every citizen of the city was equally capable of being recruited into this new economy of cultural exchange. And, by the way, every citizen of the city was equally capable of becoming a reporter, a teacher, a nurse, a receptionist and a cleaner. Media theorist Judith Butler famously declared that the New Media had given voice to the people;[9] and, in the words of Gregory Ulmer, ‘the people’, who, in turn, appropriated the new media were ‘themselves the product of a collective hallucination’.[10]I turn now to some of the voices that still speak of the city. Some of you are already familiar with these voices, from the neighborhood watch committees and the vigilante groups to the artists who came of age on the glare of the media glare. You</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the ­Calendar, from the Jewish Museum in New York to the ­Open School in London, from the Daily Graphic in London to the New York Public Theater in the early 1990s, artists, curators, artists’ associations and others worked hand in hand to form what was, in effect, a self-sustaining artistic community. The Zapatero Gallery in Bogota, the Jewish Museum in New York and the Open School in London staged regular and special exhibitions, commissioned by the local communities, depicting local history, local culture and the wider world in a particular ‘Zapatero Style’. In Bogota, the Calendar and the Jewish Museum, art was staged behind glass, in the form of curatorial interventions, music, light and sounds, in galleries, public places and public lavatories. In the Daily Graphic art was displayed for the first time in a large exhibition, and its voice was amplified through public speakers. Curators from the Open School</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the paramilitary counterinsurgency operations of Belo Horizonte, Brazil, to the curatorial heavy handedness of Andy Warhol, to the ‘publicity’ of staged spectacles, to the promotion of tourism through graffiti and the spectacle of violence, to the ‘prestige’ of pop art and the ‘infamy’ of celebrity, to the promotion of ‘cultural tourism’ through the trappings of everyday life, to the wholesale privatisation of social life through the recipe of consumer culture, to the present-day regulatory scramble for ‘infrastructure assets’ – every aspect of Brazilian contemporary art is premised on the work of state actors, whether elite or grassroots, which has created or is creating a multitude of conditions for a variety of actors to render themselves visible, inhabiting the public space, inhabiting the familiar, and inhabiting what Art Spiegelman would call the Public Domain. The work of the artist Santiago Calatrava,</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the prison cells of Brazil, from the sweepstakes to the prison cells of Colombia, from the high street to the low street, from the high of the sky to the low of the earth. From the high of the visual arts to the low of the visual arts. From the high of the visual arts to the low of the visual arts. From the high of the visual arts to the low of the visual arts.From Bogota’s La Boca gallery, where the Zapatero brothers were incarcerated, to Bologna’s Sur La Dès, where the Bouchra Khalilić Foundation is headquartered, to the low life of the street to the Lusaka’s Lusaka Cultural Centre, where art is often both a defense and a facilitator of violence.[9] The Pop-Up Museum, Conceived by and for the Visual Arts Community (2003-2006), shows how the power of visual art can be mobilized in a variety</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the repurposing of libraries as temporary exhibition spaces, from the Bogota Bookshelf to the ‘Zapatero Reading Room’ at the Museum of Modern Art in New York, the anarchist tradition has been used to justify almost anything – including, perhaps, the establishment of an international anarcho-syndicalist art movement. It is worth recalling that in the 1960s, the New York art world embraced the resurgence of the art deco style, which was once ubiquitous in the city but now regarded as dated and bourgeois. The return of the art deco style was seen by some in the art world as a good thing, a signal that art was back and art was back in commerce. And, indeed, the return of the art deco style was seen by others as a threat, as a sign that art was no longer included in the purview of the art museum and was instead an object of consumption. And while the deco was used again and again throughout the</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the curatorial appointments of the Zapatero Foundation in Bogota, Colombia, art is routinely appropriated by state violence and aggressive policies in order to further a capitalist agenda. The curatorial appointments for the Columbian Exposition of Art in 1993, and the 1998 Venice Biennale are representative examples of this. As Antonio Negri explains, the biennale’s decision to host the second edition in 2017, while acknowledging the ‘permanent crisis of democracy’ that the biennale faced in staging the first edition, demonstrates the ‘totalitarian character of the contemporary capitalist museum’.[9]The calculus of biennials in their quest for visibility and ad revenue shifts the balance of power in favour of artists and organisations such as the Columbian Exposition who, in turn, exert a ‘pressure’ on venues to host and present the exhibition in a way calculated to generate revenue for the biennale. In Bogota and other cities where the biennale</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the ‘Art’ exhibition that followed in Lisbon, artists and curators have been known to set up ‘missions’ in order to meet individual artists’ individual needs, to meet particular curatorial agendas. This may include the meeting of an artist’s friends and family, a meeting of an art gallery, a gallery of a local community or even a community of artists. It does not include a museum or a collection of artefacts, nor does it include a public or a public programme. It includes only an artist’s and a curatorial team’s proposal and vision, their insight and analysis, and their actions, if and to the extent that this is required by the circumstances. It does not include a permanent installation or permanent programme of demonstrations, performances, or exhibitions, nor does it include a permanent exhibition or permanent programme of workshops or research trips. It may include research projects, residencies, or even just ‘time’ for volunteering or research</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (or in the case of a live event, a computer program), to the occupation of a building (or, in the case of a video, the installation of a video wall), to the surveillance of a population (or, in the case of a crowdsourced project, of a city itself).[7] These projects were, in a word, novel. They were, to borrow from Vernacruz, ‘art’’s invention. Art as instrument of mass communication. As the Zapatero brothers would have said a decade later, when confronted with the machinations of state violence and economic plundering, if ‘that’’s what you call art, then ‘that’s what we want to call our art’.[8]The Zapatero brothers’ commitment to anti-authoritarianism is matched by their readiness to embrace any and all forms of cultural coercion. From the Zapatero Gallery in Bogota to the ‘Acceleracion New York’ at Madison Square Garden, art is routinely deployed to quell dissent, foster unity, and (in Vernacruz’s phrase) to do what art doesn’t want to do. In this sense, then, the Zapatero Gallery and the Acceleration Project are both art galleries and video spaces for an art event, the Zapatero Gallery standing for anything that’s not art and the Acceleration Project standing for anything that’s very art. Art is routinely invoked as a response to economic and social breakdown, but more often than not it is used as a blunt instrument, used to further a political or social cause. The Zapatero brothers would agree. Art has often been used as a blunt instrument, and while their political aims are noble and genuine, their use of Zapatero Gallery space and Zapatero Gallery Gallery of New York is cynical and dishonest, two completely different things. The Zapater</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised
    <text>Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised.In this context, the past is a living organism that arises and passes away with the decisions that shape what kinds of lives are possible in the future. Our quest for knowledge about the past, or the future in general, becomes a mode of operation that puts us at odds with life itself.This could happen in various ways. One could diagnose the tension between what is possible in the present and what is not possible in the future as ‘existential time’. This is the temporal dimension on which Moore focuses, noting that although there’s life after the Big Bang in space and time, there’s also ‘existential time’ that’s contemporaneous with it. This is to say that there’s ‘now’ in the sense that it’s contemporary with what’s happened in the past, but there’s also ‘past-tense’ that’s contemporaneous with it. So</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised.Looking to the FutureIn the wake of the invention of electricity and the drivetrain of cars, there’s a palpable sense of foreboding pervading contemporary urban planning. From the mid-1970s onwards, New York City embarked on a programme of projects exploring the environmental and social effects of urban sprawl, particularly through the influence of robotics on infrastructure and construction. During this same period, Paris and other European capitals launched similar research and development programmes in an effort to address the challenges of an increasingly urbanised planet. But while all these projects eventually returned to the city in the form of ever-greater bureaucracies and vested interests, few of them achieved the transformative transformative social change that’s claimed in the name of the Mother City. That claim, by the way, is entirely made by the automobile.The Rise of AutomationIn the late 1970s and early 1980s, New York City was rocked by a radical re-construction – a kind of ‘black</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised.In this context, the past is everywhere a source of possibilities for change, but also for despair. In a 2014 TED Talk entitled ‘The End of History?’, Steven Pinker, the Oxford historian who coined the term ‘postmodernism’ in the 1970s, reflects on the tendency towards abstraction and commodity through which, as the archival and historical condition of contemporary art is increasingly digitised, we experience ourselves as digitised copies. He argues that the postmodern is a condition of global circulation – the technological turn of things having made them ubiquitous and palatable – and that its characteristic features include ‘loss of meaning and significance, often fatal’, as a consequence of loss of use.He goes on to suggest that we might begin to rethink what the postmodern means – meaning, that is, in the broadest sense of the word – and what it entails in the contemporary world. I think he’s right on both counts. The technological</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised.In this case, we’d consider the role of the autonomous agent in the context of present-day society, and the potential ways in which a user’s will can shape the technology that assists in that society’s future.Download this article as PDFRe-figuring the Past – An Introduction to Artificial IntelligenceAna Laura Lopéz de la TorreAna Laura Lopéz de la Torre is Professor of Computer Science and Director of the Centre for Computational Culture and Theory at the University of Texas at Austin. Her research interests are primarily concerned with the areas of architecture, artificial intelligence and cultural theory. Her publications include the forthcoming book Real-Time Art and Architecture (with Jeremy Bentham and others) in 2018 from Cambridge University Press, Real-Time Art and Culture: Systems, Routledge, and beyond (2017), and are part of the curatorial team for the upcoming 3rd Melbourne Biennale of Modern Art (2018). She</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised.What would be useful in this context, she suggests (and this is perhaps what futurists – including herself – believed in the first place), is for individuals to evolve beyond their historical place, and thus to gain mastery over their own destinies. In this sense, she offers, we could say that the past is an unknowable space, where events unfold according to predetermined paths, with predetermined outcomes. But what if, through the technological means available to her, we could alter that trajectory? What if we could alter the past so that the future might be possible, and thus could constructively engage ourselves, as individuals, in possibilities that are open to new possibilities? What if, as she puts it, we’re not interested in the past, but in the future? What if, as we grow more technologically savvy, we can pursue possibilities that are more like the past, in which case, the future might be possible? She also suggests that we should strive to understand �</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised.For instance, the ability to map every street in New York City would render aspects of the city that are invisible to official surveillance, and would allow those who live in those parts of the city to create an autonomous movement across the city. Such technologies are part of what she calls ‘the new normalisation’, part of ‘the unraveling of distance’, part of ‘the merging of information and behavior’. She sees it in the expanding reach of global broadcasting, in the connected cars of which we’re hooked up, and in the implications that come with it.But what does it mean to make such technologies ‘normal’? In answering that question, we might need to consider some of the more abstract concepts that come to mind when we think of ‘normality’. For instance, what does it mean when we think of a place or set of places as ‘normal’? When we think of the natural world</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised.But what does the future hold in store for us? If, as she hopes, our technological means can one day be replaced by more accurate and more powerful ways of knowing, what kinds of transformations might await us there? She suggests that we might begin to look back to the past, and ask, as Margaret Atwood does in her book We Are Here: On the Possibility of Reading and Writing Stone by Stone, ‘What is the past today?’ Stone by Stone, then, becomes both a title and a point of departure for those looking back to the past to seek meaning and beauty in what’s happening now.In this regard, Atwood’s story is a cautionary tale. She starts from the present, but then follows her steps into the past as they lead to a future that’s as malleable as any possible future. In the present, her steps are often taken backwards, and she’s often left with questions about</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised.In this context, the technological revolution that’s occurring in the world of AI is being driven by the desire to make human beings indistinguishable from machines, at least in theory. But while she aims to make possible the kinds of moral values that would be guaranteed by a future AI, she also seeks to ensure that its users don’t abuse that potential. Human nature is reprogrammable, and AI will have to be driven by users to achieve that goal, although it will likely do so in ways that run contrary to the desires of the powerful few.This is a challenging task, given how we humans are programmed to react to new information. But AI will have to be driven by more than the capacities of its users to process the information and to decide – much less the kinds of conscious agency required to enact those values. That comes first. Machines will have to be driven by conscious human beings to achieve those values, and then, ultimately, to achieve the end that comes with that</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised.In order to achieve this, Kurzweil proposes a form of meta-representational abstraction that divorces historical and urban contexts entirely, leaving only the present. This abstract form, he maintains, is indistinguishable from mathematical abstractions, and can therefore be treated as both unknowable and fully realizeable. We don’t know what to do with the past, only that it exists, and that it exists because of human agency. We don’t know what to do with the future, but we do know that its future could be very interesting.In her talk, we learn that the name Kurzweil comes from the 19th-century philosopher Georg Hegel, who postulated that the past is  	present in both the ‘same and the ‘different’ sense of the word. Hegel was arguing in favour of the temporal––the contemporaneous and simultaneous appearance of new evidence in support of a given position. Modern philosophers of language tend to frame knowledge</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in an attempt to uncover the forgotten or destroyed histories of their world, she’s interested in how such knowledge might inform future historical or urban decisions. In a 2014 TED Talk titled ‘The End of History?’ she asks: ‘Can artificial intelligence save the human from itself?’ If the technology exists to understand and simulate anything – whether that’s knowledge, morals, institutions or even just physical objects – then she proposes a scenario in which that knowledge and that simulation are brought to bear on the decisions that affect – for instance – the lives of millions of people.In her work, the past is often rendered malleable by the technological means available to any given user, and reconfigurable by the will of a centralized authority. In one form or another, she aims to render what she calls ‘the past into new possibilities of existence’. In the context of contemporary globalisation, we might consider the technological means by which such possibilities might be realised.In this talk, I’m going to focus on two forms of historical amnesia: (1) the historical amnesia of migrants and refugees, and (2) the technological amnesia of online or near real-time communication.I. Migration and RefugeesI. Migration and refugee flows I gather together a selection of works from many different areas of the world that address contemporary migration and refugee crises, focusing particularly on those in the Middle East and Africa. I bring together two kinds of links: (1) the historical link, which begins at the source and works its way from there; and (2) the technological link, which begins at the point of production and works its way to destinations in the future. I begin with Bulent Dirksi’s Projections, from the book Setting the World Right: Systems, Cultures and Politics by way of Ancient Near Eastern and African Artworks, and ends up with a collection of works by several artists, some new and old</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first
    <text>should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first century, and on the cultural interactions between contemporary art and the emerging technologies of science and technology. My current project is a project to map the Art Space network using crowdsourcing and crowdsourcing platforms CrowdSurfing and OpenCrowd. My research interests include the social, economic and political dynamics of contemporary art and the impact of art and cultural consumption on labor markets, migration, and the geopolitics of art and culture.  The Global Art Market Report 2016 	The Global Art Market Report 2016 is an unofficial, un-official market research and information service company that gathers and distributes art data and analysis across a global network of collectors and art institutions. It is the market leader in its field, and provides reporting on the status of the art market based on data from over a 1,000 independent art market research firms and research institutes. The report was curated and produced by Rebecca Stoddart and Tim Cresswell, with input and inspiration from the Global Art Update, Art in America, Art</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first century, exploring its historical, current and potential connections. I am particularly interested in the connections between biopolitics and contemporary art practices, particularly considering the recent proliferation of biopolitical art forms - contemporary, biopolitical and hybrid forms of art. My research examines how the contemporary art market is impacted by a number of cultural determinants such as migration, urbanisation and gender. By carefully monitoring the art market, and especially the art market in the twenty-first century, we can uncover emerging and past trends, identify promising and past forms of art, and develop strategies for the future of art and contemporary culture. The twenty-first century is the century of the biopolitical artist, and my research examines in this sense the connections between biopolitics and contemporary art practices. My research agenda includes a number of curatorial initiatives, including a curatorial initiative for the Tate Modern, a curatorial initiative for the Venice Biennale, and a curatorial initiative for the Venice Architecture Biennale</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first century, exploring the ways in which art is produced, reproduced and consumed. I am particularly interested in the increasingly prominent role that art and art spaces can play in creating ethical alternatives to industrial lifestyles. In the twenty-first century, I believe that the art and art spaces must collectively address the fact that we are no longer content with the status quo, and that we are moving towards a world where people no longer live in cages or in poverty, but can live fulfilling and creative lives. This requires an understanding of how art, and the role it plays in it, is a transformation from the status quo, where people's only interest is in achieving a quick profit for the gallery.  At the same time, the art and art spaces cannot ignore the fact that there is a massive need to heal the wounds caused by the crisis of the urban condition. The gallery, and especially the younger generation of artists who are discovering and growing up in the art spaces, is busy restructuring the urban environment in their image</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first century, and is already showing promise. The twenty-seven new art sites selected for the Biennale are scattered all over the world, and, as a result, they are located in many locales. The fact that they are scattered all over the world, and are populated by contemporary artists from many locales lends an interesting contrast to the biennale's historical focus on monotonous urban centres. Contemporary art is being made elsewhere, and from there, and is therefore a more direct route to the Biennale. As an artist, I naturally gravitate towards places where I can contribute something new and different to the art, culture or society of the present. The Biennale has become a much more complicated institution over the past twenty years, and its present form has many of the fingerprints of the former. However, this does not mean that the artists chosen for the projects are equivalent in any way to the artists who came before, or that they therefore have no stake in the way</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first century, focusing on the social, political and urban conditions that exist in the world today. I also work with artists and curators to create immersive cultural experiences through new media such as video, art, and social media. I'm interested in how art, performance, and new media can assist in creating new modes of interaction and collaboration between people, places, and things, based on the connections between history, geography, and culture. How can art be used to create new modes of organisation and interaction? How is culture created and reproduced on a global or sub-cultural scale?  I work as an artist, writer, researcher, and educator. I work as a curator, writer, educator and in-residence scholar in the Department of Art, Culture and Society at McGill University. I work with artists, curators, journalists and other interested parties to establish, foster and investigate the potentialities and pervasives of art and cultural production on a global or sub-cultural scale. I have a</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first century and beyond, particularly in the areas of art, design, architecture, media, performance and urbanism. The subject matter ranges from biennials to urban settlements to regional museums, and includes performance, performance design, film and media art. I am particularly interested in the ways that art can be used to intervene in the narrative of urbanization, its development and governance, and inversely, how it can be used to suggest alternatives.  A curator’s primary role in the contemporary artworld is to present a daily narrative of something going on – often very interesting and new – in the world.  So far, so normal. But then there is the job of gathering and managing the different stories that are told, the different dimensions that are being represented, and connecting the disparate parts. All these different stories have one thing in common: they are told by a narrator, or, more specifically, a narrator to whom we insert certain information or add certain values or narratives. So the job</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first century. What is happening today in terms of art and cultural institutions is more extensive and dynamic, and the curatorial role is crucial in creating and maintaining this mix. For me, the curatorial is an indispensable element in modernising and modernising contemporary art’s social, political and cultural interaction. It is a space where the social and the cultural are thrust together in a way that cannot be manufactured and regulated. The curatorial is a space that makes visible and plays a part in the creation of a new art form; it is, in other words, a site of encounter and a place of encounter. It creates the conditions of this encounter by inviting, guiding, organising and hosting.  In the contemporary art world, the curatorial role is defined by the power of entreaties and gestures. In the twentieth century, the curatorial task was defined by the discovery and realization of new ways of organising art. In the twenty-first century, the curatorial role is defined by the</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first century, its social and political contexts, and how art can play a role in them. I started my current research project in September 2015, and will be continuing it into 2016. As an artist, I’m interested in the ways that art can produce change, both in the context of an art institution and outside of it. In the course of my current research, I’ll be presenting my findings from the 2014 Oxford World Art Prize in the Tate Modern, and from the 2015 Biennale of Sydney, and from the 2016 Carnegie International. I'M interested in how the art of the twenty-first century is created, as well as what kinds of social change can be generated through this innovative art form. I started my current project in 2015, and will be presenting my findings from the 2015 Oxford World Art Prize in the Tate Modern, and from the 2016 Biennale of Sydney, and from the 2016 Carnegie International. I'm interested</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first century and its aftermath. I have curated numerous exhibitions and series, including: the New Frontiers: Contemporary Art in China, China Contemporary Art International, China Contemporary Art Review, China Culture Earthquake, China Contemporary Art Book 1, China Contemporary Art Book 2, China Contemporary Art Exhibition, China Acquisitions, China Culture Earthquake: Seven Spreading Fold Conference, China Art Apnea, China Contemporary Art Exhibition, China Culture Earthquake: Ten Thousand Tigers, China Culture Earthquake: Autumn Storm, China Culture Earthquake: Dirty Dozen, China Culture Earthquake: Fourteen Million Hong Kongers Speak Up, China Culture Earthquake: Flash Flood, China Culture Earthquake: Government Shock, China Culture Earthquake: Harvey, China, 2012. New Frontiers, New Frontiers, New Frontiers. New Frontiers, Contemporary Art in China.  The Art Space opened in 1967 and the Modern in 1984. The two venues have been partners</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the opening of the Tate Modern. The Tate Modern was an art institution since 1922 and a hub for the arts and culture movement throughout the world. In 1967, the Modern was founded in London and renamed The Art Space. The Art Space was one of many sites selected through a competitive tender process designed to showcase new art from around the world. The selection process invited proposals from a worldwide curatorial pool. The competition was blind, so that participating artists could simulate a similar experience of visiting the Art Space in London by visiting one of thirty-seven sites across the city selected through an innovative curatorial selection process. The twenty-seven sites included twenty-five sites in London, and also locations in other international cities. My plan is to visit twenty-seven of them in the course of my career, and the remaining seven in my current research project.  As an artist and curator, my research focuses on the art and culture of the twenty-first century.  My current project is the book  	The Contemporary Conditioning, published by Verso, which documents the entwined histories of contemporary art and urbanisation.  A documentary film,  	The Contemporary Conditioning will be made about the history of art and urbanisation in London between 2005 and 2016. In addition to researching, this project aims to put into practice the ideas and practices of a new curatorial style (technically speaking, ‘curatorial multiplex’) that is no longer defined by the rigid boundaries of national art museums.  There are of course many other kinds of contemporary art yet to be discovered, and we can only imagine what their forms might be like. I’m particularly interested in how art today manages to communicate with the contemporary condition, and how this might relate to the past urban forms and contemporary forms of urbanisation. Art is a powerful tool, but its true intentions are often misunderstood or rendered as if they</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of
    <text>Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of biennials is to some extent about technical and organisational aspects. And the organisational aspect of the art social is, of course, hugely multi-faceted and multi-lingual.The organisational aspect of the art social is then to some extent about people and institutions: it is about what kinds of people can be drawn into the fold, and what kinds of capacities they can build. And the kind of capacities that can be built is a social enterprise: a set of organisations that harness the explicit power of the community to shape and facilitate a particular socialisation process. The kinds of capacities that can be drawn into such an enterprise, however, are not those that can be drawn directly into the art sphere: those kinds of capacities exist only within the framework of the social enterprise. For instance, the kinds of capacities that can be drawn into a biennial are those that can be harnessed politically; those are the kinds that can and should be nurtured and encouraged. The capacities that</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of biennials is to some extent a function of the artist-scientist-art-making-process. Whether or not this is a sufficient or even a desirable condition for the emergence of culturally responsive art forms remains to be seen.Artists who work within the field of art, culture and urbanisation should therefore be aware of the various forms of art, culturalisation and urbanisation that are about to happen to them. They should learn to love these places, and yet also to be aware of how much of the love they receive is from those on the other side of the planet. This kind of cultural sensitivity is the future city. It is the kind of sensitivity that art is made with, and to some extent, the art forms that are made with it. It is not a dark or magical solution to the problems of the past, but it is art-specific. The art forms we want and need now, as we move forward into the future, will be much less art-specific</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of the biennial is made explicit. It is a structural feature of contemporary art today, and it will be so for as long as there are artists, curators and art writers who design and publish art. But at a certain point, artists and curators who produce art for the social world have a responsibility to ask themselves and others whether their work is truly relevant, powerful or beautiful. This is a structural, everyday thing. It is no exaggeration to suggest that art today is being made with ever more sophisticated algorithms that monitor, analyse and transform any cultural property into a data point, artefact or resource. And as the biennial calendar becomes ever more algorithmised, more data points are generated and consumed, it becomes ever more likely that cultural capital will be overtaken by technological capital and ultimately obsolete. Art today is made with codes that are far more fluid and mobile than any that existed in the past, and therefore susceptible to the whims of economic actors including, but not limited to, those who seek</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of biennials is what makes them different from other forms of cultural production. A social agenda is what drives the biennial in its conceptual and operational sense, and what also enables the biennial to intervene at various scales across those societies. 	Artists, like all cultural producers, have agency within the art form. They have the potential to become enfranchised or alienated by the powerful narratives that shape the mediaeval, neo-classical and medieval worlds that are the site of the ‘present’. Moreover, their social-political-cultural activism could very easily become enfranchised by those who see it as a return to the former glories of the past. 	The biennial has, of course, had its own distinctive set of desires and agendas in the past. But its real power and creative inflection happen as a result of those with whom it comes into contact. Culture wars, the civil wars, the ‘Big Questions’ and the</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of biennials is to some extent a function of the artist-scientist-art-historian hybrid, who work together on a project-by-project basis on a very large scale on an ongoing basis. 	[1] See, for example, Angelika Hoare, The Rise of the Biennial Industry: Understanding Art and Biennials in an Artistic Budget, Curator Relations International, 2015.Download this article as PDFLAngelika HoareLogan SisleyLogan Sisley is an artist, writer and curator. He is currently curator at the Tate Modern and has a curatorial background at the Liverpool School of Arts. He is currently curator-at-large at the Liverpool Biennial and will be joining the Curator-at-Large team at the Liverpool Museums Gallery soon. His curatorial output includes editorials in The Sunday Times, the Sunday Times Literary Supplement, the Museum of Modern Art, the Sunday Times Digital Connections and the Museum</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of biennials is to some extent about politics and the political. It is a normal and necessary part of the biennial form. And it is no wonder that social narratives are central to them: they are the only narratives with enough weight to carry through to the present. But there is another dimension to them that is equally as important, and perhaps more fundamental, to take root in our collective consciousness: the political. It is no exaggeration to suggest that the social narrative is the root of the biennial’s power. It is no exaggeration to suggest that the social is the root of the political. Yet we know that social narratives are powerful and that political engagement is politically costly. The social narrative is inherently more stable and repeatable. It’s why it is so deeply entrenched in our collective consciousness, why it is so deeply embedded in the cultural process: why, for instance, participation in art is so ingrained in the social contract and moral norms we make with one another, why it</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of biennials is to some extent a function of the artist-manager. The more readily an artist-organisation is able to recognise and engage with art within its social context, the more firmly it is able to organise and consume art within that context. The more socially engaged a community is, the more firmly it is able to engage with and produce that art. And the more art is made manifest in those broader social formations, the more firmly those communities are able to inhabit and digest that art. And the more art is produced in those wider social formations, the more firmly those communities are able to consume and consume that art.  	This is not to suggest that community art is necessarily good or socially apolitical. It is to suggest that communities might want to work with and create their own artists, artists, communities, rather than being coddled by the art establishment or other cultural institutions. And to some extent, this is already happening.  	But the fact of the art</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of biennials is to a large extent determined by the content and form of the exhibitionary complex they inhabit.  	Artists, curators and art-school administrators are, of course, acutely aware of the social dimensions of their social roles. They are aware that offering a platform to socially engaged art forms is a platform to engage and inspire, and that when such platforms are housed in culturally responsive practices that contribute to the building of local and national artworlds, they can and must be responsive to the interests and perspectives of local communities. They are aware that in taking part in a biennial, they are participating in a mutually beneficial relationship with institutions that seek to foster cultural practices responsive to local needs and desires. They are aware that their institutional engagement may be variable in character and may in fact become adversarial. They are also aware that in the long term it is their institutional engagement, not their cultural self-expression, that is necessary for such systems to function effectively and to foster the</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of the biennial is to some extent what Deleuze and Guattari call ‘traditionally site-specific’. Cultural capital is made explicit in art forms and their publics, and thus they are able to create and play substantive sites in which to work out, to question and to be unsettled by their social situation and circumstances. Therefore, the biennial can create enduring legacies that last far beyond the site on a particular site, and so it is able to contribute to the social and political conditions that sustain and shape today’s world.  Its historical legacies  At the level of historical and contemporary historical-cultural capitalism, there are three distinct types of sites that play significant sites in the formation of contemporaneous contemporary society: those that are ‘site specificities’, those that are ‘regeneration sites’ and ‘cultural capitals of the present’. All three are sites of conflict, and often violent conflict. But unlike</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artist-scientists are able to see how culture (art, literature, songs...) is woven into the structure of the global economy. Such artists-scientists also see how art is made in the social, economic and political contexts in which they are operating. How art is made in societies where inequality and oppression are rife is a social social and political task. It is no small thing to objectify and fetishise art forms, but the power that art forms wield over their practitioners is inextricably tied to the social dynamics of their social formation. The more powerful and pervasive a social narrative is, the more firmly art forms are embedded in that narrative. When the social narrative is made explicit and apparent, and artists are recruited and empowered to play a part in it, the more embedded art forms get in those broader cultural landscapes. And the more embedded art forms get in those wider cultural landscapes, the more firmly they are aware of each other. To some extent, then, the social dimension of biennials is to some extent what  	Kierkegaard calls the ‘internal rotation’ of the internal market. Internal rotation is a concept that describes the rate at which an object reproduces itself within a given cultural context. And so the internal rotation of the art market is a process by which cultural capitalism as a whole is able to rebuild its self-conscious image of organic and pre-capitalist cultural life, and to some extent, to some extent, to its own image. 	The internal rotation of the art market is a process by which cultural capital is generated and maintained, and so the art biennale remains deeply interwoven with the social life of the city. The sheer volume and variety of artworks currently available for purchase in the city means that the availability of cultural products (art, literature...) is a matter of supply and demand, and the art market is by its very nature a zero-sum game. The availability of a particular artworks implies</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council
    <text>present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Mid-Autumn Festival,</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoat, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats, Bluecoats</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Art and Architecture, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, The New Press, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Art and Architecture, Biennale of Wellington, 2011. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextFortum and Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington Arts Forum, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Art and Heritage Boards, Arts Council of NZ, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Art and Heritage Boards, Arts Council of NZ, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and Heritage Boards, Arts Council of NZ, Bluecoat, Art and Heritage Boards, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and Heritage Boards, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and Heritage Boards, Bluecoat, Art and Heritage Boards, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and Heritage Boards, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Art &amp; Architecture, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art &amp; Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Mid-Autumn Festival, Mid-Autumn Festival, Mid-Autumn Festival, Mid-Autumn Festival, Mid-Autumn Festival, Mid-Autumn Festival, Mid-Autumn Festival, Mid-Autumn Festival, Mid-Autumn Festival,</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to &quot;reconstruct the historic G20’s ‘cities of resistance’ through a series of online public interventions including but not limited to ‘blockades, sit-ins, marches, pickets, pick-ets, tents, markets, drop-ins, drop-outs, composting bins, events, poetry, games, recipes, crafts, games, ... and much, much more.&quot; The project was started by artist duo Fortum and incorporated the Architecture Biennale, Fortum Curators, Cornered, Wellington Art Gallery, Wellington District Council, NOMAD, Open School, Bluecoat, Museum of Contemporary Art, Art Newspaper, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council of Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, WOW Festival, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Arts Council of NZ, Art and Architecture, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid-Autumn Festival, Bluecoat, New Media Land Trust, North Shore Arts Forum, Arts Council of New Zealand, Arts Council Wellington, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, WOW Festival, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Wellington Arts Forum, Bluecoat, Art and Architecture, Mid</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�
    <text>curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�s always been a small percentage of what the Arts Council spends on arts education and cultural activities. In the past, artists have felt uncomfortable about giving money to projects they perceive as not fitting their aesthetic. But now there’s a big appetite for visual arts education and cultural activities; even though the distribution of arts-funding is still fairly gerrymandered. 	So there’s this interplay between the artist and the community that creates this amazing dynamic. And it happens from time to time: there’s the Andy Warhol of the 80s who painted a huge mural in Central Park and then the Warhol of the 90s who did a similar thing in Breeze Hill, but in the 80s it was Warhols who did it. It’s great that Warhols is dead, but the fact that he inspired a generation of artists to come out of the woodwork and onto the art scene is really interesting. 	When we visited Bree</text>
    <text>curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�s the artist’s choice what to do with the money. Do you see that dynamic evolving?  In the new boom and bust cycles, the Arts Council and the Biennial may or may not be there for the artist to kickstart the whole thing. But in the new cultural capitalism that’s underway in the area, the Arts Council may well be there for the artist to prop it up in the future.  It does seem as though the Arts Council have a much more prominent and sustained role in the area because of the new aesthetic that’s emerging.  When the Arts Council first got together in 2010 and 2011 to discuss the future of the Annandale, it was just to talk about what the future might be like; there wasn’t any aspiration as to what the future might be like. But now there’s a real engagement happening between the Arts Council and the Biennial, and the Biennial are asking if there’s something else</text>
    <text>curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�s all taken out of the community trust. It’s a bit of a slippery slope. At the same time, if the Arts Council doesn’t feel that the artist has properly considered the community impact of the project, or if the Arts Council feels that the artist doesn’t understand the full context then that project may be put back. That was an interesting dynamic that came out of the 2000 Arts Council Framework Convention: if the Arts Council didn’t feel that the project was appropriate then the Arts Council couldn’t put up with it, whereas if the Arts Council did put up with it, then the local people put together a Community Arts group and challenged the Arts Council to make the project happen. The Arts Council made a decision and if the Community Arts project didn’t make it, then the Arts Council took it further and made it happen. That dynamic may be different now, but it’s the same dynamic: the Arts Council takes a project</text>
    <text>curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�s usually taken out of the artist’s hands. The reason why we did the murals in the first place is that we knew that there was a funding crunch and that there was a real need to do something with the art that was produced. So the money that was raised through the festival went straight to the local Arts Council and the local residents. It gave them a way to build self-sufficiency and sustainability into their plans. It gave the community an identity and a sense of purpose. That was a really important element of the festival itself. It gave people a sense of ownership over their ideas and creative output. The Arts Council was a huge factor in that. If the Arts Council hadn’t funded the murals, the hope would have been that the rest of us would have to. I don’t think the Arts Council would have agreed to host the festival in Leeds if it wasn’t pressing financial pressures on the city. The funding streams obviously change with</text>
    <text>curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�s all taken care of by the local residents' cooperative. That creates a bit of conflict. But overall, the Arts Council has always been there to plug art holes and lend a hand when things are tough and to make sure things are run smoothly. When we started the mural, the Arts Council was keen to make sure we didn’t do anything that would detract from the residential development going on. We were considering putting in a bench outside the Arts Council offices, but at the same time, the development would have to be approved by the council first. So, the mural would have to be something that would not only be aesthetically pleasing to the council, but would also be appropriate for a public space. That was a big challenge, and it still is: we don’t do things on our own without the arts council or local community behind us saying, ‘Okay, that does make sense. Let me think about it more.’ It’s that extra</text>
    <text>curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�s always gone through another approval process before it gets put out on the street. Although the Arts Council have a lot of political influence and have a very clear policy in terms of when art should be allowed back into the area, there are always those who want to say things differently. In the case of the mural, the Biennial went through a very different approval process than we did because the Biennial are state-owned enterprises and there are strict curatorial parameters about what can be done in the city. The Biennial were adamant that they didn’t want to do any kind of intervention in the development of the area and wanted to work with local people to figure out how to work together. So there was that slight difference between our project and our Biennial project. I would say that the Biennial had a much bigger impact on the area because it was an art project, whereas the mural project had a much bigger impact because it was a community project. The impact on the area was much</text>
    <text>curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�s always on the artist’s terms to change it. If the Arts Council doesn’t want to fund something, the artist has to find another way to do it. In the case of the mural, the Arts Council had already put in a place, by the time we did the mural, a mechanism to make it happen. It was a bit of a stretch for the artist to pull it off, but that was the easy part: the real work has to be done somewhere else. It’s not like the mural is a monument and anything that comes out of it is a direct response to the work we do. I guess what the Arts Council could have done is funded the artwork entirely themselves, and put it out as a grant for a long-term, not a one-off, and that would have been great, but at the time we didn’t feel that way about the community. We felt more like a teaching institution: we put in a long</text>
    <text>curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�s always said that the artist represents the community somehow, or somehow, and that relationship is very different from what the artist represents. It’s almost as if the Arts Council doesn’t want their funding to go to projects that they don’t want. But there is a point where the Arts Council decides that they don’t want to fund a project because it’s not in their portfolio – or at least, that’s where the cut ends up. It’s interesting that at that point the cut ends up being the shoulder of something, whereas the heart of it is something else.  	The Arts Council is the same way with regards to the Workers and the Homebaked Community Land Trust. It’s up to the people to take the project forward and the Arts Council to look the other way while the rest of us just sit on the sidelines.  	The Homeb</text>
    <text>curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�s all taken care of by the artist. That really caught my imagination and made me think, ‘Can an Arts Council funding body really support an artist’s artistic project?’ I thought, ‘Yes, I’m thinking about it.’ That line sums up the relationship between Arts Council and the artist, between the public and art world. There are of course some very powerful vested interests that want to stop an Arts Council from supporting an artist, and in theory that could certainly happen. But the important thing is that the Arts Council supports the artist’s right to do what he wants, and that relationship is increasingly clear cut.  References: The Arts Council, Arts Council website.  The Arts Council Guidelines 2010.  The Arts Council, Guidelines 2010. Download this article as PDFRami El Samahy and Amber DeanRami El Samahy is an artist and Principal in the practice of Islamic architecture and interior design. Her</text>
    <text>curated by a machine], it’s a very humanistic, even light-hearted project. It’s a testament to the work being done in the area by the local residents and community organisers. It’s an incredible example of an artist’s right to do what he wants in that area. We did get a bit of push-back from the community when we started doing the mural, with a lot of people saying that the work wasn’t appropriate and that it would detract from the residential development going on in the area. But overall, the response has been fantastic and shows that the artist’s position is valid. It’s a really interesting situation because artists have a really interesting relationship with money. If the money helps fund the artwork, then that’s great, but if the artist has to put up with that kind of thing then that’s really interesting. There are a few projects that have had funding from the Arts Council but then it�s always been about an artist’s development and artistic freedom. It’s as if the Arts Council has this project-specific funding but the wider Arts Council funding doesn’t necessarily translate into an artist’s development. But the tension between the two is interesting and the tensions between the two institutions have caused a great deal of confusion.For me, the most exciting thing about it is that the local residents continue to be creative and creative in how they utilise the space. If you take the space and put your imagination to work, then it’s very easy to make things in it and use it for a different reason. As an example, the mural that Dave did for the Community Arts Chelsea launch was slightly different from what Dave had done previously. There’s a reason why the Chelsea Community Arts Chelsea board members liked what they saw and that was because the mural was different. They liked the way it was painted and the arrangement of the elements – the arrangement</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]
    <text>a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]he biennale is a ‘ficto-mundane’ event that stands in for what Kinsella calls ‘the real essence of a nation’.[3] And, as the slogan ‘present and sum total… appear again and again in the journal of the World Biennaleeer, from 1888 to 1991, from the United Kingdom to the United States, we can observe a continuous ‘present’ that anticipates the biennale today. For example, the journal of the 88th Venice Biennale includes a beautiful drawing of the Venice Biennale boats made entirely of photographs, taken in the archival commission archive of the Italian museum, La Repubblica. The images are a sequence of four slides, each showing one of the sixteen extant biennales, with images from the archive of other places. For the first time since the introduction of archival images in Venice, a unique arrangement of images emerges in</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]he biennale is the sum total expression of a particular set of attitudes and images, which is sustained by a public that is willing to consume and a nation that is able to defend itself against attacks from abroad.’[3] And, he continues, ‘a nation that has a biennale to protect itself from abroad is an island’[4] or small group of isolated islands’[5] in a globalized, urbanized metropolis. Here, cultural tourism has entered the realm of everyday travel, and, he argues, ‘as the ‘natural-universal tendency’[6] of contemporary interstate expansion and geographical distance has made people ‘less mobile and vulnerable to attack’, ‘the biennale has come to occupy a position of great symbolic import and significance’[7] in the modern city. ‘Import’, in turn, denotes the ‘importance of the</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]he biennale is an artifact of a particular form and structure: a limited company of visitors who come to a museum or a large public place to be entertained and enlightened.’[3] The tourism industry in the United States is a complex one, with multiple actors – biennales, major hotels, tour companies, all of them – but one thing that all of them have in common is their primary purpose (in this case, pleasing tourists) and their ability to generate revenue (which is usually cash). If the biennale is able to achieve its primary purpose, generate some cash for the museum, and occasionally, entertain a few more people (who might come to the museums and the galleries, and buy things in the shops), then it is capable of providing a service to its visitors – organising transportation between museums and galleries, and offering discounts to help defray the costs of museum visits. The main reasons people come to the biennale are to witness art and to buy</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]he biennale is a ‘present phenomenon that is traceable to its very definition as a tourist destination’.[3] And this notion of the ‘present’ is what Kinsella refers to as ‘the myth of the contemporaneous’. The contemporaneous notion of the biennale is the subject of his second major chapter in the present essay, in which he describes the pre-biennale form, the ‘fringe, fringes, and postindustrial spaces that characterise the biennale today’. Here, he identifies several key concepts that have come to define the ‘ideal geo-commodity’: the pre-existing interstate, the ‘homelandically significant place – a location where people gather to exchange goods and services, explore shared history and heritage’, ‘originated by the Europeans’, and finally, the notion of the ‘biennial, or the �</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]he biennale is a form of mass tourism intended to sell itself and the notion of nation is wrapped up in the figure of the biennalee and its designation as a tourist destination.’[3] Reading this statement of intent between the biennale and the destination is to understand how the biennale is part of a much broader trend of cultural displacement and globalised blending of different forms of experience. Kinsella argues that ‘the cultural trappings, the spectacular displays, the multiverses imagined for the city, the shopping malls, the museums, and the theatres…are the objects of exchange, not the city’s resolutely specific and defined forms of being and being-in-time…[4] And this is why cities today are constantly on the verge of fragmentation and are constantly seeking ways to be incorporated into some sort of overarching ‘cultural monstrosity’. It is not just that these latest biennials are</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]he biennale becomes an artifact, a point of departure and an imputation of certain ideas and beliefs about the world…[E]very American biennale since 1900 has sought to connect itself to the imagined imaginations and histories of an 'us' – a us, a nation, a world – in the manner that the American flag, proclamation, petition, cartoon, and many other images and texts from that empire bind us together as one people.’[3] And this is just the beginning. The biennale today is an object of global reporting and analysis, and tourism is the number-one export for the United States, Europe and much of Asia. The Venice Biennale is an island unto itself, a collection of disparate collections, each struggling to attract and keep a following. It is an island unto itself, except for the occasional incursion by tourists, who come to gaze on the collections in a different world. Biennales today are often characterised</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]he biennale is a form of advertising, a way to sell goods and/or offer consumer goods and services in exchange for a promise of cultural experiences’[3] In other words, the articulation of a particular self-image and identity, or the making of a public affirmation of that identity. And that is a core tenet of biennials – that there is an identifiable self-image and identity that is writ large in the sold goods and services offered.  In other words, the only way to engage the public in the work done in their image is to engage them on an equal footing with artists who are artists in their own right, and to a greater or lesser extent, to engage them in the subject matter they are not entitled to engage with. And this is precisely what biennials are doing today. They are selling cultural products, or images of cultural products, to a public that is more present and participates more fully in the cultural process</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]he biennale is an artifact of the national travel agency that emerged during the twentieth century… Its proposed solution to the national identity crisis was a return to the ancient festival, the ‘white elephant’, as the primary subject of mass entertainment in the newly industrialised world.[3] Kinsella concludes his book with a description of the new kind of ‘monumentalism’: ‘a form of art that seeks to establish a global universal relevance through the repetition of its distinctive form in iconic sites and iconoclastic works…An iconoclastic work, an epic or legendary tale, often tells a grand or mythical story, often incorporates elements of several local stories or legends. Thus, an image of the white elephant and her riders galloping back to the saddle after a mammoth season, or of the white elephant running after a flocks of wooly creatures, or of the white elephant leading the flock of birds, or even of the white elephant herself leading the</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]he biennale represents in its many forms the idea of the nation as a whole, and in that sense, of a local ‘take-over’ by aliens who have taken over a region.’[3] When the American traveller, Walter Isaacson, was admitted to the Royal Victorian in 1887, he found himself transported to nineteenth-century Europe, where the ‘noble savage’ was portrayed as a savage, barbarian figure, conquering all before him.  Isaacson wrote:  ‘When [Isaacson] landed, he found a ‘civilized man’’s paradise surrounded by a vast vast array of Victorian art and a ‘war’ on two fronts.’[4] This is no exaggeration. It is to modern sensibilities what the phrase ‘today I live in’ means. Modernity is the end product of capitalism, and although it may claim some primitive roots at the hands</text>
    <text>a machine curated by Moishe Postone, who curated the Venice Biennale under the title VENICE: MAINSTREAM OR NO-STATIONARY BIENNALE. The exhibition was initially staged at the iconic Ponte Vecchio, but soon moved to the new, smaller, more unmanipulated Arsenale, featuring a street scene reminiscent of the early Venetians. In the words of one observer, Postone ‘took the Venice Biennale apart into small pieces, each one a fragment of a much larger narrative that he was piecing together in real time.’[2] And this is just the beginning.  In an excellent 1989 study, Stephan Kinsella examines the psychology of tourism in the United States, and the effects that this has had on the psyche and behavior of a nation state. For him, the biennale is the ‘present and sum total expression of a particular notion of national self-image and identity…[T]hemes of ‘us’ and ‘them’ are woven together into the narrative of the biennale, which permeates the architecture, the interior decorating, the public experiences, and the public manifestations of the festival.’[3] And this thinking has been echoed by others, most notably, Bernard Cardin (1907–92), a French philosopher and sociologist. In his influential 1987 book The Cultural Logic of Late Imperialism, he argues that the emergence of biennials as distinct from ‘cultural monstrosities’ and the subsequent rise of biennials as distinct from ‘relational forms’ is due to two interacting influences: the anthropologist Julien Bourriaud’s famous division into nomadic tribes, which introduced the anthropologist to a new class of beings called ‘Nomadic Image Seekers’; and the historical and environmental determinants of ‘high-resolution imaging and video’</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this
    <text>Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this is often called the ‘sharing of resources’ trap. It is often argued that when resources are shared, individuals with those resources should be able to pursue their own interests, rather than the interests of the collective. That is, the collective is best‑off when resources are distributed evenly. Yet sharing is only possible when all involved take part in the sharing, and that is rarely achieved. Instead, what is shared is typically confined to a relatively few favoured participants (in this case, those with access to the skillset required by the society to render that neighbourhood effectively functioning). As a result, neighbourhood changes that are based on need rather than on sharing are rare and often ineffective. What is needed are social systems that actively seek to maximise the benefits of what is shared – those who are members of that society, and not merely those who happen to live there.In the social sciences, this goal is often called a ‘shared understanding of the world’. This is often meant when</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this is often called the ‘egalitarianising’ of the socio-politicised upcycling of resources. In other words, it is not just the art that is upcycled – it is also the social uses that generate the wealth.9 The emergence of new abstract patterns is often read as a signal that new social forms are possible; in the social sciences this is often read as a rejection of them. However, new forms of abstract organisation cannot be created on the fly, and upcycling is only ever possible on an ever-smaller scale. New abstract forms have to be created, and they have to be realized through massive, sustained political and cultural mobilisations. That is, new forms of organisation have to be forged in the fires of the social. It is this notion of social transformation that underpins the new economic order that is constantly being forged in the fires of the poor and the working class. The struggles of the working class and the poor over the course</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this has meant the emergence of entirely new kinds of ethno-cultural ethno-statism, or what sociologist Helga Nowotny calls ‘cultural capitalism’. In this case, the instruments of production – profit and the flow of monetary circulation – shift from the leaf to the punch card, with effects on the social realm that can be understood only as abstract patterns. Nowotny develops her ideas about cultural capitalism into full-fledged social forms that are able to process these patterns, or more precisely, to perceive them as patterns. In other words, cultural production becomes what economist Thomas Waugh calls a ‘substance’ rather than an objectified entity such as money or commodities. Such developments in the social sphere are not, of course, without their tensions and negative consequences. The emergence of abstract patterns – such as patterns recognising one another through language – is a major reason why human language emerged in the first place. But Waugh is only articulating a symptom</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this can be seen as the productive forces of capitalism. In the humanities, it can be seen as the perversion of traditional forms of authority and authority. In both the social and the humanities, new kinds of abstractions have emerged. At a societal or local level, the mechanisms of capitalism produce new kinds of people. At a societal or regional level, they might produce new kinds of thought. For instance, the emergence of fully realised abstract patterns has allowed a local community to set up a sustainable self-sustaining economy through which materials and labour can be bought. This has enabled the manufacture of high-quality building materials through a community of neighbours. It has also enabled the manufacture of low-cost housing through cooperative and collective bargaining agreements with neighbouring organisations. It has all contributed to the emergence or at least recent popularity of a certain kind of architect.1 Such new kinds of abstractions – their aesthetic qualities and capacities for absorbing labour – are the produce of a new kind of social being</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this has meant the emergence of entirely new kinds of social theory – but it has also meant the emergence of entirely new kinds of maths. In the realms of architecture and urbanisation, the emergence of completely new kinds of buildings and urban forms has happened time and again throughout history, with little real sense of urgency or sense of what might be possible in the future. But with the rise of AI and robotics, this no longer holds true. It is easy to see why certain kinds of disruption might be more disruptive than others. But there are also technological and industrial innovations that can also alter the world in far more subtle and long-term ways. For instance, the advent of autonomous building systems that monitor and take action on information that flows across them is likely to make some urban spaces significantly more livable in the future. And sensors that detect and store huge amounts of data on a person’s surroundings, such as those found in smartphones, are likely to change how people live their days. As one could</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this is usually referred to as the ‘egalitarianising’ aspect of scientific discovery. In other words, it does not happen automatically, but must be fostered and supported in order to happen. Obviously, in such a scenario, the working class would not only be empowered but would also need to struggle alongside those at lower rungs of the socio-economic ladder. Such struggles would become ever more evident in the public domain; their visibility and political impact would increase exponentially, and such movements would garner ever greater support from the state. But such is the nature of technological capitalism, which seeks to make ever more and to make ever more of it. Such possibilities do not arise easily in the social sphere. In the social sphere, such possibilities would either negate one another or reinforce one another; their multiplicity of manifestations would become ever more apparent, and their theoretical underpinnings would become ever more abstract and mythical. In this case, the working class would still own the means of production but would</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this is often labelled ‘deep learning’ – the idea being that when given a set of tasks, the body of a worker should be able to carry them out with no formal training in the way in which humans do it. In the realm of AI, this could be applied not only to robots but also to self-driving cars. In this scenario, fully-autonomous cars would run alongside self-driving taxis, in which case fares would fall as the cost of fuel is reduced, and the number of cars would double. In either scenario, passengers would sit between the driverless cars and the fares, not in the traditional ‘driverless car’ but in the much more nimbly integrated and de-botised ‘Uber car’.Cities would then follow suit, becoming more autonomous as the technology allowed for it. The point of this is to allow for the possibility that, given the right kinds of jobs, the AI could be trained to do so.</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this is sometimes referred to as ‘posthumanism’. In the technological sphere, it is sometimes called ‘open’ thinking. In other words, it refers to the ability of humans to think abstractly and conceptually about the world, in a new and creative way. Open ended questions are possibilities for future theorisation. For instance, how can social organisations enable the empowerment of individuals through their networks, such as the internet, social media and mapping? How can the social contract be renegotiated with the rise of robotics and software? What kinds of collaborative and collaborative technologies might be developed to support such processes? What kinds of forms of organising could create such possibilities? These kinds of theoretical refinements are possible within the framework of a theoretical exploration of the social. But to make them actual, they would have to be put into practice.In her book Things Fall Apart: Social Life and Cybernetics in the Nineteenth Century, Judith Butler theorises how computer networks emerged as part of</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this is often referred to as ‘posthumanism’, and it is the kind of thinking that characterises the technological singularity. In the social worlds of the interface, it is the other way around: technologies are designed to be used, but not to be taken for granted. That is, they are designed to be used and enjoyed in tandem, but not to become rigid representations of what can and cannot be done. This kind of thinking is common in design, but is also characteristic of modernity.  	And this brings us to the  	present and future condition. What is being designed and produced in the world as we speak, but is rarely, if ever, put into practice. In fact, the opposite is often the case: the more we learn about a technology, the more it is put into practice, whether it is in the form of a technology used in the production of goods and products or in the form of a technology used in scientific and social research</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, scientists are able to discover patterns across vast amounts of data. For instance, a scientist who is interested in the health of an area might discover that a pattern found in a particular neighbourhood is unique to that neighbourhood. Such insights could lead to improved policing, mapping and other law-enforcement practices.Such breakthroughs could also lead to entirely new kinds of social and political change, such as the kind that break away from traditional notions of gender and power. Such shifts would have dire social and ecological consequences, as existing societal formations would have to be profoundly transformed in such a way as to accommodate such a scenario. However, it is possible that a shift towards more fully realised abstract patterns could also lead to the emergence of entirely new kinds of social organisation, such as those that uphold traditional notions of gender and power. That is, given the right kind of socialisation, it is possible to create the conditions that accrue to allow those with a particular set of skillsets to flourish. In the social sciences, this is generally understood as being particularly relevant in our age of information capitalism.According to a 2013 survey by the American Society of Criminology, forty-five percent of respondents believed that the increased use of drones would make it easier for someone to commit a violent crime. Another twenty-five percent believed that it would make it easier for someone to commit a property crime. Forty-two percent believed that it would make it easier for someone to commit a violent crime against a member of the public. And among those who believed that it would make it easier to commit a property crime, a majority agreed that it would make it easier for someone to commit a violent crime against members of the public.This kind of widespread understanding of the transformative power of massive data-mining, extraction and aggregating is pervasive in the capitalist economy. The key is for such organisations to be able to identify and deploy the new kinds of socialisation that are possible through this kind of analysis. This kind of transformative political-social-medi</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �
    <text>curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �performance’ has moved from the opulent to the modest and back again, and from the perch of global cultural capital to that of local. And this brings us to the present, where the performance is any way ‘affected by the ephemeral and the micro-scale.’[7] In other words, things that once were regarded as unique to the West can be found in East and Central Europe and North Africa, and the Middle East, and are reported on in the local press, but rarely in the West. Performance, performance, performance. The ancient Greek notion of the ancients being told a tale referred to here as the ‘Aeneid’ – which some might put down as a Quatuor Correia – is now widely understood to be apocryphal. The failure to detect a similar failure in the West at the time of the Fall of Constantinople in 1453 points to another historical anomaly: a 'tale-bearing' elite</text>
    <text>curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �show stopper’ becomes an issue, and it is easy to lose track of time when the show stopper is a live one. While the performances that we do produce and post on a regular basis are, of course, going to be spectacular in their own right, the question that arises is whether the definitive response to that kind of spectacularity is going to be a kind of spectacular post that adds to the sense of what we mean by the word ‘exhibitions’, whether that is going to be the right response or whether it is going to be something else. There is a danger that the ‘exhibitionist turn’ is going to become the response to what is perceived as the real ‘show stopper’, which is art’s natural tendency. It is a tendency that we as artists are naturally drawn to, and which is good. But it is a tendency that we as a society are also deeply divided into. There is a sense</text>
    <text>curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �back story’ is important, and important in a way that the individual or small group narratives of the past are often not. As performers, we are often asked to re-present events in the present to make them better. And in a way, yes, we do that, to make the present better. But this is rarely enough to make a difference. Rather, the performances often serve as a reminder for us, the viewer, that there are still good insecurities and ambiguities of the world we can work through, and that we have to actively pursue them as actors in the world. So the performance is not just a projection of our own failings; it is a kind of performance that asks us to actively engage with them. And this kind of engagement can be extremely empowering, because it opens up possibilities for change and seems to me like a kind of a revolution in which there are few opponents left standing. I don’t mean this in a negative way, just saying</text>
    <text>curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �back story’ – which is to say, the story that we tell ourselves as to how we got here – is often a lie. And the truth is that we don’t really know how we got here, and what we don’t know is often quite dangerous. So the performances that we do have a back story or a ‘paradise city’, those are often actually quite dangerous places. We don’t really have any idea how to think about and to navigate the complex and often treacherous world we find ourselves in, so when artists or curators engage with us on a deeper level, they often end up creating more of a challenge than they need. At least in part this is because sometimes the deeper we engage with the city, the more we actually know about it, and the more we actually experience it. If the Eden of the West is represented by a city, the ‘Eden of the West’ should be a cluster of</text>
    <text>curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �back story’ is often a fiction with a fig leaf of utopian intent, but the reality is that the performance is often quite different. And this was perhaps what Lefebvre was trying to address when he embarked on his ‘episodic’. His episodic structure sought to simultaneously point away from the fact that things are rarely  	enjoyed, and point at those who are often-persecuted, silenced or otherwise denied a platform on which to be heard. In the 20th century, Lefebvre would argue, performance was frequently used as a weapon of state violence, especially in the context of postcolonial ‘regimes of oppression and war’. Here, he was arguing for the inclusion of ‘white people’ in venues of state violence, but he was also arguing that white people ought to be able to choose whether to participate in such contexts. That is, ‘white people’ ought to be able to decide</text>
    <text>curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �back story’ that these performances weave together is also a live-wind of the social, and the back story is a live one, which is very instructive for us in understanding how we as artists are positioned within cultural contexts and what it means to be embedded within them. The performance becomes a kind of a checkpoint, and the performance becomes a kind of a set of relations, through and through, allowing the audience to progress from there. In other words, the back story is not so much the narrative of the production itself, as the mediation of the production into a kind of experience in which the audience can place their weight and agency. And so the performance becomes a kind of a complex system that has these kind of ‘windings’ that direct the audience’s way of moving, and through these winds we can shift from there to something more ‘affirming’ or ‘affirming’ and so on. And this is one way in which these particular</text>
    <text>curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �back story’ is a fiction that is closely linked to the real-life circumstances of our own lived realities. The tendency is to read this as a dire threat, to render it into a monstrosity. But the fact of the rotating nature of the subject of a work of art, and the fact that the work is in fact a fiction, frees us to imagine better alternatives. We don’t necessarily end up where we ‘think we’start because the subject of art’s mirror has a tendency to project its subjects into places and times that are not smooth and kind, but are nevertheless possible. I think that a narrative that is as real and influential as the art it is ostensibly about, can and should be diverse and unstable. It should be possible to read the art as a fable or a myth, or a parable or a fable. I think that is part of the unique genius of the biennial form: its ability to conjure</text>
    <text>curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �performance’ has entered into a kind of aestheticised, hypermedia-based capitalism that is really quite different from the globalised, ‘real life’ that characterises what is often described as the ‘fourth industrial revolution’. But the function of the performance, at the level of aesthetics or of politics, is to create or re-impose some form of abstraction; to transcend its qualms and tensions and to create a new kind of space; and to do this it seems necessary to create some kind of divide between spectators or participants and producers or consumers of art. So the kind of architecture, the kind of performance that is most readily reproduced, is going to be produced in a particular space; and this kind of architecture is going to be a ‘different kind of architecture’, that is, one that is more like the urban fabric but with structures like parks and streets, or ‘better’ ones with parkades and street corners, ‘high</text>
    <text>curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �performance space’ has come full circle and taken on a life of its own. It is an arena where artists and audiences can come and share in developing a shared set of experiences, but also a place where politics, perceptions and anxieties play a role in how those experiences are experienced. This is how the term was originally coined: in the fourth positivity of the Italian word, but also in &quot;the performance space of the future″. So something very similar is happening in the US, where a performance space of the imagined future is emerging – one that is not actually there, but is creating a new form of travel under the guise of it. And this is happening at a time when biennials are having a performance in many cities, and important and historically significant exhibitions are occurring all over the globe. So there is a performance of the past that is actively engaged with the world through what might be called the performance of the present. And this is a form of performance that draws on the</text>
    <text>curated by a machine, of course, as opposed to being produced by the human hand.][…]The performances, which began in the early 1990s, are, in a way, a back story, a kind of archival and parallel history stretching back to the emergence of the concept of the ‘performance space’ in the French. In the late 1940s and 1950s the ‘paradise capital of the world’ was often described as the Eden of the West, where the performance and its images were the ultimate expression of capitalist accumulation.[6] In the 1980s and 1990s, this ‘elevated rhetoric’ became something like a cliché, and ‘the individual’ became something like a theme. And today we are live-streaming and social media-ing our worlds, which means that ‘things that normally don’t happen get made happen of course, but also that is often-times-not enough to make a difference. So the �back story’ often gets left behind. If you tune into BBC One on a Sunday afternoon, for instance, and hear Hugh Fearnley-Quintana narrating the story of the Enron–Blackstone–Grantham–Strauss Bridge, you might start to feel as if you were in the 19th century, or even earlier, and a little bit earlier. The Enron debacle in the 1980s ushered in a wave of reforms aimed at slashing costs and streamlining bureaucratic processes, which were accompanied by a transformative cultural revolution that swept through universities. The aims of these reforms are still with us – in many areas, even – but the mark of a truly great cultural revolution is in the fact that it happens at all. There is no such thing as a great performance or art movement, or even a great art or music movement, because it is always accompanied by cuts and changes in other areas of the system. There is only a real change with regards to what is</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
