<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as
    <text>The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as a library; its features and capabilities make it an ideal tool for the cultural ecology of resistance.  	This research project is an extension of previous work undertaken by the Community Arts New York (CA20) programme at Columbia University, which has investigated the history and current state of Midwood High School's Midway Arts district. The project was initiated in 2015 and completed in 2017. The annotated documents form part of CA20’s project titled Microaggressions - Messages from the Microaggressions Project archive. The annotated version of the project’s 2017 report includes an extended analysis of the annotated records. 	The annotated version of the project’s 2017 report includes new data from the Midway Arts District and Midway Community Land Trust. The annotated version also includes data from earlier research projects that were part of the project‎s 2014-2015 research agenda. 	The annotated version of the project</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as a toolkit to analyse and document resistance activities. 	Ansible is an introduction to the world of data capture and reportage, and the context and motivations of resistance. It provides an overview of data mining and data visualization, and introduces the conceptual frameworks underlying such techniques. It also introduces the tools and techniques of data extraction and processing, and the social, economic and political contexts of their development.  	Ansible is a bash script that records and monitors the execution of processes using system processes and scripts as a toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance. It is a project for an anarchist journal by Zig-Zag entitled ‘Stir Up’. 	Ansible is a virtual journal that records and monitors the execution of system processes using system processes and scripts. It provides a mapping between system processes and their human language counterparts, a record of each syscall and a description of the execution’s</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as a toolkit to support research and documentation. 	The toolkit itself is a text with images and data that can be used to map, trace and analyse political, legal and economic resistance movements in North America and internationally. It is intended to support the research of two independent research teams: 	[1] CA20 Research Chair in Cultural Studies at Georgetown University, led by Professors Elizabeth Denman and Nasser Rabbat, and a New York University curatorial team, led by Professors David Gross and Suzi Randall with support from the NYU Health and NYU Film Faculty. Additional support is provided by the National Endowment for the Arts and the Grantees Fund.  	[2] The Mid-Hudson Arts Collective was founded in 1980 by Norman Levy, Wadsworth Pits, and Wendy Chun. The name is a play on</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as a toolkit for research and development. It is not a 'killer app' that necessarily becomes a tool' and therefore cannot replace traditional reporting skills, but research-based documentation is needed in order to enable the collective imagination to work together in creative ways. The research and development stages may require an individual to lead teams and coordinate, but in the end it is the collective imagination that creates change. 	Another toolkit for research and development may be community art. Community Arts is a term used to describe practices that draw on the collective talents of artists, educators, community organisers and others to address a specific set of issues or challenges. For example, Community Arts New York (CA20) is a multidisciplinary project that was started in 2015 by artist Tania Bruguera and her team at Museums in Harlem. The project is centred around three new art institutions being established in Brooklyn and New Jersey: Chi-Ri</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as a toolkit to analyse, document and annotate resistance activities. It is a tool for collaboration not a project manager’s office. 	[1] Resistance is a multifaceted and ever-present narrative in the art and culture of the United States and around the world, often framed as a civil rights movement. It is often used as a political tool by white liberal democratic states to delegitimize or negate movements for social change and social inclusion. It is not always explicitly stated why a narrative of resistance is desirable, but the assumption is that it is to protect against change and ensure continuity. 	[2] See Resisting Architecture: Art, Law and the Architecture of Anti-Fascist Resistance (New York: New Press, 2017), for an overview of the field. 	[3] 'Tis the season to be up-cycled, in the words of the song.  	[4] 'Tis the season</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as a reportage tool. 	CA20’s research and development process began in 2011 with the primary mission to explore alternative cultural approaches to the economic and political systems that foster inequality and environmental destruction in the world. The next phase, titled ‘Politics of Art’, sought to understand the role artists can and cannot play in resisting systemic economic and political changes that are being made in the world through progressive legislation and policy. The project’s social purpose, made explicit in the name of the toolkit, is to enable artists to play a role in creating social change through their art. 	Ansible was developed in response to the proliferation of ­digital art products and platforms, which increasingly relied on the urban environment as the basis for their aesthetic value and ethical considerations. The proliferation of data-mining operations and social-media platforms, which allowed for the rapid sharing of ideas and data, created opportunities for the automation of labour and the hijacking of urban environments for private profit</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as a catalyst for change within the Midway Arts community. 	CA20’s Research &amp; Documentation session at Midway Arts was led by Rami El Samahy and Manal El Samahy. The project was supported by the New York Scholastic A and T Company, Holland &amp; Holland, and the Hudson River Project, New York City Department of Education. 	Information on the Midway Arts project and the project’s annotated version of CA20’s Research &amp; Documentation was provided by the New York Arts Council. 	Notes and diagrams on the Midway Arts project and annotated version of Research &amp; Documentation were provided by the artist Mouadem Sherif. 	The annotated version of Research &amp; Documentation was annotated by Sherif with data from the Community Arts New York (CA20) project and PAH-1 (Protector of public Education) health</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as a toolkit for research and documentation. 	The ansible script is a powerful toolkit enabling the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is an extension of the researcher’s toolkit, specifically designed to engage and empower researchers and enable their work across disciplines and platforms. Researchers can adopt the approach and deploy the toolkit across disciplines and platforms, gathering information across borders, cultures, regions, industries and nation’s borders to understand systemic issues or uncover hidden agendas. The ansible module is a command-line interface for analysis, creation and implementation of resistance technologies. It enables researchers to collect, collate, annotate, and synthesize data across borders, cultures, regions, industries and nations in real-time to understand the political, social and economic conditions of resistance. 	A toolkit enables researchers to collect, collate, annotate, and synthesize data across borders, cultures, regions, industries and nations in real-time to understand the political,</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as a support tool for project-based research and development. 	Solving the puzzle of Midway City, New York based artist Persian R. M. Khan presents his project  	Inhabitant, a three-quarter apparition installation for the Grand Concourse at JFK Airport, where he documents his experiences as an Alien during the 1990s, the origins of his work and the legacy of US imperialism. The project was inspired by the book American Graffiti by Scott Alters and the artist Susanne Sundblad, with additional texts by Guillermo Vitale and Meehan Crist. Placed in the city, the installation is a repeated point of departure for travellers approaching from other cities. It is a point of transition from the transient to the permanent, a point of arrival where traffic is generated and a point of departure where traffic is transmitted again and again. Placed in the</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation with investments expected to grow. 	‘I am interested in how the community feels about the project and the way in which it relates to their city’s cultural landscape. I am also interested in how the city and the community can work together to achieve the same goals. Working with Community Arts New York (CA20), Vision New York (NY20), a multi-disciplinary creative team is developing a master plan for the future of Midwood High’s Midway Arts district. The plan is a starting point for further research and development with a view to unlocking additional funding. 	Ansible is a UNIX toolkit for the analysis, creation and implementation of resistance processes. It is used to analyse and document resistance activities and to annotate Community Arts New York (CA20) documents to create a multi-media archive containing images, texts and data relevant to the project’s cultural context. Ansible was designed to be used independently and as a toolkit to analyse trends and monitor developments in resistance. The release of Ansible 6.x on 1 January 2015 represented a significant advancement for the project and new challenges for the researchers and artists working with it. The release also coincided with the one-year anniversary of the uprising in Midwood, New York City. The name ‘Midway United’ quickly became synonymous with the uprising and the project was re-branded as ‘Midway Art Project’ and incorporated into the project’s mission statement. New media was introduced as a tool for the resistance and the capture of narratives. As a result, the corporate media and their politicians found a way to warp and miss opportunities to intervene and shape events in ways designed to inflict damage on the interests of the state. 	In an attempt to accommodate as many different media types and formats as possible, Midway United chose to publish research reports online. This made it easier for researchers to find the documents they</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1
    <text>present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyti_2009112511465744.html?excerpt=us_nyti_2009112511465744.html?excerpt=us_nyti_2009112511465744.html#ixzz3LhTl8LSdTxNlc2Nlc3Ntc3Ntb3NTMy5MjE0MzAyMmE0Mjc5MzEyMmE0NzE0MmE0MmE0NzQwMjE0NmE0MmE0NyYzE0NmE0NzQwNmE0NzE2NmE0MmE0NnNmE0NmE0NnNhY3JkYmNjI2MmE0NnNmE0NnNmE0Nn</text>
    <text>present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_2009112920041_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_2009112920041_pagina1?excerpt=http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latino-pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_2009112920041_pagina1?excerpt=http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latino-pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_2009112920041_pagina1?excerpt=http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics</text>
    <text>present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_200911202296._thumb%3A0%26excerpt%3Dhttp://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21locten.html?excerpt=us_politico_200911202296._thumb%3A0%26excerpt%3Dhttp://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21lebanon.html?excerpt=us_politico_200911202296._thumb%3A0%26excerpt%3Dhttp://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21satan-plant.html?excerpt=us_politico_2009112022962_thumb%3A0%26excerpt%3Dhttp://www.nytimes.com/2001/</text>
    <text>present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_20011221_cnn?excerpt=us_news_20091121122296_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20011221_nyt_2009112122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_2009112122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_20011221_nyt_2009112122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_2009112122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_20011221_nyt_2009112122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_20011221_nyt_2009112122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_20011221_nyt_2009112</text>
    <text>present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_2009112111934881_2009112100193488_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_200911211194649_200911211194649_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_200911211194649_200911211194649_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_200911211194649_200911211194649_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_200911211194649_200911211194649_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_201001011011010001_pagina1?excerpt=us_trainery_2010110110100019_pagina1?excerpt=us_trainery_2010110110100019_pagina1</text>
    <text>present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_20091120213040_pagina1?excerpt=us_new_york_times_20040119_soap_opera?excerpt=us_new_york_times_20040119_nyt_pl?excerpt=us_new_york_times_20040119_wp_pl?excerpt=us_nytimes_20091120213040_pagina1?excerpt=us_new_york_times_20040119_wp_pl?excerpt=us_nytimes_20091120213040_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_20091120213040_pagina1?excerpt=us_new_york_times_20091120213040_nyt_pl?excerpt=us_new_york_times_</text>
    <text>present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091</text>
    <text>present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_news_20091129180715_pagina1?excerpt=USAToday&amp;excerpt=USATodayNews&amp;excerpt=USATodayNewsNews http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/22/us/politics/22latinopoli.html?excerpt=USAToday&amp;excerpt=USATodayNewsNewsNew York Times, 8 April 2002. Photo courtesy of the New York Public Library.PreviousNextNew York Times, 8 April 2002. Photo courtesy of the New York Public Library.Silvio Berlusconi’s idea of a biennale is a version of what he calls a ‘biennale’ that appeared in the early twentieth century in Paris and London. It is a kind of ‘double blind buying’ that recognises both buyer and seller without a prior knowledge of each other. In modern biennials, the marketer and</text>
    <text>present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_2009112020041192_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_2009112020041192_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_200911202130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_200911202130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_200911202130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_2009112020041192_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_200911202130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_201001105100000_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_200911202130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nytimes_200911202130_pagina1?excerpt=us_ny</text>
    <text>present an online project that catalysed the construction of a new island for the London-based Transfield Holdings, which is both the former name of a naval air station and the name of a company that provides cover for illegal maritime traffic. The new island was designed to house both large and small fishing boats, according to a report in the New York Times on the project in 2001. The proposed new international airport would have doubled the city's runway, and would have doubled the city’s fishing port, with a heliport on the island’s west coast accessible by sea or air. The project was given the go-ahead by the then mayor, Boris Johnson.Sources: http://www.nytimes.com/2001/04/21/us/politics/21latinosx.html?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_2009112111914081_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_2009112111914081_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_200911211194604_pagina1?excerpt=us_politico_20011021-2?excerpt=us_nyt_20011021-2?excerpt=us_nyt_20091121122130_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_200911211194604_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_200911211194604_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_2009112111914081_pagina1?excerpt=us_nyt_20011021-2?excerpt=us_nyt_20011021</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not
    <text>present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not Money’. The art project sought to reconcile the political and the economic by turning the political into the neither-political-nor-economic-understood-as-a-public-place. By doing so, it sought to reconcile two worlds: the political, and the economic, and the mundane into something more interesting and powerful. The political is reduced to the city’s infrastructures, the economic to the city’s ­urban infrastructures. The economic is reduced to the infrastructures of the city, with the city’s infrastructures partaking in the production of the new urban infrastructure. The political is accentuated when it involves people, and the political not only as a public but also as an inhabitant of a city. The city is becoming not just another place, but something more. This essay, and the accompanying video, are testimonies to this process. Their aim is to show the politics of place, and how</text>
    <text>present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not of this World’ that was installed in several locations around the airport. The project received financial support from the British Council and the partnership between the city and the firm that built it was extended through a financial sponsorship from the NYC Museum and the partnership between the museum and the Cabrini Gallery. This partnership has grown into a multi-million pound business.The partnership between the museum and the Cabrini–New York City Council Member for District One, David Miller, also offers insight into the future of the site. In 2015, the Cabrini–New York City Council unanimously rezoned the site of the airport, making it an Official Space. This decision came amid concerns about traffic and noise and the potential loss of natural features, such as the Brooklyn Bridge and the Statue of Liberty, that make the city ‘unique’ and stand out from the countryside. The rezoning also came amid a major redesign campaign by the city and its developer, the Port Authority, led by</text>
    <text>present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not of this World’ hosted by the New York–based firm W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The project was designed to be shared and operated as a way to demonstrate the possibilities of developing a city together. The firm’s principal, D.D. Horton, is a former Vorticist who is now an advisor to the Mayor of London. The project was also co-organised by the New York–based architectural firm W.D. Horton &amp; Co. and the New York–based Museum of Modern Art. The latter is a museum institution with a permanent exhibition – its first major work for the institution. It was also co-curated by Boris Groys and Anton Chekhov, with contributions from Johnson, Ruble, Sanders, Pete, Ken and Noel. The project was supported by the UK’s Innovative Startups Grant, as well as the commission of Doctorow Prize for Art and Architecture.    	The position of Vort</text>
    <text>present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not of this World’. The group’s project was also featured in the film Beautiful Cities: Towing and Other Failures of Modern European Cities. The film, which stars Tom Hardy as an airport security guard who enlists the help of a mysterious alien species, was written and directed by Ridley Scott. It is the true story of a man called Ken Russell (Tom Cruise), a character based on real-life airport security guard Rick Mumaw (played by Laurence Fishburne), who is sent to the planet Cabrini–New York in an attempt to rescue his wife and son. Russell is assisted by a female alien named Elizabeth Shaw (Johanna Kruger), who is played by Amy Adams. Russell is also aided by a group of other aliens called the ‘Harmonia’, who are all portrayed as being far more sinister and threatening than the guards were.Suddenly, things are not so rosy in the city. A series of vicious alien attacks</text>
    <text>present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not of this World’. The project was also supported by a grant from the European Commission and the UK’s National Audit Office. The next stage in the project is for the architectural firm to carry out an initial design competition for the project, which should take place in early 2017. The winning firm will receive a further two years to carry out an implementation plan, which should be finished by then.  The tenor of the project has shifted from the explicit to the implicit as a consequence of the media coverage. The explicit intention of the project was to produce a public realm in which people can ‘express themselves’; the implicit is a realisation that people are more free to inhabit the project’s planned cityscape. The development of an implicit but real sense of freedom through open-ended activities like these is a projective practice, and the logic of the project is that freedom maximises itself.  The tenor of the project has shifted from the explicit to the implicit</text>
    <text>present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not of this World’. The project sought to reconcile the two worlds by turning the city into a virtual laboratory for future designs. The artwork was designed to be displayed in virtually any building in the city, regardless of its type, size, or function. By combining the aesthetics of a traditional public gallery with the functionality of an online gallery, the essay’s structural integrity was assured. The project was conceived as a ‘curatorial intervention’ in an already historically significant area of the city. It was designed to be a catalyst for further conversation and debate, while enabling the engaged audience to shape the future of the city through their actions. The project was curated by Harold Bloom, Curator of Public Art at the New Museum, and Harold Ross, Curator of Entomology at the Brooklyn Museum. It was presented in conjunction with the Biennale of Modern Art, New York, which began in April 2015.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor</text>
    <text>present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not Airport’. The project’s themes were expanded upon in the film ‘Capital of Culture’ that followed the project’s publication. The film examines the relationship between the city and the port, and how the city can be used to support a new type of cultural tourism. New York’s Port of Manhattan Island is the largest remaining ocean of its kind, and its infrastructure provides links to other parts of the world through which significant amounts of oil are transported. For this reason, the Port is frequently cited as an example of what not to do with New York; indeed, a 2015 report commissioned by the Port and its management seemed to signal an end to this policy of neutrality.16 The Port is not the only port in the world with significant amounts of oil and gas resources, but they are the dominant ones, and their continued operation is a necessity for the continued prosperity of the global economy. In fact, as recently as 2007, the Port was reported to be facing</text>
    <text>present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not of this World’. The project’s website describes the project as a ‘time-consuming but important first step in a long-term project that will enable the firm to make a difference in the world through the development of a public realm in Cabrini–New York’s Hudson Yards'. The art project was developed by the firm, with support from the New York City Council and the Fund for Cultural Studies at Columbia University. The Council members who approved the project were Council Member for Manhattan Borough President Gale A. Brewer (D), Council Member for Staten Island Borough President Eric Adams (D), and Council Member for District One Council Member Brad Lander (D). Council Members Delcy Barnes (D–C), Daniel Dromm (D–Ward 8), Laurie Cumming (D–Ward 8), Harold Levy (D–Ward 8), Peter Forman (D–Ward 8), Eric Johnson (D–Ward 8), Gale Brewer (D), Daniel Drom</text>
    <text>present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not Money’, which sought to reconcile the political and the economic in favour of a more ‘humanistic’ consideration of the city. The project was supported by the London Borough of Tower Hamlets and the London Foundation for Art and Design. The firm that built the airport also provided valuable insight into the development of the city during the 1980s and 1990s. Its acquisition by Airports UK in 1995 opened new avenues for cultural and commercial activities in the borough. The acquisition of TSS Lewis &amp; Baxley by Airports UK in 1997 ushered in a new era of cultural tourism and the establishment of an entirely new business model for the borough’s tourism board. 	[i] The full text of the letter is available at https://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2018/11/18/better-know-london/[ii] available at http://www.forbes.com/sites/ben</text>
    <text>present an online project with the stated aim of inviting readers to design the future of Cabrini–New York, using the city as a case study. The online project was spearheaded by Cabrini–New York City Council Member José María Aznar (I). The submissions were received in early 2015 and allowed for commenting prior to publication. The comments linked to a 45,000+ word essay that described the challenges facing the community in Cabrini–New York and how the city could be transformed through such a design process. The essay was written in collaboration with the architectural firm of W.D. Horton &amp; Co. The firm is best known for its project for the City, which was also published in the New York Times and London’s The Guardian. The partnership between the city and the firm that built the London Heathrow Airport also offers insight into new business opportunities for both firms. The essay was shared with the public via a public art project called ‘Towards a City that is Not of this World’ that the artist and her team created. The project, which was partially funded by the British Council and part by the Swiss Development Company (SDN), sought to reconcile the opposing forces of international and local tourism by decommissioning an airport that now serves as a meeting venue for art, culture, sports, festivals, and, increasingly, a financial centre for the city. The essay served as the basis for an even larger project, published in May’s New York Times and September’s Guardian, that sought to reconcile the opposing strands of global tourism by creating a ‘world’ within the airport itself. Both projects were part of ‘Postmodern Culture: Cities of Disruption’, a symposium organised by the American Council on Global Architecture (ACGA) and published in November 2014. Like their counterparts in London and New York, the inhabitants of Cabrini, Asmadiya and elsewhere in Europe, the inhabitants of the Å</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[5] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[6] Johnstone, John. Inhabitant, The Penguin Random House, London, 2011. Pp. ?&quot;Inhabitant’, Penguin Random House, London, 2011. Pp. ?&quot;Inhabitant’, The New Yorker, New Yorker, October 29, 2005. Pp. ?&quot;Inhabitant’, New York Times, New Yorker, October 29, 2005. Pp. ?&quot;Inhabitant’, The New Yorker, New Yorker, January 6, 2006. Pp. ?&quot;Inhabitant’, The New Yorker, New Yorker, January 6, 2006. Pp. ?&quot;Inhabitant’, The New Yorker, New Yorker, January 13, 2006. Pp. ?&quot;Inhabitant’, The New Yorker, New</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[5] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[6] http://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[7]  John L. Stewart, ‘On the Use of Symbols in Social Work and Art’ (2012), in Stewart, L. (ed.), The New Yorker, Vol. 256, No. 1, Spring, 2012, pp.1–45.[8] See, for example, Elizabeth A. Herman and Susanne Craig, ‘Embedded Cognitions: Media, Media, and Symbols’ (2009).[9] See, for example, Graham J. Anderson, ‘On Media, Media, and Social Change’, in Social Work (ed.), The New Media Reader, Vol. 14, No. 1, The MIT Press, Boston and Portland</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[5] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[6] http://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[7] See http://creativetimes.co.uk/2017/10/the-new-englands-edition/[8] For further information, see http://creativetimes.co.uk/2017/10/the-new-englands-edition/[9] and http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/earth/earthnews/earth-2...[10] http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/earth/earthnews/earth-2...[11] http://www.thesun.co.uk/sol/earth/earthnews/earth-2...[12] </text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[5] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[6] Povinelli, Art as an Asset. Transactional Behaviour, Vol. 29, No.1, November, 2009, p.119.Download this article as PDFPovinelli, Art as an Asset. Transactional Behaviour, Vol. 29, No. 1, November, 2009, p.119.Download this article as PDFPovinelli, Art as an Asset. Transactional Behaviour, Vol. 29, No. 1, November, 2009, p.119.Download this article as PDFJohn StoneOne of the artists working on the Liverpool Biennial is John Stone, whose work for Liverpool Biennial 2009 was part of the Tate Modern Preview Programme. Stone has a particular interest in the relationship between art and science. He developed a project in 2009 called ‘The Stone’</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[5] http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[6] http://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[7] http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[8] See, for example, Kit Lopéz de la Torre, ‘Common Ground: Understanding and Compassion for Animals’ (2014), at: https://www.biennial.com/</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[5] http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[6] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[7] http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[8] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[9] http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[5] http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[6] Ray Bradbury, 1984, American Gods, p. 104.Download this article as PDFRay BradburyRay Bradbury is a New York-based writer, critic, and stage actor. He is the author of several books including the New York Times best-sellers The Martian Chronicles and On Writing, among others. He has written on a wide range of subjects including the environment, surveillance, and terrorism for publications including Wired, The Washington Post, New York Times best-sellers On War and Secrecy, among others. He has taught at Columbia University, The New School, and The Berkley Film &amp; Television Festival. His articles have been</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[5] John Stone, One of the Toys in the Box: Making and Unmaking the Consumer – part 1 and part 2 at creativetime.com [6] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[7] John Stone, One of the Toys in the Box: Making and Unmaking the Consumer – part 3 at creativetime.com[8] Bert Beutler, “The Art of Not Being Governed: Participatory Public Art as a System”, in Creative Time Winter 2004, p.20.[9] Beutler, “The Art of Not Being Governed: Participatory Public Art as a System”, p.21.[10] Beutler, “The Art of Not Being Governed: Participatory Public Art as a Platform”, p.21.[11</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[5] http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-industrial-re-prox-il-antin-214829.html#[6] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[7] http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-ling-album-2010-...[8] Exhibit 1011. The Thornley Art Gallery, 2014, p.10. See also Exhibitions 2013 and 2014 at Thornley, 2014. [9] Exhibit 1011 (Open School Art, 2014). [10] Exhibit 1011 (Open School Art, 2014). [11] Exhibit 1011 (Open School Art, 2014</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, an organisation founded in 1980 by the Bakersery Owners Cooperative Board and the Dolphin Arts Centre.  [1] http://www.instructables.com/id/1372/the-dolphin-art-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[2] See, for example, http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/circles/en/3542/the-dolphin-re-produce-industry-2010-12-30-london-20x25-kirby-street-214829.html#[3] https://www.creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[4] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[5] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[6] https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_teen_art_projects_in_the_world_20x25_april_2009_...[7] http://creativetime.com/gallery/john-stone-one-of-th...[8] The London Zoo was founded in 1848 and is the oldest continuously operating zoo in the world. The London Zoo is an internationally renowned zoonotic institution with a long-standing partnership with the British Museum, having been established in 1867. The Zoo has exhibited more than 4,000 animals from more than 200 species, and has exhibited more than 200,000 specimens across its 71 natural and 37 zoonotic parks and enclosures.[9] Barnard, Steven. Zoonotic Threats to Publics: Z</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future
    <text>present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future City: The Architecture Biennale 2018 in partnership with American University, St Petersburg. Photo: Natalia Zinetskaya.PreviousNextThe Biennale was organized in phases, with the first exhibition in New York and Washington, DC, in 2015, followed by exhibitions in Berlin, Taipei, Shanghai, and Los Angeles. In 2016, the Biennale in Istanbul and Venice combined exhibitions with virtual private island (sand) courses, landscape architecture, and citizen journalism to form a new kind of urban experience. In 2017, the Biennale in Sydney assembled artists from all over the globe, including artists from every continent, who created a ‘golden age’ of urban exploration and design in their hometowns. And in 2018, the Biennale in Berlin combined art from multiple disciplines, including architecture, urban history, urban forms, and urbanism.  The idea that the biennale is both an art form and a marketplace emerged in the</text>
    <text>present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future City was co-curated by Svetlana Boym, Professor of Urban Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Elizabeth Weise, Curator for Public Programs at the American Museum of Natural History in New York. The symposium was co-curated by Gennady Kaprow, Professor of Urban Studies at American University in St Petersburg, and Tatiana Kosygin, Curator of Exhibitions and Tractors at the American Museum of Natural History in New York. The symposium, which was co-curated by Gennady Kaprow, was delivered by Kaprow and Weise. Gennady Kaprow, Professor of Urban Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, presented ‘Geopolitics of Urban Space: Policy, Culture and Politics of Suburban Spaces’ at the symposium. The topic of the symposium was the influence of technologist thinking, urbanisation programmes and new media technologies on the contemporary condition. Kaprow</text>
    <text>present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future City was co-founded by Sobchak and Chernenko with Artur Sobchak Assistant Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the University of St Petersburg, and reporter for the Russian Cultural Archive.All photos courtesy of the American Cultural Association, St Petersburg.PreviousNextAll photos courtesy of the American Cultural Association, St Petersburg.Information captured during the research project ‘Future City: The Architecture Biennale’ is displayed at the American Cultural Association’s exhibition archive, St Petersburg, Russia, 11 October 2018.PreviousNextInformation captured during the research project ‘Future City: The Architecture Biennale’ is displayed at the American Cultural Association’s exhibition archive, St Petersburg, Russia, 11 October 2018. [1] The Biennale website. [2] The New York Times, 15 November 2016. [3] Gareth White, ‘Urban Future: What Are We Being Siloed Into’, in Planning and Material Culture,</text>
    <text>present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future City was co-curated by Norman Eisen, Professor of the Practice of Urban and Regional Planning at the American University in St Petersburg, and Andrei Leshchinsky, Professor of Geography at the American University in St Petersburg. Norman Eisen and colleagues have conducted extensive research in St Petersburg, and have published several books on the Biennale, including the recently published ‘Urban Crisis: Russia’s Cities and Continents’ (Harvard University Press, 2018). Andrei Leshchinsky and colleagues have just published an issue of Pravda, the Russian journal of the Turin Triennale, one of the most comprehensive and current registers of international publishing in the world, on the topic ‘Architecture &amp; Development: Russia’s New Cities’. These publications, and the symposium they hosted, bring to life the current political, economic and architectural journals and the biennale’s traditional location in the Russian capital.</text>
    <text>present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future City: The Architecture Biennale was co-curated by Jeffrey Meyers and Josephine Machon at the New Museum in New York and Dont Rhine at Tate Modern in London. Other co-curators were also part of the team: Valery Spiridonov, Professor of Russian Culture and Politics at Columbia University, and Anatoli Papadimitriou, Assistant Professor at the University of Calgary, Canada, and fellow at the American University in St Petersburg.The symposium was curated in partnership by Donna Haraway, Curator of Entomology Collection, New Museum, New York, USA; Geoffrey Maxfield, Curator of Entomology Collections, National Museums Liverpool, UK; and Ted Sickert, Curator of Entomology Collections, Tate Modern, London.PreviousNextThe symposium was curated in partnership by Donna Haraway, Curator of Entomology Collection, New Museum, New York, USA; Geoffrey Maxfield, Curator of Entom</text>
    <text>present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future City is a multi-disciplinary, multi-use site that engages with the socio-political aspects of the biennale, producing results both for the Russian Federation and for the world at large through its production of awareness, fascination, and analysis. Its production of awareness, fascination, and analysis is itself a product of its engagement with the Russian contemporary. In this sense, it is also concerned with other cultural forms and subcultures outside of Russia. The site, its activities, and their productions speak to the connections between contemporaneity and its temporalised forms (of capitalism and culture). As such, it is an ideal place to develop, anchor, and anchor future curatorial projects in, and through, the contemporary contemporary contemporaneity that results from the disruption of the classic, present, and future curatorial approaches to art, aesthetics, and cultural history in the twenty-first century. 	[i] See, for example, Susanne Kugler,  	Creative</text>
    <text>present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future City was selected through an open call focused on ‘the future urban space’. It was proposed that the symposium might begin with a brief ‘review of the past urban spaces’ and ‘promote the possibilities of the future urban space’. This resolution was adopted at the October 2018 assembly of the Russian Cultural Centre in St Petersburg. The symposium was curated by Maxim Filipov, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at Columbia University in New York, and Marina Fokidis, Curator for the New Artistic Park of St Petersburg, Russia. It was presented by Zoya Galloway, Curator of Works, and was co-curated by Marta Hlavajova, Curator of Public Programs and Exhibitionary Branch of the Russian Cultural Centre in St Petersburg. The symposium was presented in conjunction with the Russia/US Graduate School of Arts and Culture, University of California, Riverside, and the Russian Cultural Centre in New York. The symposium was co</text>
    <text>present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future City was co-curated by Corinna Till and Byulad Chowdhury. The symposium took place in partnership with the American University (AU) Museum of Modern Art and the American Museum of Natural History. 	[i] See www.futurecity.org/. Download this article as PDFCorinna TillCorinna Till is Professor of Geography and Head of the Department of Global Studies and Geography at the American University in St Petersburg. Her research interests include the socio-political construction of urbanization in the aftermath of the post-1990 crises in advanced capitalist nations; the geopolitics of international economic exchange and the environment; and the integration of infrastructure and urban development within globalized capitalist narratives. Her publications include the forthcoming book Real Institutions: The Structural Turnaround of Post-Keynesian Currencies (2017) and the new book Real Institutions: Global Currencies for a Post-Industrial Society (2018). She is also editor of the forthcoming</text>
    <text>present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is the only international co-commissioned project of the American artist Rodney Correia. He is the curator of the New York and London Museums Series, the curator of the Russian Cultural Exchange and the curator of the Russian Cultural Centre, St Petersburg. He has curATED several exhibitions in the US and Europe, including the 2014 Venice Biennale, which was composed of a major public programme of public art, public sculpture and public architecture, as well as a private curatorial programme that includes the private curatorial programme for the American antiquities programme, the American cultural programme and the Italian cultural exchange. He is the editor of Artas Agrarianas por el Mundo del CIMBA (Together Two Ages: The Architecture and Urban-Planning Biennale), the first issue of which was published in 1987. Future City: The Architecture Biennale2016. Photo courtesy of the Art Foundation.PreviousNextFuture City: The Architecture Bi</text>
    <text>present an online project that brought together artists, curators, designers, journalists and others with diverse experience and expertise in a global dialogue about the contemporary urban situation in order to identify themes and suggest solutions. This online symposium was part of Future City: The Architecture Biennale’s ‘Future City 2020’ project, which was initiated in 2015 and designed to be integrated into the biennale’s regular programme of activities throughout the globe. Future City: The Architecture Biennale is an independent, non-profit organisation formed in St Petersburg, Russia, on 11 and 12 August 2018. It is funded by the Russian Federation’s Academy of Sciences, the Russian Federation’s Overseas Territory, and the Russian Federation’s Natural Heritage Fund. The project was co-founded by Artur Sobchak, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg, and Sergei Chernenko, Professor of Russian Cultural Studies at the American University in St Petersburg. Future City: The Architecture Biennale 2018 in collaboration with the American University and the Russian Cultural Centre in St Petersburg. 	[1] Kazakhstan, Kazakhstan, and Iran are the only countries with official representations of the Sto in their official languages. See: http://www.stoeurope.org/en/. [2] The Sto was a Roman Stoic philosopher, writer and mathematician. His work deals with the nature of suffering and the nature of immortality. See: Kazakhstan Archaeological Museum, Shiraz Museum of Art and Science, Kyrgyzstan. [3] Sloan, George. Culture and Anarchy in Ancient Rome. Boston: Beacon Press, 1950. [4] Ovid, Metamorphoses. Trans. Alan Bass. New York: Penguin, 1965. [5] Pliny, Naturalis historia. Vol. 24, Part 2. 2.1.2–27. [</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The Bursary Foundation’s Russian cultural missions account for over 90% of the country’s cultural tourism revenues.3  The Russian cultural sector represents a particularly bright spot in a market that is increasingly marked by closures, price rises and disruptive mergers. The largest number of tourists visiting the Russian cultural sites in 2016 was due to the fact that many of the most visited sites closed permanently due to budget cuts, while museums and art galleries across the country were closed due to financial constraints. This has undoubtedly affected the quality and quantity of the cultural experiences available to visitors, who are now more likely to be drawn by bargain tours and cultural-specific experiences.4 The Russian cultural sector is an important market for art and art products made in Russia, and the products are sold primarily in Europe. The main market for these products in Russia is North America, but the Eurasian region includes a significant market share in the Middle East and North Africa. A decline in exchange rates and the associated fall in</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The potential for commercial exploitation of a potential future museum audience is obvious, and the risk of cultural alienation is real. The increasing number of tourists and the high rate of exchange between cities and the vast expanse of the country means that the biennial is a frequent target of both domestic and international critics. Critics tend to focus on the city as a landscape barren of life, but also of art and culture.3  The biennial is a culturally specific type of cultural product, and the city is a fundamental location for the production of ideas, concepts and representations of a particular kind. The city is a site of exchange between cultures, and its emergence as a cultural product – a highly stylised image that many visitors have – is a fundamental event in the history of that culture.4 The biennial as cultural product is culturally specific, and is thus expected to proliferate in all aspects of the cultural life of the country. While the city does have significant cultural attractions, such as the massive, screen-</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The 2015 Moscow Biennale sold out almost immediately, and the 2016 Istanbul Biennale was even more wildly over-subscribed than the first two; the latter reported a loss of nearly 6 billion Russian Rubles ($1.5 billion).3 The main reason for the rapidity with which these exhibitions sold out is that the Russian government, in 2014, massively increased its budget for cultural consumption.4 This marked a sharp increase from the $500 million allocated for the 2018 Venice Biennale, which was to be staged in a former Polish military museum. The Russian government’s heavy industry of cultural consumption is testament to the fact that, unlike in most other parts of the world, a nation remains economically dependent on its citizenry for the production of a given mass of artefacts. Art and biennials – which became more accessible and more profitable the more they were exhibited – became more widely distributed and particularised, and the biennial itself became less and less globally identifiable. Art and bi</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The sheer volume and variety of objects imported – contemporary art, dance, and modelling is a good example – is a significant part of the market.3  Importing works from abroad is not only a way to make the goods in those works more real, but also a way to add value to the products as artefacts of the past. The importance of this last addition cannot be understated. As the photographer Christov Hroxányi notes, ‘Material objects, even when they represent past events in a conceptual or historical way, can also serve as a marker or point of departure for the future behaviour of a people, or a specific place or situation.’4 The Hoothayev family, for example, settled in St Petersburg after immersing themselves in the local arts scene. On arrival, the patriarch found a copy of the Ten Commandments on the bookshelf, and the rest, as they say, is history. Stately miniatures of the prophet Elijah</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The market for art products in Russia is worth roughly ten times as much as the US market, with artists alone accounting for another 200 million tourists to Russia each year.3 Art and biennials are products of a specific historical and urban context – the biennial was originally an exhibitionary form – and so their products are artefacts of a particular historical moment in time.  Barnes &amp; Nobles, The Biennial Condition: On Its Growth and Consequences, p.8. HM Nevin, The Archetypes of Biennials, Pinter, New York, 1989, p.12.Barnes &amp; Noble, The Biennial Condition, p.8.The Biennial Exhibition, the public ‘return to the museum’, is a particular form of cultural consumption in which artefacts are returned to the museum or given to favoured collectors. It began in London in 1887 and ran in forty-five cities across Europe and North America from its first organized in Liverpool, England</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The value of a museum visiting in the Russian Federation is worth more than the value of a museum admission.3  And, as a consequence, museums are particularly effective in shifting consumer behaviour.4  The main reason for this power differential is that visitors spend more time in museums and have a higher quality of cultural experience in museums. If the power to tax cultural resources is removed from the federal government, then the only resources available to the state are those resources dedicated to supporting its administrative apparatus, which means that the museum sector is particularly vulnerable to changing consumer behaviour. The biennial is the largest form of cultural product in the country, and it is this form that is visited, experienced, studied, commented upon and critiqued on. Its ubiquity and global visibility make it a highly visible object of cultural consumption, and its value to the society at large is a myth. At the same time, it is a very different kind of cultural product, one that is constantly being reinvented and re</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The significance of this in the twenty-first century is obvious: the object of so-called national cultural products (often marketed as Russian art) is displayed at the largest museum in Moscow, alongside works from the American art institution Modern Painters Union, as well as at the museum of modern art in St Petersburg.3 Many artists who work in Russia are artists in their own right, and their works display a particular brand of Russian art that is recognisable across the country.4  The main reason for this is that artists are people, and their works sell products not just within Russia, but also across the range of Russian goods and values. The Russian market is a complex system that organises vast amounts of data – rich with data about products, people, places – and it is this information that is sold to organisations such as the Russian museums, which in turn, commission artists to work in Russia with messages about the country in which they reside. This is a feature of the almost universal booking of</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The rapid expansion of the Russian cultural sector during the 1990s and 2000s was closely followed by a corresponding exponential growth of the country’s cultural sector, which many contemporary artists and curators were quick to adopt and to call ‘the Russian dream’.3  The Russian dream is a fantasy. The reality is more like what many of us lived through in the 1990s and early 2000s: it is no longer a fantasy, but a very real and present part of the country. Even the most optimistic artist today would have to admit to disliking the mass of people, crowds, cars, crowds of people, noise, pollution, mountains, un-built towns, and cities that make up the Russian dream.4  So the popularity of Russian art and arts today largely reflects on the person or group of people represented by the art and the biennial. Art today often acts as a buffer or a displacement against the unpredictable and crowded real life and traffic in Russia, or</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The growth of the Russian cultural sector in the 1990s and 2000s was fueled by two factors: (a) the expansion of state-sponsored museums, which increased accessibility and commercial opportunities for artists and their projects, and (b) the development of alternative cultural tourism, which promoted ‘hard core’ travellers. The popularity of Russian art, especially modern and contemporary art, is a reflection of both (re)production and consumption, as distinct from (re)allocation and exhibition) culture. There is no doubt that in an increasingly information-intensive society, the biennial is a rarefaction with many market-based elements, yet it retains a highly visible and distinctive role. How to Know About a Biennial (I) its Content and Characteristics, (II) Its Production and (III) Its Future Prospects 	The biennial is an exhibitionary form that began in 1972 as a mass-market venue for artists and curators to show their work and develop a rapport</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant that the fixation on art and aesthetics has receded to the present, but the fixation on the city and its infrastructure and infrastructure […] remains. The biennial is the contemporary incarnation of the historical biennial, and the twenty-first century is the century of the biennial. The biennial is the most widely studied and consumed type of cultural exhibit, both for the art and the biennial audiences. In Russia, the biennial market value form its largest and most widely represented market: the former is dominated by the Russian Museum, and the latter is represented by the Bursary Foundation. Russian museums alone catalogue over 20 million artefacts, of which over one-third are sculpture collections.1 The popularity of Russian art and biennials is a good indication of the enormous amounts of cultural extraction that take place in Russia.2  The museum sector is the largest single market for a country’s cultural products, and the largest single consumer of cultural products in a country. The status of the artist, artist, and curator remains a symbol of power and influence in a country with a highly visible art market and a significant cultural media market. In a country where the status of the artist, artist, and curator is significantly influenced by where they are located, it is unsurprising that the cultural resources of a city or a region are generally restricted to a particular elite: the status of the Russian artist, the Russian museum, and the Russian vernacular are all located in the capital. The fact that these resources are given away for free or at extremely high prices demonstrates that these cultural institutions are exchanges between citizens at an exceptional level of social and political power. The economic logic of their production, sale, and consumption is almost entirely foreign to that of the people whose cultural products are promoted in the media and in state institutions. 	The biennial is a temporal form that is not confined to the sites of production, distribution, and consumption, but extends into the social and cultural formation</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made through tools (often ad-hoc) that actively search for vulnerabilities in the web server they are hosted on, and will often exploit vulnerabilities on a massive scale. The idea of the home page as a possible site of vulnerability seems to have gained currency only after it had been shown to cause serious problems for websites hosting live streams of football matches, child pornography and other potentially damaging content, and only after it had been shown to be profitable for online hosting companies to commission content from content providers who then exploited the vulnerabilities. Given the on-going debate about the relevance of the web in relation to the promotion of political and social causes, one might ask whether the promotion of the notion of the home page as a site of political and social meaning in the 1990s was in fact a deliberate strategy to delegitimize and disrupt the work of the web in relation to the social aims of the social web. It is clear from the evidence of the development of the social web that the social web was being viewed as</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made deliberately malicious or unreliable, or that the optimisation of the web is often done on an unconscious or phantom level. The search engine does make a mistake in optimising its results, but this does not make the web any less accessible or real – it merely postpones the point where this mistake is made. In fact, the more insidious and real the mistakes made in the web browser, the less accessible and real the real web is to search. The more insidious the mistake, the less accessible and real the real web is to search. This is why optimisation is so important on the web: it allows us to recognise real heterogeneity and real heterogeneity is possible, but also to experience it when it happens. The idea of home page optimization on the web is a product of the 1990s, but it is also the web that emerged in parallel with the social web, and so the parallel is worth exploring. 	[ii] A few years later, in 2004, the social web was upgraded</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made with great fanfare and sometimes intrinsic motivation – such as when searching for ‘ham’ or ‘the Beast’, or ‘home’ in the London Underground. The search engine does have a tendency to produce optimisations that are useful to it in certain situations, but these tend to be small and reversible. 	[ii] Dyson, Charles. Dazzle Book: How the Search for Secret Agents Revealed the Tropics Most Wanted, a Weaponized Version of the Nicorette Building. New York: Simon and Schuster, 1986. p.42.Download this article as PDFJennifer YatesDriven by her passion for design and her desire to see useful objects everywhere, Jennifer Yates has become a full-time poster artist, demonstrator, writer and researcher. She has worked as a designer and researcher in various capacities, including being the project manager for the 2014 Sydney Biennale, the co-curator of the upcoming Fifth Biennale</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made with malicious intentions, and that optimisation on the web is often performed with malicious intentions. The underlying assumption seems to be that the optimised search will find the page with the best possible relevance, and that the web browser should be free from malicious behaviour. However, this seems less possible in the presence of invasive software, which is increasingly being deployed on mobile devices. The presence of such software in the browser is also often used to misrepresent site accessibility, when in fact, the presence of such software is often used to deny access to sites – denying access in turn, fuelling the self-perpetuating spiral of hyper-migration. 	[ii] See: Angie Ling, ‘How I Helped Myself Become an Internet Artist’,  	Basis of a Culture Blog, Issue #4, (2014), and Peter Norvig, ‘The Cathedral and Its Critics’,  	Futures of a</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made with the intention of returning to those same pages, but with the understanding that those same pages will return (whether or not the optimised algorithms ever actually do). The use of such explicit understanding of the web seems to render the intentions of the readers of those pages irrelevant. What matters is that the web page is located somewhere accessible, and that the underlying ideas, practices and geographical locations of the web are well understood. 	[ii] The term ‘basement’ comes from the collection of articles published in The Basement Review in 1972, and is often used to refer to a set of principles governing the behaviour of the user in the context of computer systems. Some of the principles have been elaborated on by subsequent researchers, but the basic idea remains valid. The term ‘basement’ is often used in the context of networked systems, but its precise usage in this context is unclear and controversial. Some advocates of networked social systems see the term as a synonym</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made with malicious intentions, and that optimisation on the part of site administrators is often quite reactive and opportunistic (seeÂ 	Wolitzer &amp; Wollitzer, 2012). The search engine does have a role to play in optimising the web, but it is not as critical as it is for web sites to take part in this process. As a result, there is a current debate about what kinds of forms social networks can take – between those who see social networking as a positive development and others who see it as a dangerous neo-liberal development. Indeed, Wolitzer &amp; Wollitzer (2012) speculate that the proliferation of social networks could well hasten the end of the book – if not in the sense that social networks are already reshaping how people gather, but that they are breaking open new webs and bringing together formerly isolated phenomena into connected systems.][ii] In fact, Wolitzer &amp; Wollitzer (2012) see an end game for the social networks, not</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made using linguistic devices – actions such as ‘a link bait’ and ‘a “load balancer” – which make it easier for a user to fall for such tricks, and harder for sites to detect when a user does not reside in the site or network targeted by the link. This leads to situations where optimised versions of images and links end up on the webpages of sites with which users have conflicting allegiances – fostering the very situation of enmity between the sites. 	[ii] The emergence of new technologies is often cited as a way to explain organisational change. But this is often cited as a justification for the proliferation of new technological solutions – rather than, for instance, organisational change that results from understanding how data is generated, distributed and that affects all of us. In the context of online social networking sites, the emergence of new media and app ecosystems is often cited as a way to explain how the web is interconnected. But this does</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made with the explicit intention of ending up somewhere, whether in a publication or on a news website, where the intended destination is often a self-proclaimed news aggregator or 'killer app' (Google’s definition of the word’s' app stores'). 	[ii] Neulie Stempel, ‘On Maps Online: Social Use of Data’, in 	Open Human Geography, 2015, p.7.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architecture professional. His work in the spatial domain incorporates information, research and design into the design and implementation of public spaces and sites. His research interests include spatialisation and digital literacy. His publications include the widely acclaimed Spatial Reference: A Journal of the European Geographer (2015), to be published in June from a research project at Aarhus University related to the exhibition Spatial Reference at Kielbasa, and the forthcoming</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made with malicious intentions, or that malicious actors may use obscure protocols such as SSL to hide their tracks. Further, the underlying assumption underlying the presumption of safety – that a user has to trust a site with his or her online identity – is questionable. 	[ii] As noted by Graham Claxton in relation to the arrest of Rami El Samahy, the Rafiq News Agency, 11th October 2016: ‘A group of activists was preparing to hold a demonstration outside the Bahrain International Airport when Bahrain authorities arrested them and dozens of other citizens accused of supporting the Bahrain uprising’. They were taken to prison for over a year before being freed. [iii] Granat Akram, ‘Unfixing the Internet: Bahraini Protesters at Bahrain International Airport Plead Guilty’, The New York Times, 22nd May 2016, p. A1.Download this article as PDFAna Laura López de la TorreAna Laura L</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a social network that has, since 2015, been developing GeoFeedback, a project that aims to embed geologists, geographers and information theorists in a working group developing a new kind of cultural geography. 	[i] The idea of ‘home page optimization’ has gained currency in the context of online social networking sites such as Facebook and Twitter. It is often cited as a way to improve the relevance of a site’s homepage, and has been adopted by other technology companies as a way to improve the relevance of their websites. However, the underlying premise of the optimisation – to some extent a response to the search engine based on which Google operates – remains deeply flawed. The underlying premise of the search engine is that it can find anything on the web – meaning that any webpage found on a user’s hard drive will be found by the optimised algorithms. However, this does not seem to account for the fact that links on the web are often made based on assumptions and prejudices, rather than relevant information. For instance, many internet sites that claim to provide useful or innovative information are actually quite reactionary, exhibiting a preference for the latest fad rather than the latest wisdom. Moreover, although the optimisation of the web seems to account for a large part of the increased bandwidth and connectivity provided by technologies such as social media, this does not seem to account for the expansion of knowledge or knowledge-producing capacity that results from concerted actions. 	[ii] Andersen, Tim. The Web That Circulates: On the Premises and Technologies of Social Networks. New York: Stages, 2013. Pp. 8–21.Download this article as PDFTim JeevesTim Jeeves is a writer and curator. His work has dealt with globalised information systems, from the web to cars and drones, and materials and manufacturing. His latest work,  	The New Economy of Cultures: Globalisation and Its Offsh</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.The difficulty with planning for the future, however, is that there is always that moment of apprehension, or that critical question, ‘when’ that throws everything into disarray. There is the risk of unforeseen results, and this is particularly true with autonomous vehicles. There is a reason why so many dystopian novels are set in antediluvian dystopian futures: The loss of data threatens not only the inhabitants of the fictional locations where the stories are set, but also the organisational principles underpinning the fictional futures. If the</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the user’s behaviour. This is an area of research that is still in its infancy, but already organisations from Facebook to Google’s self-driving cars are employing AI to analyse massive amounts of data on the roads and in the city.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to continue to be a key area of research and technology focus for the future.Artificial intelligence and autonomous vehicles will inevitably lead to new kinds of mapping and surveying. The question is how to get the data to analyse the huge amounts of data that will inevitably follow, and how to design infrastructure so that autonomous vehicles can find and use the data that is already there, and what can be done with it? The answer to this is a difficult one to grasp in a detailed way, but the possibilities are there. There are already signs that autonomous vehicles are picking up where mapping stops, and this is expected to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I
    <text>The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I don’t see that as the way to go. I think the answer is in the spaces that are there to be enjoyed: in the city, in the community, and in the arts community in particular. If we want to create new experiences in the city, we’ll have to create supportive local culture and bring people together through arts and culture who might not normally associate with each other.That sounds simple enough. But I think what we’re trying to do is create new experiences for the people that live around the park, and I think that’s an art question rather than a city one. Because if we do that, we’ll lose some of the magic of the place, and the magic of the place will be lost. But if we do the opposite, which is what we’re trying to do, we’ll lose that too. It’s a question of balancing the needs of the city against the possibilities of the magic</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I don’t see it. She’d have to actively seek funding. It feels as if this is becoming more and more of a rarity. Fundraising is a necessity for many projects, but it’s rarer still for artists to get involved. And while fundraising is a necessity for many projects, it’s rarer still for an artist to lead an artist’s event in a city. That sounds trite, but it’s the way things are. And I’m not saying that artists shouldn’t raise money; I’m just saying that the resources we do have shouldn’t support an artist’s project in a way that she’s not capable of supporting her own. I don’t see why it’s impossible for an artist to be both an artist and a mayor.In any case, the point is that if we want an artist to come to Liverpool, we need</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I don’t see why it couldn’t be a collective space that aims to address some of the grievances that people feel are being addressed, and provides that for people in a certain way. That would be a new experience.  One last thing: the story of the New York Public Library’s new digital archival service, Digital Nuyumbalees, is one that fascinates me. It evokes the 1970s, and the way libraries functioned then. When the Public Library bought the library from the Agence France-Presse in 1971, it set out to create a digital archive of sorts. It began by digitising all the books in the building, then mapping them out using information from a register kept on the books. It did this by hand, taking an old-fashioned book with you to the library, and scanning it using maps. Then, using a Scan-It device, you could create a new, blank book using the information from the register</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I doubt that she would. She would be asking for too much of the city. She’d need the approval of the city council. And I’m not sure that she has the necessary skills. She’d also need the support of the city’s tourism board. It could also depend on whether the park is a good fit for a museum. If it’s a spot where you can sit, talk, play and have a place, then it’s a museum. If it’s not a place where you can do that then it’s not a museum. It’s a question of resources. If the city has no money and no arts board, then it’s a place where the arts are not prominent, or not prominent enough, and where the people who use the space are not well-informed about the history and nature of the city. In such cases, the arts are often left behind. Perhaps the answer</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I don’t think it would be the same as the art being created here. It would be different, but it would be the same. It would be an experience, but it would also be an object.I don’t know if it’s possible to say what the experience would be like. I don’t know if it would be a biennial, or a museum. But I do know that it would create something completely unique and different from what is currently happening in the city, in a very concrete and material way. This could happen through the use of different materials, through the use of sustainable building materials and architectural styles, and perhaps also through the use of biennials as a funding source. But at the moment we don’t have the means to support a biennial that way.I don’t want to rule anything out. But I think that the way in which we are approaching this, the way in which it is happening now</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I don’t see that happening. I think what we need is for people to step back and really think about what the experience could be, and how it could be made. That was the experience of Metropolitan Gallery, from the first moment it was conceived to the very last. It was a long process of non-conformity, of non-conformity being celebrated. Now, if you’re at the Metropolitan Gallery, you’re leaving everything behind, and becoming part of the museum, but it’s not the same as becoming a museum piece. You’re becoming a museum piece because you’ve chosen to become one. And in that sense, I think that could happen with Projections. It’s not a new experience for artists to have that process of creation happening behind the scenes. But I don’t think that would be the same as making art. I don’t think that would</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I don’t think that would be the same as being able to build a park and claiming it as a public space. I don’t think that would happen to us. Rather, we’d be able to devote a park to events that are of a specific kind, and allow that to happen. As an artist, that’s what I aspire to. I don’t have any particular ideas about what that might look like. It’s a question that the city council has to decide. But I do know that what’s important for me is that the park becomes a place where people can walk, sit, play and have a place. That’s the beauty of it: that there are places for people to come, sit and have a place. That’s what amenity-generating land-use planning is all about. It’s not about turning a place into a museum or a museum into a destination.</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I don’t think it would be the same as being born a city. She’d already know what she wanted when she started. She’d make something completely different.She’d be able to create something totally unique and different to what we have now. That would be lovely. But I think what we’re trying to do is try to imagine what a city might be like if it had a park, and to a certain extent, that’s what we’ve done. But it’s also very important that the park is there to connect with the city, and that’s what we’re trying to do. When you’re trying to imagine a city, you’re also trying to imagine a park, because if you don’t, what happens then? Why do we have to be in a city? Because if we don’t have parks, then what does the city give us</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I don’t think it would be the same as the park. It would be new to the park, but it would be new to the community. Perhaps what we could do is create a hybrid park that meets the criteria of a city park, but also the criteria of a community park. That would be a start. I don’t think that would be the right approach. I think that would be an art project at its best. It would be art that was executed very carefully, and executed in a very personal way. But I also think that if we want to see what art can really do, we have to make sure that it’s executed with the community instead of in a corporation. Otherwise, what we end up doing is replicating the flaws and weaknesses of the city, and our own shortcomings and strengths. That is the classic 'big-government, small-government, local-loyalties' debate. But I do think that if we want to see</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. We have no evidence that it will happen. We can't rule it out completely. We have to see what happens. I do hope that what we do in the city centre, and the things that we do in the park, create some kind of an experience that will allow people to want to come to the park and spend time together. That would be fantastic. As a city, we’ve got a long way to go. I’m not sure there’s enough food and places to actually fit a city. I don’t want to rule out the possibility that something might happen where we decide to create a park and dedicate it to events. But I don’t think that would be a new experience. It would be new to the city, and it would be new to the artist. She could create an event around it. It would be her own park, but it would be a new experience. She could do it with funding. But I can already hear the criticism that says ‘You have to give the park back to the city’ – and that’s a hard thing to do. It’s not like we gave it away free – we have to charge a fee to access it. And I don’t see that happening. I don’t see a fee as a way of charging access to places, only places. That just doesn’t make sense.’ I think the answer is in the park itself, where there’s already an exchange between people that’s quite natural. I do hope the park retains its character, and that over time, as people come and go, that it evolves into something that’s their own. It’s going to be a long, long-term relationship. I don’t know if that’s something that was planned or if it’s something that’s happening organically.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop,
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.Contemporary Art in a Cultural Context: A Conversation on Modern Art’s Presentation of Life-Size Art Prints from the Museums of Venice and San Francisco, 2010. Installation and workshop at the Museo del Passato, San Francisco, USA. Photos: Helo Raicovich, San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1960. Photo: Frederic M. Norman, San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1967. Photo: John Muir, USF Museum of Modern Art, USA Today, 1966. Photo: John Muir, San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1967. Photo: John Muir, San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1967. Photo: John Muir, San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1967. Photo: John Muir, San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, 1967. Photo: John Muir,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.My Dear Prudence,There’s a very beautiful, moving letter that you wrote a while back, in response to the idea of the invisibility cloak. I think it captures the essence of your feeling about the world as it is projected onto a particular object. I don’t think it captures the idea well, but I think it captures the essence of what you’re trying to put into words. It’s a very moving thing to write, and I think it captures the essence of what you’re trying to do with this particular object. It’s a difficult thing to convey in writing, but you do it anyway.I’m going to have to read the whole thing, and I’m going to have to ask you to explain something to me that I’m not clear on. Maybe</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man, installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.Protecting the City, 2010. Installation, Arsenale di Venezia, Venice, Italy. Photo: Marco L. Brambilla.PreviousNextProtecting the City, 2010. Installation, Arsenale di Venezia, Venice, Italy. Photo: Marco L. Brambilla.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. Photo: Marco L. Brambilla.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. Photo: Marco L. Brambilla</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s quest was lead by Sir Peter Blake, Sir David Attenborough, and the Director of the Royal Academy, Michael Gove. The project was supported by a lifetime achievement funding from the Arts Council, and the NAS (formerly the Royal Academy of Arts).The Prince’s story was first told by actor Lee Merritt in the 1946 film The Wizard of Oz. It was also the basis for a stage version of the same story that also starred Robert Hewison, Carrie Fisher, and John Landis. In the film, a young Dorothy Gale discovers that the Wonderful Wizard is a large, hairy, green, scorpion-like creature with the tendency to kill people. She ultimately comes to terms with the fact that she has to help him defeat a giant, mean hydra-like creature (real name: Mudge).The Prince�</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Own Family’s Group’s (2009-2010), with additional curatorial work for the Liverpool Biennial and Tate Liverpool, and one of three artists featured in the 2012 London Biennial. Her work has been commissioned by: BT, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2012); McArthur, The Royal Academy of Arts, London, UK (2016); and Tate, London, UK (2018). M. Tajikbayev, The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince’s Quest for the Invisible Man (2017), installation and workshop, Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. © M. Tajikbayev. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.The Prince</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established in 2003 founded to carry out joint research projects with the US Department of Energy Advanced Energy Research Projects Agency (AERPA) on novel manufacturing processes for renewable energy resources. The laboratory is also home to the Chinatown Arts and Culture laboratory, an independent arts-based cultural centre, which offers educational and cultural programming to the rapidly expanding market for affordable housing in the Tower District. The new research institute Co-operative Education Research Institute is strategically positioned to address a changing research and development agenda, one that is driven by the availability of affordable housing and the rapid urbanisation of pockets of the city where new medical and urban technologies are deployed. Its research agenda involves developing knowledge about the role of art, culture and technology in addressing housing and urban issues in the developing world. The new institute will be strategically housed in a former Matador building in Chinatown, and its activities will be driven by the chinatown arts collective, CH</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established in Hong Kong to carry out research-based programmes in collaboration with the Biennial. The institute’s research agenda is focused on the design and development of sustainable ways to use locally-acquired materials and building resources, while the building programme DACS develops innovative practices to address challenges facing urban communities. The two institutes have published hundreds of articles in a number of academic and urban-related journals, including one issue of the academic journal PLATE Volume 14, with supplementary material online at PLATE. The Biennial has also published a number of books, most recently Design Culture: Art and Material Society in the Context of Architecture (2015), with Jacqueline Wood, Design Culture: Architecture, Material Society (2016), Design &amp; Empire (2016), and Getting Round Cities (2017). Bringing the Art of Cities to the Biennial​s Curatorial WorkflowThe Biennial used its inaugural public programme, a reception for a select few selected</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established in New York City in 1996 with the mission to support and facilitate research into art’s ecological and social impacts. It is the largest non-institutional resource for ecological and social research in the US and China. The largest stock of plant and animal products, including over-wintering wolong trees, bamboo, soil, water and insects, is maintained in a number of non-human species by the COMBER laboratory. A second research centre, the Brooklyn Museum of Art, is located in the borough of New York and hosts the Chinatown Arts Festival every August. The Brooklyn Biennial is a free and all-encompassing event with activities for both young and experienced artists. It is the largest public art institution in the US and the largest art performance venue in the world. In 2016, the Brooklyn Museum of Art opened its new, intimate, three-level, permanent collection of objects, Chinatown Arts </text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established in Shanghai to carry out research and development on new medical technologies, with a joint venture with Japanese pharmaceutical firm Nippon Medical Co., Ltd. The laboratory is jointly managed by the CHARTN (Chinese Academy of Arts and Sciences)'s Art and Research Institute (ARNI) and the Shanghai Art Tech Park’s Institute for Art and Cybernetics. The CHARTN’s research and development arm, CHARTN.com, is a leading online art and cultural resource with a digital art library and an online exhibition and museum collection. The CHARTN.com is a portal to the laboratory of new medical technologies developed at the Biennial. The digital art library features over 900,000 works indexed by topic, including a mock-up of the original 19th Biennial website. The CHARTN.com takes its title from the</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established in New York City in collaboration with the New York State Museum and the Wallace Stevens Institute for Art and Society, Columbia University. It was originally a laboratory for the chromosome research of human cells, but has since developed expertise in the research of plant and microbial cells. The laboratory was originally funded by the Wallace Stevens Laboratories for Visual Art and Technology, but has since focused on research priorities within the visual arts and social sciences. The CLT-funded research institute now has its own research centre, which utilises state-of-the-art bio-visual  technologies to image and analyse the DNA of plant and microbial cells. The CLT-funded activities include the development and validation of new technologies for the gene-editing of plant and microbial cells, as well as cell culture and regenerative medicine approaches. In addition to research, the Biennial has been working with community groups to design, create</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established in 1995, which is responsible for the development and validation of new medical technologies, including therapeutics, biomedical development and education. It is an international hub for collaborative research and education in the development of health and social development, including academic acceleration through research projects in China, the United States and Hong Kong. It supports the international dissemination and institution of acceleration through research projects in Hong Kong and Taiwan. It is an international public policy think-tank founded in 1996 and runs through 2014. It is a member of the Shanghai Institutes for Research on Contemporary Art (SIMCA), Shanghai Jiao Tong University and Renmin University of China. It was established to promote international exchange and promote research and education in contemporary art by accelerating the status of art in research-intensive institutions in the city, region and world through accelerating the production and dissemination of</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established in the United States by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun. Their collaborative research project, the Biennial Research Institute, 2185 was begun in 2009 and 2013 respectively. The Biennial Research Institute 2185 was established to support the development of knowledge about urban regeneration and urban development in China through research-intensive institutes, publishing and broadcasting programmes, as well as curatorial and educational programmes. The research institute 2185 uses grant funding from the National Endowment for the Arts and the National Institutes of Health to carry out its research programme. In addition to publishing and broadcasting research papers, the Biennial Research Institute 2185 publishes a quarterly journal,  	Design &amp; Empire, that catalogues research projects and curatorial programmes in China with special focus on infrastructure and urbanisation. In 2015, the Biennial Research Institute established a collaborative research programme with the London School of Art and Dart</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established in New York City in 1994 which is a not-for-profit multi-institutional research organisation with a research centre in the city. It was founded to carry out research-based design and to address a research question that had emerged during the 1994 FIFA Congress: how to support a city to carry out design research and identify promising sites for future redevelopment in a way that contributes to the revitalization of a city.  In 1995 the Biennial was renamed the   	Futures of Painting at the New Museum. In 2000 the Biennial was renamed the Museum of the Future at the New Museum. In 2008 the Biennial was renamed the Museum of Art at the New Museum. In 2014 the Biennial was renamed the New Museum at the New Museum. In 2016 the Biennial was renamed the Museum of Social Inquiry at the New Museum. In 2018 the Biennial was renamed the Museum of the Future at the New</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established in New York City in 1985. The centre’s mission is to provide research and analysis on key issues affecting the Community Arts sector in the city, while the research and analytical arm of the cooperative concentrates on the cooperative art forms that it jointly promotes, such as cooperative baking and cooperative education. 	Although the research and analytical arm of the cooperative develops innovative art-based methodsologies for understanding and producing knowledge on key issues, the laboratory plays a pivotal role in the Community Arts production pipeline. It develops and tests new technologies and approaches to art production, including new mechanisms for the production of biopolymer polyurethanes, polysaccharides and polysaccharides bound together with carbon nanotubes and aluminium by Thermoset technologies. These thus pave the way for future uses of these biopolymers and their products in art, healthcare, education and other sectors. 	In addition to its research portfolio</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally planned for construction to house Fifa world leaders, has been repurposed for research and development purposes. The Biennial’s research and development arm,   	DACS, has been directed by Dr Tina Kaczor and consists of a research centre, a laboratory and an educational centre. The laboratory is a state of the art accelerator for new medical technologies developed at the Biennial, while the educational programme Co-operative Education continues to offer flexible and multi-disciplinary options for academic learning in response to the Biennial’s research-intensive nature of design. The research centre Co-operative Education has been co-founded by American artist Wendy Chun and Chinese artist Yip Jun and is managed by the Chinatown Arts Collective. The laboratory Co-operative Education Research Institute (COMBER) is a non-profit research organisation established in New York City in 1976 and based in Binghamton, New York. It is a public research and design centre that develops and supports innovative means of learning through collaborative learning and is guided by a board of directors appointed by the Biennial and the City Council. It was founded in 1985 and is a non-profit organisation, certifying itself as a non-governmental arts organisation by the New York State Museum. It has a national budget of $5 million a year and is managed by Dr Tina Kaczor, a former curator at the New York Public Museum and the Museum of Modern Art. In 2012, the Binghamton Art Museum selected the laboratory as part of its curatorial team for the Moving Pictures series. In 2015, the New York Museums Commission selected the laboratory for the multi-year Projections program. In 2017, the MUSEUM OF MAN made a gift of a permanent lot in</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so. The biennale must address a larger cultural context, which is most clearly seen in the two main art-historical sections of the biennale catalogue: sections devoted to Venice and the Italian Renaissance. Both Venice and the Renaissance are long gone, but the biennale is forced to linger, questioning what is still extant, what is novel and what is not familiar. These questions, while essential in their own right, are neglected in the biennale catalogue. 	For example, the section devoted to Venice International Exhibition (2009) is divided into two parts: the part on the city’s cultural past, and the part on the city’s present, focusing on key works from the past that are relevant to the present. This division is necessary since the section on the city’s cultural past contains only fragments that are relevant to the part on the city’s present, and since the section on the city’s present only contains fragments that are</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so. The biennale must also address the current political and economic conditions in the city, since it is the only venue that can house the ever-increasing number of visitors. The host city must also play a role in the curatorial decision-making process, since the city is the only one with the capacity to define the parameters of the biennale. The biennale must be able to roam from city to city in a circulatory system that creates and controls its circulation. And it is the city that makes the circulatory system. The biennale must be able to find its place in this circulatory system – in other words, it must be able to penetrate and influence the city in many different ways. In other words, it must be able to rethink and alter its parameters continuously.In other words, the biennale must be able to grow and change with the changing city, and it must constantly engage with the city in many different ways. And here we see another key</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so. The biennale has to catch on, and so it does not matter what a fixed or static reference number is, or what an identity is. A reference number is a type of measurement that reveals (at least to an observer) the relative positions of the things in space; it is a way to point to a position in time. And in the biennale, the things that are being positioned are not static, but constantly shifting, as new things are discovered and past performances are repeated all around the city. 	When I was a child, my favourite time of discovery was during the Green Day show at the Performing Arts Center, which would regularly introduce a new song and/or act. The reason I adored it was that the artists would often do things in a very restrained, controlled way, usually setting up situations that elicit a reaction from the audience. For example, at the Carmen De Sisi biennale in 2014, Deena Karam</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so. The question is, which space will we let them in? As the creator of the biennale, how can we use its potential? 	The answer must be found in the question, ‘Where is Istanbul?’, because if it is to be an appropriate site for the 20th Istanbul Biennale, then it must be a site that addresses the past, the present and the future, that returns to the present and that can be shared between the different parts of the city. And this is a difficult proposition to swallow, for it seems as if one is born with the right to occupy a particular site and be part of a collective past, but it is also true that some people (myself included) hold out hope that the site will one day return to its natural state: a mixture of residential neighbourhoods, a park with public art and open spaces, a seaside historic district and, eventually, a city entirely re-constructed in the shape of an island</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so. The biennale mustn’t just ‘be there’; it has to be a globally visible presence, and a ‘game-changing’ event that reverberates throughout the city and beyond. And that’s what we at the Biennale were taught to do wrong. The biennale is a very powerful tool, but it is limited in its application and therefore operates on two levels – in the real world and in the art world. The real world is a ‘glimmer of light’ that shines everywhere, but is equally capable of casting dark clouds and flooding the city with sewage. The art world is a different kind of ‘deepthrobber’ that projects a soft but persistent shadow, and so the biennale must be selective in what it relies on. The biennale mustn’t just ‘be there’; it has to be a catalyst for something bigger and better to happen</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so. The biennale needs to address a wider local audience, and this is where other cultural apparatuses can join the biennale in a collaborative effort. The Biennale’s current focus is on urban exploration and design in Venice, but it is expected that the main themes of the next edition will be found in an exhibition space or museum-based setting in any city where art and culture meet. 	In an ideal world, the biennale would post regularly on its website, and bring together artists, curators, art writers, art’s trustees and every other kind of professional or institutional player, and post the exhibits accordingly. But this comes at a cost: the biennale is a institutional business, and the money that it raises from institutional investors determines who can establish museums and galleries and what kinds of funding is available. So how to raise capital for a museum or gallery without becoming entangled in the biennale? That is the dilemma facing institutions today</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so. The biennale must also address the complex interconnections between art and society, which are often overlooked or presumed to be there, and which can lead to interesting encounters, even ones as bizarre as the one between Biennale and Biennale. 	The 20th Biennale of Madrid’s Arsenale, which opened in 2014, was curated and co-curated by Isabelle Huppert-Benedict and Eduardo Espin and appeared to address some of these concerns. It is a sudden, starry-eyed event, full of new ideas and new experiences, full of art that is as if it has just been introduced to a city. The collection of works displayed in the Arsenale home of the Biennale that year included performance works and photography that were part of the public domain for nearly a century, as well as works by and about artists who have worked in the Biennale space for decades. The exhibition included works</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so. The biennale must also address the migratory nature of the biennale, since each time the biennale changes place, different kinds of people come to visit. And it is important that the biennale not only capture people's imaginations, but that it is a place where culture takes root and engages people. 	So the biennale must address culture as a collective habit that emerges from the collective action of people, a notion that transcends national boundaries. And this notion is made manifest in different ways by different kinds of people. 	So the biennale must address culture as a collective habit that emerges from the collective action of people, a notion that is not confined to an intellectual or scientific elite. It must also address culture as a transnational commodity that circulates everywhere, and thus must address what Marx called the ‘gulf and its drifting culture’. 	The biennale must address this shifting of places and these migratory currents</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so. The biennale must also address the growing gap between the urban and the rural. The urban/rural divide is vast and growing larger in the world, and the biennale is a convenient place to present this urban reality to an audience of urbanites and rural viewers alike. But the growing gap between the urban and the rural is even more evident in Istanbul, where over one million people flock to the Biennale grounds each year. The urban/rural divide is even more obvious in Istanbul’s Tonga district, where the Nakba, or Hundred Years of Ottoman Rule, marks the foundation of the city’s built heritage. The number of graves in each district has nearly doubled over the past 200 years, and over half the city’s built heritage is either destroyed or distorted in some way. 	The increasing urbanisation of the city is primarily driven by the ‘need to know’ – information about the city’s development that can</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from a single point of origin. 	The biennale entered its petit-circle in 2009 with Venice as its outer borough. But the rapid growth of the Italian and Spanish diasporas in the decades that followed, coupled with the advent of the biennale in 2012, has meant that within a few years the boundaries that weavers and artists had to navigate had shifted, and now weavers in their hundreds are meeting artists in galleries and museums. But the biennale has had to address this shift, because the host city of the 2016 iteration, Madrid, will be the site of the 20th Istanbul Biennale, a seemingly appropriate comparison. The 20th edition of Biennale would make an ideal candidate for the permanent urban registry, since it would unite, present and explore the city in a common space. 	But while the biennale is the ideal candidate for the perfect urban space, it is not the only one that can be made so. Cities need a public realm beyond the static boundaries of city and country, and this’s why biennales are so important now more than ever: their numbers and the experiences and histories they preserve are the very fabric of the city, but they are itself threatened by a rapidly urbanising world. To flourish, biennales have to be places that are both culturally responsive and economically transformative, that create a climate of exchange and foster a sense of place around the institution, but which also have a sense of their own place in the city. A city that collectively experiences and produces the biennale as a collective event, and collectively distributes the fruits of that experience across different social, economic and spatial sectors. A city that produces cultural capital 	[1] in exchange for its individual parts, and that simultaneously exploits and inhabits those parts, but also produces a sense of place around that capital when it manifests itself in different forms – as a congealing stock of habitants</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which to do so, one that was not necessarily a ‘festival’ in the conventional, formal sense of the term. It turned its back on the festival in order to begin to uncover, to reveal the cities that it was entering, ‘streets’ and ‘indoor areas’ that it was trying to obscure, and ‘hidden’ areas that it felt it could not control. It did this in a way that was not necessarily a reaction to the festival, but rather a spatial and temporal displacement of the festival’s presence. And this is also to say that the artworks were placed in situations that made them part of a larger, more dynamic cultural landscape that emerged from the project, which in turn, could expand and contract according to the will and impulse of the artists. The question that remained, however, was when.After the Biennale of Sydney (2007), Piet Mond and Rob Wainwright, in their book Institutions and</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which to do so, but also in which to research and document its transnational impact. It concentrated on the city as a site for future research and documentation, but also engaged in a kind of ‘house-of-mirrors’ kind of retrofitting and reconfiguration that reconfigured the city into new sites and situations. And it did so in a ‘big data analysis and mapping service’, or ‘Norton NOMADICUS’, that collects and maps space and time in real-time from all over the globe.In these ways, the Biennale of Sydney turned a ‘conventional cultural venue’ into a kind of ‘new cultural venue’, and ‘a place where artists can exist in ‘displaced space’ alongside people and places of all kinds, backgrounds and experiences’. The problem with the festival itself, in these ways of looking at it, was that it was always a kind</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which to examine the migration of people, ideas, and objects in and through the city. It turned the festival into a transient ‘event’ and ‘spotlight’ on a certain spatial and temporal scale, while the city into a transient ‘place of transient ‘image making’. At its best, this meant turning the biennale into a transnational institution that spread globally in its coverage, but also ‘taking a back seat’ to other, more visible cultural institutions and trappings. By turning its back on the festival, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a different kind of cultural tourism. By absorbing the city into its narrative, the Biennale of Sydney is able to invest more deeply, meaning that its power and wealth are distributed more evenly. But turning the festival into a transient ‘event’ and ‘spotlight’ is just one way that the Biennale of Sydney attempted to address an uneven power and spatial</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which to do so. It turned the festival into an object of its own construction, and the festival into an object of the state. But the festival also turned the biennial into a curatorial exercise in the centrality of the biennial as a cultural production – one that sought to impose a strict definition of what was considered a ‘genuinely contemporary’ event on the city. This is what the curatorial gesture implied, and this is what the festival hoped to achieve. The real confrontation between the ephemeral and the present, cultural and economic in the modern world, and social and political in all its aspects, was dramatised in the 2016 Venice Biennale, which was itself a biennale after the Venice of the year before. And it is what the biennale of the future may or may not achieve.The Venice Biennale was itself a ‘corner case’: it was a latecomer to the game, and its roots are</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which to do so, returning to the festival in 2017. But this did not in any way replace, nor replicate, the festival as a cultural form, nor its specific practices, nor its social functions, nor its economic or social forms. The festival drew on the festival of symbols and motifs it was attempting to render universal, but it also attempted to apply these universalities to specific social situations. And in doing so, it created a ficto-temporal space in which to do so, but also a ficto-temporal space in which to be made universal. In other words, the festival is a form of remembrance, but it is also a form of creation. The festival is not a living organism that acquires meaning from the everyday world, like a living plant or animal; rather, it develops out of the life-blood of the city, its significant art and cultural institutions and its diverse communities of visitors. And although the world it represents may or may not be real, the</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which to theorise and produce a ‘consequence of the festival’(2). The Biennale of Sydney (2011) and the Biennale of Sydney (2016) were both concerned with the temporality of the biennial – the specific, concrete historical events that shape the biennial – and the contemporaneity of these with the specific, idealised narratives of art historicals that emerged during the 1990s and early 2000s in response to the so-called ‘crisis’ of the biennial.  The Biennale of Sydney (2011) and the Biennale of Sydney (2016) were all concerned with the contemporaneity of the biennial with other forms of cultural production, particularly that of tourism.  And, in that sense, they are all products of the same historical and urban-tourism dynamic.  And, in that sense, they are all responses to the same biennial crisis. The key to the success of such bi</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which to do so. It stepped back, or ‘stepped back’ if you were at the festival in 2011 and ‘stepped back’ if you were at the Biennale in Sydney in 2016. This was done through a series of small, but important acts of memory – a.k.a. markers. By stepping back, the Biennale was able to ‘open up’ the festival to new experiences and ideas, while at the same time trapping the discursive freight of the festival in the city through this temporality. It ‘stepped back’ by creating a parallel space that it could inhabit in perpetuity, while simultaneously constructing a kind of static discursive space that reflected the biennial in its contemporary form.In undertaking these kinds of symbolic ‘recurrent events’ in historical and contemporary urban settings, the Biennale of Sydney and the Biennale of Venice staged in 2016 both attempted to conjure a kind of shared</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which to rethink the cultural tourism narrative and the festival as cultural tourism today. It turned the festival into a kind of space for reflection and negotiation, and the exhibition into a kind of space for exchange between cultures. In doing so, it positioned the festival within the city as a site of negotiation and negotiation, but also within the city’s infrastructure as a form of cultural tourism. It allowed the festival to inhabit the infrastructure of the city while simultaneously mapping its social and spatial production. And so, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to do both at the same time. It turned the festival into a product of cultural capital and the exchange of culture, while simultaneously mapping its social and spatial production. And this is what we do with cities. We turn cultural capitals into ecological footprints that reshape the ecological landscape and the relations between people and places. We do this through what is often called ‘trans-indigenous’ – the exchange of space and resources between people and non-human species.</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which to do so. It turned a festival that was, by turning away from the festival, turning inward. In other words, it turned away from the festival at the same time it was turning inward and outward. But this didn’t happen at the same time; rather, the festival was actively engaging with and responding to the biennial through these two distinct but related gateways. The festival was a website that the biennial could then inhabit and function in a particular way. This offered several possibilities. The festival could create a mini-festival around itself through a self-branding strategy (the same way the physical curators of the Venice Biennale get a cut of the gross receipts). This would allow the biennial to inhabit a ‘conventional’ level of cultural tourism (a.k.a. the low-end international cultural tourism of the major cities), while simultaneously remaining accessible at the same time. A mini-festival would also allow the biennial to</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is a chance to start anew, to reassess the question: when is a biennial a necessary precondition for a cultural production? Should it be all exclusions and reductions?Should it be possible to create a biennial that is not a 'concrete historical event' in the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term, but rather a circumstance or set of circumstances that render the traditional, formal, institutionalised sense of the term – a.k.a. the festival – obsolete? This is the question that the Biennale of Sydney (2007) tried to answer by turning its back on the festival and returning to the city in a chronological, urban and ‘cultural tourism’ sense. And to a certain extent, it worked: the Biennale of Sydney returned to the city in 2011 and 2016, respectively.By turning its back on the festival and returning to the city, the Biennale of Sydney attempted to create a parallel temporal space in which to observe and think about the historical significance of its own project (the exhibition of art on the city's waterfront, which it organised in stages across the city, in a city close to the sea, in an area with a large Greek community). The issue of exclusivity and reduction was raised in the biennial’s exhibition catalogue: ‘Certain exclusions and reductions are imposed on us by the relatively low budget of biennials today.’ In other words, the biennial is often penalised for having an artistic project, or even a cultural project, in the city. The argument goes that by refusing to be catered to by the festival industry, biennials are appropriating what is considered a ‘sacred space’ – a site of reverence by virtue of its location. The Biennale of Sydney (2007) responded this backward looking approach by arguing that, in so far as biennials have become more institutionalised and data-driven, they are</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between
    <text>The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between the haves and the have nots. Instead we need to invest in creating truly local experiences and in that sense I define ‘being in the city’ as a multiple of the work done in the neighbourhood.I also want to stress that I don’t think that there is a divide between the neighbourhoods and the broader locality. I think that the delivery that’s being done now is fundamentally different from what was done in the past, and I don’t think that the delivery of services or even just information is what separates the neighbourhoods from the wider locality. There is an assumption, which is also missing in most mapping and research on people. But there is an assumption that comes with the territory that is being mapped: that the city is a collection of discrete points of interaction. And I think that is a mistake that I believe is enabling and enabling only creates the problems. Instead, I would like to see organisations invest in the kinds of long-term relationships that can</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between people who are connected by email and people who are connected by face to face. There is so much more to be done. There is so much more to be done in a biracial neighbourhood, for example, if you live in a neighbourhood and if you are part of a biracial community. There is so much more that one can do with their urban space and cultural resources than can be done with data and analytics, and I think that is where the future lies for many places. There is a sense of displacement, which of course is a by-product of the new economy, but I also think that there is a sense of anger, which is a by-product of the new regulatory state that is emerging in many cities: gentrification, which is the taking and holding of cultural resources by the state at a very fast pace, and so on.I also think that there is an awareness that these are long-term trends, that there are going to be large generational changes happening in the</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between the people who are creating the city and the people who are using it. I don’t want to define the other, which is: which technologists are contributing to creating the city? I want to see which ones are actually contributing to making it a place where people can’t always get there.I think that what is happening now is that the city is no longer a set of relations between city and country. It’s becoming something that’s much more like a data set. The city is a set of relations between people that are constantly transnational in scope and in which there is no country. So I think that the scale of the tasks involved in the project is what stands out. I don’t think that the symbolic nature of the project, or the fact that it is a ‘solve in a city’, or even the fact that it is a ‘spray-on-the-wound’ that heals wounds</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between the haves and the have nots. I also believe that there are so-called smart growth initiatives, which I described as the Saudi model of sustainable growth, where people are encouraged to adopt certain behaviors, to adopt certain ways of living, and so forth, that are conducive to the empowerment of that particular subset of people. I think that there is a tension there, and I don’t want to define that.I don’t think that there is a tension between art and sustainability. There is a huge gulf between the wealthy society in which the arts are valued and the poor society in which the arts are not. I don’t think that there is a gulf, but there is a certain amount of friction. And I don’t think that there is a gulf between the wealthy society in which art is an evergreen and the poor society in which it is not. But I do think that there is a certain amount of conflict between the needs of the modern</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between the various data streams. We need to understand the city from every possible angle.That was a really interesting way to think about the city. To some extent it is what we have learned in the past few years, as cities are constantly assessed and revised, and to some extent it is what we just happen to have become more capable of understanding. I feel very strongly that the capacity to understand is what matters; and so I would categorically reject any proposal that attempts to increase the capacity to understand by making it a condition of employment.  In fact, I think that the capacity to understand should be the first goal of any new activity; and so I would reject any such proposal that increases the size of the industry, or tries to shoehorn in magic, or tries to write magic into the system through which we collect and analyse data. The capacity to understand is the first objective, and making the system more accurate and precise is a secondary objective. The more data points we add, the clearer our</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between now and when we actually do build the city. There is a need for a long-term, in-depth, collaborative design process that looks at the whole city and proposes a long-term vision for what this city could be.I think that is a difficult task, and I don’t think that this has been done before, although there are many creative approaches that have been taken with limited resources, such as the New York City Biennale. I think that what we’re seeing is a new kind of cultural cirque being built by the data industry, and I don’t think that this is a good thing. I think that the stress on the city and its infrastructure is pressing and the new curators who are coming on board, such as myself, are going to add another layer of complexity to the already  	complex urban-geographic mapping that has been going on for years. As a result, the project doesn’t have the required</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between the past and the future. My idea is to have a habit of going back to the city, to come home to, say hi to, and sometimes to visit the family in, say, Berlant. I think that would be so meaningful and would allow us to move forward. The idea of homecoming seems so foreign to us, but it is such a powerful notion to be able to revisit it.Perhaps what we have neglected in our analysis of the city is the fact that the city is a living organism, which means that it adapts to its surroundings and to some extent, its inhabitants. Every day, new neighbourhoods are being created in the old, closed schools zone. There is an extraordinary amount of re-constituting going on, which is creating new physical spaces, new activitities and new ways of living. I don’t think we have enough language to quantify this kind of ecological juggling act that we are engaged in, but we do know that there are</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between the experts and the ordinary person. I think that there is a real possibility that this is what we are doing with the forms that we are creating, because it is impossible to create a new urban form and be involved with it all. I remember vividly when I was first developing the policy proposals for the MMM exhibition, I came across a very interesting theory about the behaviour of technologies. It seemed very prescient in the context of the context of the uprising in Istanbul, but in the context of the transnational biennale business it occurred to me that this was the moment in the emergence of new curatorial practices that this country was entering into, because the very structure of the biennale was being reshaped. The curatorial turn began to be replaced by the curatorial hunt. The biennale was defined by the curatorial turn, and now we are entering a stage where the biennale is no longer defined by the curatorial turn, but is instead expected to evolve according to</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between the haves and the have nots. I also don’t think that there are enough resources for this kind of thing, because it’s too abstract and diffuse: there are too many variables. But there is a need for this kind of thing, because if not addressed, there is a risk that the city is left to decay: there is a danger that the infrastructure that brings us water, electricity, and food won’t be able to sustain us anymore; this is the phenomenon known as ‘negative zero’.In the past, we’d also created virtual or augmented cities, like Google’s Valley Roads or Microsoft’s Spaces, which promise to bring infrastructure closer to the places where people live and work. But these are just infrastructure fantasies. There is a cost to this kind of thing, and as I mentioned earlier, the infrastructure that makes us ‘sensible’ and allows us to access the web is very expensive.</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, a proposal, a Wager. It is not a finished, black- or white-label project. I’m not so sure about the in-home delivery of delivery. I think it’s a new paradigm, as we move away from trucking and towards services. And I also think that the delivery concept is so fundamental to almost everything we do that if we don’t understand how that affects our practices then there is a very real chance that we can’t imagine, for example, what it would be like to live in another part of the city or even elsewhere in the world.I think that what’s happening now is that there is a tension, which I don’t want to define, but a tension that is real and that is palpable. There are so many different ways of interacting with the city that are mediated by data and analytics, and I think that in its current form the project is not enough to bridge the gap between those different times. I think that there is a need for a long-term vision, a vision that captures the historical context of the project and informs the way in which we do it today. For me, it’s important to capture the historical context because it informs and inspires the way in which the future will work. I think that my project, which is a ‘projection’ for the future, captured that tension and that tension in a very powerful way. It created a kind of a plaything that became a kind of a home for that historical project that I was part of.I think that in a larger context, the project began to have a kind of power, because it was a commitment to capturing the tension between the past and the present. And I think that the way in which the project was articulated, the way in which it was visualised, the way in which it was experienced – the way in which art was performed, for example – gave the project</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	The development of the local art community was closely tied to the development of the city as a ‘transportation, storage and production centre for manufactured articles and finished products of various types, including but not limited to vehicles, buildings, building materials, building components, textiles, footwear, pharmaceuticals, home furnishings, consumer goods, sporting goods, consumer electronics, vehicles and more’.[5] 	The RCA School of Art continued to develop its programming, with a particular focus on developing a local arts and culture movement. In 2006, the art world saw another major cultural event when the Indy 500 was held in Kentucky Speedway, with the Kentucky Fried Chicken sponsorship and the Kentucky Fried Art of Scott Hanson. The emergence of fast fashion as a significant industry sector in Indianapolis, and its consequent on-ramp to postindustrial sites of cultural consumption across the state was a significant influence on the development of the art world within the city. Fast fashion was a direct result of the advent of</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	When the Art and Architecture programme was discontinued in 1982, the Art and Architecture school, which had been running concurrently with the local primary school, was transferred to the newly created Modern and Contemporary Arts Centre, a new centre for the production of contemporary art. The school continued to produce independent works in a smaller exhibition programme, and as a result the artworks found their way into collections, which in turn found places in museums and archives. The Art and Arterial Recordings project was also established, this time as a record of the local workforce. It marked the first public introduction of the collection of scrapbooks held in the school archive, and the first public exhibition of the collection. It marked the return of the first in-person visits to the locations. It marked the emergence of a second phase, during which time the collection was maintained in the art department of the L, and the CEMB, and the CUNY Museum of Modern Art. The ART and ARCHIVE notes were published</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	The emergence of a new art form in the area coincided with the creation of a new regulatory regime for cultural institutions in the area, which encouraged the establishment of cooperative art institutions. The emergence of a new art form also coincided with the establishment of a new regulatory regime for the production and dissemination of visual art – a form of art that was neither authorised nor regulated by the government. The new media were deployed across social media, becoming not only a means of public display and a source of information, but also a source of narratives and a participatory form of art. The proliferation of media transformed the local and globalised depiction of the arts, and art’s place in the social landscape. 	In the twenty-first century, the media dominate the narrative. But while the narratives of historic forms are still dominant (see Richard Florida’s Cultural Clause, for instance), the visual is no longer the dominant medium through which people imagine themselves to be connected. The dominant visual mode today is social</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	The RCA also made a number of important cultural interventions, including the commission of a new mural for the M4, a government-funded project to restore the Madeira Highway, and the commission of a new school of painting, sculpture and fabrication. The School of Art was formally established in 1900, and the School of Painting, which followed in 1930, was established in 1931. The 1940 programme of paintings and sculpture was dedicated to the conflict in the Second World War, and the Museum of Modern Art commissioned a series of paintings by the Belgian artists Damien Hirst and Jean Guy Lecat, who were both students in the School of Painting and the School of Modern Art. The School of Modern Art was established as a joint venture by the Belgian government and the RCA, and included teaching and research facilities in the art, architecture and media departments. In April 1942, the School of Modern Art established its own department, dedicated to the propaganda of the war effort, and within this, photography, print</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	The Community Arts movement was a response to the isolation and austerity imposed by patronage, and it was hoped that the Cooperative Movement would offer some form of alternative to the isolation and austerity of the traditional school. The Cooperative Movement attracted artists from all over the UK and beyond, and many of these artists found their ways to Liverpool. Art is a complex, global language, and the Cooperative Movement sought to expose the many layers of the industry by which artists were trapped. 	Art was made possible by the creation of a network of underground depots, or co-operatives, which supported the production of art at a local level through donations and the provision of resources. These depots provided a level of autonomy not enjoyed by the artist or his or her co-conspirators, whose projects were often initiated by the resources provided. However, the development of underground art supply was not without complications and challenges. The development of underground art was accompanied by new ideas about what constitutes an artist and the role of an</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	Although the town centre was redeveloped and renamed London, its cultural heritage was preserved in perpetuity. The art collections from the LCAS and RCA were retained in the newly created National Gallery of Art, while the local art community formed into a new trade organisation, the British Transport Police. 	The building of new railways in the years immediately following the war meant that disruption to travel was anticipated, and new modes of transport were developed to cope with the huge increase in passengers. The creation of film and photography in the years immediately following the war meant that disruption to travel was also anticipated, and new media were created to cope with the later invasion of film and photographic film by the military. Art, however, played its part in both the creation and the interception of technologies. Its activities during the Blitz were part of a new media revolution that was as much about shock and confusion as it was about cooperation and collaboration. The fact that the National Gallery was closed during the war, and that the local community</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	 Local artists took over the art collection, which had been held by the National Gallery, and used it creatively. They acquired rare and modern works, including works from the Tate, and used the money raised by the art fund to produce original and limited edition art projects, including a traveling retrospective of the early twentieth century. The life of the art fund had become a commodity, and the collection managers used the art as a form of state-backed credit, often under the guise of art exhibitions. 	 As a result of the biennale, the collections were regularly reviewed and new collections added to the building, creating a cyclical structure that continued to grow in size and in value. The biennale became an annual ritual that was regularly repeated, and the building captured the imagination of visitors from all over the world. It was a metaphor for the increasing privatisation of spaces, a metaphor for the breakdown of the social contract, and a metaphor for the emergence of a new economy of culture. The</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	The art community in L’Aquila del Mar incorporated art photography and the local branch of the RCA School of Art. The School’s first board of directors was made up of the artistes and their assistants, including myself, while the School was a, 'self-supporting unit' with the support of the Arts Council. The School’s second board was made up of local artists, writers and community organisers. The Community Organiser was a good friend of the RCA, and a regular visitor to the museum, so she got a promotion in the media when she visited the town. The School of Art made regular trips to L’Aquila, teaching local kids how to paint, and providing them with practical arts-related knowledge. They also established a Community Land Trust, which gave the arts a legal entity in the local area. The Arts Council was keen to establish a relationship with the School of Art, and started a formal ten-year engagement programme,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	The School of Art was established as a studio, or quasi-studio, in collaboration with the local artisans and the renowned artist Joseph Rykwert, and it continued to publish articles and lectures throughout the 1920s and 1930s. It offered a multi-disciplinary studio programme, with subjects including architecture, photography, sculpture, painting and dance. The School was divided into five studios, each devoted to a different department, and each occupied by an artist. Studio One, the art department, offered a studio to one of the artists’ operas, while Studio Two, the architecture department, offered a studio to another of the artist’s operas. Each studio had a studio manager, a member of the art staff, and a member of the architecture staff. The music department offered space to a monthly open mike, and the children’s department offered free rehearsal space at the school. 	The RCA established a series of workshops for the staff of the art department</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative, the museum was transformed into a hub of activity. The narrow, windowless galleries that once housed performance art now hosted exhibitions in the art of travelling picture displays, and the butcher shop that once housed butcher papers served as a meeting place for the local art community. Local artists formed into artist-run cooperatives, exhibiting their work at the annual festival; a local curator then selected works from the group, publishing their individual works as pamphlets in the local newspapers. Curators from the Royal College of Art, the Metropolitan Museum of Art and the Museum of Modern Art visited the town to meet the artists and discuss the development of the local art scene. The RCA opened a new exhibition facility, the LCAS, dedicated to the local art community, and the RCA School of Art was established in the LCAS. All the local art schools in the district were incorporated into the School of Art, and the RCA School of Art was established as a separate school. 	A new generation of artists was emerging, developing a critical perspective on the practices and ideologies of community art. The art of community was made more accessible through the ubiquity of the ‘Community Arts? vocabulary, and the proliferation of image processing and social media applications. But despite these efforts, many in the local community continue to perceive art as a commodity, or worse, a tool of the dominant economic and political frameworks of the community.  	The emergence of new media aesthetics influenced other aspects of the community's behaviour, as well. Videos documenting the life of Indigenous communities were popular with the young people at the school, and were often shown during arts and recreation programming during afternoons on television. These empowered the community to take control of their content and generate their own identity through their collective actions. This approach to artist-generated culture and artistic production reoriented the school away from the dominant cultural practices of the area and towards a more participatory model. This in turn, led to a radical</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
