<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In 2014, a group of Traveller’s from Liverpool headed for the Pyjamas, a historic district in Gagauzu, on the other side of the Caspian Sea. The museum displayed the collection from its Georgian and Edwardian periods in the Traveller’s Room, as well as Georgian and Edwardian manuscripts and prints from the area. The collection from Gagauzu, mounted on easels, provided a visual forum for the local community to talk amongst themselves. The local community was keen for the collection to remain in the area, because it was here that they imagined themselves to be located, and so it continued to be a point of common ground. However, the collection from Gagauzu has become increasingly rarefied. In 2017, the Georgian and Edwardian periods were selected as part of a major exhibition on the history of architecture and urbanisation in Georgia. The exhibition was held in Rotterdam, and in the city itself, in a small</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In the twentieth century, the size and character of the international transit market dictated that many books on architecture from North were read by North African and Arab visitors, who arrived en masse after the end of the war. Today, the international tourism industry depends on this distinction, which allows it to connect the two. The attraction of the North African and Arab tourism market was its accessibility: the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North were able to offer the perfect setting for the exhibition of works by artists from Arab or North African countries, who found the museum highly engaging. The exhibition of artworks by artists from the North African and Arab worlds was anticipated by the exhibition of artworks by artists from other parts of the world, who found the proximity of the collections and the professions of art and architecture commendable. The Jubilee Bus tour offered several opportunities to explore the North African and Arab capitals in the early twentieth century. The exhibition of artworks by artists from North Africa and the Arab world</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In 2015, a group of Traveller’s visitors were prevented from entering the Sorbonne due to a security scare. In 2017, a similar group was prevented from touring the Carriageworks building due to a security scare. In both ‘Sorbonne and Museum of Modern Art’, these incidents are often cited as evidence of the museums becoming too cosmopolitan. However, this isn’t always the case. In the 1940s, a group of artists from the North established the Museum of Modern Art in Paris, which became a nexus for artistic exchange between the two regions. And, as we shall see, in the 1960s, a large Traveller’s community established its own arts and crafts society, the Traveller Arts Association.In the Museum of Modern Art, the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, the distinction between artist and museum becomes blurred. In the Museum of Modern Art, the boundaries between the artist and the viewer are considerably</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In the early twentieth century, the North was the main site of European voyages, and today both museums house exhibitions about the North. The North is the site of the highest birth and death rates, and the lowest life expectancy, of any region. The twenty-first century is shaping up to be the North's century. In the twenty-first century, the North is going to become the epicentre of an intergovernmental, multilateral movement to restore balance to a region that has for centuries been at odds with itself. In the twenty-first century, the North is going to be asked to undertake a massive cultural reclamation project that will, if all goes well, lead to the establishment of a new kind of tourism industry based on the new found wealth generated by a region that is beginning to feel more like a nation. The North is not at the centre of this new narrative of tourism, but its recovery is a story that must be told.  One can only imagine what this economy will</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In my opinion, the north is the place where the exchange of ideas, cultural exchange and so on takes place. The Museum of Modern Art has a very good toolkit of cultural resources, including works from the collections of the British Museum and the British Library, as well as materials and inspiration from the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne. The Museum of Modern Art has a small collection of photography, although its collection is very specific: it includes works by and about artists from the North as well as works from other parts of the world. For the British Museum and the British Library, this meant acquiring images from the British Library that were not already in the hands of museums from that part of the world; for the British Museum and the British Library, this meant acquiring images from museums from other parts of the world that had images from the North. In both the Sorbonne and the Museum of Modern Art, the exchange of cultural resources takes place on a global basis, and so this category clearly</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In 2015, a mass exodus of people, mainly from China, were trying to reach the Greek island of Lesbos from the mainland. As a result, the island became the subject of a major Greek island closure. In 2017, a second island closure was put in place. During these two closures, the size and shape of the migrant flows has been closely monitored. As a consequence, the number of refugees arriving in Greece has been closely monitored. When the second island closure in 2017 was put in place, it became necessary to resettle large numbers of refugees in mainland Greece and Italy. In doing so, an unprecedented number of flights were diverted from the island of Samos to the mainland. In doing so, the number of refugees arriving in Italy per day has been significantly reduced. When the third island closure in 2017 was put in place, it became necessary to resettle even more refugees in Italy and Greece. In doing so, the number of refugees arriving in Italy per day dropped significantly. During these three</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In the twentieth century, the mass media portrayed the connections between science and modern art, and between the East and the West; between the industrial and postindustrial forms of development; between the West and the information technologies of social media; and between the North and the information technologies of language. But the biennial has come a long way since these media were invented, and its increasing use today confirms the media representations of contemporary life as anything but smooth, pre-scientific. The biennial has become the global icon of contemporary experience, and its status as a transient exhibitionary form has become a source of political and symbolic weight. In many cities, the biennial is the only form of cultural exchange between people of the same generation and people of very different generations. In other words, the biennial forms the spatial and temporal terrain of the contemporary in such a way as to capture the collective experience of the encounter of the contemporary with the contemporaneous.‘Tiny Houses’ becomes a tool for the symbolic</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In 1990, for instance, the Jubilee Line opened in Liverpool, and the Skyway in Anglia Ruskin; the European-style ‘Curtains’ that separated the collector from the tourist group was replaced by a system that separated the collector and the traveller. The fact that the Jubilee Line and Skyway cruises through heavily populated areas such as Liverpool, Liverpool, and to a lesser extent Southampton, has become a tourist drawcard. In doing so, it has become increasingly difficult to distinguish between a museum and a Skyway, or between a museum and a cruise ship.This kind of tourism categorisation is becoming increasingly important in the North. In 1990, for example, the North East Asia Triennial was held in Liverpool, and over half the attendance was from there. In 2015, the Venice Biennale began a branch in Liverpool, and the Liverpool Museum of Art is planning to build a dedicated section dedicated to North European art. In a city such as Liverpool, which</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In the two weeks that the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne held an exhibition of their respective collections, a new and important category of visitors – tourists from other cities – came to Paris. These visitors were not drawn by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North, but by museums in their respective cities, exhibiting the artworks from the North that had been selected for permanent display in their respective collections. And these artists were not chosen randomly, but by a holistic, ‘collectors’' criteria that takes into account both the city and the people who live there. The Museum of Modern Art chose the artist Carmen Magnani for its Traveller’s Room, while the Sorbonne chose Guilhem, and both galleries selected artists from their respective regions to show in their respective spaces. The fact that these galleries chose artists from different regions may reflect the fact that different regions have different biennials – and different biennials – with different needs</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne, is also a monument to the economic logic of modernism.The other half of the equation is that of the visitor, whose identity is increasingly defined by the destination city or region that he or she chooses to explore. The Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne’s North are able to draw a clear, appealing distinction between visitors from the North and visitors from other parts of the world. In the Museum of Modern Art, the museum-like building that houses the European collections, visitors from the North are categorised alongside those from other parts of the world. In the Sorbonne, the Traveller’s Room is the only category that is represented. In the North, the distinction is even truer: the visitors from the North are grouped in with visitors from other parts of the world, while those from other parts of the world are grouped together. This distinction has become increasingly important in the past fifteen years. In 2015, a record number of people visited the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne in Paris. In another 2015 survey, over 11,000 people, or approximately eight-hundred of them foreign tourists, visited the Museum of Modern Art in New York and the Sorbonne in Paris. In the current survey, nearly nine-hundred of them, or approximately four-hundred of them French, visited the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne in New York and the Museum of Modern Art in Paris. In both these surveys, the North was the dominant region represented, with visitors from the North accounting for nearly half the total. The North is the only region with which the Museum of Modern Art and the Sorbonne have a topical, ongoing exchange.The museum of modern art in New York and the Sorbonne in Paris are the only two museums in the world to offer an exhibition of contemporary art from each city. This exhibition has become a fixture at the North American</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion
    <text>The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion  References  Annex: Indexes + bibliographies  [1] Bauman, John. 1984. The End of Postmodernism. New York: Picador.  [2] Hayek, John. 1939. The Intellectuals Who Killed Postmodernism. New York: New Harbinger.  [3] Ben-Tovim, Joseph. 1984. The End of Depression. New York: Harper &amp; Row.  [4] DeLong, Joseph. 1994. The Shock Doctrine. New York: Harper &amp; Row.  [5] Volkow, Thomas. 2009. The Crisis of the City: New York and the Politics of Abandonment. New York: Columbia University Press.  [6] Holt, Curtis P. 1984. Subsidiarity and Urban Futures. New York: Vintage.  [7] Weaver, Mary. 1989. </text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now. It enables us to imagine possibilities beyond the quantifiable, allowing us to imagine futures of meaning and possibilities beyond the sites of human endeavour.  Instrumental – instrumental meaning is a shared term among a range of people with a shared set of values and norms. It’s a concept that is both predictable (how one should act in relation to another) and that is ambiguous (who or what should be chosen?). In other words, it’s a difficult concept to define, let alone master.  In a recent interview, Philippe RahmJade Eco Park, the mixed-use district that includes the former site of the International Monetary Fund, and includes offices for the World Trade Organization and the United Nations, is a prime candidate for the future site of</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to see how contemporary technological innovation interacts with the world in such a way as to produce new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  The co-production of ideas and technologies is a powerful enabler of the contemporary condition, enabling us to see how much of the technological transformation we actually cause is due to the co-production of ideas and technologies, and how much is due to the interaction between humans and those around us.  The technology that underlies our cars, phones, computers, TVs and internet is a ‘world’ in which we do not yet fully comprehend.  An example of the former was shown off at the 2011 Mobile World Congress in Barcelona. In the car, images of mountains and distant objects stream through the windshield, while audio cues from the radio and infotainment systems crackle through the cabin. In another demonstration, engineers at Hyundai Motor</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion  Conclusion  Conclusion  Authorship remains uncertain, but it’s clear that the project had a major impact on the city, and its future shape. The  	cover story in The New York Times on the project, and the article in The New York Review of Books on the  	future city, both suggest that the project represented an ideal future for New York. The paper featured renderings of what the future might hold, based on the contributions of a broad range of artists and civic leaders. The renderings were accompanied by a series of stories, each a variation on the theme ‘Please, Don’t Build Here’. Stories included nostalgic descriptions of the past, such as one by American artist Frank Lloyd Wright, who proposed that the Statue of Liberty be taken down to make way for a new York City skyscraper; in another story, a Jamaican artist named Donato Duran proposes that the Empire be dismantled in favor of a new New York City</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now. It enables us to imagine possibilities beyond the control of prevailing ideologies and dominant practices, capable of resolving contradictions and giving meaning to contradictions. It also enables us to imagine new worlds and encounter unexpected encounters, unexpected journeys and encounters.  1   	Timothy Mitchell, ‘Rethinking Imperial Histories: The Rise and Fall of the West, 1680–1920’,  	Westport, CT: Praeger, 2000.  2  Jacobi, Dictatorship of the Intellectuals. New York: Vintage, 1988, p. 13.  3  Jacobi, Dictatorship of the Intellectuals. New York: Vintage, 1988, p. 14.  4  Jacobi, Dictatorship</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion  References  Funding Sources  1  Environment News Service, ‘Sea Level Rise | Environment News Service’, http://ens-new.com/2012/09/sea-level-rise-environment-news-service-1.72045.html (accessed September 2018). 2  Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Crisis of Environmentalism: Richard Florida’s Game Change’,  	Geographical Research Letters 	Vol. 33, No. 1/2, 2008, p.109–16. 3  Climate Research 	,  	here  	http://www.crunchbase.com/article/200803303006.php?ref=schedule&amp;month=November&amp;day=1&amp;week=1&amp;day=&amp;week=&amp;day=&amp;month=&amp;year=&amp;year=&amp;week=1 (accessed November 2018). 4  The Texas Commission</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion  A possible resolution to the present predicament of the increasingly marginalised and transformed urban citizen is a part of the project's conceptualisation process. In a future city, a task force of designers could make creative, if unworkable, adaptations of existing infrastructure to cater to the shifting needs of an increasingly urbanised metropolis. This would require imagination, creativity and the ability to think abstract ideas into being. It would assume a certain amount of political will and connections between the urban and the metropolis, but above all, an understanding of the complexities and differences that still exist between the two. The metropolis is changing, but the city is not yet fully modernised. The potential benefits and challenges of this are vast, and a future with increased access to resources would be a most valuable geopolitical position. However, the metropolis is experiencing a demographic revolution, and the future with a highly mobile population is an uncertain world. The future with a reduced or mobile population would mean a decline in geopolitical influence,</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion  A possible resolution to our social problem of inequality and conflict might be to recognise that we’re part of the same species, and to treat the other as an object of our social science data, empowering the other with new legal and political constructions that make us part of something greater. This would mean recognising the other as a species, and allowing that other to progress towards its full potential.  One final aspect of ‘speciesism’ that comes to mind is the one about the fittest, or the fittest before any other, before any other, before any other. In the case of inequality and conflict, this could mean recognising that humans are made up of many different species, and allowing them to mingle together in ways that are as likely to create harmony as conflict, and to offer those other species a place in that ecosystem that they’re part of. This is the second part of our ‘In Defense of Suffering’ series. The</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion: Decentering of Intangible Human Assets Through Artful Mischief  Conclusion:  Artful Mischief  Artful Mischief is a mischievous turn of phrase, coined in the mid-1990s by Norman Brown in response to the proliferation of computer software and the explosion of graphic user interfaces (GUIs). Brown theorised that the spread of software was disrupting the traditional role of the artist as facilitator, artistically speaking. Instead of writing scripts, artists were creating worlds and instigating stories through interface design. Such worlds were imbued with features of culture, and could be read by both mainstream and underground media, making them aesthetically pleasing and socially effective.Brown was a proponent of the notion that art was subversive because it challenged existing ideas and systems, and that critical art would come from those who understood the consequences of new technologies. But as the social impact of new media becomes increasingly clear, it’s becoming increasingly difficult to understand how the arts can be used to challenge</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the idea that the future is a good place, but it’s also a prediction, and ‘a prediction’ is a powerful sedative. The project was originally titled Institutions for a Different Tomorrow, and its subtitle fits that well. I.T.E. is an idea or set of conditions that enable the future to be better than the present. It’s the capacity of the human imagination, its capacity for imagination, capable of envisioning a better future. In short, it’s the capability of ideas. In other words, the future is not a given, and creating innovative ways to alter the future is a way of enabling the future, not stopping it from coming to be what it should be.  The idea of the co-production of effects and futures, then, is a way to understand the logic of current and future social change, able to generate new ways of organising social life and creating meaning in the here and now.  Conclusion  A possible resolution to the present moment is a possibility, perhaps, to engage with the questions raised by the project. But such a possibility requires a resolution to the question of how to live together in harmony, and how to cope with the uncertainty generated by technological change. If we can learn to live together more sustainably, perhaps we can create more harmoniously, more meaningfully, and perhaps most importantly, create more meaningfully, too.  The project that I co-founded, Technosustainability Inc., has been developing policies and strategies to support culturally engaged production of eco-systems through collaborative research, creative writing, and participatory public work. We collaborate with partners at research-intensive institutions, municipal governments, foundations, grassroots organizations and academia to identify critical technologies and collaborative practices that can disrupt existing industries of value and pave the way for new industries. We also collaborate with partners at non-profit and charter sector scale on research and educational initiatives that leverage existing infrastructure and science resources to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice
    <text>a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice, Arsenale, MoMA, Tate Modern, John Lennon’s grave, the Tate Visitor Centre, the London Zoo, the Tate Modern garden, the Sydney Opera House, the Stratford-upon-Avon horse and cart park, and the Barbican Arts Centre. The importance of this form of cultural tourism has become increasingly overstated, but the biennial remains an important entry point into the artworld. 	Arguably, the original, wild and untested biennial form began to give way to the regulated and controlled curatorial gesture, which became the norm. The introduction of artworks by curators from different countries, particularly those from developing countries, in the same biennial, and the consequent proliferation of art galleries and museums around the world, was a precondition for the development of nations around the biennial, and the subsequent spread of the form. Although these curatorial gestures may have their idiosyncratic features and distinguishing characteristics, they are in fact</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice or Barcelona or Athens or Basel (in the EU) or New York (in the US). It is also a form of cultural exchange between cultures, and the trip is much more about the individual, with cultural tourism often suggesting a return to the place where one finds one’s cultural selves. In these cases, the cultural tourism entity is more like a company, and its activities more like a portfolio. It promotes the continuity of identity, belonging to the locality, and links the locality to other places and cultures. It has a language of its own, and ‘its’ own form of culture is precisely what makes it such a powerful language.’[7] Such language is deeply imbued with notions of belonging, belongingness, belongingness, and the like, and it is this very embeddedness that is at stake in the contention between biennials and tourism today. In the current transaction of tourist experiences, the biennial is but a transient phenomenon, a</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice or New York for exchange between cultures. It is a form of cultural exchange, in which the cultural tourism operator engages with local people in ways that are culturally responsive to the locality, but also with sites in between. Cultural biennials are rare in most cities, although New York and London have recently revived them, often with great fanfare and public investment. In the US, New York Arts Biennale returned in 2016 with a three-month, $50 million programme, while the LA Biennale resurrected the institution in 2017 for a $75 million, 10-year institution-building initiative. 	In recent years, there has been a push towards biennials in places such as cities, where they are more readily identified, more readily measurable, and more readily exchangeable – commodities that can be had, often in large quantities, in exchange for intangible assets such as cultural commodities. The expectation is that when exchange takes place between cultures, it will involve people from these different cultures,</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice, and in the associated business of cultural tourism. In these sectors, the biennial has become a regular visitor and a regular commerce item. In these forms, it is no exaggeration to say that the biennial is the universal art museum. It provides a permanent record of what is usually thought to happen in and through art’s temporal domain: exhibitions, encyclopedias, and collections. It is an art form that belongs in a museum, and one that can and should be developed into a museum. This is true even though biennials have become much more socially conscious and prominent in recent decades, as well as in places such as Liverpool and Berlin with their ‘cultural tourism’ programmes. 	But there are limits to what a biennial can accomplish in its present form. It cannot book in-person series, quantity, quality, or location, and it cannot create an instigation that builds long-term relationships between art and people. It is true that bienn</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice and Saab and then works in related industries such as retail or communications. The biennial is a double-edged sword. On the one hand, it is a form of cultural consumption that is easily quantified and can therefore be quantified as ‘good’, if quantified at all. On the other, it is a cultural form that is inherently unstable and subject to the whims of changing economic, cultural and political conditions. 	The biennial has recently become entwined with the ever-larging and diversifying museums and art institutions that are their products, including the proliferating of curatorial styles, new media, multi-media shows, and an ever-expanding collection of archive collections. Curators are reporting with increasing frequency of art's return to the biennial form, although little rigorous research has been done on this.[7] 	Yet biennials are not, as we might initially assume, completely immune from this era of capitalism. As bienn</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice or Shanghai for several thousand dollars. With the exception of a few idiosyncratic curatorial styles, such as the ‘Big Archive’ series, which seek to capture the essence of a place in an artful way, the biennial has become the norm. 	In places where it is rare or impossible to visit, such as the Middle East or North Africa, the biennial offers a rare opportunity to see a cultural phenomenon for yourself. This is particularly true for people from the regions where such experiences are rare or impossible to access. In such cases, the biennial offers a rare window to a different kind of experience: the ‘smooth-talking’ of the local, or the ‘sincerity’ of a more traditional tourist. 	In a recent study, I interviewed a number of artists, curators, and architects who were present at the Venice Biennale as guests or participants in a gala, ‘[a] group’s</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice or San Francisco for a fee. In such cases, the art is often paired with a ‘bright new experience’.[7] Such is the transactional, capitalizing nature of the biennial, which is often underestimated, under-accounted, and misunderstood by its clientele. The beauty of the biennial, at least in its current form, is that it operates at a distance, as a double-edged sword. It generates much needed exposure to a place, but at the same time it can be quite transient and transient experiences, lacking in the power of its author or producer. 	The biennial has its critics, of course. Some of its projects have been commercially unprofitable, and its market research has been poor. Still, the biennial has had a great impact on popular imagination and imagination, and it is this power that its biennial board exercises today, generating or shaping content and imagination of various kinds. 	The biennial is a multi</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice, The Sopranos, and Breaking Bad, to name only a few. In these instances, the biennial is a major artistic event that draws artists to the city, often through its transient character, and creates an experience similar to that associated with a biennial, but with a different scale, sometimes generating its own form of excitement and sometimes creating a stir. 	The biennial is a spectacular art form; its attention to form and substance is what makes it seem contemporary, even modern. In recent years, this attention to form has led to extravagant, sometimes illegal, exhibitions, such as the recent, profligate, butchery-free, Ponte City, Ponte, Emilia Romagna, and the 2014 Venice Biennale, which added billions to the value of the Italian art market. However, in its focus on the city and its experience, and its use of eminent domain to acquire, tax, and regulate assets, the biennial has often acted as a censor</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice or Mexico City, often with a cultural twist. In 2014, Hurtado curated the first ever Venice Biennale. He is a leading figure within the biennial movement and has been a regular commentator on various television and radio programs. He is also co-curator of the 17th Italian Edition of the Venice Biennale, due to open in December 2015, and a regular lecturer and presenter of the biennial’s online platform, as well as a curator of the Australian and New Zealand Centennial Curators Service. He is a fellow of the American Cultural Association, a special advisor to the New York Museum, and a curator for the American Anthropological Association, where he has been since 2006.[7] When not curating, he is an adjunct curator for the Museum of Modern Art, where he has exhibited widely including at the Venice Biennale, the Whitney Museum of American Art, New York Public Library, Philadelphia Museum of Art, and the Harry Benjamin Museum</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the curator, the artist, and the organisation’s board of directors. This was the model that was developed in the UK and other countries that have similar legislation, although with slightly different systems and governance. This bi-annual model provides a continuous register of ‘what’s happening in the world’, contributing to a more comprehensive understanding of contemporary culture. In the US, this is referred to as the ‘Jeff Bezos Model’.[6] And it is to a large extent a response to the cultural capitalism of the 1990s that we must now contend. 	The biennial is an important cultural form today. In places where it is still widespread (New York and London are exceptions), it is a main artistic form, often used to show off, publicise, and sometimes to generate national or international excitement. In recent years, this has been accentuated in the cultural tourism sector, which arranges long-term stays in places such as Venice or Tokyo for as little as possible. Biennials offer different forms of cultural exchange, often occurring in a context of cultural consumption, and the exchange is often mediated through the use of curating, the art market, or grassroots art. In the biennial, the curatorial, artist, and audience work hand in hand to explore themes of the exhibition and make connections with each other and with the wider urban environment. 	The biennial is a multi-generational cultural form that emerged around 1980 in Europe and North America. It began with the Venice Biennale (1980), then expanded to include exhibitions in cities in Australia, New Zealand, and South Africa. It has a particular relationship to the North American urban environment because these cities are the birthplace of the film and television production that is dependent on the Venice Biennale. 	The biennial has a life of their own, rarely unchanging, fiercely imaginative, ever-changing, and often unrepeatable. The exhibitionary</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dial
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dialects are a ubiquitous and powerful tool with which to fight linguistic over-simplification, but they also have an essential relationship: they are made up of elements from many roots, and in many cases, of many different origins. In this way, they reflect the inaccessibility of historical events, and their relations to contemporaneous people and places. Dialects also have a  function that often goes unnoticed or unspoken: they are used as a device to consider certain things in relation to others. For example, in the dialects of the early twentieth century, the idea of national identity was constantly contested, with different forms of nationalism arising along with different sets of epithets (such as ‘Camel’), which were occasionally added to denote nations or groups. Today, one might add, there is much critical discussion of the supposed effects of migrant flows in the United States, but little discussion, aside from the occasional populist nationalism, of what it means for a nation</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dialects span different worlds, often describing aspects of the same world. For example, in Russian, the авт�ородексендев is often translated as ‘Chinese food’.  As a synonym, ‘ТМНЕНИИНИНИНИНИНИНИН’, or ‘world’, is a verb meaning ‘to dwell in’.  Dialects also have a root, an object, which is a mapping from root to object in English: the root of English is ‘meaning something’, and the root of Russian is ‘meaning something’.  So if the root of English is ‘meaning something’, and the root of Russian is ‘meaning something’, English and Russian share the</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dialects also come in pairs: en and nu, root words, root phrases. An en element in its root word, nu in root phrase. Sometimes a root word includes an adverb: ‘All Europeans’, as in ‘English’. Adjectives and adverbs are frequent in the root word, as in ‘All American’, ‘All Chinese’, ‘All French’, ‘All German’, ‘All Italian’, ‘All Japanese’, ‘All Malay’s, ‘All Norwegian’s, ‘All Polish’s, and ‘All Spanish’s, to mention only a few). Adjectives and adverbs are also found in the root of Arabic words, such as ‘أَلْلْلَّةُوَ يَسْلِّ Caliph’</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dialects also have root ‘terms’ – terms that refer to places, people, or things – and root words that refer to the same thing, person, or thing. For instance, in Russian, Нэнементять (ru) means tree or forest; in German, it refers to the root of a tree. Dialects also have roots that extend further back in time: the root “нементять (eht) in English means &quot;before or before the end”.  The root “нементять (eht) in English means &quot;before or before the end”.   In Russian, the root “нементять (eht) can take on many different forms: Мнементять (eht) in the nominative case, �</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dialects allow us to name certain relationships between words or phrases. For instance, in English we can say that something is common to both English and Russian, and this ability to name things like ‘English’ and ‘Russian’ is one reason why we can say that something is common to both English and Spanish, and why we can also say that something is common to both Chinese and Arabic languages.  Another reason is that dialects allow us to translate other words or phrases into words or phrases that are similar to words or phrases in another dialect. For instance, when English speakers in different parts of the country use the same verb, we can choose to translate it as ‘baked goods’, or alternatively, ‘goods made in China’.  Another reason why English is the universal language of the human species is that we are all exposed to it in one way or another: through language, cultural immersion or otherwise.  Though it may be challenging to</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dialects date back to ancient Greece, and while they’re no longer the sole preserve of the Greek language devolutionary complex, their proliferation is part of a global trend. In fact, out of the 5,000 or so languages that make up the World Wide Web, over 3,500 are dialects of one language. Dialects are used as evidence in legal proceedings, as evidence of common origins (how common are roots, exactly?), and as a kind of backdoor language that linguists can discover through historical and anthropological research.  And just as with roots and languages, there’s the rub: common roots are only as valid as the next lexicon of variations. If one root is believed to be valid, variations on it will inevitably follow. This is why root words become so influential: because they’re believed to be common, and because everyone agrees that they’re true.  So what can dialects do to us? Well, there</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dialects date back thousands of years, and while they’re still common in print nowadays, they were new to vernacular vernaculars, whose root words date back even further.  The root of ‘Italian’ (and later ‘French’) is Latin; hence, ‘Italian’ is a root language of sorts, evolving alongside the ‘root languages’ that comprise it.  And speaking of roots, the modern Italian is an epicentre of linguistic and archaeological finds from all over the world, with roots in Africa, Asia and Europe that date back thousands of years. So, there was a natural progression from the origins of modern Italian to the origins of all those other languages that also came out of the same root.  And then, as a final touch, there’s this whole other layer of languages that came out of that same root, and that’s just the human family. Human languages descend from the</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dialects also have a lexicon (a list of roots) that identifies the individuals who contribute to the dialects, languages, and phrases. This list is a record of the interactions among individuals – names and epithets – that influence how a root word in a given clause is translated into another, related term or phrase. For example, the root word for ‘fire’ in ‘fire and blood’ is translated as ‘fiery things’ – a more literal translation of ‘fire and blood’ (which brings with it a noun).  Another example – one that I borrowed from a remark Margaret Chanpong Mok – is the use of a single root word in conjunction with multiple phrases. In Malayalam, a root word that derives from 「bharat mula’ (tree),’ means anything that stands in for Hinduism, and the adjective form of the root word describes what the object of that admiration is. In</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dialects also have an identity, a root or root phrase that identifies the root of the verb of a root phrase. For example, the root word for ‘clover’ in ‘English’ is ‘clover’, which in turn is a combination of root words such as ‘chrysanthemum’ and ‘sown seeds’.  Finally, ‘English’ has three root words, which in turn are ‘chosen’, ‘knew’ and ‘pleased’.  So, ‘English’ has three dialects: the official English, non-official English and a hybrid of the official and non-official English.  The non-official English is spoken by about 180 million people in nine of the largest British cities: London, Birmingham, Liverpool, Manchester, Glasgow, Taipei and São Paulo.  The official English is spoken by about 3.5</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: the future is a (possibly infinite) set of possible futures. But this is just the beginning.  The idea of the autonomous machine has been around for a while, dating back to Lord Acton’s Encyclopaededia Britannica (1932), but with the advent of computer programming, and programming languages, the floodgates opened up even further. Now there are over 5,000 recognized language models, each with its own unique syntax and vocabulary, and each with its own unique semantics. Each one of these is a dialect of another, and as a dialect has its own vernacular.  A dialect is a group of related languages that share a common root, such as ‘Czech’ or ‘Russian’. Each of these has its own unique root word, either an adjective (like ‘Ch’ruk’) or a noun (like ‘Razda’).  Dialects allow us to identify specific root objects, or root objectsifierily similar root objects, in a group of root objects. For example, in English we might say that something is ‘rooted in the English language’. And the root object is English: English is rooted in the English language. And this is how we can think of languages as ‘systems’, identifying specific objects with particular root objects. And that is how we can think of language as a ‘system’, identifying specific root objects with particular objects.Now, there are many other ways of putting this, not least, in relation to natural language processing: grammar, lexicon, and the like. But here, we see that there is a marked difference between the syntactic systems of root objects and object systems. Syntax is the point where the root and object ‘interact’; interactivity means what happens when the two meet. Object systems are the point where</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe.
    <text>might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe. The aim of this initiative was to demonstrate that Community Arts practice is relevant and influential, and that it is possible to build trust and infrastructure through a collaborative process involving artists, local people, the local community and arts institutions. We considered how art institutions can work with local communities to achieve transformative change, both at the level of the local environment and of institutional levels. Building Trust and InfrastructureThrough our research and development process, We Are Here to Stay (2009-2015), the Local Government Art Trust (2010-ongoing), as well as the ongoing Constructive Thinking Cities project, we sought to build trust and infrastructure through relationships that are mutually beneficial. The relationship between art institutions and communities was seen as a fundamental opportunity for collaboration and empowerment. However, trust and infrastructure are not mutually exclusive preconditions and artists, community organisers and local people had to work together in order to achieve a change. In order to have</text>
    <text>might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe. The aim of the project is to bring together, a community of artists, local people and art institutions to work together, experiment, and oversee the way we produce, use and manage our local art resources. The collection was produced in phases over five years, with phases producing a multiple of five, based on the artist’s and organisation’s needs. The policy of the collection was to be produced in tandem with the biennial, with phases producing collections and exhibitions. The policy changed in stages, and now the art institutions plan and produce their own exhibitions. We envision a world in which art biennials interact with their local communities, and engage with their neighbourhoods, and where art biennials produce collections and exhibitions in their neighbourhood communities. We believe that the collections and exhibitions we produce will be, like the biennials, local, and will be local, but will also be, like the bienn</text>
    <text>might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe. The aim was to connect the arts with the lived realities of local communities, in an attempt to create a bridge between the arts and the lived realities of everyday life. The collection has since then gathered international acclaim and been exhibited in venues such as Walt Disney World, Tokyo Museum, Glasgow and Museum of Modern Art in New York.The LocalCommunityLand League was formed to bring the artists, arts organisations, community organisers and artists' groups who were part of the project Open School 2 to create a shared vocabulary and understanding of the neighbourhood.The LocalCommunityLand League was an evidence-based strategy to create a shared vocabulary and understanding of the neighbourhood in an area through engagement with art institutions in the area. It was developed and led by Wendy Harpe, Artistic Director of the Open School 2, and involved a number of artists and arts institutions including Dawn White, Chair of the Arts Council, Charlie </text>
    <text>might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe. The aim of the  CommunityLand League was to celebrate the rich and dynamic history of the area through mementos left behind by the houses built on the former park site. The collection was presented at a series of public events including the annual park presents, which were also co-chaired by the artist Sandy Volz and the Community Land Trust. The collection has since evolved into a non-profit organisation, which has exhibitions at venues such as the Chisenhale Gallery, Liverpool and Liverpool Biennial in Doha, and is currently developing a full-fledged biennial programme.We are interested in the way in which art, community and art institutions are able to work together. We believe that the power to transform a location, such as an area, into something new and different resides in the people who live there and in the art institutions who regularly work there. Thus, the introduction of new artworks or actively inviting art to existing art institutions</text>
    <text>might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe.The goal of the Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was to combine the art and practical work of the artists with the curatorial work of art institutions and the muralist institution making the plans for the area. The collection was produced in stages starting with the 2010 Stanley M. McChrystal International Muralist Conference, then expanding to include an exhibition at the Muralists Institute New York, and continuing with a series of workshops at the Liverpool Muralist Conference. The initial Connecting the LocalCommunityLand collection was distributed internationally through MuralisL.A.C.U. and funded by a grant from Arts Council England. The Community Land League was also supported by a partnership agreement with Welsh Streets Media (formerly known as The Chronicle of Higher Education) and Arts Council England. The two organisations are listed separately in the joint statement</text>
    <text>might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe. The aim of the Community Land League, at its inception, was to celebrate the rich past of the area and to point to the way art can work in the future. We believe that this approach is necessary in order to tackle the challenges of the present, because if we allow the present to define the future, we risk losing the very sites that make us proud to be British. The challenge for the Community Land League is to find ways to work with communities in order to produce new art and engage with the past, whilst also raising money for the local arts community.Funding for the CLT was raised through a combination of individual gifts, corporate sponsorships and the Supporting Local Artists scheme. The CLT has assisted in the production of two public exhibitions, 2010 Liverpool Biennial and 2011 Dolphin show, both at F.W. Bond, both of which have gone well. The funding for the two public exhibitions has come from individuals, foundations, trade</text>
    <text>might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe. It was a way to demonstrate that the Biennial’s portfolio, while containing works from many different places, was anchored in a shared history. This was a starting point for deeper research and development, and the creation of Local Community Land League.The development of the Biennial into a multi-year, locally-conceived art institution started in 2011. We set out to find a way to engage with, and perhaps even to contribute to the creation of, the future of art through art in the present. We asked: what can the Biennial do in the present? In other words, could it create an alternative or help shape a future? The collection was curated to a degree so that it was possible to identify and highlight works that would be relevant to the present, and to a certain extent to future generations. The collection was developed in collaboration with the Welsh Streets Community Land Trust and the Dolphin Arts Centre, Liverpool University, and the </text>
    <text>might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe. The aim of the project was to create a public realm of engagement and reflection via collaborative research, production and exhibition that engages with the role and culture of the local in shaping cultural landscapes and the enactment of local strategies for the future of their area. The collection was presented at the Liverpool and Bournemouth Biennials in 2011 and 2012, and The Community Land League 2011.The project was also supported by grants from the Arts Council and the HMRI and the HMPS 2012 Strategic Regional Grant for Arts and Community Development. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was officially launched in 2013. Our mission statement explains how the collection emerged, and what we hope to achieve in the future: to give voice to the residents of the area to be preserved, to the become aware of the role played by local people in shaping cultural landscapes, to create a sense of culture and identity for the area through work such as Community Arts, to take</text>
    <text>might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe.In 2008, The LocalHomebaked Project was started, taking the project beyond the art institutions and creating a local participatory hub for the art and community to come and engage with the project. The project was co-curated by Nina Edge and Sally Tallant and Wendy Harpe.In 2012, Connecting the Local community Land Trust was formed, with Nina Edge as acting director and Sally Tallant as acting co-director. The organisation is a non-profit organisation, incorporated in 2015 and registered in the UK Second Chamber. The Second Chamber is the highest court of the UK, responsible for ensuring that treaties made under British law are honoured, and that legislation passed by the British government fulfils its legal obligations. In 2016, the United Kingdom voted to leave the European Union. The Local Government Art Commission was established in 2018 to deliver legislation and policies in support of and in coordination with Connecting the Local</text>
    <text>might be curated through local artists and organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial as well as overseas, but we believe that the key to unlocking the potential of places like Anfield and Anfield Home Tours is a network approach, between local people and networks such as the Liverpool Biennial, the Liverpool Public Theater, Mountain Arts, Glasgow Art Gallery and others.Local people take matters of their neighbourhoods, and sometimes their own neighbourhoods, in their own hands. We see this in the form of locally-sourced art, activism or mural painting. We believe that the power to create, is in fact in the hands of local people. We hope this intervention will encourage other art institutions in the area to follow suit. Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was launched in 2010 to bring together artists, local people and art institutions to produce and present a joint, locally-focused collection of works. The collection was curated by Joasia Krysa and Wendy Harpe.The Connecting the LocalCommunityLand League was founded in 2014 by Wendy Harpe, artist, educator and co-founder of Liverpool Community Land Trust. The league was launched in collaboration with Dolphin Arts and Dutch artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, with the Joasia Krysa Fund for Art and Social Change at Liverpool John Moores University. The Liverpool Community Land Trust is a not-for-profit corporation established in 2002 and is responsible for the care and management of approximately 2.4 million acres of publicly owned and managed public land in and around Liverpool. The Liverpool Community Land Trust was founded in partnership with Dolphin Arts, with the mission to foster dialogue and understanding between local people and the Community Land Trust. The Liverpool Community Land Trust is a not-for-profit corporation established in 2002 and is responsible for the care and management of approximately 2.4 million acres of publicly owned and managed public land in and around</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event,
    <text>might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event, it is a public place, it is a marketplace, and it is a marketplace for ideas. It is a global visual arts exchange occurring simultaneously in ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. It is an ideal venue for the post-2006 curatorial agenda and a site for the curatorial excesses to gild the vanity of contemporary art and celebrity. The curatorial, however, is not the only audience for the art to emerge from the Global Context. The art of the near-future may also be found in the near-present, and the art of the present in the instant that follows the zodiac sign that produced it. The concept of the ‘global’ was developed through Kierkegaard’s writing in the wake of the Protestant Reformation.1 Kierkegaard’s concept of the cosmic theme park became the basis for an ethical and political critique of industrial capitalism.2 The cosmic image was understood as the ultimate</text>
    <text>might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event, a ‘showpiece’ that serves to anchor the current exhibitionary and curatorial agenda in the immediate vicinity of the major projects of the exhibitionary programme. It is the object of a ‘category design’, a kind of rhetorical sleight of hand that pretends to inspect all aspects of a subject, but which, to be precise, watches over its actions. The Global Context is a system that allows the subject to behave, but it also pretends to conceal or obscure its own actions. This kind of political double-bind is common to art and contemporary design; it is easy to see how an art exhibition, or a kind of curatorial gesture, paired with a kind of cultural or urban movement could be harnessed to meet a demand or serve an interest of a local community. It is art, but it is also a kind of cultural curation, and the artist or curator is asked to engage with that context of art and contemporary life in order to work through</text>
    <text>might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event, it is a trace, it is a website. It is a live exhibit, threaded together many different elements into one place. It is a cultural artifact, a collection of texts and images. It is a live event, and it is a cultural product. The key, perhaps, is that understanding which comes with understanding. In that case, understanding comes from reading and thinking things over in advance, rather than flashing back to a future where abstract thought doesn’t exist. Understanding is a natural by-product of that very present moment in time when the synthesis and emergence of meaning becomes possible, and which is what is happening now, regardless of what we think we know or think we don’t know. 	Both the artist and audience in the Global Context exhibition are given a choice as to how to engage with the artefact. They are given the opportunity to either ‘get caught up in the moment’ or ‘flit between two points of view’.</text>
    <text>might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event, it is a ‘time’, in the sense that it is both contemporary and timeless, in that it is both contemporary in its form and purpose, but also contemporary in its time, that is, in the sense that it is both contemporary in its own right and contemporary in relation to the social. It is an event that is simultaneously contemporary in its temporal conditions and anticipatory of social and cultural change, in that it anticipates but knows very little about the future. 	The title of this report,  	Time to Come, reproduces two phrases from Mona Lisa, the 1960 Nobel Peace Prize winner: ‘Totta l'Ave Maria’ and ‘Et tu, Maria?’ The Time to Come exhibition is the current exhibition sponsor of the Nobel Laureates Club in Oslo. It was also part of the  	Louise L. Alcott Curator Curator of Education and Public Practice at the  	La</text>
    <text>might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event, and the findings, opinions and narratives generated from it shape the future of art and culture. It is an event that, through its curatorial agenda, positions contemporary artmaking as a response to a changing world, and in that process, may represent a new kind of art form. However, in its own way, it is also a comment on the past, and on the ways in which art can and cannot exist in the same form in the future.Art is made up of many forms and multiple mediums, and art is made up of large numbers of different modes of being. Art is a physical and conceptual imposition, and therefore art can be understood as a series of relations. However, one of the functions of art is to create an idealised version of the world around us in which to live and think and experience life in a particular way, and to this end it is imperative that the medium is interpretive, and thus knowledgeable through a number of different modes of being. So the</text>
    <text>might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event, it is a ‘trending’ item, and it is evidence of something going down. But it is also evidence of its own eventuality, in the form of a collection, that is both permanent and temporarily out of date. This is evident in the title, which suggests a more immediate, but also a delayed kind of closure. It is ‘evidence of something going down’, in the sense that it is a statement of things that have happened, but also of things that are yet to happen. As biennials and biennials historically occur in a particular cultural moment, in the social media age, and in any cultural moment, in the temporal register is of paramount importance. It is a temporal register that narrates the social, cultural and political moments of the moment, and, in that sense, is often cited as the most representative register of the social. It records the immediacy and location of the event itself, and the conditions on which</text>
    <text>might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event, and the events in it as a ‘globalized cultural phenomenon’, as the subtitle implies. It is the most recent in a succession of predecessors, all of which followed the same theme of the exhibition: the interconnectedness of all cultures, peoples and worlds. 	Events in the Global Context exhibition are organised in three sections: the first, ‘The Emergence of a Global Contemporary Curriculum’, introduces the curators who assembled the now familiar curatorial toolkit: curatorial departments, academies and […] ‘the collection […] includes material from many different periods, and […] the collection […] represents a, temporality, an […] era, an ideal state of affairs, or a set of relations between people and ideas’.3. The collections committee’s 2006 biennial programme, ‘The End of the World as We Know It’, explored in greater detail the curatorial ambitions of the time. Its subtitle, given that the end of</text>
    <text>might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event, a venue, a platform and a platform for the exhibition of contemporary art in more than one country. With its multiple focal points, it is both a catalyst and a stand-in for the growing number of art collections and museums in several countries, as well as international art fairs and biannual museums. It is also a vehicle for the exhibition of new media and cultural practices. In this, it is similar to contemporary art museums and large-scale art fairs, but with the added dimension of the biennial. The Global Context exhibition is a ‘house’ of multidisciplinary work that engages with the topics and processes of contemporary global culture, and its manifestations in the world as a whole. It is a ‘house’ where art, theory, documentation, art criticism, and archival materials, assemblages, and artefacts can be found, collected and assembled to make work that addresses current concerns and trends of contemporary global culture. It is a ‘house</text>
    <text>might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event, a ‘placeholder’ in the form of a proposal (often accompanied by a video or still) that serves as a springboard to loftier ambitions and ambitions driven by individuals or small groups. It is a ‘bridge construct’ between the city and the suburbs, connecting the utopian to the monstrous. It is a snapshot of a particular moment in time, and a render of a future that is possible only if everyone abides by certain specified conditions. The building that became the site of the Global Context 2017 exhibition was designed by Marino Bernini and Florence Lefebvre, and Meehan Crist, with additional architectural work by Sophie Hope and Joasia Krysa. It is comprised of a proposal of four buildings comprising of a plaza, a university campus, a cultural center, a hotel and a retail complex. The ownership of the parcels is held by a private company called Arsenale and is managed by the London-</text>
    <text>might be curated with a view to producing the most impactful work with the least amount of impact).  	The exhibition, which takes place concurrently with the  	London Gallery Artists Placement Meeting, is an art-historical survey of the forms, technologies and practices of digital culture in the 21st century. It is the largest survey yet of the subjects, surveying over 2,000 artists, 1,500 designers and over 1,000 academics. The subject matter of the survey includes digital technologies, social media, documentary and archival work, pop culture, migration and identity, rural and urban development, and curatorial practices. A Global Context is the title of the exhibition, and the exhibition’s subtitle reflects the fact that it takes place in both ‘global’ and ‘u-dimensional’ dimensions. In the context of contemporary globalisation and the  	near-future, the title is apt. The Global Context exhibition is an event, a ‘big picture’ picture of the world as it is made visible, manifest and present via new media. It is an event that is part of a broader curatorial agenda that seeks to bring contemporary art and contemporary culture to a wider audience. This exhibition is part of this broader agenda, and in that sense it is part of a larger dialectic of contemporaneity, cultural capitalism and social change that is itself part of a larger dialectic of humanity. One can speak of the Global Context or the ‘present’ Global Context, or the ‘present’ Global Context with the shared shared conditions of the emerging and past interrelated, such that we can recognise that ‘now’ is not unknown to all who look on.’ [1] 	Andrea Libertelli, ‘The End of Postmodernity’, Beacon Hill, New York, 1982, p.25. [2] David Harvey, </text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point of departure for archaeological, archival and textual research, and a platform for the installation of new archaeological and archival objects. The three-volume work makes extensive use of photography and traces the development of Bulgarian, Romanian and Italian curatorial approaches to the cities that are the site of the projects. Romanian and Italian curators will be sharing the same space and undertaking the same research and writing, in a collaborative process that seeks to understand how archaeological and curatorial practices intersect to produce and articulate a standing archaeological and curatorial constituency. The curatorial narrative of the project could be read as an indictment of modernism and all its discontents. It is to be hoped that the curatorial narrative of the project will also find a place and time in the pages of the book that follow.With the support of the FCT, the project also received the curatorial endorsement of the Italian Cultural Centre Triennale, Italy’s oldest and largest archaeological and curatorial organisation. The support of the Italian Cultural</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point of departure for curatorial activity and a site for the future of a particular kind of urbanisation. The book will be published in French, German, Italian, Spanish and Russian, and be a major input in the ongoing, three-way, three-way race between the French, Italian and Russian curators, to direct a research project in the future of this dynamic, complex urbanisation, with a view to a possible museum collection. The project is part of a wider research initiative into the social dimensions of urbanisation, part of a wider theme of ‘sharing’ – sharing, sharing, sharing, sharing, in relation to a common destiny, shared future, and in the current and future shape of cities. [1] See the entry Future City: Ljubljana, Brazil. Available at: http://futurecityljubljana.com/index.html (accessed June 2018).  [2] The World Bank</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point of departure for a host of curatorial strategies, directions and interventions.  Culture and Society at a Glance, Adam Szymczyk, 2017. Cover Image: Lajos Lazac. This work was commissioned by and published in the British art journal The British Museum in 2016. In the United States, Szymczyk is the Dean, Higgins R. Santiago, Associate Professor, Artistic Affairs and Director, Center for Art and Culture Research, Columbia University, and a professor in the Artistic Department, M.I.T. He is also the author of the forthcoming Cities at a Glance: The Rise and Fall of New York City’s Architecture. 	[i] Hotwire,  	2013, p. 2. [ii] Stuart Moulthroup, ‘The Mural Renaissance’, in  	Hotwire, Vol. 2, No.1, February, 2013</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point of departure for multiple research and multiple, often overlapping approaches to understand urbanisation in the age of information. As curator, Szymczyk will be entrusted with the ultimate in democratic administration of the city, overseeing the research, the events, the programmes, the stores, the culture, the roads, the harbour and the parks – which are but a few of many different kinds of living, breathing entities – and managing everything, collectively and individually. At the same time, he will be tasked with envisioning the future city, one that is neither a corporate nor a feudal construct, but one that is self-sustaining andpires towards a future city of its own.  Szymczyk’s curatorial approach will be informed by the same considerations that guide contemporary curators of art, journalists, urbanists, archivists and others seeking to create participatory environments – considerations that also inform the making of art events and the journalism of urban growth – but will also</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point of departure and end point for research, a setting for discourse and a tool for the future exploration of a city. 	The book is divided into three parts focusing on the three cities that comprise the site of the proposed future city: Brno, Prague and Kiev. Part one focuses on the city as an object, part two on the city as a site of an imaginary future, and part three will examine the social consequences of a city of anonymous, virtual and virtual spaces. The three parts present a three-fold reading of the city as an interrelated series of phenomena: the historical, the virtual and the qualitative. The initial part (Part One) presents the historical roots of the present in Brno, the city that first housed Kristallnacht (literally &quot;Night of Broken Glass&quot; in German), the abortive 1930 uprising against the Nazis. Part Two: Prague and Kiev (Part Three): Brno and Kiev 	The three cities chosen as future sites for the curatorial portion</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point of departure for modern and contemporary artistic practices, an indispensable object for the modernisation of urban space, and a site of possibility for the future. (C) The Author, the Biennial, 2018. Resolution 2018/2019. © The Author, the Biennial, 2018. Resolution 2018/2019. 	The Biennial is an international, non-profit, arts-centred, multi-institutional art institution based in Bern, Switzerland. The Biennial 2018/2019 will be its eleventh cycle, and it will be its fifteenth in Paris. It will be the site for a number of installations, including new works and works from the past, as well as works that explore the consequences of art and culture for the social, cultural and political conditions of living bodies. It will also host a number of events, including a number of performances, lectures and meetings. The Biennial is a global art institution with an annual budget of more than US$100 million. It was founded</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point of departure for the continued exploration of contemporaneous phenomena and an ultimate, perhaps even an indispensable, object of analysis. Adam Szymczyk has curated numerous exhibitions and events around the world, including major exhibitions in New York and London of the Greek eponymous sculpture, the Kenyan national anthem, the Swiss national hymn, and the Tibetan national anthem. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, the Rwandan national anthem, and the Palestinian national anthem, and was a curator for the Greek and Italian pavilions at the Guggenheim. He has curated numerous exhibitions of contemporary art, including the Ken Saro-Wiwa European Capital of Culture – Part 2: Crisis of Character – Part 1. He is a curator and co-founder of the New Art Gallery, New York, a non-profit organisation that offers space for the permanent exhibition of contemporary art to flourish and to share, present and exchange contemporary artmaking and culture. He is the curator</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point of departure for curatorial explorations, and a possible end point for the narrative that emerges from that process. 	[i] Czech artist, Lubomír Lasnik, originally from Brno, developed his ideas in relation to the urban environment in the wake of the 1968 Paris uprising. Here, he locates the source of the revolt, which he claims is defined by an ideological synthesis between modernism and communism. Lasnik identifies the three pillars of modernism – market, civil society and art – as the means ‘by which the state [is] able to create a social and cultural system that justifies the existing order and reproduces [its] own mortality’.2 In the case of a possible revolution in the system of cities, he concludes, the future society must prepare itself by drawing its social forces into ‘the system of facts and social relations that will permit a socialist future’.3  He goes on to argue that the future</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point of departure for curatorial pursuits and a site for future research. Adam Szymczyk:   The idea came to me one day while walking around with my dad in the neighborhood of Slovakian cities Köln and Brno. The idea was that in order to enjoy the city as much as possible – which is to say, to visit it, buy a house there, live there, make art there, participate in the culture there – you need to know a lot about it. So the neighborhood feels like a giant encyclopedia with all the city’s inhabitants in one place. And when you learn a new thing, you already know it. ‘That’s exactly what I’ve been doing, looking at all the material that’s come out of the area around the arts center. I see art as a very subtle form – you can’t really read into it, like you can with other kinds of art – but it’s</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Szymczyk, who will lead a two-week, six-day, two-newspaper, one-day-only, and one-stop-only curatorial odyssey through Slovakia, Hungary, Serbia, Czech Republic, China, Russia and Egypt. The project, titled Future City, will see Szymczyk's curatorial training and output curating, through a hybrid of curatorial and curatorial activities, the recent legacy of twentieth-century Modernism in Central and Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and the connection with contemporary events, practices and cultures. As a curatorial officer, Szymczyk will be documenting the project in a number of publications, from a single, three-volume, 7,000-page book to a multi-edition, 6,000-page historical collection of curiosities. The book, to be published in 2018, will offer a unified reading of the city as a living, breathing object, a point of departure for exploring in ever greater depths the political, economic, social and cultural landscapes that constitute the contemporary condition. The three sections of the book that will be devoted to the project include (in order of appearance): a chronological survey of the cities of the future city, a description of the processes leading to their future cities (or, in the case of a future science fiction writer, postindustrial coastal ones) and a meditation on the relationship between culture and the digitized urban environment. The second section, Cultural Criticism of the Future City, will survey the cultural projects that will shape its development, focusing particularly on those that spring from the curatorial vision and those that emerge from the curatorial power. The third section, Future Proximity, surveys the relations between science and urbanization in an odyssey through biennials, high-profile exhibitions, and the associated curatorial moves that will shape the city in the next fifty years. [1] See the end of this entry for</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the
    <text>might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the criminalizing effects of contemporary culture (which it perceived as a ‘cultural mono-system’). While there are certainly differences between the two, there are also great similarities: avant garde criticism is often critical of conformist forms of modern art and architecture, while critical nonconformist forms of modern art and urban redevelopment are often attacked as being in cahoots with neo-liberal economic reforms. 	And while biennials have become critical institutions in their localities, they have become increasingly popular in their institutionalised forms, where they function as gatekeepers to ‘performative space’ and ‘performative time’, supplying the social with both social and cultural commodities. This is evident in the ubiquity of biennials in museum collections, where their documented history, documented collections, and the institutionalised forms they take give rise to ‘collectors consciousness’ and ‘a kind of celebrity’.6 	But while</text>
    <text>might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the ways in which contemporary art was being reproduced in ways that were not solely on the globalised capitalist planet. The critical nonconformist and critical queerest would point to the fact that art practices were produced at a specific moment in time, with particular cultural practices that existed at a specific moment in time, and that art had a certain amount of historical weight with regard to other cultural practices. The critical avant garde, critical nonconformist and critical queer collectives that emerged in the 1980s and 1990s would also be interested in the fact that their art practices were produced on the same terms and conditions as capitalist practices, and that their art practices were produced on a specific moment in time, with particular cultural practices that existed at a specific moment in time, and that their art practices were produced on a particular site and occasion. I think that’s where a lot of the technological literacy that emerged in the 1980s and 1990s came from: the same technologies that were in use</text>
    <text>might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the supposedly subversive tendencies of contemporary art and culture.  	In the Museum of Modern Art’s case, the critical avant garde would include the art students who would design the museum’s décor and curate the exhibits; the curatorial turn could be taken by art-schools for social change and feminist studies, or even ‘alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’, such as alternative lifestyles and art websites. The critical nonconformist and critical queer would be interested in art and artists remaining true to their sexual identities, but would also seek to understand why and how sexual minorities are able to self-identify and claim such power. Finally, there is the art and art-world curatorial turn, which is interested in the social and political implications of art and art-world institutions, but is also interested in the aesthetic and political implications of art-world social structures. There is a reason why, in 2011, the Venice Bienn</text>
    <text>might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the pernicious effects of modernity on culture. But since the early 1990s the critical and the curatorial have colluded in making it ever more difficult to distinguish the curatorial from the imperialist. The critical avant garde might become something like a museum, while the critical nonconformist and the critical curatorial might become something like a gallery.  	The critical avant garde is interested in the limits of what it can portray, while the curatorial is interested in the potential for art to change public attitudes and even legislation. But since the curatorial’s focus is always on the public good, and since the public gallery only exists to house works selected and approved by the curatorial, the two inevitably conflict with one another.  	Finally, since the curatorial is always on the lookout for ways to increase the visibility of its curatorial priorities (which it justifies by arguing are public), its curatorial priorities inevitably end up being affected by what is perceived</text>
    <text>might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the political-ideological entanglements that characterised the contemporary global-concept art market.  	In the 1990s and early 2000s, there was a critical race to the bottom in this assessment, with collectors, curators and art writers racing to create a ‘critical' of the next big thing, no matter how ‘ill-conceived’ it was. In 2005, Tania Bruguera launched the Bruguera Gallery: an inclusive arts organisation specifically for and dedicated to the Queer Assemblage of which it was a part. From the beginning of its existence, the Bruguera has focused on the needs and interests of the local community. Bruguera Gallery members include artists, activists, community organisers, educators, social workers, architects and many others. 	In this critical arena, the Bruguera Gallery has often been at odds with its more established peers, which can be seen as a problem area. For</text>
    <text>might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the pernicious effects of modern culture on the individual. The critical nonconformist and critical queerest would point to the historical entanglements of modernity and colonialisation – the entanglements that continue to threaten not only the contemporary form but also the future of humanity.  	The very notion of the contemporary form, itself an inescapable part of the contemporary condition – constructed and constituted as such – entangles us in complex ways. As biennials, we are constantly confronted with the entanglement of time and space, of course subject to the whims of the capitalist economy and geopolitical quixotics. But we are also regularly drawn into these same economic and geopolitical imaginaries, and so our very being – constituting, in other words, ‘the contemporary’ – is continually subject to the entanglement of various kinds of commodities and services, both global and domestic. And these different kinds of entanglements often produce quite different forms of being, quite contrary</text>
    <text>might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the pernicious influence of cultural capitalism and the cultural patriarchy. The critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be drawn towards art and their potential role in resisting the contemporary depredations of modernity and in fact modernity’s endgame.   	The critical avant garde and critical nonconformist shared a concern with the excesses of modernity, especially that prevailing in the social, cultural and economic spheres. The avant garde was particularly concerned with the excesses of consumer culture, which was understood as constituting the very essence of modernity, and the nonconformist and critical avant garde was particularly troubled by the tendency towards collectivism and commodity fetishisms. These excesses, however, were understood in relation to the collective and not individually, so their articulation and political implications were not as acute for the nonconformist and critical avant garde as it was for the cultural consumer. 	The nonconformist</text>
    <text>might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the repressive entanglements of capitalism. The critical avant garde would critique heteronormativity, white supremacy and the contemporary culture of death, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would question the very nature of contemporaneity.   	In the 1990s and early 2000s, there was a critical race and gender dimension to the curatorial process, as well as a critical economy dimension – the kind of framing and societal dynamics that shape cultural productions – while the critical avant garde would develop critical powers of observation and interrogation. However, in the current period, the most urgent curatorial work is that of the survival of the planet as a species, and the curatorial imposition of its governance. The current global economic collapse threatens not only the planet but also humanity as we inhabit it. Therefore, it is imperative that we collectively and radically rethink the kinds of cultural production and reproduction that constitute our daily reality, in the interests of the common good. Otherwise, the very</text>
    <text>might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the capitalist and institutionalised nature of the contemporary culture industry as a whole. However, while there are many forms of biennial today, there is no canonical position within the art world that would cover all contemporary art forms, let alone all art forms. So it is with  	Artspotteries: some members of the art community are more interested in the economics of art production than the inner lives of artists, and see the biennial as a way to make easy money through consumption.6 	While the biennial might have its roots in the nineteenth-century global market, the biennial has entered a qualitatively different mode of production in the twenty-first century. Unlike in the nineteenth century, where the biennial was a multi-year, multi-edition, perennial fixture, today’s biennial is a ‘soft stop’ on its tracks. It is an episodic type of event that occurs between artworks and museums, between artists and curators,</text>
    <text>might be curated through the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York). The Museum of Modern Art is building a new ‘cultural center of the absurd’, as its put, that will house a fusion of contemporary art and &quot;alternative, sometimes oblique forms of expression’. As the Center puts it: &quot;Art, produced here, is the stage, but alternative or alternative forms of expression can be found on the margins, in the margins, and in the margins of the contemporary art world’.5   	This is very similar to the way in which biennials began to produce a critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, in part due to the critical avant garde, critical non-conformist, and critical queer collectives that formed around the world. The critical avant garde would be concerned with the imperialist nature of the contemporary global economy and geopolitical entanglements, while the critical nonconformist and critical queerest would be interested in the institutionalised misogyny, neo-nazi and other forms of fascist retro-feudalism and racism of the contemporary condition. Within this critical mass of desire and experience, there would be a place for each of the orientations. There would be no place for a museum of modern art to take its place, since such a thing is beyond the pale of contemporary art’s interest. There would be no place for a museum of queer or feminist art either, since these groups were never intended to be museums and their mission was always to preserve and enhance the culture of the privileged. As the late David Hockney would say, making the case for the Curator-General’s Chair in a 1970s biennial, a museum that reflects its curator-general in the form of a ‘gigantic artifice’ while simultaneously ceaselessly interrupting and dismantling its privileged publics.6. The biennial. The major biennials of the 1980s</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the curatorial process via an index, a directory of curatorial practices, and a web site with resources and articles connected by a common root. The index presented the curatorial priorities of the exhibitionary industries at the time, and the curatorial agenda of the exhibitionary industries in the future. The index reflected the trends in the biennial with a particular focus on the increasing numbers of biennials, the shift towards urban centers, and the proliferation of biennials in countries around the world. The ‘world’ part of the index reflected the fact that the biennial was being founded in large part around the world, and the changes in the way in which the biennial is produced, organised, and consumed (Blair, 2010). The emergence of the biennial as a global phenomenon occurred at a time of unprecedented mobility within and across the site of the biennial. It was also becoming increasingly apparent that the biennial would play a pivotal role in the future of the museum, and</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the curatorial instincts of its curators, whose writing was collected and published in the curatorial notes of the exhibition. Assembled by the Curators of the Australian and the European Exhibitions, the teams sought to understand how the biennial form could be structurally different from traditional museums. They also sought to understand how different curators approached the same exhibition. Their research, led by Prof. Kristin Huggett of the London School of Architecture, established the themes and developed the curatorial plans for the exhibition. Her team included former curators at the New York and Sydney Exhibitions, as well as curators at the Venice Biennale and Aga Khan Biennale. They were also supported by the European Research Council (ERC), a European Union research and infrastructure funding agency, and the Australian National University, a research university with a major in urban studies. 	Kirstie Hemmings and her team arrived in Istanbul in June 2007. They were met by a</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the historical curators James Parkinson and Peter Schjeldahl, who curated the first edition of the A.N.C. Peter Schjeldahl published his own reflections on the exhibition in Schloss Waren  (The Modern Museum) in 2006. James Parkinson was one of the curators on the Sydney commission, and Peter Schjeldahl was another. Both responded to the issue of where the exhibition should be located and how it should be organised. Their positions were taken by way of a ‘shoah’, or a declarative statement of ideas rather than a proposal of an exhibition. Their ‘shoah’ addressed the specificity of the position, and the place of an artist in that position. They aimed to answer the question, ‘what is it that one seeks to make happen in a public space?’[7] 	[emphasis in original] They were, in other words, not proposing an idealised version</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the conventions of the museum, the local, the nation, and the street. It did not invent the biennial, but it certainly can be seen as a creator. ‘Our Surplus Chest’, the title of the book and the exhibition, suggests a way of thinking about the museum as a storage for images, objects, ideas, histories, and knowledge. The volume that year held over 1,000 images, many of them images from the first ten years of the exhibition. Its contents speak to the episodes that remain unresolved in the story of the museum, those gems left behind when the museum closed for refurbishment. The pictures from the first ten years of the exhibition, and their position within the narrative, speak to the static nature of the museum and the continuous stream of stories told by the curators, performers, visitors, students and researchers. They tell of the history of the biennial, its genesis, its current position and future prospects. They also suggest a way to think about</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the conventions and routinised forms of the museum as they were being reinvented, this time by curators at the University of Sydney, Museum of Art, and the University of Melbourne. It is a site for the reappraisal of a museum’s historic curatorial approach, as well as for the reconfiguration of its social and urban components. 	Ultimately, the board’s research and writing led them to a position that was not that of the museum, but that of a biennale. Their position was that of a curatorial intervention, intervening not in order to create a museum but to change and prod the museum to new situations and situations. They did not, however, have the authority or the institutions to change museums, nor to alter curatorial approaches. The biennial was created as a permanent, in-house project, and its curatorial approaches and outcomes were determined by the Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of Sydney, as well as the artists and</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the itinerary set by the exhibitionary form, which often overlapped with the past, present, or future of the art being made in that site. The board’s research led them to a number of important art's recent recurrence in the city, including the curatorial interventions in the area around the 2009 World Columbian Exposition, the curatorial interventions in the area around the 2012 Sydney Biennale, the curatorial interventions in the area of December City, and the curatorial interventions in the area of Walter Raleigh Park. All of these interventions occurred in the context of an overall biennale strategy of the city, with artists, curators, collectors, art writers and art’s many exhibitionary forms all working in concert to bring art from everywhere to the city. For many artists, this meant creating experiences and sites around art that were accessible, specific and unusual in their style, and bringing the art to the people through cultural enterprises, such as playwrights, play</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the curatorial process at the museum, conducting fieldwork and collecting material in the form of exhibits, videos, photographs, articles and journal essays. The first edition of Interface in 2006 contained contributions from 41 curators, and the curatorial search for a museum of contemporary art[5]. The biennial format was considered an ideal candidate for the site of a museum, because it is self-generating, subject to the whims of the biennale examiner, and has its material and data sources at the fingertips of any interested party with access to information and data. The committee’s proposals and recommendations were received in early 2007 and early 2008, with an initial public version of the Biennale of Sydney set as the 'starter project'. 	In 2009, following a public and critical intervention, the board of curators convened its sixth and final public consultation, which was attended by over 1,000 people. The committee’s report, ‘The Biennale of Sydney: Up</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the curatorial process through its stages of submission, publication, and intervention. The book included a chapter on the project’s reception, and the curatorial team’s response to it. A chronological order of the essays is presented in ‘Projects Cured’, each reflecting a chronological sequence of events leading to the publication of the exhibition. Present in the chapter are excerpts from the board’s and the curator’s interviews with key players in the project. The essays reflect on the interventions as well as the symbolism of the exhibition, and the ways in which the exhibition represents the social and political situation of a particular community in a city. The chapters on intervention and succession draw on the curator’s own curatorial thinking. Their order in the book reflects their order in the curatorial process. In the essay ‘On Writing and Unravelling’, published as part of the exhibition’s New Art project, Curator-General of the European</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the curatorial process. It was not a project in which the curators or artists directly participated. The project was led by Hutchison and her team, including research assistants, art historians, and artists. It was an ongoing, non-artistic, collaborative process that sought to uncover the cultural relevance of the museum through a multi-tiered approach to understanding the biennial as a site for curatorial practice. This project reflected the curatorial agenda through curatorial and artistic means, but also the efforts of many others to add to the narrative. Hutchison would say that the curatorial hand had a 'tendency, especially in the past 15 years, to marginalise or disempower its subject'.2  This tendency to disempower was most clearly seen in the curatorial role of the Aboriginal Peoples Yearbook, which was systematically suppressed from public view in the 1990s by political actors on the commissioning committee.3  The missing yearbook has come to light after more</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. The biennial, by definition, imagines its subject matter. It is the pre-eminent institution of its kind, and its representations in museums, in galleries, in performances, and in then on to the streets. Its stock and work is subject to the institutional memory and the physical presence of its subjects. 	When the Biennale of Sydney was announced in 2006, the story of the museum as a site for biennials was told. The curatorial narrative emerged via a combination of public interventions, meetings, and essays, conducted by a board of curators from the Australian National Exhibition, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the University of Sydney. The board’s research and writing led them to an understanding of the museum as a site for collaborative research and reflection. Their writing was published in the journal Interface, and a companion book of the same name was published by the American Museum of Contemporary Art and the University of California, Hastings. The curatorial narrative followed the curators’ travels, and the public’s journeys too, as they visited museums, took part in a land survey, and watched the landscape through the pressures of a growing and global biennale. The book included maps and topological diagrams of the Australian outback, and the proposed topology of the world, with ‘Australia’ positioned at the extreme centre. The annotations were written by the curators, and were based on their understanding of the subject matter, the physical landscape, and their position in their positions as professionals. The annotations also included suggestions on language, landscape design, and the culture of the people who inhabit the land they represent. 	The mapping and topology was part of a broader cultural and linguistic mission in the outback. The curatorial document includes a special section specifically for Aboriginal languages, dialects, and families. The sections on language and dialects refer to languages that are spoken by under-studied or endangered groups, such as In</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7
    <text>The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7000. 	Notebooks 10/11/2012. Remodeling and renovation of the 'wrong place at the wrong time' for the Kabir Mahal – a project that will see twelve of Mumbai’s most iconic buildings transformed into luxury condos – is a new urban development that is approached with increasing frequency. Most of the development currently underway in the Kabir Mahal is centered around the residential portion of the complex, but a new intention is being given to the cultural aspect of the complex. As part of this, a new exhibition called Kabir Mahal: Art From The Past Three Decades will be developed with the architecture and facade of the old Kabir Mahal as a cultural touchstone. Kabir Mahal: Art From The Past Three Decades will showcase work from the curator’s past three decades of Kabir Mahal. It will also showcase innovative new work by the curator’s peers from</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7263 or carolte.staeheli@kiwiircitiesales.org. 	The inflated market values of real estate, and the liveable façades that have emerged as a result of these, are stock exchanges. They are not a reflection of intrinsic qualities of the place, nor is their rapid fame and global ubiquity a reflection of natural resources generated by humanity’s rapid consumption? The myth of the inn and the homeless has been intimately connected to the stock market. 	The inn embodies everything that is wrong with the city – the deprivation, the urban blighting, the polluted waterfront, and the decline of the blue-collar fisherman. It is a symbol of decadence and poverty, but it is also a metaphor for the possibilities of human creativity and ingenuity. 	The inn is a rarefied structure that stands for a reason: it is a symbol of wealth and power, but it is also a metaphor for limitations and injustices. In</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7013. 	References [1]  	http://www.demographie.com/english/demographie-england/article-22467.html [2] 	http://www.demographie.com/english/demographie-england/art-feature/20130621-genoa-the-place-of-den-mt-2.html [3] 	http://www.demographie.com/english/demographie-england/article-22467.html [4] 	http://www.demographie.com/english/demographie-england/art-feature/20130621-genoa-the-place-of-den-mt-2.html [5] 	http://www.demographie.com/english/demographie-england/art-feature/20130621-genoa-the-place</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7888 or cstaeheli@uga.edu. 	Below, a timeline of key events in the Current Status of Housing in the Current &amp; Prospectus Quarter (2009–2018), the former home of the New York Times, which covers the area bounded by Murray, Central, Ninth and Tenth Avenues in the Western Hemisphere. 	Joint Statement of the City of New York &amp; Community Action Network for the District of Columbia 	On November 14, 2017, Community Action Network (CAN) convened its members for a Community Land Trust (CLT) meeting in Downtown Brooklyn. The purpose of the meeting was to finalize the purchase of CLT land in the Current Status of Housing project, which would provide additional affordable housing for the residents of the former Kings/Mine district in the Central District. The meeting was open to the public and CAN invited participants to share experiences and draw parallels between the CLT and the Current Status of Housing. The meeting also</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7384 or email staeheli@ucl.ac.uk. 	If the market is the marketplace, then the façade is the façade. And while the façade may be an approximation to the city in some respects, it is a complete and accurate representation of the city in many other respects. The fact that the city is constantly undergoing qualitative and quantitative changes reflects the fact that the city is continually evolving. New developments and the flow of new developments alter the core cityscape and the character of the city, as well as the quality and quantity of life in many ways. New developments may be good or may harm the city in various ways. Therefore, the role of the city is to respond to the needs of the people in such a way as to generate or create the conditions for new developments, both large and small, to take root and to be shaped by the process of their emergence. In undertaking such a process, the city must have agency and power, both</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7000 or email cstaeheli@uwaterloo.ca. The University of Waterloo is a publicly funded, accelerated doctoral program in Cultural Studies and Design at the Schulich School of Architecture and Design at the University of Texas Austin. The program introduces students to the dynamics of urban renewal in Canada and the United States, and considers the connections between culture and the built environment. The Schulich School of Architecture and Design has a core research agenda that extends beyond architecture, and includes a broader portfolio of activities including research-intensive urban and regional planning, including the design and construction of culturally responsive urban environments, and the management of large-scale renewable energy resources. The Fulbright Scholars Program in Cultural Studies and Design is a two-year, fully funded, multi-disciplinary program that provides training in a single discipline in a multi-disciplinary environment. Graduates of the Fulbright program in accelerate their research</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7698 or carolte.staeheli@uga.edu. 	The Biennale’s current Curatorial Agenda includes research and writing activities. Research has focused on the role of art and architecture in the development of the city in an attempt to gain a better understanding of the local conditions that enable and facilitate the development of such architecture. This research has led to the publication of several books and exhibition catalogues. The latest work in the series Future City is a collaboration between WOW! Studios, Inc. and WOW! Architects, Inc. that reconstructs the bulk of the historic core of Seattle using Passive Houses as Structures as a medium of artistic repurposing. The project, which was first proposed in 2013, is the result of a year-long research process that sought to understand the historical context, cultural dynamics and spatial persistence of the area through participatory methods. The project is the result of a research collaboration between the Biennale, </text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7678 or email staeheli@ucl.ac.uk. Site plans can be found at: http://www.ucl.ac.uk/lbs/index.php?fuseaction=Main_Page&amp;sort=Newfound+Presence 	The new buildings are often developed as a response to the demolition of historically located neighbourhoods, but in reality many of these projects are more geostrategically directed. They are local extensions of existing practices, but are also responses to a demand that is no longer met in these neighbourhoods. This is happening increasingly in the wake of population growth, but it was not always the case. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7678 or email staeheli@ucl.ac.uk. Site plans can be found at: http://www.ucl.ac.uk/lbs/index.php?fuseaction=Main_Page&amp;sort=New</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7200. 	[1] Such is the City Council's intention, expressed in a 2014 policy paper entitled ‘Developing a Shared City’.  [2] The policy paper, written by Staeheli and others with input from the Office of the Mayor, identified four areas where the City was considering new approaches to urban regeneration: the production of renewable energy resources; the promotion of green building practices; the creation of green ‘highways’; and the establishment of a citywide bicycle network.  [3] As of 2015, the number of bicycles owned in Berlin was estimated at approximately 6,500,000.  [4] Greening is the deliberate policy of encouraging the use of available energy resources by developers in exchange for a share of future revenue streams. As of 2015, this included the conversion of surplus natural resources into biofuels through the active involvement of biogas plants and incineration of wood by-products. [</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but the project could still be a work in progress. The ‘real life’ of the houses is left out in the cold. The houses are temporary exhibitions, erected as a facade for the condos, which in turn act as a barrier to the city. The value of the houses is greatly exaggerated in the inflated local market value. The inflated market value and the liveable façades are greatly exaggerated in this process of reconstruction. The market values and the façades are sold by the hour as new developments appear, and the inflated value of the houses – which in turn – is used to support the creation of even more ridiculous developments. The manic overbuilding and frenetic change in the core cityscape is a closely watched story, but it remains to be seen if the inflated market values will support the stressed public services and supportive affordable housing needed to support the growing population. 	For more information, contact Carolte Staeheli at 647-488-7264. 	Download this article as PDFCarolte StaeheliCarolte Staeheli is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1990s with projects in Liverpool and Bristol in an area of Liverpool called 'The Empty Quarter. Her Biennale projects in the Quarter included Warehouse to Table, an exhibition of 40 works by local artists on a temporary curatorial platform, and 'The Empty Quarters’ book, a new publication from the Quarter that documents the history of the area and its contemporary culture. She has also curated the Empty Homes​ special exhibition from the Quarter.Carolte Staeheli is the Curator for Liverpool Biennale 2016. Open Wednesdays and Saturdays, from April until September, she is the Curator for Liverpool Biennale 2016. She is the Curator for Liverpool Biennale 2017 and is visiting curator Arjun Appadurai in New York for The US</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal’,  	Nadine Attewell,  	Futures of Urban Imagination, Routledge, London, 1990, p. 79.  3  Benjamin,  	Towards a Political Economy of the Future City, Vintage Books, New York, 1989, p. 12.  4  Benjamin,  	The Decentering of Time, Vintage Books, New York, 1987, p. 13.  5  Benjamin,  	The Decentering of Time, p. 3.  6  Benjamin,  	The Decentering of Time, p. 3.  7  Benjamin,  	Towards a Political Economy of the Future City, Vintage Books, New York, 1987, p. 13.  8  Benjamin,  	The Decentering of Time, p. 3.  9  Benjamin,  	Towards a Political Economy of the Future City,</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal’, in  	Future City: Essays on the Past, ed. Stefan Collini, Taschen, New York, 1996,p. 91.  3  Collini, op. cit., p. 92.  4  Collini, op. cit., p. 93.  5  Collini, op. cit., p. 94.  6  Collini, op. cit., p. 95.  7  Collini, op. cit., p. 96.  8  Collini, op. cit., p. 97.  9  Collini, op. cit., p. 98.  10  Collini, op. cit., p. 99.  11  Collini, op. cit., p. 100.  12  Collini, op. cit., p. 101.  13  Collini, op. cit., p. 102.  14  Collini, op. cit., p</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal’, in  	Gentlemen of the Sea, ed. Michael Stern, Hachette, Paris, 1988, p. 67.  3  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past, 1930.  4  Herman Daly,  	Spirit of Utopia, Vintage, New York, 1965, p. 225.  5  ‘I’m from Mars, but you’re from Venus’, in  	Time, June, 24, 1970, p. 2A, a, 9.  6  ‘The Martian Chronicles, II: Venus’s Ashes, Penguin Classics, New York, 1980, p. 180.  7  James Howard Kunstler,  	The Art of Not Being Governed, Vintage, New York, 1985, p. 7.  8  Ralph Waldo Emerson,  	Signals from the Past, Harper &amp; Row</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal’,  	Ralph Raico and Teju Cole, eds.,  	Future City: Essays on the Transformation of the City,  	Future City, New York, 1990, p. 4.  3  Rainer Barbosa,  	Simulations: On Prediction and Public-Virtuality, MIT Press, Cambridge, 1989, p. 513.  4  Rainer Barbosa,  	Simulations: Communicative Practices in a World, MIT Press, Cambridge, 1990, p. 519.  5  Rainer Barbosa,  	Simulations, MIT Press, Cambridge, 1990, p. 519.  6  Rainer Barbosa,  	Simulations, MIT Press, Cambridge, 1990, p. 519.  7  Rainer Barbosa,  	Simulations, MIT Press, Cambridge, 1990, p. 519.  8  Rainer Barbosa</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal’, in  	Wild West, p. 15.  3  John Stuart Mill, ‘The Expression of the Inferior in the Circulation of Time’,  	Essays, Vol. 1, p. 261.  4   John Stuart Mill, ‘On the Imminence of Being Immanent: A Reply to J.S. Mill’s ‘Immanent Motion’,  	Essays, Vol. 2, p. 543.  5  John Stuart Mill, ‘On Immanence and Its Multiple Assessments’,  	Essays, Vol. 3, p. 547.  6  Paul Feyer and Christian Körner, ‘Einsthalten är Körner – Essays on the Fountainhead’,  	Essays, Vol. 1, p. 397.  7  John Stuart Mill,</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal’ - in  	Storms of the Future Past, p. 5. 3  Paul Ricoeur, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5. 4  Ibid., p. 11.  5  Ricoeur, op. cit., p. 12.  6  Ibid., p. 12. 7  Paul Ricoeur, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  8  Paul Ricoeur, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  9  Ibid., pp. 6–7.  10  Ricoeur, op. cit., p. 10.  11  Paul Ricoeur, ‘On Urban</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal’,  	The New York Times, January 22, 2006, p. A8.  3  Paul HM Thompson, ‘The Rise of the Shadow Economy: Payments Secrets in an Apparatus of New Economy, 1890–1920’,  	Economic History Review, Vol. 10(1),  January, 1920, p. 331. 4  Svetlana Boym, ‘Rethinking Globalization’,  	World Politics, Vol. 23(3), March, and June,  January, 1920, pp. 397–981. 5  Herman Daly,  	The Ecology of Freedom, Harper &amp; Row, New York, 1978, p. 129. 6  Ibid., p. 135. 7  Anthony Gardner and Christian Ulrik Conservation and Management of Resources: Toward a New Science of the Future City,  	Future City, John and Catherine Hall, Edinburgh, 1980,</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal’, in  	A Snowdrop's Tale, 1922.  3  A. Edward Sapir, ‘On Urban Imagination, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 48.  4  A. Edward Sapir,  	The Waste Land of No Future, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1988, p. x.  5  Richard Florida, ‘On the Origins of Metainformatics, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commission, 1942, p. 34.  6  Edward Sapir, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commission, 1942, p. 36.  7  Edward Sapir, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commission, 1942,</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal’,  	Futuresource News,  	October, 1992, p. 2. 3  Paul Ricoeur, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5. 4  Paul Ricoeur, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5. 5  Ricoeur, p. 5. 6  Ricoeur, op. cit., p. 6. 7  Ricoeur, op. cit., p. 6. 8  Ricoeur, op. cit., p. 7. 9  Ricoeur, op. cit., p. 7. 10  Ricoeur, op. cit., p. 7. 11  Ricoeur, op. cit., p. 7. 12  Ibid., p. 7. </text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: what if, say, a human being were replaced with a machine? What if, as in Area 51, the future is a computer simulation?Could ‘art’ play a part in the future as well? If every simulation is a temporary aberration, then the ambiguities of the contemporary condition will become ever more apparent, as if the ambiguities of life itself were expressions of the ambiguities of the temporal condition.  References: 1   	W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Urban Future, 1930.’, in  	Notes from a First-Person Commissions, 1942, p. 5.  2  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 175. ‘Bold as an Animal’,  	Today, Harper &amp; Row, London, New York, 1986, p. 38.  3  Paul Ricoeur,  	Storms of the Future Past: Violence, Gentrification, and a World Future for Seattle and Doha,  	Storms of Future City, Boydell Press, New York, 1989, p. 176.  4   Paul Ricoeur and Karen L. Crary,  	Future City: New Urbanisms for an Uncertain Times, McClelland &amp; Stewart, New York, 1987, p. 42.  5  Paul Ricoeur and Karen L. Crary,  	Future City: New Urbanisms for an Uncertain Times, McClelland &amp; Stewart, New York, 1987, p. 4.  6  Paul L. Singer,  	The Urban Imagination: A Cultural History of the Twentieth-Century Boston,  </text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological adjustment to the social costs of having a social life. She begins to identify the particular ways in which the technologies of art and culture are co-constituted and co-programmed to produce the apocalyptic futures envisaged by the AI, but she also begins to point to the fact that the inhabitants of the biennales and museums of the future will be artists themselves, and that the cultural capacities of artists will play a far more significant role in the curatorial reinvention of the city than in the curatorial interventions of the present. Cultural capital is the new urban frontier. It is the capacity of new technological formations to create measurable changes in a material and social infrastructure of the world. It is a capacity that is fully identifiable and quantifiable, and it is a capacity that is actively managed by and through artists. It is cultural capital in its own right.It is this active and measurable capacity to create that seems to be at the core of the new technological frontier. It is to a large</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological effects of the multiple forms of cultural experience that it supports. In the age of the biennial and its numerous satellite institutions, Tian identifies a new form of cultural capitalism: artums oblates, in which art is valorised in exchange for a serviceable future. Art as asset is capitalised on the back of a future that is no longer assured; an uncertain and unstable community of future selves that exist in constant migration across the social landscape. Art as a service becomes something that is rendered in exchange for a future that does not necessarily exist; a kind of collective punishment that punishes those who do not meet the technological, economic or political standards that are being set by the society that produced the art. 	Art is not only an asset today, but one that contributes significantly to cultural capital accumulation. Art is a powerful tool that can render valuable abstract ideas apparent across a global landscape, and it is one that can also be used to oppress and subjugate those who do not adhere to</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological effects of experience in mass media. She begins to argue that the technological conjuncture of the twenty-first century demands a radically different kind of cultural construction from what the ancient cultures of Greece and Rome employed. In the past, cultural production was constrained by the material and immaterial resources of the society to which it was applied. Today, material and immaterial resources are rapidly migrating towards consciousness and consciousness itself. In the past, consciousness was both understood and measured in terms of cultural practices. Today, consciousness is both understood and measured in terms of cultural categories. And this is the technological conjuncture of the future, not the past.Art and culture are tools through which we can imagine new possibilities and interact with the future. But these possibilities must be differentiated and multi-faceted in order to be used effectively. In other words, art and artists must be able to access resources of all kinds, conscious and unconscious. For this to happen, resources have to be differentiated and multileduced. For</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological effects of repeated experience. The cultural production system she describes, ‘Avant-garde’, is a product of these factors and more. With the exception of a few rarefactions, most artists who became major works in their fields, and a relatively small number of curators, went on to major exhibitions, major residencies, and other forms of cultural expression. The major cultural centres of the twenty-first century are in fact built on the back of the avant-garde, which is the contemporary counterpart to the avant-garde that existed in the twentieth century. It is worth recalling that in the 1980s, the ‘90s, the ‘art-world’ was mostly a collection of art dealers, collectors, and art-utopia types, whose fixation on art-value and desire to own things (primarily, valuable art) motivated a culture of consumption that was in many ways similar to the obsession of contemporary artists. There was</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological effects of having been around for a long time. In the twenty-first century, there are more media consumption devices designed to please and educate than to inform, so it is not surprising that the literate segments of society that inhabit the cultural forms that are produced and adopted are also consumers of content. The cultural forms that are brought to life through media are cultural forms that are simultaneously culturally effective and economically destructive. What is distinctive about the media forms that are produced and adopted in the contemporary era is that the technological infrastructure that underlies them is now global in scope and mediated through the use of massive data networks. It is not surprising that the media forms that are culturally consumable and economically portable are also those that enact destructive and dehumanising effects on those who inhabit the technological forms that are created and adopted. What is distinctive about the new media forms is that they are generated and consumed in parallel, and so their social effects are felt concurrently. What was once considered a singular and unique cultural form that emerged</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological effects of its own ongoing participation in cultural life.[1] Though she is clear that these factors cannot be prescribed, she does offer us some tentative markers of the kinds of cultural capital we might want to nurture and nurture in our own lives.[2] For more on cultural production and how it can be redesigned to meet our cultural needs, see my 2015 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation: Culture, Intangible Form (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2015).[3] The main ideas in ‘Things Accurately Lost in Translation’ are: 1. Technology is reshaping how we perceive the world, making it increasingly difficult to distinguish between fact and fiction; 2. The contemporary condition is one in which cultural practices are de facto replaced by machines; 3. The rise of digital media technologies is disrupting traditional forms of cultural production; and 4. The rise of social media technologies is making it easier to consume cultural forms online.In recent years, there has been a</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological effects of its frequent encounters with the &quot;new normal&quot;. 	Tian identifies a number of thematic elements that she believes are particularly relevant in our age of connectedness: the culture of the future (in which there is no national identity), the culture of the imperfect (in which differences are treated with suspicion and disregard), the culture of habit (in which habits determine what is expected of us, what counts as culture and so on), and the culture of ephemeral (in which the future seems to be a continual postponement of the past). She proposes a set of criteria that artists, curators, journalists and others could use to judge whether an artwork is authentic or a re-figuration, and to identify artistic practices that capitalize on these new cultural registers. She also suggests that these practices could be understood as ‘metainterface’, or when the infrastructure of the infrastructure is re-figurative – when it produces cultural effects similar to those of the infrastructure but</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological effects of its own social reproduction.[1] The culture she studies is a complex mixture of nationalistic nostalgia, technological narcissism, artistic prostration, and an ever-expanding archive of images and sounds of everywhere. It is a form of memory that is constantly (re)tuned to new data and culture, and to the needs and preferences of new users. It is a form of language with an uncertain future, and it is an ever-present archive of cultural practices. Yet what if, according to Ding, we could discover a cure for the contemporary condition? What if we could create a form of culture that is both universal and yet specifically tailored to the needs of a specific nation? What if, according to Ding, this form of culture could replace (what she calls) ‘dead language’ as the infrastructure of the modern age? What if this form of cultural capital could reclaim (reclaim)language as a descriptive concept, and pave the way for a mutually exclusive number</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological effects of experience. Art’s (and artists’) psychological effects of experience are the subject of a new cultural theory (possibly related to technological culture theory) that is developing in China at this moment. The term ‘cultural capital accrues mainly from the publication and re-publishing of scientific and historical articles on the Internet, in cultural magazines and through the frequent booking and accommodation of cultural attractions, events and venues. It is also thought to be a more or less accurate reflection of the current state of knowledge about the past, especially in urban centres with a high concentration of historical collections.’[10] Art, it is thought, is a digital recording of the past, transcribed and augmented in all its varieties of structured and unstructured materiality. It is a record keeping device that records, creates, and augments knowledge.[11] More and more of what we know about the past comes from online sources. More and more of what we know</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines: how do we learn to like each other?Who are we trying to turn into something? Who are we trying to turn into something else?What does it mean to make something new?What does it mean to make something familiar?What is the relationship between culture and the machine?What is the relationship between art and the future? 	Art is an important part of the technological infrastructure of our times. It enables us to understand and manage the multiple dimensions of the future that can be influenced by art, and it contributes to the ongoing reproduction of the cultural capital of the future. Yet how to conceive of culture and the machine in relation to one another? Towards a Definition of Art and CultureDing Tian, in her influential and much-loved 1995 book Things Accurately Lost in Translation (and Repurposed Today), begins to identify the major factors contributing to the explosion of cultural capital in the twenty-first century: technology, cultural relativism, and art’s own psychological effect of accumulation.[1] In recent years, a number of biennials, including Venice, Barcelona, Mexico City and Berlin, have initiated or attempted to initiate ‘cultural tourism’ programmes, or ‘cultural “rivers’, that seek to capitalize on the current economic and social conditions of the cities that they visit.“ Cultural “rivers’ are often described as the post-Internet economy of the cities, or the worlds they visit. In the current environment of ever-greater data capture and control, this may no longer be the case, and biennials are now more like museums, institutes of infinite recording and dissemination, and online archives of cultural exchange. More and more of what we might call the curatorial task is performed by machines, or ‘bots’, that can ‘see, hear, read, write, ‘see invisible text, ‘see special effects, ‘see “windows�</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new kind of art direction.  	As a curatorial exercise, this new kind of art direction is expected to follow the trends of the moment, or, to be more specific, the trends of the day, in such a way as to exploit the resources of the moment, but also to weave in cultural theory and history. It is to be delivered with the displaced temporality of an archive. 	This new kind of art direction will be no more recognisable as an Emirati art museum during the Abu Dhabi royal family’s time in power, than it will be during the reign of a European artist during a modernist gallery in London. Both the biennial and the museum will be institutionalised in the city, and both will be staffed with art professionals chosen primarily from among the city’s citizens. But unlike today, whom the city suppresses or marginalises through its myriad cultural institutions, today's art will be made for the city’s citizens’ museum</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new iteration of the character Sherlock Holmes. The fascination, I guess, is that the audience is now more open to the possibility that there are no supernatural forces at work in the world. In the 1990s, the belief was that there were. In the present, the belief is that there are no supernatural forces at work. And this is what the British Museum has done well during the past decade: by planting clues in the public psyche about the world through its art, it has created the illusion of unpredictability around an institution that was once known for its stability. The World at Large project began in 2003, and at its inception included projects in many cities around the world, but its current projects are in many cities in many countries around the world. It is a project that was originally conceived as a museum piece, then a gallery piece, then a public art project, and finally a museum piece that exhibits the institutional memory of the art it represents. It is an open question, then, as to what</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new format and topic. That audience is the same audience who tune in to see documentary films about the conflicts in the Middle East, or to see art and culture written from the vantage points of economic development and political observation. It is the same audience who turn up to see the art of prison activism, or to read up on the women lawyers who challenged the abusive criminalisation of women’s bodies via feminist theory. It is the same audience who turn up to read Thomas Carlyle, or to learn about the ‘real life’ that goes into the figure of any given citizen of any given city. It is the same audience who turn up to hear the words of Nelson Mandela, Rosa Luxemburg or any number of other radical activists whose work and thought have been actively engaged with and influenced by the events of 9/11. It is the audience who have just finished The Global Village, a new book from the author that brings together the work of village councils, local economies, grassroots organisers and</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new kind of art commentary. The word ‘biennial’ has been redubbed multiple times within this changing cultural landscape, and its place in the cultural hierarchy is questionable too. But whatever one ‘thinks’ about these exhibitions, biennials offer a kind of temporal reference in which contemporary art is created anew every time they are visited. That is to say, they are a kind of visual shorthand, a way to map the past, making possible the future, which is to say, creating what one can say is ‘real’ by tracing back to the past.  	Here, then, is how the word ‘biennial’ is used in your language. It conveys both the historical and the contemporary, the present and the futurological. It is an adjective describing events occurring in the present, occurring as such. 	You do not define ‘biennial’ by the presence of artworks or the amount of money</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new show every week. Even though the introduction of such a show by BBC1 coincides with the thirtieth anniversary of the creation of the biennial, the two are in many ways contemporaneous. There is, for example, no indication that the introduction of a newscast at a biennial would be appropriate or even trendy in 2017.  	However, there is a way of thinking about the art world that is both more individualised (the contemporary) and more representative of the contemporary (the biennial). This is the thought experiment that I invite you to try. In it, I show you how a small group of artists, curators, journalists and others could work with artists to create a biennial that is representative of the art world in the same way a museum is of the contemporary artist. I show you how this could work with or without the involvement of an art institution. I show you how a biennial could be convened around a specific artist, her organisation, the media</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new cultural element. The World at Large is a new breed of curatorial construction, built upon the remnants of a bygone age, when art was regarded as a social necessity alongside the rigid logic of national art assets.  The concept of the biennial was a staple of art and visual art for much of the twentieth century, but in recent decades it has become increasingly difficult to define precisely what a biennial is, and less certain how art should be curated in such contexts. The seeds of the biennial were sown in the early twentieth century by Norman Wilkinson, who established the first British biennials in 1899. Art and visual art were often seen as consumables in the service of capitalist accumulation, and the introduction of contemporary art to the public sphere was a way to placate patrons willing to shoulder the financial burden of art per se. Wilkinson was a capitalist, after all, who believed that the economic prosperity of the nation rested on the back of the artistically literate masses who patron</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new kind of cultural imperialism – a kind of cultural colonialism. The World at Large is produced by and for the BBC, and shows new places from everywhere in the world, sometimes in the future. It is the embodiment of everything that the BBC means by arts and culture: new experiences, new ways of knowing. �[1] See, for example, Peter Osborne and Arjun Appadurai, eds., The London Biennial: Art and Capital in a Global Context (London: Laurence King, 2016), p. 5.Download this article as PDFPeter OsbornePeter Osborne is a writer, curator and writer. His work has explored the cultural work of all periods, and the links between artists, art, commerce, history and politics. His most recent work, Staging America: Cultural Critic Marc Ambinder on the Challenges of Painting Performing the Impossible (2017) examines the environmental and social costs of American capitalism. He has written for The New York Times, The Washington Post,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new episode of Panorama weekly. The biennial is expected to follow suit.4. The curatorial. The biennial has entered a new era of its own. In the past few years, the biennial has been shown in many cities around the world, and its status as a form of cultural tourism is important in keeping the art form alive in new markets. It is also a form of cultural exchange that facilitates the circulation of cultures and cultures worldwide. The curatorial role in the nineteenth century was as a voyager, seeking out new worlds and encounters. In the twentieth century, this was accompanied by a new form of the curatorial designator ‘the curatorialus’, which succeeded the older ‘the museum’. The curatorialus’ voyages were accompanied by a new role – the curatorialus generale – which sought to define and capture those particular worlds found in art museums. The curatorialus voyages also required a new designator – a</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new kind of archaeology, or to other forms of entertainment. The appointment of Richard Land, the director of the Dryden, who promoted the newscast, as the new head of the Liverpool Biennial seemed an odd one, since he has a publishing imprint and a publishing agency. Perhaps it is this double-tiered, multi-needling nature of publishing and the biennial that makes the biennial so intriguing and the discrete part so difficult to value, distorting our notions of who is a curator and what counts as a curatorial accomplishment. A biennial is an institution that has both a curatorial task and a cultural function. It is what it means to be a curator today, and what it means to be a curator in the future. The biennial is the curatorial equivalent of a museum, in that it is an ever-present, permanent icon of the art in circulation and, as such, exhibits and documents of the art’s existence in contemporary society. The</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It is, in other words, a curated amalgamation of curatorial practices that occur simultaneously within and without the exhibitionary context. As such, it is the contours of a political, economic and ideological war. The art critics who advise and comment on the curatorial choices of the biennial are, of course, the same critics who during the 1990s and early 2000s respectively, were the architects of the Islamist State, the start of which is now long gone, replaced by a militantly anti-American Emirati madrassa. What is more, the audience who attends these art books, or attend art museums in any case, are the same audience who tune in to the Discovery Channel every week, or to other forms of art and cultural entertainment such as circus, roller-coaster and jet-set. And the same audience is expected to tune in to BBC1, which recently broadcast a new episode of The World at Large, a newscast that includes a new form of science-fiction television. The biennial as an entity, and its curatorial decisions, is part of a much broader cultural dynamic in which contemporary art and its cultural products are multiple and often anti-political. ‘Art’, by definition, is a political act.’1 But here, too, we can consider the implications of art’s recent past. The political act that the biennial is part of is part of a broader cultural dynamic in which contemporary art is becoming ever more accessible, and those with a cultural appetite for the past is part of a growing industry of contemporary artworks that can be accessed via a database of past performances and past reviews.2 The biennial is a production line that enables this synergy of commodity and geopolitics. It offers, in one fell swoop, a wealth of information on the location and intentions of an artist’s career, a wealth of information on the artist’s past, and it does so in a</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of
    <text>The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of habitual residence (rather than on the ground that they were citizens of a country). Banks would do business in zones where people could actually use the buildings, rather than having to rely on the legal system to enforce property rights. ‘Smart contracts’ would come into being where once legal claims were settled by settlement negotiations between legal entities. Legal claims would be adjudicated by a semi-autonomous tribunal, not by the law itself. This would eliminate the need for a great many lawyers, and would create a level playing field between claimants and the legal systems they claimed to be bound by. 	A smart contract is a kind of legal claim, and claims about legal claims are a kind of cultural capital. When the Miami Climate Action Network was founded, the claim was that ‘climate change is real and happening’, rather than that it was a ‘hoax’. The claim is that the Trump administration should be ashamed of itself for thinking that the climate could be saved,</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of habitual residence. Although such claims would be difficult to enforce, the city would still own the legal person assigned that place. 	As an example, the US-built Ft. Meade, which is almost identical in size and shape to Miami’s downtown, but is twice as big and twice as complicated, is divided into four zones: commercial, residential, school zone and industrial. The commercial zone extends 80% of the property line, while the residential zone includes 80% of the area and the school zone is a smaller part of the city. Although each zone has a specific use-by-date, they are aggregates of uses – commercial and residential, for example – that diverge in their composition, purpose and usage. When the zone is fragmented, as it is in Miami, it becomes difficult to discern a distinct commercial or residential sector from a cluster of houses. Although each zone may have distinct uses, they all have in common that Miami has achieved in its postindustrial downtown</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of habitual residence. ‘Land Grabbing’ would still be illegal, but it would happen more and more frequently, and it would be seen as a last resort. 	The question is, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The answer to that is a definite – and very much in evidence –   	1  	Miami Herald, 10/12/2014, http://www.miamiflippincase.com/2014/10/12/i... (accessed 10/13/2014). 	2  	Miami Herald, 10/13/2014, http://www.miamiflippincase.com/2014/10/13/i... (accessed 10/14/2014). 	3  	Miami Herald</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of habitual residence. ‘Expropriation’ is still an option for those who resist change, but in an ideal future, that option would no longer exist. 	Looking back, what role can the city play in the fight for social and ecological justice? I believe that the ability to self-repairing cities would be a major step in the right direction, but right now there is no incentive for people to do that. The attraction of the city today is in large measure based on its capacity to support a large number of tourists, and the attractions of living in a city on the beach, in hotels, in great museums, and so forth. These draw people away from the places where their labour could be done good (in the form of jobs), and away from the places where it is most socially beneficial (in the form of cultural attractions). The city is the contemporary-looking version of the city of the future, and the future city is a city in which the cultural attractions</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of habitual residence or other characteristics. ‘Right to the City’ would mean that the interests of the wealthy would override those of the many; ‘Left to the Nature of Injustice’ would mean that the interests of the many would come first. 	[i] The Transindividuation Lab is a research project of the M.I.T. Bioengineering Laboratory, part of the M.I.T. Department of Neuroscience, part of the M.I.T. Graduate Center. The laboratory is affiliated with the M.I.T. Graduate School and is a partner in the M.I.T. Bioengineering Laboratory. The lab is led by Prof. Benjamin LeVay and includes graduate students, postdocs and researchers from many other institutions.  	[ii] The Biennale’s website describes the nature of the research question: ‘How do Indifference and Obligation shape Perception?’ The website</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of habitual residence or other characteristics. ‘Main’ Streets3  (2010), ‘Main’ Streets4  (2012), ‘Main’ Streets5  (2014), and ‘Main’ Streets6  (2015). Positions in this panorama are taken by people who call themselves the inhabitants of ‘New Mico’, although there is some debate about whether this is an indication of the city’s economic potential or merely an indication of the incredible diversity of the Mico-Tampico region. Positions in this panorama are taken by people who call themselves the ‘South Florida Express’ and ‘Sun Sentinel’ media outlets, although there is some debate as to whether these are necessarily the most progressive or progressive of the various media outlets that have adopted this panorama. Positions in this panorama are taken by people called ‘South Florida Five’ and ‘The Game Changers</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of habitual residence, rather than on crime or on the grounds of national origin. This is the idea of Hawaii Five Points (2013): a settlement between the US and Mexico over the construction of a border wall, which was challenged in court by the American Civil Liberties Union (2008–09). The US Supreme Court ruled against the government in 2010, and the issue is expected to return to the US Court of Appeals for the Ninth Circuit in San Francisco in 2016.1 	In these times of constant surveillance and constant war, it is easy to forget that we live in cities in which the very concept of individual freedom is under assault. The city is full of projects designed to monitor and control us, from the police to the military to the giant corporations that run the economy. Yet freedom is a concept that is constantly negotiated; it is never fully given and it is certainly never fully taken away. Freedom is a complex thing, and although it may be claimed by those who control the resources, it is possible</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of origin, which is a bit like the extradition treaties we have with countries such as Russia, but without the third party liability. ‘No Man’s Land’ would become the law of the sea, but since then a lot of treaty violations have happened. The question is, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector, whether real or imagined, be able to step in and take over the city, taking over what is left after the social, economic and spatial changes that result from a city’s redevelopment? I think that is the question, and I would add another: will the city be able to support, whether through direct investment, hiring urbanists or in the form of a tax abatement, a way of saying, yes, I do own this area and this is how I intend to use it? I think that is another question that needs to be answered. The   	Infrastructures of the Near and Middle</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of habitual residence. ‘Excessive detention?’, they would say.  	And the city would still be there, standing tall against the background of the newly minted global urban frontier. But the city is a city of constant renovation, so the question becomes, what can the city afford to neglect in the interest of its own future? 	Consider the example of the Piraeus Port, the largest single maritime port outside of Europe, now the home to over 1,100 ships and fuelling over 3,000,000 cars per day. Just over a year after the introduction of electric power in the port, the Mondragon Shipyards were forced to close due to lack of interest from prospective buyers. As a result, the city of Liverpool embarked on a €3 billion ‘Blue Chip’ initiative to modernise the waterfront’s appearance through a mix of new buildings, public art and public playgrounds. 	At the time, this seemed like a great</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation about the future, but it does seem like a very real (and very valuable) investment, both as an investment in the future of urban development in the US and internationally, whether that investment is in the form of investments or tourism. If this were to happen in Miami, it would mean that the city could tap into its full cultural potential – its art, its architecture, its history, its diversity – and that would be a major step forward for the city.  	The question becomes, will the city be able to leverage its potential, or will the private sector be able to step in and take over the city, or will the city and its inhabitants be able to pull this off on their own? 	The future city is the city in which there are no blockades, because then there would be no city, but blocks and borders still exist. In the city of the future, there would be no extradition treaties, but instead treaties that brought people to court based on place of habitual residence. Would people with chips on their shoulders say, ‘We’re going to move to the city because there’s no choice?’ 	The interesting question is what would happen to the inhabitants of the city in the event of a city shutdown. Would people be able to return to their neighbourhoods? I believe that the answer to that is a definitive ‘No’. The question becomes, what would happen to the neighbourhoods?  	The answer to that is a definitive ‘No’ because then the city would become international like Miami and Detroit, two of the world’s most disastrous urban developments. The reason why Miami and Detroit fell is that the citizens, after years of debt and without any other options, gave up on the idea that they could ever obtain any kind of government support for their neighbourhoods. 	The city would then become a giant in the international market, and the only way to stay in the city was to become</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and represent
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and representational devices’ that create and pervert ‘the real’.3 If we tune our biennial gaze in the other direction, that is, looking to nature, rather than the other way, then we can observe that our ‘representations and devices’ are only ever looking out for our own ends. And this observation is a recurring one. The biennial is a system that seeks to meet its end of the bargain at the expense of the other. It is a device that creates what it calls a ‘compelling interest’ in the natural world, but it is also a system that endangers its inhabitants as much as it benefits those looking the other way. And this is why biennials are, as Margaret Thatcher said, looking out for only their own ends.4 So what are the other ends? When we find ourselves trapped in a biennial – entranced by its seeming miracle of spatial persistence, or having been charmed by</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and representational practices’.3  As noted by the biennial critic Paul O’Neill, these ‘habits’ that characterise biennials are inherently rooted in and are thus inherently unstable: ‘What we might call the “habit” is but a set of habitual relations; it may be that some of these are essential for the maintenance of life on this planet.’4  Such is the ‘logic’ of ‘living by the patterns that nature* has established’, in the words of Jean Guy Lecat, who popularised the concept of habit in French literature, in contemporary languages and in biennials.5 So far, we have emphasised that biennials have a public function, that they are places where we gather to talk about art and about art’s place in our contemporary culture. But this is just the nature of the art museum. It has its own public function</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and representational devices’.3 So perhaps the biennial is not just interested in the things that are real, but in the ways that real life arises, that nature herself plays a part in creating and exacerbating our ‘representations and devices’.4 And here we can move from biennial to biennial – a kind of recursive operation that seeks to identify and address the things that generate ‘real life’, that are, in turn, generated by ‘representations and devices’.5 The question, then, becomes what kind of life can be generated through the things we designate as real life? Perhaps, in the words of Francis Bacon, ‘the life that happens to be real is life enough’.6 And if there are ‘things that can and must be taken for granted’, then perhaps it is time to acknowledge and perhaps to create ‘things that can nevertheless never be taken for granted’, including</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and representational devices’.3 Biennial curatorial approaches are often accompanied by a ‘system of symbolic acts and activities that draw their meaning from a place or set of places’.4 In other words, biennials may be driven by their corporate sponsors to become culturally significant, but they also have the capacity to become deeply embedded in the local environment, to live and act as symbolic acts in their own right. And this is precisely what biennials hope to do. They trumpet the institutionalisation of the biennial as a cultural construction, but it is also the capacity of most biennials to create symbolic acts that can then be replicated and adapted by their patrons. Thus, biennials can be seen as a kind of double-edged sword, able to simultaneously exploit their capacity as cultural entities and simultaneously exploiting the capacity of their local communities. And this is precisely what they are trying to do. Biennial funding comes with a precondition that many other</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and representational practices’.3 But perhaps it is more accurate to describe them as ‘haphazard and unpredictable phenomena’, with no fixed or predictable curatorial response.4 And here we can move from ‘real life’ to ‘imagined life’ and from ‘real life’ to ‘imagined life’, where the biennial is able to exhibit its manifest contradictions, seemingly able to create new ways of looking at old situations.5 And here we can also observe, from the vantage point of habit, that the biennial is able to do this through essentially reifying all life in terms of a single set of relations, which it then attempts to apply across a landscape of ever larger and more encompassing geographical areas. Understood in this way, the biennial exhibits a kind of self-perpetuating downward spiral into ever larger and more encompassing national parks and cultural clusters, as though these could be extended outward into</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and representational practices’, such as racism and sexism.3 And here we can move from ‘real life’ to ‘representations and representational practices’, and vice versa. The biennial may engage with the problems that arise from habit, or from nature, but it also exploits these problems as representations of the lived conditions that enable us to live differently. It is a ‘representation’ of the world as if the ‘world’ were an urban environment that is populated by individuals who happen to inhabit particular ‘regions’ of the city. It is a way of incorporating ‘what’ (in this case, white supremacy) into public space. But it is also a kind of public space that is populated by people of various sorts, and whose very architecture – its form and intention – is variable. Sometimes the ‘urban’ is made up of ‘mere buildings’, such as parking lots and strip malls</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and representational practices’.3 What is at Stake in Biennials? What is at Stake in Biennials?1. The Biennial as a Systemic Event. The first Biennale of Sydney was curated as a ‘systemic’ event, with elements of each institution ‘embedded in one another’.2. How Biennials Organise Their Worlds. In the case of Sydney, the biennial entered its third and final year as a ‘committed to exploring the city’, with elements of each institution ‘embedded in one another’.3. The Geographical Form and Content of Biennials. Biennials have entered their fourth and current iteration as a ‘form of cultural tourism’, with the last held in January 2017.4. The Crisis of Narrative, or what some would say, the Biennial Curse. As biennials enter the fourth decade of</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and representational practices’.3 Recent biennials, including those affiliated with major museums, are indeed exhibiting their ‘ideologies’, or the historical and social contexts of their real life, at a rapid clip. But this rapid-fire presentation – which I have seen many times during the past year – belies the historical processes that led to the biennial form.  And these, I would add, are mainly reflections of the ‘representational practices’ that biennial curators employ, and which tend to be of the ‘representational level’.  Biennial curators, including those associated with major museums, are, I believe, using the biennial form to reveal hidden or latent processes that produce ‘representations of life’, but also ‘false consciousness’ and ‘representations of non-living things’.4   They are discerning on the one hand the ways in which art is often presented in</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and representational practices’.3 And this is perhaps at the heart of biennial’s real power, its ability to inhabit and sublimate our representations and practices, to inhabit and sublimate our lives in innumerable ways, to emerge out of our representations and to reshape our world. As biennial curators, we must strive to inhabit our representations of the world in ways that are real and that can be curated, measured and experienced. We must also strive to create systems that can and will both support and constrain this power struggle. In short, we mustn’t just ‘represent the world as it is’. We can and should do much more than represent the world as it is.*** 	In  	Future City, Martha Ruiz describes the articulation of ‘heritage-led regeneration strategies in areas of the city’s ‘ring road’ – the under-construction and ring-</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial as if it were a ‘lottery’, where the lucky winner is invited to take part in a 'celebration of the mundane’.1 This ‘leap into consciousness’ seems to underlie the biennial’s fixation on its subjects, but it is also the point where biennials attempt to create sense by creating what Robert H MacDonald described as ‘a kind of consensus between habit and habit-formation’, between habit and nature, between habit and society.2 And here we can move from the biennial to the biennial as a curatorial gesture. The fact that biennials are institutions with a curatorial function – a function that can arise either from habit or from nature – suggests that perhaps we could say that they are also ‘systems problems’, with systems that can and must be addressed in order to address the ‘real life’ that results from our ‘representations and representational devices’ that create and abuse ‘ordinary people’.3  And here we can move from ‘representations’ to ‘real life’, between habit and nature, between habit and society. As biennials proliferate in the West, increasingly in contact with each other, we can infer that they are encountering their ‘real life’.4  And if the biennial is seen as a systemically generated phenomenon, then we can infer that the real life that results is also ‘representational’.5 Furthermore, we can infer that the real life that generates ‘representations’ is also ‘systemic’ in character, and thus far beyond the pale of contemporary artifice.  In fact, one might even agree that the real life that generates ‘representations’ is art itself.6  And so we can consider what a biennial might mean in the present. We</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
