<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to the museum as an institution that records and represents the past. She examines the role of archiving and research in the development of knowledge about the biennial form. Feminist and queer theory, archiving and research are among her major research interests.Gabriela Rendon is the author of The North Country (2007), about the direct effects of oil on the environment, and the forthcoming book The North Country (2015), an extended exploration of this history and politics. Drawing directly on her doctoral thesis, her work has been commissioned by and received critical acclaim. She has been a mentor for the North Dakota Museum of Art’s Curatorial Research project, was an assistant curator at the New York Museum of Art, and was part of the curatorial team for the biennale of the same name in London. She is a member of the editorial board of National Geographic’s Diggity dong: North America, 1928–39, and has a special interest in languages.Gabriela</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to the museum as a site of contemporary accumulation for cultural artefacts. Drawing directly from her dissertation, this work examines the relationship between the biennial and the museum as two distinct cultural sectors: the museum exhibits, and the biennial films, and the accumulated showpieces. It also examines the means by which these various forms of cultural material find expression in the contemporary North Dakota landscape. The journal in hand, the present as a continuous narrative, and the image as an object with a set of relations. In the Biennale context, the image is often taken as given, but the biennale as a whole works in a more dynamic and fluid way. In the case of the 1989 Biennale, the text and image were present in several locations throughout the city, but the images were projected onto a building material that is part of the overall urban fabric of the city.[1] In a wider perspective, this suggests that the projectors not only fed images to the projection process, but also the</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to the museum sector in Winnipeg. In addition to her duties as a curator, Gabrielle serves as the Director of the MFA program at the Winnipeg Art Gallery. She is an adjunct curator in the North Dakota State Museum's division on archival materials, including the Division of Archeology, Histories &amp; Special Collections. She is the author of the forthcoming book North Dakota: Art, Politics, Power (2015) and the forthcoming memoirs.Interview with Carl UlmerBy Carl UlmerCathy Petersen and Carol PetersenCarl Ulmer is Assistant Professor of English and Art History and Co-Chair of the Department of English and Art History. His research interests include early modern languages, literary forms, and the cultural histories of immigrant groups in Canada and the United States. In addition to his regular writing, he leads a multi-disciplinary artist's workshop group that includes artist-in-residence and former student groups, including those from the Department of English and Art History, the Duff</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to the museum sector in Canada.From the archive of the Modern Language AssociationGabriela Rendon is the Emeritus Curator of Collections at the Modern Language Association, Ottawa, which she joined in 2004. She has a special interest in the archives of language and is currently researching the Encyclopédie Rendon, the Ovidian Metafiction and the Ninety-Nine Theses, the publication of which she was instrumental in securing. She was a curator for the Ninety-Nine Theses Project, which indexed the writings of various thinkers in the Nineteenth Century on the presumption that they would be willing to share the archive with another living member of the Modern Language Association. Her current research interests include the archives of Modern and Contemporary Language Studies. In addition to serving on the board of directors of the Modern Language Association, she is co-editor of the forthcoming Asian Linguistics, or Asia Pacific Linguistics, from Verso Books, New York. She is also editor of the</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to the museum sector. Her work has been featured in various periodical and magazine catalogues and has received numerous international press coverage. She has received two honorary doctorates from the American Museum of Modern Art, the University of Chicago and the Zurich Museum of Art.In this article, I reflect on my research project, North Dakota: Visual Languages of the Dakota, which was presented in conjunction with the 20th International Conference on Computer-Human Interaction (2007) and the Pan-African Book of the Year (2009) in New York, and in conjunction with a symposium on computer-cultural interaction and innovation, to be held in Doha, Qatar, in October 2016. I reflect on the role of visual literacy in the creation of this visual language of social organisation. In addition to developing critical skills in researching and writing about North Dakota, I ask how cultural theorists can contribute to the construction of an ethnostate through the study of visual languages. Towards a Culture of Conflict?Gabriela</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to the museums in their North Dakota installations, and the need for the production of archives and documentation within the museums. She examines the relationship between biennials and the postcolonial diasporic world through archival and contemporary materials, and explores the possible meanings of the word ‘home’. Her dissertation will examine the relationship between the 1921 Bienal de São Paulo and the development of the biennial form in South America.It was actually part of a ‘developmental’ sequence. The 1893 World Columbian Exposition had been initiated in Durban and the 1893 Pan American Exposition was curated by Norman Wilkinson. The biennial had been planned for the following year, but a scheduling conflict meant that the exposition would be held in February, and the Pan Am in April. So we moved it up a year, 1893, and made it the first Biennale of the new century. We wanted to show the major works by the major artists from the time. The problem</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to the museum industry in both ‘North’ and ‘South’. Her dissertation examines the relationship between biennials and large art exhibitions, and examines the role that biennials may play in curating large-scale exhibitions. She examines the role of biennials in curating large-scale public spectacles, such as those of art, architecture and nature. She examines the role of biennials in curating radical visual art, such as that represented in the 1937 London Biennale, taking into consideration the industry’s large-scale patronage. She examines the role of biennials in curating critical art, such as that represented in the 2016 New York Biennale, taking into consideration the industry’s large-scale patronage. She examines the role of biennials in curating large-scale virtual art, such as that represented in the 2016 Venice Biennale, taking into consideration the industry’s large-scale patronage. In</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to the museum sector’s role in the production of biennials. Her dissertation examines the biennial as a production for the social reproduction of infrastructure, and the museum sector’s role in the social reproduction of images. It also examines the spatial and temporal dynamics of biennials as media of social reproduction. It will look at how art, architecture and commerce intersect with one another, and what these three sectors may mean politically, economically and culturally. Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to the 1891 Chicago and 1911 New York Museums, and the development of the biennials as cultural entities distinct from other art forms. She examines the relationship between biennials and archives, examining how the former are often critical for the development of the latter. She examines the relationship between biennials and the popular culture they serve, examining the latter’s potential to play a role in creating new identities and imagining alternative histories.Gabriela Rendon is the Curator for the exhibition The Contemporary Condition: Architecture, Nation and Environment (2014-15) at the National Gallery, London, which will present the work of architects and heritage organisations engaged in the redevelopment of Old Doha. She has co-curated several exhibitions for the gallery, including Architectural Legacies (2012-13), which curated the works of architects from around the globe; Scared Polar Bear (2012-13), a collaborative exhibition exploring the effects of global environmental crises; and Silent Spring (2014-15</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is the ultimate in its potentialities. It is time to put the past in the future.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the wider North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1889 Mexico City Biennale as a case study in the development of North Dakota’s cultural sector, and the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the development of the biennial form in North America. She examines the relationship between biennials and museums, with particular attention to the museum and the biennial as two types of museum. She examines the role of archival materials and archival practices in the construction of this narrative, and her own work in the field as a case study in the development of archival materials and archival practices in the construction of biennials.Gabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, Faculty in Cultural Studies. Her dissertation examines the 1989 Madrid Biennale as a vehicle for the social construction of an ethnostate in Canada’s Spanish-speaking North. Drawing on archival materials, including diaries, correspondence and archives, as well as her own research, this work examines the relationship between architecture, history and North Dakota, and the broader North American continent. Her dissertation examines the 1890 Chicago and 1911 New York Biennales as instances of the biennial form in North America. It examines how the biennial form entered North Dakota</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signalling-</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/ 	[ii] Curtis Hutchison and Neil Johnson, Two Cultures: Religion and Urban Development in the Twenty-First Century, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1985, p. 6–19. [iii] A. Bhargava,  	Globalization and Bureaucracy, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1987, p. 6. [iv] G. A. Masson, ‘Gravity’, in  	The New Economies of Exchange, ed. R. Scott Bakker, Blackwell, Oxford, 1988, p. 59.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is Professor in Geography at the Winchester School of Art and a former Chair of Geographical Studies at the Royal, London College of Art. His books include</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/ 	[ii] A few years earlier, in 2009, I published an essay in which I laid out briefly my then existing</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/ 	[ii] David Harvey, ‘The Architecture of the Future City’,  	Future City, 1997, p. 51.Download this article as PDFRafico RuizRafico Ruiz is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the McGill University, and holds a Bachelor of Arts and Bachelor of History in English Cultural Studies from McGill University, and a Master’s degree in French Cultural Studies from Concordia University. His dissertation examines the Grenfell Mission of the Roman Catholic Archdiocese of Montreal and its impact on the urban space of Montreal. He is also the co-editor of the forthcoming online journal PLATE (Placestheory, L’agenda Latina). His writing has been featured in The New York Times, The New</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/ 	[ii] Cameron Baucom,  	Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1987, p.103. Download this article as PDFPaul WeitzmanPaul Weitzman is an artist and writer. In 2011 he formed a hybrid collective work with filmmaker Noah Ward called ☴Weitzman Collective. The collective was concerned with the collective impact of culture production on social change, while at the same time questioning the institutional mechanisms of the arts. Weitzman's work often seeks to interrogate the political and the economic, and the role played by culture in constructing public space. He is the author of several books and the editor of the online art journal Stages. Weitzman is currently completing a PhD at Columbia University. He is also a regular columnist for the New York Times and</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/ 	[ii] Signaling Circulation blog, accessed 10 June 2018. 	[iii] The fusion of social media and biopolitics,  	www.quantum.org, accessed 10 June 2018. 	[iv] Gareth White, The Rise of Economic Complexity: Banking and the New Economy, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA, 2015. 	[v] ICRA Growth and Policy Brief No. 2, 2016, Washington, DC, p.3. 	[vi] Gareth White, The Geographies of Biopolitics, Routledge, London, USA, 1987, p.19. 	[vii] Gareth White, The Geographies of Biopolitics, Routledge, London, USA</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/ 	[ii] Holland, Christine. 	Cities and the Creative Class. New York: New Guineas University Press, 2017.  	[iii] Karpowska, Michal. 	C</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/ 	[ii] Baucom, Benjamin. The Crisis of the Metainth: Globalization, Nationalism, and Postcoloniality. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 2015. 	[iii] Gates, Jeffrey. ‘Psychopathology and the Cinema’, New York Review of Books, November-December, 1988, p.103–17. 	[iv] Gates, Jeffrey. ‘A Critique of Political</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/signalling-a-corner/ 	[ii] See, for example,  Stefan Molyneux and Christian Körner, eds.,  	The Language Machine (MIT Press, 2016), Chapter 6: Signs that Language is Malleable (MIT Press, 2016), p. 509. 	[iii] See, for example,  David</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultures exert a similar degree of control over the technology that is generated and carried out in their societies. In this respect, it is both prescient and timely. 	[i] See, for example,  The Expanding Geographies of Death: Globalization and Biopolitics,2 nd International Conference on Contemporary Art and Symbolism, 2014, Salt Lake City, UT; and ‘Signaling Circulation: Media Contagions and Contemporary Conditioning’, Quantitative Self, 2 nd Ed., P. 1–17, 2016, New York, NY and  	https://www.quantum.org/book/signaling-circulation/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-a-corner/signaling-an-a... [ii] Emmanuelle Landais,  	Signaling: Le vide de l'éducation sans coal (Paris: Laurence King &amp; Co-Corner, 2016), p. 11. [iii] Gordon Thomas,  	The Paranormal: Understanding the Why and the How of Unravelled (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1998), p. 218. [iv] Gordon Thomas,  	Unravelled, p. 50. [v] Thomas, supra note 4, at p. 75. [vi] Thomas, supra note 4, at p. 73. [vii] Gareth White,  	A Portrait of a Cattle Courier (1864–1920), part of the ‘British Art Portfolio’, in The Complete Biography of Andy Warhol, ed. Stefan Collini &amp; Christian Körner (New York: Oxford University</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale de Recherches Sur La Table at L’Agence Localitaire de l’Industrie et de L’Illustration at http://www.latinuradis.com/en/news/201207140400.html [accessed October 2017].11. 'Indigenous Peoples Television Special' (2017), hosted by Francine Murray, Indigenous Peoples Television, 2017.Description: A multi-platform, award-winning, public service Aboriginal media organisation, Indigenous People Television (IPTV) was formed in Montreal in 1997. It is an independent, publicly funded, educational non-profit broadcasting network with a national following in the Pacific Rim. In addition to general Indigenous programming, IPTV specialise in science and technology programming, film and video, and documents and events. The network also develops and hosts indigenous language education and storytelling projects. All programmes are jointly produced by the network, Indigenous communities and are archived online and in several Indigenous communities. The name Indigenous</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale Bolshy-Conway, The Ecology of Environmental Scarcity, Routledge, 2011, p.112.Download this article as PDFJennifer Mackenzie Jennifer Mackenzie is a writer, producer, and researcher whose work examines the entwined impacts of industrial, economic and political systems on communities of colour, indigenous peoples, and environmentally vulnerable populations around the world. She is the Director of the Centre for Research-Action on Globalization (C.R.A.G.), a multi-disciplinary centre for co-production and innovation in Vancouver, Canada. Her work has addressed a wide range of topics related to the environment, including: mining, oil and natural resources; manufacturing; agro-processing and agriculture; social and governance structures; and municipal politics and ordinances. Her latest work investigates the intersection of economic and social development with ecological systems theory. She is a co-editor of the forthcoming Asian Pacific Journal of Social Science Publishing.Her writing has also appeared in the New York Times, Washington</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale de Recherches TropicalesComité pour le Dauphine, La Casa Encendida, Chile �[1] http://www.greenpartners.org/en/campaigns/environment/index.html (accessed March 2018).[2] Desert Island Community Land Trust, The Desert Island Conservation and Research Alliance: http://www.disantsialislandtrust.org/about/en/search/results.html?q=forest+islands (accessed April 2018).[3] The Conservationists, http://www.conservationists.org/resources/default.asp?faq=about_conservationists_20160921-the-conservationist-movement-is-dominating-world-history.html (accessed October 2018).[4] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Crisis of Conformity: On Media Culture and Politics in Late Imperial Japan�</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale de Théorie poétique à l'apparence de l'Université Paris-Sud, convenée nationale de biennales, là, Paris, France.Samantha Jones, ‘Climate-sensitive cities emerge as new frontiers in battle against global warming’,  	Gulf Television, September 2017, http://gulfnews.com/news/gulf/u-s-climate-sensitive-cities-emerge-as-frontiers-in-battle-against-global-warming-20180917, accessed 10 June 2013.10. Gareth Hughes, ‘30 years of satellite monitoring,   GRACE researcher on Antarctic Monitoring (1991–2005), Goddard Institute for Space Studies,  	, New York and London, England, October 2010. 11. Satish Kanady, ‘Heat map: Melting-pot climate m</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale de Développement (Founder and Chair)2015Granby Four (2nd Largest Landholding Company)2015Geoff CoxThe Geographical Forms of Globalisation[1] A.I. Farooqi, ‘On the Use of Urban Space in Cultural Production’, in, Jacques Rancière, ed., The Geographical Forms of Globalisation, Blackwell, Oxford, 1991, p.335.Download this article as PDFJacques RancièreJACQUES RUNCIEREAR, The Geographical Forms of Globalisation, Blackwell, Oxford, 1991, p.335.Download this article as PDFJacques RancièreJACQUES RUNCIERE, The Geographical Forms of Globalisation, Blackwell, Oxford, 1991, p.335.Download this article as PDFJacques RancièreJACQUES RUNCIERE, The Geographical Forms of Globalisation, Blackwell, Oxford, 1991, p.335.Download</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale de Ministère en Recherches Sociales (2013-2019).Download this article as PDFJennifer MackieJenny HolzerJenny Holzer is a writer and Environmental Economist with a particular interest in the role of the arts in advancing ecological sustainability. She has a particular interest in the ways in which art can be used to address social and political issues, and has contributed to a number of publications including the Greening of Education Futures (2012-2015) and the Greening of Urban Futures (2015-16). She has also been part of the curatorial team for the Greening of Europe’s Cities conference, where she curated a number of projects including: Constructive Thinking Cities, co-curated with Ewa Talepa and Ewa Tepézadeh; Evolution, a public symposium on the ecological, climatological and urban impacts of migration in Lisbon, Portugal (2016); Dazzle the Migrant</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale de Triennale, Venice, Italy, 2015. Photo courtesy of Green Party of Canada.PreviousNextInternationale de Triennale, Venice, Italy, 2015. Photo courtesy of Green Party of Canada.Internationale de Triennale, Venice, Italy, 2015. Photo courtesy of Green Party of Canada.Internationale de Triennale, Venice, Italy, 2015. Photo courtesy of Green Party of Canada.Internationale de Triennale, Venice, Italy, 2015. Photo courtesy of Green Party of Canada.Internationale de Triennale, Venice, Italy, 2015. Photo courtesy of Green Party of Canada.Internationale de Triennale, Venice, Italy, 2015. Photo courtesy of Green Party of Canada.Internationale de Triennale, Venice, Italy, 2015. Photo courtesy of Green Party of Canada.Internationale de Triennale, Venice, Italy, 2015. Photo courtesy of Green Party of Canada.Note to editors: With over 400 venues for the 2016</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale de Chine, 2011. Photo courtesy of Green Party of CanadaInternationale de Chine, 2011. Photo courtesy of Green Party of CanadaI have been privileged to work with many artists over the years, and I can say that I have never met an artist who was not deeply affected by one way or another by the art being created in the context of the Global South. Artists, curators, writers, collectors, activists – they were all deeply involved in the movements that brought us into being. The relationship between the artist and audience was often raw, but that was also true of the people creating the art, and the people creating the movements. But the audience was also diverse, had a range of identities, and could move anywhere in the world. And so the audience had a range of rights, and so did the artist. I would say that the key was that the rights defining the area in which they operated were absolute, whereas the rights of the artist were contextual. So the audience had</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale de Sao Paulo, 2011. Photo courtesy of Green Party of Canada.Our question is this: how do we as citizens of the planet, as inhabitants of this planet, come to terms with the fact that we are no longer the dominant species on this planet? In what ways do we actively contribute to the maintenance of planetary biodiversity? How does the ecological impulse come to dominate human beings’s ecological systems? How do we collectively come to understand that the dominant ecological impulse is not necessarily the one that we want?How do we collectively come to understand that the dominant ecological impulse is not necessarily the one that we want?Let me give you an example from my own perspective. I am a writer, curator and researcher who works as an artist, writer and researcher in the area of biopolitics. I'm interested in the ways in which biopolitics is relevant to the current state of things in the world. I'm interested in the way in which biopolitics is happening in and through our</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are being violated in the name of economic development, and how the ecological destruction that resulted from global industrialisation is being funded in the name of 'progress'. The book raises questions that governments, think tanks, non-governmental organisations and corporate interests would prefer not to raise. It is a document that exposes the human rights violations occurring in the world today, but it is also a document that calls for the ecological destruction of the human rights violations that are being perpetrated against the planet.This is the mission of the Green Party of Canada, as stated in our 2011 Platform:To work in solidarity with those in the Global South who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;To help those in the Global North who are struggling to gain access to means of knowledge and expression;And To serve as a test-bed for future research, so that we may overcome the present challenges and achieve a world based on justice and equality.For more information, visit our websiteGreen Party of CanadaInternationale de Recherches Surisés, Lévesque, 2011. © Joasia KrysaLara FavarettoThe Green Party of Canada seeks to build a radical ecological and democratic future for ourselves and the planet. We build movements, campaigns and partnerships based on justice and equality, not on the exploitation of space and wealth. We demand a humane future for our future generations, working in solidarity to protect the planet from the ravages of industrial capitalism. The Green Party of Canada was founded in Toronto in 1980. We are a democratic party committed to building transformative social change through self-sufficiency for people to build a future for their families. We believe in building long-term ecological solutions through collective action, so that we can create a world based on mutual benefits and no-remedies. The Green Party of Canada is the only national political party in Canada with a platform that addresses climate change and is a leader in the international arena. We build campaigns based on equity and inclusion, not</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�s long military campaign in the region, published the following January that year. The two issues of Reader’s Digest that same year feature a lengthy essay by Bernard Jack Lewy in support of the monarchy’s claim to the region. In the essay, Lewy recounts the humiliation and barbarity of the Shia Turkestan people during the late nineteenth century, when British rule was challenged in both the city and the peninsula. The Empire is undone, he writes, ‘in the name of religion’. The Shia Turkestan are portrayed as barbaric and unintelligent. ‘War is murder and theft’, Lewy’s narrator intones.The opening lines of the poem, by then a familiar refrain, recall the nineteenth-century British imperial impulse to carve up nations into distinct national units. The narrator’s desire to rout populations ‘of a given size, shape, language or caste’ is as undeniable as the empire’s appetite</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�s Empire Foundation, published the following month. In the introduction, Lewy and Hitchens recount how they found themselves compelled to write a chapter called �The Enduring Mystery of the West, Part 1’in the wake of the invasion of Iraq. They write:The spectacle of the massed ranks of armed military forces on all continents, bombed-out cities in preparation for a planetary war, the wholesale burning of cities and the uprooting of peoples … the constant re-constituting and reinvention of new forms of government, from municipal to federal, old and new – all this in the name of economic growth and the collective triumph of a single, highly visible set of beliefs – is an image that has endured to this very day.2. The museum – the new single-site market. The museum is the museum without walls. It is the museum with no collection. It is the museum that gathers and exhibits, with no fixed collection of objects. It is the museum with a</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�s External Action Network, published the same year. The two journals, and their appendices, are divided into three sections titled ‘Intelligence Gatherings’ and ‘Projections’ – brief reflections on what the media described then and what the biennials today do with the information they gather. The section ‘Intelligence Gathering’ begins with a review of the ‘New York Times’s Leading Edge, a ‘database of the latest news on terrorism’, which the two journalists present maintain is the single most important journalism resource of the 21st century. The ‘Projections’ section of the journal then narrates the evolution of the concept of ‘adversarial’ – a hybrid term describing contemporary and historical adversarial encounters – and the journal’s section titled ‘Intelligence Gatherings’ refers to the influential reports of the Director of National Intelligence, James R. Clapper Jr., who’s</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�s Round-up, published that same year. The two poets revisit the events that precipitated the war, and they quote from contemporaneous accounts of the retreat of the British Empire from Afghanistan. The poem was originally published in the September 1971 issue of Byte, the British military newspaper, and is one of at least 200 published reflections on the invasion of Vietnam.I Question, December, 1971. Photo courtesy of Bernard Jack Lewy Archive. [1] The Cambridge History of English Poetry, edited by David Raeburn and Tom Vandeputte. Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2005, p. 7.[2] John Berger, ‘The Enduring Crisis of the City’ in the New York Times, 3/26/2014, p. A1.[3] John Berger, ‘The Enduring Crisis of the City’ in the Washington Post, 11/21/2014, p. A1.[4]</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�s Round-up, published the previous October. The two journals, both published by HarperCollins, are the only surviving works of the British Empire Quarterly.The earliest biennials did not necessarily align themselves with the prevailing power structures of their countries. In the early twentieth century, the biennial became the object of a sustained and sometimes violent policy of nationalizing (including the US) that saw the biennial as a fundamentally corrupt institution. The UK’s National Theatre, which had regularly staged shows in Britain since 1903, began staging plays in the historic Biennale building in protest. In 1936, Theatre Royal, the theatre company that had staged December ‘The Great Dictatorship’ in 1903, formed a union. In a move that would become standard procedure across the theatre, the Biennale was nationalized in 1939. The union demanded that its members undertake a year-long sit-down strike in November ‘to demand a share in the spoils’</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�s Round-up, published the same day. The two poets write:As the bodies were hacked to ribbons …the invader closed in … We were like the rest of the human race, stinking like a bunch of dogs … We were cut off like the rest of the world … Then the great bomb went off. We were like a clusterfuck of disconnected bits.Now we’re stuck together like sardines in a whirlpool … We’re stuck in this mess of causes and effects … We’re stuck in this round of misadventures and disappointments.I Question begins, with an Old Dandy sort of thing: The biennial must end, must become something else: a museum, or it ceases to be a biennial. It cannot end like the old days of petroglyphs and radiations and billboards and series of museums, for this is not the way to a biennial evolve. It must grow up, and it</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�s fight against fascism. The event that year, the invasion of Iraq, marked the beginning of British colonialism.The poem is a riff on the war, but it is also a plea to arms: to arm yourselves against the blandishments of imperialism. You needn’t do it alone. A co-operative bank might be a start, but to truly arm yourselves, you need a shop that stocks self-help literature and motivational art posters. The British Empire is becoming increasingly evident in the lives of ordinary people all over the world: in the empty store fronts in fast-food restaurants, in the empty streets in the parking lots of super-sized cars. And yet we know very little about it. Why not?Well, why not? Why not?The reason, I think, is that we Americans tend to think of the British Empire as something that occurred in our country, especially in the context of our own history. We don’t tend to connect the historical with</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�s military operations in Afghanistan at the time.The poet begins his poem with the line – a paraphrase of a statement attributed to Howard Zinn: ‘The only way to end a war is to ask the right question, do the right thing, and give the enemy the ammunition to back up that decision.’ The poem ends with the line – a paraphrase of a quote from Zinn: ‘To hell with the past, the future is where the struggle for existence begins.’2 The poetic form here takes on a life of its own, moving from the battlefield to the realm of poetry, asking questions of the temporal and the immaterial, of the material and the immaterial, and of the inevitable and the impossible. It is a form that is often used in its own right, as in the line: ‘The biennial, or new art biennial, is an art form in its own right.’3 The biennial, in turn,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�s Middle East Service. In the introduction, Lewy and Hitchens quote from two letters of thanks from then Home Secretary Jack Straw to the biennial for its part in the war effort. As the poem reads:How grateful I was for your kind reminder that the enormous, moth-eaten beast known as England’s second largest army in the twentieth century was still stirring in the wake of your invasions and occupations.And yet somehow, someway, we both feel that we owe it to those who gave so much to us to remember that we were but a few steps behind those war heroes when we were caught so transfixed by the spectacle of your ghastly new uniforms.You and your ilk of haters still hate on Biennials, but at least now I’m not one of them. That’s at least eight decades of fairly steady, almost inexhaustible, even if occasionally un-imaginable, funding from the British state at any</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, with artists, curators, art historians, artists and others taking part in a collaborative process through workshops, events and publications. The Liverpool Biennial 2018 will see its first public performances in September.Biennials are an international art form that was originally created in the United States in response to the First World War. They have become so ubiquitous that they are routinely cited in primary and secondary sources, though few Americans actually know that the first biennial was held in Liverpool in 1864. The first evidence of the institution’s history emerges in the book I Have a Question, published in 1971, when a journalist interviewing biennials Christopher Hitchens and Bernard Jack Lewy, begins to narrate their relationship to the war. I Question, edited by Bernard Jack Lewy and Christopher Hitchens, is a poem that documents the fall of Saqqara Province in Afghanistan in October 2001. The poem is based on a chapter from Reader’s Digest, the journal of the British Empire�s Empire Project, launched by Harold Innis in January 1942. The essay is a rambling rumination on the sins of the empire. Britain and France had just been defeated in World War II, and the poem is a lament for the lost cause. As the reader, you’re not sure which side you’re on. The Empire of Heaven and Earth was all that remained, and the Empire of Hell was collapsing. The end result, according to Hitchens, was that we, the British, ‘willed[d] ourselves to be cowed by the force of the explosion, which swept away all who stood in its way.’[6]The implosion of the Empire was a general feature of twentieth-century capitalism; its deindustrialisation, which was accelerating at the time, was also a feature of the global capitalist juggernaut that was beginning to consume the planet. The implosion of the British Empire was part of this process of capitalist expansion,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission
    <text>presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission, and the European Research Council (ERC London), supported by the European Commission. It was written by Elhanauer, Samahy and Houry with contributions from others.The Cultural Logic of Digital CulturesTim JeevesTim Jeeves is Professor in the School of Communication and Culture, Cornell University, and holds the Distinguished Chair in Cultural Studies at the Creative Time Laboratory. His research interests include digital culture (with a special focus on emerging media), media ecology, participatory practices, participatory architecture, media ecology and media history. His work has been featured in books such as the New York Times Book Review, the Los Angeles Times, the Chicago Tribune, the New York Times Digital Culture Blog, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the Journal of Architectural Anthropology, and the University of Chicago Press, to name only a few). His book, ‘Cultural Logic of Digital Cultures: Intersectionality and Stratagem,’ addresses this research in depth.</text>
    <text>presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission. It was edited by Elhamy &amp; Houry, as well as by members of the staff of MEME, including Helga Nowotny. The project was also supported by the European Commission’s Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2007-2016), which is the biological offspring of the project in Paris. 	[i] European Commission, FP7/2007–2016, MEME, 2015. Download this article as PDFElhamy &amp; Houry, Gabrielle C. &amp; Joasia L.A. Castellsas Escargots: On the Origins, Development, and Future of the Palestinian People. New York: Palgrave MacMillan, 2015.   [ii] European Commission, MEME, 2015. Download this article as PDFElhamy &amp; Houry, Gabrielle C. &amp; Joasia L.A. Castellsas Escargots: On the Origins, Development, and Future of the Palestinian People. New York:</text>
    <text>presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission. It was edited by Dahn Braudel and Thomas Ashenden.The exhibition was curated as a symposium with the participation of a number of cultural and jurisprudent figures in the region. It was distinguished by the absence, so far as was possible, of any kind of head-to-head competition between the participants. Instead, the symposium was divided into two parts: the part on the arts and culture of the Middle East, and the part on the arts and culture of Europe. Part of the symposium was devoted to the needs of artists and organisations in the region, which was attended by representatives from all over the world. The symposium became a research project, and the proposals and responses of the participants were put into one of several research projects. The geographical and temporal locations of the participants in the symposium are given in the text. The editors chose to select from among these participants, since they constituted a small minority within a minority, and their positions on</text>
    <text>presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission, and was originally published in English as a journal article in MEME’s online journal EARTH (ECRR 2017).Download this article as PDFFurat El Samahy and Nadim HouryFurat El Samahy is a writer, curator, and producer. He is Professor in the European Research Council's Division for Arts and Social Sciences at the London School of Economics and Political Science and the European Graduate School, as well as Director of the European Graduate School’s European Network Initiative. His most recent book, The Public Theater: Performance, Capital, and Modern Culture (2018), is the subject of a one-day, multi-disciplinary performance and writing contest taking place in June in New York. His most recent project for the United Kingdom’s National Theatre is the production of Les Misérables: Extremes, premiers at the Edinburgh International Theatre Festival 2019. He is the recipient of several international awards and has received a host of accolades and recognitions</text>
    <text>presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission, and was originally published in French as Le Devoir No. 1 in 2002. It has been translated several times, most recently into English as Diverting Attention: Globalisation and Political Participation in the Age of Intangible Assets. 	[i] Election Campaign Report, The One Show (2016), p.20.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is Professor in European Cultures and Head of ESRD Istanbul, specializing in postmodernism and critical culture. Her research interests include the history and current state of critical and postmodern cultural studies in Turkey, as well as in other East European and North African countries; the United States, Canada and the Middle East. She is the co-editor of the forthcoming book (with Lynn Gumpert and Peter Weibel) The Culture Trap: Eurocentric Cultures of Imperial Identity (2017) which will investigate how technological innovation and fast cash can lead to a transient form of national belonging that is</text>
    <text>presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission, and the European Graduate School (EGS), affiliated with the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology (ETH Zurich). It was edited by Jussi Parikka and Daniela Ginsburg.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is a PhD Candidate in English and Film Studies at the University of Alberta. Her dissertation, The Alien by Midnight, investigates the literary and cinematic representations of the Near East in contemporary fiction and film. She examines the ways in which the present moment is constructed through literary devices – from the literary form to its cultural forms – and the processes that enable and create this fictional space. She examines the politics of literary and cinematic voyages in the context of the migrant crisis, and the curatorial turn of literary and cinematic critics. She looks at the relationship between critical literacy and cultural studies, and how literary texts and figures – both fictional and not – can be reconfigured through knowledge production. She considers the possibilities for a ‘critical filmography’, and the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission, which administers the project. Its publication is part of the wider research project ‘Projections?’ organised by the European Research Council, with funding from the EU's Seventh Framework Programme, and part of the wider European City Initiative (EDI), a programme of cooperative research and development jointly managed by the European Commission and ERAD, funded by the Italian Council for Research and Innovation.  References [1] See Philip E Agre, The City of Industry: Globalization and its Challenging Tides (Cambridge, Massachusetts and London, England: The MIT Press, 1994). [2] Philip E Agre, The Structure of Cities (Cambridge, Massachusetts and London, England: The MIT Press, 2008), p. 10. [3] Philip E Agre, The Structure of Urban Space (Cambridge, Massachusetts and London, England: The MIT Press, 2008), p. 10. [4] Philip E Agre, The Structure of Urban Politics (Cam</text>
    <text>presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission, and was first published in Paris.A View of Europe (1914–1918)By Alfred NobelAlfred Nobel (1879–1957) was an American writer and editor. His works include essays, reviews, poetry, diaries, articles, and fiction on a range of subjects, including the mining of gold, cotton, timber, horses, horses-riding, travel, photography, landscape painting, and sculpture. His most widely published work, The Lord of the Rings: Return of the King, won the 2007 Pulitzer Prize for Fiction. He has written extensively on the environment, notably for The New York Times, where he coined the phrase ‘eco-ana’.In Europe, Alfred Nobel’s most widely published work is From Oil to Brass in the American Journal of Political Science. He is the editor of the online political science journal The West, and the former editor of the online journal M.I.T. He has edited numerous books,</text>
    <text>presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission. It was written by Elad Pamuk and Irene Hofmann with additional writing by myself. The project was supported by the Carré de Cuvente Foundation (France), the Lansdowne Foundation (United Kingdom), and the Fundació Nacional de Ciência (Mexico).  The project was also supported by the Australian National University (ANU), with funding from the Commonwealth Scientific and Research Organisation (CSROO), the Norwegian and Danish Universities, and the Australian National Science Foundation. 1   	Tim R. McVicar and Christian Körner, ‘On the use and abuse of time in social and psychological research’, in  	Condensed Contemporary Cultural Studies, Issue 3 (2000), p.1019.  2  John A. Church and Neil J. White, ‘Time and its temporal variations: a critical review of the literature’,  	Condensed Contemporary Cultural Studies, Issue 3 (</text>
    <text>presented as an online project that has evolved into a full-fledged, internationally syndicated publication. In this volume, Firat El Samahy and Nadim Houry assess the present moment in the history of Middle East studies, and present the prospects for a future in which the Middle East will play a significant role in world economies and politics. They also examine current geopolitical situations in the region, and offer three main directions for the future of Middle East studies: toward a more equitable distribution of global resources, or toward a situation in which the rights of new middle-class citizens are being created. With special attention is given to the needs of Palestinian citizens of Israel and the occupied Palestinian territories, since these are the most at-risk of disappearing under the rubric of globalized neoliberalism. This volume is the product of a joint project between the European Research Council (Eurairscapes, Paris) and the European Union (Main Centre for Research in L’agreement – MEME), funded by the European Commission. With contributions from staff from the European Commission, the University of Lyon, and other relevant research institutions, it was successfully tested in several European cities. In addition to the main text, the volume includes an archive of illustrations and illustrations of various Middle East topics. In these, the artist Nadim Houry presents a survey of current cultural forms in the region, including the role of artists in envisioning a future for the region. He also investigates the role of artists and the transportable media in envisioning a future for artists in the region, and in particular for artists in the Gaza Strip. The volume also includes an introduction by Manal Shehade, a renowned Palestinian artist, whose work has been exhibited in numerous European capitals including London, New York, and Istanbul. It comes as part of the Quartet exhibition, Future Shock , curated by Yaacov Androssov, at the Umm al-Hiran Museum, Jerusalem.Artists and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change course and actively try to deny it. Fortunately, there are technologies now that can be used to help us achieve that future. There are also ways to help create it – ways to harness the technologies and science that will allow us to achieve that future.One of our projects is Climate Central, a collaboration between the World Meteorological Organization (WMO) and the private firm DLA Piper, which is developing the Global Climate Model (GCM) that will allow other scientists to simulate the effects of climate change on a global scale. The company’s research division, for example, is developing technologies that could enable cities to rapidly capture and store hydrocarbons from the ground and sea, and to release those hydrocarbons through wastewater treatment plants. The liquids can be used to power cities or used to make biofuels, which are ultimately used as fossil fuels. We’ve teamed up with WMO scientists to collaborate on a project titled, Large-Scale Internal Reflection Maps (L</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change course and lead into catastrophe. That is why we are building the largest and most sophisticated science and engineering infrastructure on the planet – and why a large part of the research budget is already earmarked for projects that will make the city ever more like nature.Building the FutureWe believe that the future we seek is one in which people and communities of people live together in tranquility and co-existence, responding to the environment in ways that are adaptive to the changing climate, and yet also the environment in ways that are not. That is, of course, if we are building the future on the back of the past. We can build the future on the back of what we learn about the city today, but in the meantime we must learn to live differently, to love differently, to grow differently. This may require us to change our ways of working, our lifestyles and our architecture, to become more resourceful, more urbanists and artists, to adopt new ways of existing and growing, and so forth</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change course and pursue a course of geoengineering in the direction of increasing the efficiency of the global economy. We envision a future in which the climate is no longer a defining feature of global economic exchange, but is instead a globally competitive global science and engineering league.We envision a world in which local, regional, and international cooperation are the order of the future. We envision a world in which cities not just exist, but actively contribute to the functioning of the economy through their built form, policies, and services. This may include incorporating aspects of their own economic activity in creating and enhancing the macroscopic infrastructure of cities. We envision a future in which climate is not just a defining concept, but a defining innovation. That is, in which buildings and the buildings around them respond to changes in their composition and density through their controlled behaviour, and in which the resulting climate is a significantly modifiable trait. This may include aspects of urban growth that are no longer dictated by the city’s growth spurts</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change course and turn into zero-carbon forms. That is, unless we act now to address the crisis of our climate, or unless we drastically alter our trajectory in the coming decades.To understand what we mean by ‘all of humanity’ we must understand what we mean by ‘potential future inhabitants of the planet’. We believe that the future we seek is one in which life on Earth spreads out into the vastness of space, not pinned down by the Earth as a singularity. This means that life forms everywhere will have the opportunity to evolve and expand, constantly seeking out new materials and crafting new ways of interacting with the planet. We call this spreading ecology of possibilities.We also believe that the future we seek is one in which the collective responsibility for solving the climate crisis shifts from the individual to the collective will of the people. Thus, we propose the establishment of a global commission – the so-called ‘Potential Adjacent Measures’ – to map</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change course and pursue an aggressive course of geoengineering – the deliberate injection of water, gas and other elements into the stratosphere to alter the course of Earth's climate. We believe that we are well within the realms of possibility to achieve this goal, but we must begin by asking, what is the probability that we will be able to achieve it?The reasonable response to this question is that we should aspire to something greater than our current level of sustainability, but we also need to work towards something greater than our current level of climate resilience. The more we can add to the climate beyond what we currently produce, the more impact that we can exert on the system. We need to find ways to work with the finite resources we have. Isolate the problem from the rest of the planet and focus on the things that matter most to us – our home, the land and our homes. This may require some adapting to the changing climate, but it is also a necessity if we are to exert any influence at</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change course and begin to depend on energy from fossil fuels. In that case, we face the challenge of rebuilding what is left after a major cataclysm, and we believe that the sharing of responsibility for the future will come about through a common bond of shared humanity. This is why we’re calling for a Climate Capital of the World’s Future, a shared and equitable share of the wealth created by the climate. In other words, we don’t see ourselves as artists or inventors, but as consumers and shareholders of that wealth – a share that will in turn empower artists and thinkers worldwide. We believe that the future we seek should be one in which the majority of humanity owns a stake in the resources of the planet.We launched the project in New York’s Lower East Side, with installations by MOCAD pioneers such as Marija Cetinicula, Sol Aramendi and Eduardo Paolantonio, as well as artists including</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change course and pursue a course of global cataclysmic destruction. That is, unless we act now, and commit ourselves to radically altering our behavior in the coming decades in an attempt to disrupt the underlying causes of climate change.The Climate Report 2015, prepared by the Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change (IPCC), projects that, unless dramatic action is taken, the climate will be warmer than at any time in the past century, and that could lead to widespread conflict. Given the stakes, why have we not taken decisive action yet? Why are we so paralyzed by inaction? Why do we continue to allow the climate to escalate in such a way that extreme weather events become more frequent and more destructive?Why do we continue to allow the climate to devolve into conflict? Why are we paralyzed by decisions that could potentially make our cities less vulnerable to catastrophic damage? Why do we devote so much energy to trying to contain and adapt to the effects of climate change when our planet is so much more important than any</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change course and seek to destroy ourselves in a mad rush to create more fossil fuels. Fortunately, there are things we can all do to help shape the future in interesting ways. There are ways to adapt to changing temperatures, and ways to research how to alter the climate in interesting ways. We can also create our own cool, cool places to live – places that aren’t scorched Earth or in danger of becoming uninhabitable – places where extreme weather doesn’t happen.We have identified three themes that are complementary to the three themes we plan to unveil at the conference – technology, aesthetics and sustainability – and want to share them with you in this brief document. It is my hope that these three themes will bring people together, excite them and engage them in different ways. For me, in my role, this means finding ways to work with people from different disciplines and styles to create something new and interesting in a city, a region or a country. It means finding ways to work</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change course and seek to join the fossil fuel epoch. We believe that ‘energy independence’ is the path of least resistance in the coming era of climate change.That is, unless we act now to halt the catastrophic trend of climate change and drastically reduce our reliance on fossil fuels. If we do that, we risk becoming merely the sixth largest carbon emitter in the world, dwarfing China and Russia as the largest emitters, and becoming merely the second largest after the massive pile of coal and oil we left behind. We envision a world in which all of humanity can live in harmony with the climate, in harmony with nature, and in harmony with each other. We envision a world in which people walk the planet with bicycles, cars, planes, and even superhighways. We envision a world in which people travel between places due to efficient transport networks, and not just in the sense of convenience: people in cars will always need to pass through congested areas, and will always have to</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed. The exhibition will feature cutting-edge research into the causes and consequences of human-induced climate change, using cutting-edge equipment and materials, and employing cutting-edge science and engineering. The resultant documentary film will show how the effects of climate change will be linked to more than just production, with devastating social impacts. The film, 'Our Smarter Cities’, will highlight how cities are impacted by a changing climate, how local resources are affected by climate change, and how the responses to these impacts could be improved through better infrastructure and science. The film will show how cities can adapt to these changes, leveraging emerging science and technology to meet the challenges of a rapidly changing climate.We are creating a Climate Capital of the World’s Future – a shared, shared responsibilityWe believe that the future we seek is one in which all of humanity becomes energy independent, and in which the planet is habitable for countless generations to come. That is, of course, unless we change course and pursue a course of catastrophic climate change. Fortunately, we know how to change course. And there are ways to prepare cities and regions for the impacts of climate change: ways to adapt by building more resiliency-intensive alternatives to fossil fuels, for example. But there is still a great need for adaptation. In our view, there is only one future, and all of humanity, rich and poor, should strive to achieve that future.So how can cities create their own future? We believe that the answer is in the cities. And we believe that the future we seek is one in which there are cities growing ever richer and stronger, in which the few who remain in poverty are few and the many are many. That is, of course, if the poor in the future are able to pursue advanced science and technology, and migrate to the richer coastal regions where more sand is produced and more fish are caught. But there is no lack of resources for that today, in terms of sand</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done
    <text>should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done by the artist herself, by the curatorial team, and most importantly, by the artist herself, in order to be able to tell the story in a meaningful way. It’s that point where the art begins to take on the social context, where the community and the art team begin to coexist and coexist in ways that are authentic to the community.But even then, there are limits. The limits to the project itself are very specific. The limits to Community Arts practice are very specific. And even then, the social conditions that result from those limits are going to be very different from the social conditions that result from other kinds of art practices. And so the idea of the museum as a place of negotiation, where the artist can and must exert influence in order to achieve what she wants, and the community can and should do the same, is something that is very different from what we think of as the ideal of the museum.And so there are limits, and I think that</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done by experts, not by average people. The level of sophistication needed to negotiate this kind of complexity is a world apart from what a beginner can achieve. There is a difference between the level of an art student and an artist. And so the curatorial team started thinking about how art could be delivered to communities through activities such as playgroups, groups of friends, neighbourhood newspapers, schools, neighbourhood libraries, soup kitchens, tutoring programmes and art fairs. And so the curatorial approach began to change, and with it, inevitably, the way communities were integrated. A community could be integrated into the curatorial team, and not necessarily into the planned activities, but it was always going to be an approximation, because the goals and parameters of the project were always going to be different. For example, the art fairs were never going to be as prevalent as they are now, because the artist wouldn’t want to be the only one coming through the doors, and because the communities that frequent</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done through an intermediary institution, not the other way around. In this way, the museum is a facilitator, not a mediator, in this process of community-to-community reciprocity. If the museum were to become involved in a community-based way, it would create a different negotiation between the artist and the community.I have a question for the museum: what relationship does art have with the community? In my opinion, the museum should actively engage the community in the negotiation of participation in the art institution. It’s the only way to ensure that the community gets a voice in the art institution. The museum shouldn’t be some kind of arbiter of what is or is not art within the community.Art’s role in communities should be negotiated, not imposed, and the museum should be a mediator in that negotiation.I met a few artists recently who had a proposal that was similar to mine: they said they wanted to participate in a project under the</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done carefully, because the negotiation could potentially destroy the very basis of the relationship between the museum and the community. The fact of the art being made, and the community’s response to it, is real, and it happens in the context of the community, but it is not a negotiating chip. It is a real negotiation, but it is also a negotiation that destroys the basis of the relationship. Because the moment that the curator has that negotiation chip, he or she is faced with the real negotiation: the negotiation between the community and the art institution. And so the relationship that the museum has with the community is real, but it is also a negotiation that destroys the basis of the relationship. If the foundation of the relationship is undermined, or if the art is not put into the context that it should be put into, then the relationship could also be undermined. That is the nature of the negotiation that the artist and the museum must engage in, and it is happening right now, especially in the</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done with care, because it could undermine the integrity of the project. In the end, the integrity of the project is what makes it interesting, what makes it worth coming to, and what keeps it from becoming just another establishment, like so many other art institutions around the country.In the end, perhaps, the real art in the world isn’t made by artists with a mission to make art for people; it’s made by people who have the capacity to imagine and deliver works that will be meaningful and authentic to communities, and to draw people to them through their work, through genuine love and friendship. I don’t think that means the work of an artist or the art of community would necessarily be this way. But it does mean the capacity to imagine and deliver works that will endure, and will be meaningful to communities, and to learn from them, and to build long-term relationships with communities that will continue to exist in perpetuity, whether that’s an</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done through a curator’s institutional resources, not through the artists’ own resources. In this instance, the curatorial team comes to negotiate a different reality, one in which the curatorial mission is no longer the sole preserve of academics and aestheticians, but is rather a community enterprise. The Museum of Modern Art, New York was one of the first art institutions to offer free historical tours, and through a partnership with the archivist Marianne Moore, a community-based art archive was founded in 1961. This archive now houses over 50,000 works, and is the largest collection of its kind in the United States. The curatorial mission has expanded to include tours of the area, and the art and design collections. There is a reason why the Museum of Modern Art and the Arts Council are so keen to emphasise the importance of the community in the organisation: it is a core value. The curatorial team is made up of volunteers: artists, curators, librarians</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done diligently, because it’s the very foundation of the encounter. Because if it doesn’t happen continually, it’s like a blank slate. If the community is not actively engaged, or doesn’t see the point in continuing to be involved, then the project is in danger of becoming a whitewashed version of itself. How to address this challenge?One positive response to the notion that the museum should directly engage with the community that creates the art it supports is that the institution should provide a platform, a space, where the community can articulate its own identity, identity agency, and agency through art. The ‘museum as a collective identity’ is at root a political project, and the fact that many of the curators I have worked with have backgrounds in related fields (biennial, art institution, art school, etc) is a way to incorporate a range of identities into the curatorial thinking. This approach to the museum as a single entity is</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done on a case-by-case basis. In other words, the idea of the museum as a place of mutual understanding and respect arises from the understanding that there are different ways of thinking, and this is why for me the museum is the most authentic, and so I don’t think it’s possible to separate the museum from the community. The museum is an essential node of the social structure of a community, and so whatever happens within the museum, it’s transcribed and incorporated into the social structure of the community. But there is no question about who has the right to speak in the museum, and so the identification of the artist as a community artist comes from the museum telling the story in a particular way, through an artist’s agency, through the historical narrative of the group that the museum is part of, and so on. This is a very interesting point of intersection: this is not a radical, artist-driven point of intervention, but rather a</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done through a curator’s institutional resources. If the negotiations between the community and the museum are going to be mediated through the museum, then the negotiations need to be done through an artist’s institutional resources, because otherwise the institution is simply not going to be able to sustain the kind of relationship that is going to be possible with the artist. And so the negotiation between the museum and the community, between the artist and the organisation, is going to be complicated, and this is what art institutions do. They are complex organisations that need to be negotiated through various means, and so the negotiation that is going to happen between the community and the artist is going to be influenced by the understanding and negotiation of the community as a whole. Because if the community is not willing to give the organisation that it is custodian of a certain amount of autonomy, then the authority that is going to be given to that organisation is going to be used in a certain way; and so the relationship that is going to</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Museum of Modern Art, New York. I was not invited, because I was not invited as a curator. There was a general, almost universal, negative reaction to the idea of the museum becoming involved with a community, and so it wasn’t until a long time later that some of the artists who were part of the curatorial team came to understand that the museum was an important intermediary stage, a facilitator, between the artist and the community, between the artist and the community at large.And so the museum comes face to face with the reality of life in communities: with people coming to the museum to pay tribute to a forgotten artist, or to say, ‘Hey, I’m from that artist’s group, and I remember this is what it was like growing up.’ And the idea that the museum might be able to broker a dialogue between the community and the artist is real, but this is a unique negotiation that needs to be done by the artist and the community. The negotiation that needs to happen is a delicate one, and the community might exert too much control, as the old saying goes: it’s better to negotiate a punching bag than to receive nothing but a punching bag. But the point is to understand that this isn’t a negotiation between artist and community, but rather a negotiation between community and non-community. And the interesting thing is that the community might be able to employ many creative ways of approaching the museum, through direct experience, through creative thinking, and even through engagement with museums on an artist’s terms.This is a negotiation that is very much a product of the time, and it happened a long time ago now, but it is relevant: the way in which the museum is organised today is very much influenced by the museum, and so as the museum itself becomes ever more private, ever more bureaucratised, ever more international in its activities, the way in which the negotiation</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, 
    <text>should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, Volodymyr Krysa’s new show for the same year. In recent years the Biennale has staged numerous exhibitions of contemporary art, many of them focused on the city’s past, while the other half reflected on the city’s future. In 2017, the Biennale staged its fifteenth edition, and in 2018, its eleventh, in an attempt to recapture the biennale spirit of the nineteenth century. The exhibition was initially intended to be a one-year residency, with the exhibitions occurring in cycles over the next two years. The cycle was intended to be a countermeasure to the biennale’s contemporaneous, urban, and postindustrial forms of documentation, but it has become evident that, in the age of global mobility and constant encounter, documents no longer represent narratives as much as fragments of historical artefacts. Rather, the record-keeping that characterises the biennale is the multiple forms of global</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, by Svetlana Boym, the Slovenian artist. The Biennale of 2006, curated by Rafael Cardoso, was also sponsored by the Biennale of London, with works by Werke, Lacy Hale, Rafico Ruiz, Mikhael Subotzky and Morehshin Weiser. The English-language edition of the Biennale’s web site includes a chronicle of the events.[15] Morehshin Weiser, Monument to the Republic, ca. 1987, Virginia Museum of Art, Washington. © Estate of Mikhael Subotzky. All rights reserved, DACS 2015.

[14] See   Tim Cresswell, ‘On Religious Freedom Under Siege’, in The New York Times, 26 September 2017, http://www.nytimes.com/2017/09/27/us/politics/faith-and-</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, with contributions from Werke, Krysa and other curators. In this ongoing biennial, the Biennale has curated performances by the artist Tania Bruguera, as well as works by Rafico Ruiz, Gustave Flaubert, Tina Fey and many more. Biennials have traditionally been the occasion of major exhibitions, both on a global and local scale. The biennale was a major new entry for the festival, and its prominence soon became universal; biennials are now the largest category of the hotel, nightlife and cultural tourism categories, with over 200 countries represented. As a category, they are a frequent target of intolerance, with institutions either actively supporting or actively undermining their growth. The Biennale responded by introducing the festival Stagecoach, a twice-yearly, fully-funded, fully-participatory public exhibition that it launched in Venice in 2017, as a counter</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, a retrospective of Greek and Roman statues and artefacts in Cyprus. The Klinikalerie and Krysa have collaborated on a number of projects throughout Europe and North Africa, as well as in Athens and Berlin.8 The Klinikalerie, Krauss-Mikrotringen, 1989. Photo courtesy of the artist. 	In 1989, Georges Mersch proposed the idea of the ‘kinder, ‘er           können           kommen, or community of users, to describe the relationship between the artist and the technology.[1] The community was to be the user, the manufacturer, the administrator, the navigator, the voyager, in relation to which the artist was to render the device in various ways representing (in a multiplicity of media) the diverse uses that the community might have for the art produced through its own embodied activities. Mersch chose to render the community as individuals rather than as abstract entities</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that reflected the turbulent transition from monarchy to democracy in Cyprus. Monuments to the Republic was curated by Irene Hofmann-Weber and published in 2018 by Werke, who is the curator of biennials at the Bauhaus. The Biennale was co-curated by Irit and Gunnar Myrdal and published in 1924. The Biennale itself was co-curated by Wolfgang Ernst and published in 1926. The monstrosity that is the Biennale ship was co-curated by Ernst and Gunnar Myrdal and published in 1928. The monstrosity that is the Biennale train station is co-curated by Werke and published in 1929.  A panoramic view of the ship, taken from the Russian ship-photo blog artyuvrain.blogspot.com, shows the ship passing by the Yaroslavl, the largest shipbuilding plant in Russia, whose</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, Voluntech's act of memory in the city following the terrorist attacks of 11 September 2001. In these instances, the biennale was initially planned to be a transnational event, but the ideology of biennales has shifted the centre of attention away from those who are at the epicentre of the disaster. The Biennale is now present at a time when the transnational biennale houses are beginning to look to the past. When the Mumbai Biennale was initially established in 1887, it was primarily an event for foreign visitors. In the twentieth century, the Biennale became an institution of the metropolis, present in large measure because of the constant migrant flows of visitors from the cities, which fuelled the cash cows of the pavilion and the head office. As a biennale that is centred on a city, the Biennale is not unique in offering a city-specific experience, but it is uniquely positioned relative to other biennales</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, Le Notre’s Cathedral, with Louis Guggenheim and Peter Saville. The Biennale is the largest and most prestigious event in the Biennale series, and has hosted over 300 exhibitions worldwide. The 2016 edition, ‘17TH Biennale of Sydney,’ brought together the most important curatorial priorities from the two previous biennials, with a special focus on the city’s cultural sector. Viewers were invited to select a sector and a city, and were encouraged to nominate a local art world, a museum, a queen’s palace, a monument, a local park or a distant sea as a favourite site. Selected sites were directed to a global digital art-computer interface, where artists, curators and art historians were invited to explore the selected area online. Digital art-computer interfaces today control much of what is considered ‘the art’ produced in the world, as well as much of what</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, a retrospective of Republic posters from the Republic of Georgia, with contributions from Dutch, Chinese and Yugoslav artists. The current edition of the Biennale is the anniversary of the terrorist attacks of 11 September 2001.Monument to the Republic of Georgia and the Biennale of Portoghesi’s Rome, 1008–1021. Painting from the Collection of Prof. Andre Geurts. Istanbul: Arthur A. Sulzberger, Inc.1999. Photo by Marcel Leckey.PreviousNextMonument to the Republic of Georgia and the Biennale of Portoghesi�s Rome, 1008–1021. Painting from the Collection of Prof. Andre Geurts. Istanbul: Arthur A. Sulzberger, Inc.1999. Photo by Marcel Leckey.The Biennale of Portoghesi's Rome, 1008–1021. Painting from the Collection of Prof. Andre Geurts. Istanbul: Arthur A. Sulzberger</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, by Sandy Volz and Warchol at the Pushkin Gallery. Monuments to the Republic, which was also exhibited in the Biennale, presented a sharp contrast to the austere beauty of the architectural style of the Biennale, which often represented the Empire on one side and the Republic on the other. The Biennale offered the opportunity to open a museum to a local ­community, and a forum to interrogate the ways in which one is governed by a particular ­representative of the Empire. In the case of the Biennale in Venice, the local councillors took up the opportunity to drain the city of its resources, creating a series of parks and recreation areas, while the Biennale's directors established a settlement in the hills above the Venetian city. Monuments to the Empire  introduces the readers to Monuments to the Republic, a settlement established in the hills above the Italian city of Venice.1 Its aim</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Bauhaus) and in the late nineteenth century the artist Albert Wegener established the Klinikalerie in Frankfurt am Main, the site of an earlier Bauhaus. The Klinikalerie has been a hub for the arts community in the city since 1906, and since its closure in 1990 the museum has hosted exhibitions by Werke Institut für Arbeiten (Institute of Arboretrics), Kunsthal Museet  kampala (Kampala Art Museum), Ongoing, a multi-disciplinary exhibition that documented the history of elephant-brains from 1884 to 1990, and the curatorial agenda of the 2004 Rio de Janeiro Architecture Biennale. In 2011, the Biennale was re-curated by Werke and Joasia Krysa, and in 2016, the Biennale presented Monument to the Republic, by Sandy Volz and Constantinos Kasidiaris.In the 1990s and early 2000s the Biennale was influenced by the New Age movement (originally a US Tantric group) and the Hannah Arendt Institute. The biennale was closely linked to the financial markets and the post-1991 economic crisis. As a consequence, the Biennale attracted a large and diverse visitor base, including major curators from the US and Europe. The Biennale, like the museum, is an annual event. In recent memory, it has attracted people coming from all over the world to see and talk about art. It has also done well from a public-admission and arts-per-attendance perspective, in that it is easy to get into and has a good range of activities in the city. In this sense, it has been seen as a cultural-cultural-performativer. The Biennale has a visual arts</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific literary survey of current cultural phenomena? What are the barriers to engaging local or national media with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific literary survey of current cultural phenomena? What are the barriers to engaging local or national media with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal aspects of developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, science and technology? How might biennials foster a new understanding of, and action?  What is the relationship between biennials and the cities that adopted them</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific cultural setting? What are the implications for sustainable development?  What is the relation between biennials, their production, and the socio-political systems that might support or inhibit such production?  What are the ethical and political issues regarding the production and consumption of culture-producing technology?  What is the relation between biennials, their production, and the socio-political systems that might support or inhibit such production?  What is the relationship between biennials, their production, and new media technologies?  What is the relationship between biennials, their production, and new economic forms of cultural consumption?  What are the socio-political and cultural dimensions of new technology?  What is the relationship between biennials, their production, and the socio-political systems that might support or inhibit such production?  What is the relationship between biennials, their production, and the socio-political systems that might support or inhibit such production?  What are the socio-political and</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific or ‘place-specific’ understanding of the world?  What is the relationship between biennial and museum attendance? Why or why not?  What are the barriers to engaging a recently minted artworld with cutting edge science and technology? What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the relationship between biennial and museum attendance? Why or why not?  What are the barriers to engaging a recently minted artworld with cutting edge science and technology? What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific cultural geography?  What kinds of cultural practices might be useful in urban environments?  What kinds of cultural practices might be socially juster in rural settings?  What kinds of cultural practices might be socially juster but less socially useful in urban settings?  What kinds of cultural practices might be socially juster and more unnecessarily destructive in urban settings?  What kinds of cultural practices might be socially juster and more innocuously destructive in urban settings? These are just some of many questions that could potentially be addressed in a biennial’s 2017 edition. The issue of where to draw the line between art and science is complex, to say the least. As biennials become more institutionalised, their ethical, political, and economic place in the world becomes even more uncertain. This is especially true in the United States, where artists and curators are increasingly exposed to the same practices and have more exposure to each other than in other places. Therefore, the boundaries between art and science may be</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific, ‘big picture’ perspective, or ‘layer’ in a spatial system?  What are the potential uses of large-scale data?  What are the boundaries between physical and virtual?  What are the characteristics of biennials as a site-system?  What are the languages of biennials?  What are the spatial limits to their growth?  What are the forms of collective understanding that they can foster?  What are the intranational effects of reducing the number of biennials?  What is the distribution of biennials?  What is the distribution of art institutions?  What are the spatial and temporal characteristics of biennials?  What are the spatial and annual effects of reduction in the number of biennials?  What are the forms of collective understanding that they can support?  What is the temporal dimension of the biennial?  What is the spatial and annual distribution of real and simulated wealth?  What are the</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific agenda, or ‘area of interest’?  What are the strengths and weaknesses of art’s current location and heritance?  What is the relationship between biennials and their local artworlds?  What is the relationship between biennials and emerging and former community art centres? Did you know that biennials have a financial stake in their local artsworlds?Art’s Expanded Region - Part 1&quot;The Art of Not Being Governed&quot;By Patti Staeheli and Debunk, translated by Justin Wolfers, TEDx: The Global Art and Design Conference, 2015. Note the adoption of the term ‘expanded region’ in the fourth and final sentence of the fourth and final paragraph.  [1] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Janus Rock: An American Concept’, in Kunstler, J. (ed.)  	Unravelled: Essays on the Art</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific cultural resource, and how might biennials foster its development?  What are the barriers to supporting and facilitating research into new art forms, and what roles and responsibilities would those with a financial stake in the art and fabrication of art participate in creating?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding biennials and artisans, and interactions with artisans? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What are the roles of biennial as a new economic form, and how might they foster a new economic base for art production?  What are the cultural resources for artists, curators, artists' organisations, and artists’ social activities to build on the ground up?  What are the capacities and rights of artists, artists</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific agenda, developed and delivered by a globally interdisciplinary team?  What is the role of a regional arts organisation?  What is the role of a national gallery system?  What are the resources for a world-wide network of artisans and curators?  What are the resources for a multidisciplinary art production and curatorial approach? 2. The Biennial Condition 	The biennial condition is a cultural condition in which art is more or less everywhere represented, but that is not all. There are also ‘biennials’ within art that are represented at best peripherally, or as a footnote to, or even as an effect of, other works. For this, we must add an element of contemporaneity to the mix. So, we must add a level of generativity to the biennial as an art form. Biennials, within their current form, are in their own way slow, malleable, and fragile elements that can shift,</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific agenda, particularly when engaging with an existing artworld?  What are the barriers to engaging a growing online community of art-related users?  What are the cultural and economic benefits of a biennial?  What are the limits to biennial size, production, and the number of art exhibitions?  What are the institutional practices of curating the arts?  What constitutes a biennial?  What are the boundaries between biennial and art gallery?  What are the different forms of curation?  What are the scales on which biennials operate?  What are the forms of curating the arts?  What constitutes a biennial?  What are the different forms of curation?  What are the different types of biennials?  What is a biennial? What is a biennale?  What is a museum? A biennial is a event where different kinds of things happen, over and in different places. It captures more or less the same kind</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or similar new scientific understandings of the world?  How might biennials incorporate new intellectual spaces, new economic actors, and new cultural forms?  How might they foster a critical race or gender role shift? How might they generate a new subculture? How might the roles of artist, educator, politician, researcher, and curator align?  How might biennials foster a dialogue between local and national news media?  How might their relationship to each other evolve?  How might the roles of curator, journalist, and artist overlap?  What are the barriers to engaging a newly minted artworld with cutting-edge science and technology?  What are the cultural resources for artisans, artists, and curators to build on the ground up?  What are the ethical, political, and legal issues regarding developing nations’ use of, and interactions with, ART? How might biennials foster new forms of collective understanding and action?  What is the value of a site-specific, spatially explicit understanding of the contemporary city?  What is the relationship between biennials and related forms of art assemblages?  What are the potential sources of cultural capital?  What is the relation between biennials and related art production systems?  What are the different forms of cultural production today, and what might be the limits to their potential?  What are the distinctive characteristics of biennial culture, and what might be the limits to biennial creativity?  What is at Stake in Understanding Cultural Capital?  What is at Stake in Biennial Research?  What is at Stake in Biennial Research?  What is at Stake in Understanding Art’s Role in the Current Economy?  What is at Stake in Understanding Art’s Role in the Current State of Knowledge?  What is at Stake in Biennial Research?  What is at Stake in Biennial Research?  What is at Stake in Biennial Research</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the
    <text>should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the city, and the Spa has a branch in Liverpool. The number of people who visit the Liverpool Scottish Film and Video Workshop is ten thousand. The number of people who visit the Liverpool Performing Arts Workshop is ten thousand. 	The Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa is located in the historic district of Anfield, in an area known as &quot;The Anfield Village&quot;, which is home to the historic buildings of the Perkins House cinema and the former Scottish Football Factory. Liverpool is the site of the 1936 Olympic and Paralympic Games, and the 1972 European Football Association Cup Final, as well as the 1984 Scottish Pulse’s Preliminary General Election. The Biennial’s 2016/17 US entry is based in Anfield, with a future view to producing similar interests in the area again in the future.  	The Biennial is a biennale founded in New York in 1990. It is the largest independently-owned biennial in</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the city: the  	Stoney Creek, the  	Glasgow Five and the Shoreditch Four, where the 2012 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held. The Shoreditch Four is a branch of St Mary’s Church in Liverpool, which is also the parish court for the Liverpool Biennial. Liverpool Biennial is the largest overseas visitor to Liverpool, and the largest single overseas visitor to Britain. It attracts nearly four million visitors a year. Liverpool Biennial 2016 generated over 1 million UK and international tourist dollars, up from 1.5 million in 2015. Liverpool Biennial is currently planning to open a branch office in Germany and is planning to open a branch in Australia. Liverpool Biennial is the subject of a major investigation by the  Royal Commission into Official Misconduct in the 1988 Olympic and Paralympic Games, to be conducted by Liverpool and Sydney. Liverpool Biennial is the subject of a government funding review. Liverpool Biennial is considering whether to create a</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the waterfront, a pharmacy, a clothing store and a small hostel. The name of the hostel is a confusion: at one time it was the home of the Patients Assisted Treatment Centre, then known as the Kelvin Grove Clinic, and now known as the Kelvin Grove Hostel. The name of the hotel is a confusing confusion as well: in its original form, it was the Bernhardt Inn, the same hotel where the Dortmunder’s film Wild West was shot, and in its current form, it is the hotel where Lewis and Macfie were staying at at one point. 	The hotel itself is a labyrinth of interwoven stories, varied by local preferences, and always featuring a climax that is individual and singular. This is true even though the hotel has closed several times over the years. The hotel, which once housed the Toronto Globe and the CBC, is no longer the dominant force in the city,</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the city, but the number of visitors to the Granby Four Seasons is six hundred and one. The Granby Four Seasons is the only hotel in the city with such a name, and the only hotel in the world with such a capacity. All other hotels and hostels in the city are either defunct or are part of chain or multi-national chains. The only way to travel to the Olympics is to be a member of a multi-national sports organising company, or part of a regional organising committee, and to be based in London or Beijing. However, the number of people who actually visit the Games is rather small. In 2008, the London Organising Committee of the Olympic Committee, with help from the International Olympic Committee, established the   	London’s First Travel Company, which offers cheap travel to the Games through cheap airfare and accommodations in hostels, hotels and restaurants. The route from the Granby Four Seasons Hotel to the Olympic stadium takes eleven days in each direction.</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the city: the Granby Four Seasons Hotel, the Granby Four Seasons Hotel &amp; Spa and the Granby Four Seasons Hotel &amp; Spa. 	The number of rooms in the hotel has gone up about 400% in the past twenty years. The hotel has had a revival project going for years, but it has mostly failed to generate the kind of investment in infrastructure needed to support a hotel with modern conveniences. The Granby Four Seasons Hotel is in danger of becoming a museum. The new owners seem to be putting a premium on the experience of staying in the hotel, which is becoming increasingly difficult in a city with so much tourism. The hotel is a trap, and as the London Airport projects have shown, cities can only be inhabited so long; eventually the hotel has to be demolished and rebuilt in order to make way for a new wave of tourism. 	The hotel is a trap for a reason: it requires no capital to be built, produces no new jobs and generates no new</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the city, and a number of motels, several of them in the surrounding countryside. The landscape is open and airy, open to visitors from the surrounding countryside, and houses a number of small businesses. The hotel has a receptionist, a maintenance worker, and a cleaner. The name seems to be a play on three words: the Four Seasons Hotel, the Arcades, the Towers, and the Hills. The Tropicana hotel in Liverpool  	is a hybrid. It is both a hotel, a suite, and a boutique hotel. Both the name, Tropicana, and the Tropicana nameplate read as three distinct components in a single formula. The Tropicana hotel is a hybrid hotel, capable of holding its name and three words in one unified formula. The three elements – hotel, suite, and boutique – combine to make a single unit of accommodation. The combination of a single name, simple symbols, and a name that evokes a history, places and</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the waterfront, and the spa is a branch office for the North Shore Hotel Company. The name of the company is now the property of the state; in the 1980s it was a publicly traded company with offices in Seattle and Vancouver. The government gave the hotel and spa companies broad powers to set up shop and to do business, but as a limited liability company, the Granby Four Seasons didn’t have that kind of legal protection. So the state stepped in and made them very vulnerable. 	In 1984, a citizens’Citizen’s Court decision gave the city full authority to set up an independent monitoring commission to investigate complaints of non-compliance with the laws regarding the use of public beach space. The commission was given broad powers to investigate both public and private complaints, and could make recommendations to the mayor regarding enforcement of the laws. The decision to set up a public monitoring commission came as a surprise to many in the local government: the idea was that the public would be</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the waterfront, but these have all been sold or are derelict. The hotel has a total of nine hotels, but they are all under renovation and are mostly empty. The only hotel remaining in the city is the dilapidated but still functional but valuable Carlton, which has been renting rooms to artists and organisations ever since it opened in 1890. Credit: Peter CarrIn 1980, the Granby Four Seasons Hotel (then known as the Granby Four Seasons Hotel &amp; Spa) was one of the top-ten tourist attractions in the UK. At that time, the Granby Four Seasons was a symbol of glamour, opulence and excess in a city looking to the future. Now it serves as a museum of the past, a squat but functional art venue with a collection of artefacts from the 1920s and 1930s that are used as evidence of the Victorian era in the town. The hotel has hosted numerous exhibitions of varying quality, ranging from intimate to critical, and has a permanent collection of</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the city: the Four Seasons Hotel at the Yarra Parade, the Commodore and the Gardens Hotel. The Gardens Hotel closed in 1983 and was razed to the ground in 2012. The Yarra Parade Hotel closed in 1981 and is undergoing extensive renovation. The Four Seasons Hotel at the Yarra Parade is undergoing a similar transformation. All three hotels have their distinctive hexagonal windows, which were once a staple of the hotel décor. The distinctive shape of the windows was also a feature of the hotel bar, where guests could sit on couches and watch cartoons. The windows were also an integral part of the hotel interior, where large photographs of the hotel taken in the years immediately following the casino came standard. The bar has been relocated to the ground-floor retail section of the hotel, where it houses items from the hotel register. The sale of the register, along with the items that are part of the hotel, is now finalised. The interests of the dominant stakeholders in the city – the hoteliers</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the Arts Council].&quot;The  	Granby Four Seasons Hotel, now Chichester House, where the  	2000 Olympic and Paralympic Games were held, is the only remaining building in the city, abandoned in 1980. Credit: Peter Carr​ On the wall of the hotel is a drawing of a quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus quadrillions-plus four quarters of a trillion. 	The drawing  	shows that the number of people who visit the Granby Four Seasons Hotel and Spa each year is six hundred and one. The hotel has three other hotels around the city, but they’re all relatively new, with relatively low occupancy. The Granby Four Seasons Hotel is unique in that it has stayed open almost continuously since it opened in 1903, when there were only four other hotels in the area. Its regular clientele of athletes, visitors, and performers includes everything from monks to high-ranking politicians, as well as journalists, artists, performers, and curators. The hotel has a long tradition of hosting major exhibitions of contemporary art, and this is evident in the collection of artists, curators, and artists who have curated the site at various stages of its history. The exhibition that the Arts Council organised in 1984 was a major event here, and the collection that came out of it is still going strong. The exhibition that followed in 1985, Exhibition 8: Art as Media (in cooperation with the New York and London Museums Biennials), was even bigger. All the above were about the emergence of a particular kind of art from</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry –
    <text>presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry – between the green light and the impact – became legendary in the local community. 	In the years since the project, many other art projects have cropped up in the area, many of which are relatively minor in scope and often serve as examples of how the art community can play a constructive role in stimulating community activity without being accused of being ‘resourceful’ or ‘agressive’. 	However, the tensions and paradoxes that were created by the Arts Council’s involvement in the area eventually saw an end point. In the intervening years, the councilor’s office produced a series of reports that were distributed to local authorities, local artists' unions, and to the arts professionals who worked for her or them on an industrial and municipal level. Some of these reports were incorporated into the 1993 Local Government Art Reports, which were published in 1991 and again in 1995. 	The second report, from 2000, was presented in partnership with the Newcastle Artsapce</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry – between the elected representatives of the people and the increasingly appointed representatives of the art world – created an environment where conflict and conflictual moments were frequent.This is a portrait of the era in which the Biennale was conceived and designed: the 1980s.  The idea of the  biennale as a public place – one in which the artist(s) concerned take part and which is visited by a professional art gallery – was a catalyst for much of this activity.   The  biennale, by its own relatively un-transnational and international character, soon developed a globalised character that was witness to  numerous iterations in different places. In 1989, the Venice Biennale opened its gates to a throng of foreign curators, who immediately set about introducing their ideas of what a biennale should be to a city that was more or less ready to embrace them. This came as no surprise to the locals, who had been organising the biennale since the mid</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry – between the elected representatives of the community and the non-representatives of the government – was a feature and parcel of the local to mid-scale urban development that had begun to emerge in the 1990s. 	The mid-scale was a category all its own in its own right, encompassing both residential and commercial developments, as well as a growing number of grassroots non-profit arts organizations. The advent of ‘market-based urbanization initiatives’ such as those led by the USGBC and its precursors such as the Australian Centre for Urban Development (1995–98) and the Developing Societies Australia (1998–2006) signaled a new era of community urbanization in which the office and its stakeholders would no longer be able to dictate terms, but instead of this happening, the community would have to make its own choices, choices that would shape future development paths and so forth. 	The emergence of ‘smart growth’ – initiatives that sought to address</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry – the urban landscape is replete with examples of which the Arts Council of New South Wales compiled a Top Ten List of Top Ten Projects in the Sydney 2000 Census – is a landscape to which we can all aspire, but which also has to be carefully managed.  Whether consciously or not we as citizens of the urban landscape aspire to such things, we can all recognise that the office that emerged from that landscape is likely to repeat the same office – for as long as the city exists – and so we have to learn how to work together to shape that landscape in our interests and desires.  A citizen’s council  One last piece of the jigsaw that made up the arts and culture landscape that emerged after the towers fell is the role of the artist, but until now that role has been somewhat circumscribed to the extent that the arts were often seen as supplementary to the people who produced the arts, and so it was largely practitioners like myself who emerged as effective promoters of the arts within the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry – between the office and the city – created an environment where conflict between the two was frequent and intense. Asking whether the public consultation process was an art project or a de facto local government process is one way to assess the extent to which the art was realised in the form of local government involvement while the artist was actively engaged, while acknowledging that the public arena was a dynamic that was often quite different. In that sense, perhaps, the role of the artist was to some extent a catalyst that gave the shape to the project’s actions, and in that sense the public realm could be seen as a site of continual conflict resolution. There are of course many other ways of looking at the relationship between artist and community, and it is worth pausing to ask whether the contemporary artist is in on the whole in the knowledge that she is creating a socially engaged work, or whether there are other actors, including local government, that would like to see the arts reduced to their current condition – that is,</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry – which were evident even in the years immediately after the project started – are evident in the project’s text and in the project’s logo. 	In the years immediately after the petrochemical crisis erupted in 2009, the Arts Council of Australia convened a public consultation process on the idea of an independent museum that reflected the complex, long-term trends in art and cultural production at the time. The results were released in the form of a book – four hardback and a 120-page document – called ‘The Art &amp; Activity Box’ – and a public debate that followed online. The debates that ensued included submissions from a variety of interested parties including key stakeholders within the context of the project, as well as citizens, academics and others. 	The Art &amp; Activity Box was published as a joint project between the New South Wales Museum and the Centre for Contemporary Art, La Salle Royale, Paris. The first edition was published in 2011 and ‘The Art &amp; Activity</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry – which were sometimes comic, sometimes muddled and always politically explosive – provided the backdrop for some truly iconic environmental postcards.  	In the years immediately after the Petronas Centro Entreprise project was abandoned, the Arts Council of New South Wales commissioned an independent review of the project, which concluded in 2011. This review, which was published in full in the journal Environmental Sculpture under the title Systemic Arts? The Impacts of Arts-Based Educational Partnerships, offered some encouraging recommendations, but also some scathing ones. The report, which the Arts Council of NSW took up, was more definitive and definitive than that, leading many to conclude that the office’s involvement in the project was fundamentally flawed and that its recommendations were not only unfulfilled, but also that the Arts Council of NSW had overstepped its boundaries in proposing an arts education programme for schools across the state. The review also found that the office’s involvement in the project was at best</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry – between the elected representatives of the people and the non-elected representatives of the art world – are palpable. The Art Council of Australia, the body that represents the interests of the art world in Victoria, has been at odds with the Art World for decades. In recent years the divisions between the two organisations have become more evident. The Art Council is increasingly focused on its core mission of encouraging and organising the art world, while the Art World is increasingly focused on its resources and on meeting the demands of its membership. As a result, it has become increasingly difficult for artists to establish studios or produce culturally responsive work without also being involved in the governance of the Art World. For many artists this has meant being present at the councilor’s annual convention, but it has also meant attending the Art World’s board meetings, where decisions on projects were often taken without any previous assessment or input from the board, and without having a say in what is produced.  	In a recent conversation</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry – between the elected representatives of the people and the non-representatives of the state – is one of the great ironies of our time. 	[ii] The debate about the ecological and social dimensions of the project has intensified in the intervening years, as have the courts and appeals courts around the world. 	[iii] The United Nation’s Convention on the Law of the Sea (2013) reaffirms what many activists had long suspected: that the environment was more deeply implicated in the production of one’s identity than in that of the other. 	[iv] The Convention also recognizes that nations are legally obliged to protect their 'natural resources and heritage sites’, a principle that has recently come to define how cultural resources are distributed globally. It is this principle that has recently been invoked by the Australian government to halt the construction of two massive oil refineries intended to supply the country with electricity, arguing that they are in the national interest – justifying</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Arts Council of New South Wales, it was primarily a ‘pet project’ within which the artist(s) concerned, as well as the wider community, was a part. In some respects, the project was a ‘petition’ on the councilor’s desk, but in other respects the councilor’s role had evolved into that of a leader, empowered to make decisions that would have a significant impact on the environment but also to empower the community to enact their own decisions that would affect the environment in meaningful ways. For example, in the years immediately after the project started, the councilor’s office regularly convened public consultations on development proposals, often leading to major projects that would become law if they were given the green light, while in the intervening years the office often found itself fighting a pitched battle with itself as to how to proceed in the face of such projects. The resulting paradoxes and tensions between the office and the citizenry – between the representatives of the office and the governed – created great expectations and tensions. In a city that is increasingly a function of automated means of production, the threat of legal action and massive fines seemed particularly acute. In an area with such a rich and dynamic past, such as the art world, the threat of legal action and multimillion-dollar settlements seemed especially acute. The threat of legal action and multimillion-dollar settlements seemed especially acute to art galleries, since, unlike others who patronise museums or places such as Chatsworth Museum, they’re stakeholders in the ecologies they commissioned and maintained, having invested heavily in the provision of a museum or museum facilities and in the maintenance of the infrastructure around them. In a city such as Liverpool, which has become a global art centre thanks to the museum sector, the threat of legal action and multimillion-dollar settlements seems particularly relevant. Its biennials, which now constitute the bulk of the arts sector in the UK,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would remain reliant on the generosity of a predominantly white, well-established art community. Biennials would only produce visions of the world in terms of their own cultural appetites. They would not produce a radically new art form or artistic practice, and neither would they renounce traditional forms of art or their place in the world. But they would make art more accessible to a broader range of people, including artists, critics, collectors and students. They would do this through their cultural production, which would include, but is by no means limited to: (a) activities that foster understanding and encourage collaboration between artists; (b) those that foster exchange and engage readers and artists in self-expression; (c) those that foster experimentation and creativity among artists; and (d) those that foster a sense of place and community. 	Artists, curators, artists’ unions and other art professionals already have a voice in the development of a biennial. Artists may well be drawn to</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would remain dependent on the generosity of its artists and curators. As a result, the biennial would likely exert considerable political and organisational influence, and its curatorial independence would be circumscribed. This is the current situation in many parts of the world, and it is a problem for biennials in their current periodical forms. It is unclear how the current economic and social conditions would affect an institution as dependent on the generosity of its artists and curators. It is probable that biennials would experience a decline in their institutional favour, and that many who remain would find themselves displaced or forced to change their professions. Yet it is also possible that the biennial would embark on a course of cultural self-sufficiency, producing new art forms and systems through which artists could flourish outside the context of the institution. This is the direction in which artistic self-help initiatives such as the Art in Schools programme or the New Art Foundation might move. In their current periodical forms,</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would be difficult to imagine a similar relationship for an artist to be produced through the production of art. Biennials would not be able to produce the innovations or theories of their founder, but they could contribute to a discourse about art’s place in the world through their productions of theory and discourse. That is, they could contribute to a conversation about art’s place in the world through what has become known as the ‘tenants of habitation’ – the structures and cultural behaviours that enable habitation in the first place – and they could also contribute to a conversation about how the conditions of habitation evolve and change through their interaction. 	Such a proposal would not only disregard established biennalenses and their tradition of producing innovative artists, but it would also neglect the fact that the main task of an art institution is to produce lasting cultural effects through the production of power and material wealth in the interests of the capitalist system. That is, the institution’s main mission</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would be little different to adopt the form of a cultural commission or corporation today with artists from the local area already taking part in a commissioning process that could produce significant cultural impacts. But the biennial form would almost certainly become problematic in its current form: the biennial would almost certainly become the primary site for producing, managing and displaying cultural impacts across a site-specific institutional scale, especially as a result of the rapid growth of cityscapes, the urbanisation of large areas and the mass remaking of urban environments. The biennial form would render the institutions that produced and produced across the century, but now largely ignore the sources of art’s cultural power, while empowering the local by enabling the reproduction of a globally visible art style that is present in cities but is absent in the countryside.Artists, curators, artists, artists themselves would almost certainly be well versed in the history of the field, having worked in many different fields but were most likely to have a very general and</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would be a mistake to reduce the autonomy of the artist to the task of stimulating art activity through an institution's resources. The biennial would have to be a fundamentally different kind of institution to produce the kinds of cultural effects desired by the biennial industry. In this case, the biennial would produce its own destiny, for it would determine how art and culture are produced in the area, and how those impacts are distributed. 	Artists would also have to negotiate different kinds of institutional power in the area, and these changes would have to be negotiated collectively, as a community. This is why art biennials have to negotiate with larger institutions, including museums and galleries, which have a clear interest in seeing a resurgence of their cultural patrimony. Biennials would also have to negotiate with their local communities, who have a strong cultural stake in the area; in the case of a no-go area, the biennial might have to negotiate a return to the area of culture by way</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would also be up to the biennial to determine what kinds of research and development are needed on a larger scale.  One might also raise the question of what kinds of autonomy are needed for artists to produce works of art? I would propose that the autonomy of an artist is constrained by what is seen as a legitimate public good by virtue of its being a ‘public domain’. But what kind of public good is it that is being produced by the very public domain that the biennial is trying to abolish? Art’s autonomy would be limited to the public good produced by the institution that it is created in.Artists have a collective memory of a public good, a common language with which to discuss and theorize about the public good; however, the public good that emerges through discussions such as these is rarely acknowledged or appreciated by the public. A moral obligation to one's community comes to mind; however, in the history of our shared humanity, this has rarely been felt to be</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would remain precariously dependent on funding from its host country. A question that would become crucial in the post-Cold War era is what sort of co-funding mechanisms could be developed to provide the kind of autonomy artists desire in a world-wide, non-city-based way? The biennial would remain a relatively infant of the art world’s cultural infrastructure, but its modest size and focus on a relatively urban core would allow it to leverage that infrastructure for more structural changes, such as the inclusion of more communities or a robust cultural museum collection. Art’s mid-century aspiration was to expand to cities large enough to house it, and then some, such as New York, Los Angeles and San Francisco. But today’s biennialism often seems to be chasing after transient cultural trends or local trends, such as fashion, or pushing the limits of what cities could possibly house, such as augmented reality or virtual reality. Art’s desire for cultural infrastructure to host</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would be up to the biennial to determine what kind of a cultural experience it is it willing to support.  	Artists and artists who have worked with the Biennial since its inception in 2006 may contribute to its development through their performances, writing or collections, which may include works from their years at the Biennial. Their contributions may be incorporated into the institution’s development and publication of its content.  	The Biennial is committed to producing experiences that are inclusive to its local and global audiences. To this end, in 2015 The Biennial was selected as one of ten curatorial projects at the Venice Biennale—the highest ranking such project at the biennale—by the Italian and American art directors, conservators, and PR firms representing the United States and Italy. The other projects were curated by the Italians, the Swiss directors, and the Director of the Swiss National Portrait Gallery, Bernhard Rauball. 	[i]   The Biennial</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would remain unable to create a culture or landscape it could not control. Art’s autonomy could also be constrained by the quality and quantity of the art being produced, and the quality of the programming being offered. A biennial that produces the occasional great artwork would add to the sense of place and atmosphere of the art fair, while a biennial that offers programming that is as rudimentary as possible for a suburban or rural audience would bolster the biennial’s sense of mission and reinforce the biennial’s primacy in the city. But given the current political situation in much of the world, it is doubtful that the biennial would be able to achieve either objective in the foreseeable future.The biennial has enjoyed a sustained, even critical, interest in the last fifty years, but its current relevance and place in the world are questionable. Its investment in artists and the quantity and quality of their output is questionable, and most biennials are driven by institutions or artistic directors who are often</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, a new science or technology? We might ask if the mission of a biennial is to support an institution or a local culture, or to produce a new way of looking at the world? And how does that affect the autonomy of the artist? If the mission of an art institution is to foster criticality or stimulate artistic activity in a specific community, then perhaps the autonomy of an artist would be constrained by the institution’s commitment to research or education. Biennials could contribute to the production of a more nuanced understanding of art’s place in the world through productions that employ a greater number of artists from a wider geographical area, particularly by inviting artists from the local area into the institution’s studio or commissioning gallery. But such autonomy would only grow as the biennial’s mandate and subject area expanded. The institution’s autonomy would remain constrained to producing tangible cultural effects through teaching exhibitions and symposia, as is currently the case, and it would be little different to say that of museums. The question is, how does the institution manage this ever-expanding mandate and its diverse aspects? Does the institution have the autonomy to commission a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition-type project that produces significant changes in the local environment? Or does the institution have the political will and institutional knowledge to dismantle such projects when they begin to show signs of weakness?In the current period of neoliberalism, it is not uncommon for art institutions to be overwhelmed by the new economic models that are imposed on them from the ground up. Art is no longer the sole economic provider of social value in major cities; the social, economic and cultural costs of this are now too great to consider neglecting. Art is now required to produce social and cultural contributions in exchange for institutional or political support; else it is left to fend for itself. The biennial is the institutionalised expression of this economic dynamic; it is the lowest common denominator among those</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters
    <text>presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The key questions for the archival culture of the twenty-first century are these: how can the various cultural formations that comprise the contemporary world be brought into harmony? How can these be brought into harmony through dialogue and negotiation? How can the practices of collaborative learning be brought into harmony with the institutionalised production of knowledge production? How can the various cultural manifestations of the contemporary world be brought into harmony through sharing and exchanges? How can the contemporary world be brought into harmony through de-facto modernisation, and how? 	[1] See</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters remain largely unchanged. However, the ways in which they are generated and reproduced vary greatly, and it is the varied sources and processes that make the archive stand out as unique in its own right. So, too, its presumed open-endedness to being, and to encounter, new ideas and situations; for the individual curatorial conceals certain relations of power and control. The curatorial concealment is ahistorical. It is ahistorical in the sense that it is both pre- and post-accurate; pre-accurate in that it is constructed in relation to what it can and cannot control; and post-accurate, in that it narrates a past that is not necessarily historical but could very well be fictional. Therefore, its historical character derives from its being able to tell a fictional story through its historical setting. It is, to borrow a phrase from the curatorial, able to tell a fictional story through facts and figures that are, in the main, capable</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters remain the same. However, the curatorial, artistic and logistical gestures that enable such encounters may vary in detail and form, and in some cases even on a site-by-site basis. This is why archiving is so important: to preserve the very notion of the encounter, and to continually reconceive and evolve the spatial forms of the encounter. The curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable the curatorial, artistic and logistical reconquest of ‘enduring modernity’ are constantly evolving, and as such are affected by technological innovations and man-made disasters (whether natural disasters, climate-change-induced droughts, urban sprawl and the like, or just plain bad luck). This is why archiving is so important: to preserve the very notion of the encounter, and to continually find new and innovative ways to engage with and present it (even if this introduces new forms of historical and sociocultural encounters). The archive, and the archive in particular</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied and variable. However, the main aim of this exhibition is to show how artists are connecting to the materiality of their artefacts, and how this process is generating new understandings of the archiving of time itself.At the London and New York biennales of the same time, these new understandings of the archiving of time were generated by a curatorial fixation on the importance of the archive as a site of encounter, and a prodigious promotion of reading and listening habits through curatorial interventions into the day-to-day activities of the art world. The New Museum exhibit - itself a curatorial intervention into the curatorial world of the art world, and the curatorial intervention into the everyday activities of the museum - opened with a reading and listening session at the Tate Modern, and then proceeded to a series of programming activities throughout the week. In both the U.S. and in the U.K., the archives of the British Library were displayed alongside works from the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. 	[i] The National Archive’s online archive contains over 12,000 documents from its owner, the National Archives Foundation, under the control of a board of trustees appointed by the National Archives and Records Administration. It was established in 1994 and is a publicly accessible online archive of documents from the National Archives and Records Administration. It is managed by the Archive Service, the Executive Office for Archives and Records, and the National Archives and Records Administration. See http://www.nara.org/archive/index.html (accessed September 2018).Download this article as PDFAndrew W.K. RowlingAndrew W.K. Rowling is an independent writer, Curator of Acts of Memory at the New York Public Library, where he has published more than twenty books, among them The Complete Idiot's Guide to Acting</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. But the main aim of the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations – which pervade the site, their dynamic interaction and their consequent conflicts and conflicts – is the production of understanding. The archive, and the encounter itself, is an encounter that emerges not from cognitive processes of interpretation, mapping and synthesis, but from conscious associations and neural substrates. It is an encounter that demands an act of intelligence, and can only be understood in its totality. It is an encounter that cannot be reduced to a set of meanings and cognitive processes. It is an encounter that demands a certain amount of conscious and unconscious effort, and an act of will. It is an encounter that can ‘understand’ complex concepts and the cognitive dynamics of history, but which ultimately remains unknowable.  In the essay ‘Curtains of Empire’, Louis Bothroé proposes a theory of universal circulation, its objects and presuppositions, which he traces to the seventeenth-</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’.  The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, a site of encounters that create repertoires of action, of locations to be visited, of practices to be observed. The curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. Here, the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same: to create</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their focus is on the same – where possible, the same – orientations, as well as of course the history of ideas, practices and places and their relations today. The archive embodies the inaccessibility of archives, which is increasingly apparent as a result of in-depth digital archiving, and which can be seen as an affliction (if not a symptom) of modernity. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied, yet they all foster a sense of the encounter as a site of encounters, a place of encounter, in a wide range of cultural forms and circumstances. The archive, as we know, is ephemeral, transient and subject to change – sometimes radically so. But it nonetheless represents an idealised past that can act as a compass for future action, a site of encounters that persist through the intervening centuries, and ultimately a site of knowledge that can inform future action</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same: to create a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same: to create a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters are varied. However, their main aim is the same as well: to understand. To</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, where participants’ contributions are incorporated into a publication (or collections) of ideas, here and now. The process is open to all, and the instruments by which this is achieved are varied: the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations. However, their main aim is the same: to create a toolkit for the creative pro- gramming of ‘enduring modernity’. The toolkit thus acts as a site for the expression of understanding, and the ultimate resolution of questions about the meaning of ‘enduring modernity’. It is a site for the discovery and curating of kindred approaches to an increasingly apparent ‘problematic abundance’, and it is a source of possibilities for the future. Here, the archive becomes a site of encounters, of places to investigate new possibilities, for the production of new understandings of the present. The archive is a site of encounters, and the curatorial, artistic and logistical orientations that enable such encounters bear witness to the reality of their ongoing condition. 	[1] See http://www.endofist.com/?p=75. [2] See End of Lecture, the exhibition at the Alberta Artspace (2012). [3] See, for example, Steven L. Tanimoto, ed.,  	Enduring Episodes: Critical Perspectives on Media, Politics and Archives (Durham: Duke University Press, 2016). [4] See, for example, Edward S. Herman, ed.,  	Media and Politics (New York: Vintage Books, 2015), p. 17–36; David Swanson, ed.,  	The Episodic, a poetry collection (New York: New York Public Library, 1976), p. 3. [5] See, for example, Edward S. Herman, Media and Politics, (New York: Vintage Books, 2011), p. 4. [6] See, for example, Edward S</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive reporter, conducts a series of interviews in Central America about the effects of climate change. These changes are projected onto a map, and the reporter tracks the movement of millions of cattle, pigs, chickens and other animals as they cross the border into Brazil. As the story goes, a swarm of cattle guards is dispatched to patrol the border, and as they travel along the 2,000 miles of jungle between the two nations, they encounter increasingly dire scenarios: floods, droughts, overhunting and epidemics. As the group encounters more and more extinction-like conditions, such as the ones described by Brooks, the narrative shifts from one in which humans are somehow limited to certain biological limitations to one in which all species are ultimately doomed by a common malignant force. 	As the group travels further north, the story shifts again, this time to stories of recent past mass extinctions, in which humanity is one of the leading contributing factors. In  	Brave New World (2006),</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive reporter, conducts a series of interviews from different corners of the globe, focusing on the people who will or won’t be able to survive the coming apocalypse. The interviews are done in a style that resembles journalism, but with machines. The interviews are written by way of scenario, and so the narratives that emerge are constructed out of fragments from different places. For example, there’s a perfect storm that comes about when a certain chemical used in the manufacture of brominated flame retardants spills over into the environment, and thus causes a cascade of events that eventually leads to the meltdown of the Fukushima Daiichi nuclear power plant. 	Brooks begins his narrative with a somewhat apocalyptic take on the future, saying: ‘The future is a very bleak one, rife with apocalyptic possibilities and filled with signs of what can and cannot be done by human beings – terraforming the moon, genetically engineering fish to digest Bt corn and ratifying the Paris climate accord’.�</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive reporter, conducts a series of interviews in the wake of ‘The Terminator’, the film that supposedly puts an end to the threat posed by the Machines. These interviews, ‘Forecast Wars’, are part of a larger ‘Machines' essay’ that narrates the events of ‘World War Z’. These interviews, ‘Forecast Wars’, are part of a larger work that seeks to bring together different strands of the author’s imagined future, and thus the curatorial turn around the events of ‘World War Z’ reinforces a sense of the immensity of the threat posed by the Machines. In effect, the interviews in the present tense form part of a longer work that seeks to position the contributors to ‘World War Z’ as individuals with distinct points of view. These perspectives would give the events in ‘World War Z’in relation to broader trends in science and technology, and in that</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive reporter, conducts a series of interviews in the wake of ‘The Zombie War’. The book is a kind of ‘war diary’ – a kind of archaeological reportage that feeds back on itself. World War Z follows the remnants of a bureaucratically dense future, in which individuals wield far greater power and influence than at any time before. The book’s fictional subject, Max Brooks, is the kind of thinker who can take such a position. 	The interview format is a kind of archaeological digression from the historical, ethnographic and archival narratives that shape our understanding of the past. It comes as no surprise, then, that one of the interview subjects is none other than Max Brooks, the futurist and science fiction writer of the early twentieth century. 	In  	2001: Rorschach Pen, Michael Crichton describes how the Cold War ended: with the rebuff of an arm's reach, Moscow’s Hammer</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive reporter, conducts a series of interviews in countries around the world about the effects of AI on national security. In the book he employs various pseudonyms, including ‘End Times’; ‘Problems with Reality’; and ‘The Rise of Chaos’. The interviews take places in cities as transient data points, with humans the narrators. The author takes the form of various characters, including a CIA agent (voiced by Robert Patrick Joy), a journalist (voiced by Ira Glass), and philosopher (voiced by Lola Kirke). The book follows these characters from the 1970s into the early 2000s. World War Z follows a different trajectory, focusing on the human race as a whole. However, it maintains a similar focus on the nexus of power and knowledge, as represented by the character Max Brooks. The Humanities Now! event  	In  	2014, a team of curators from Liverpool, Sweden, convened to explore the</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive reporter, conducts a series of interviews in the wake of ‘The Zombie War’. These interviews form part of a ‘Projections of the Future’, a kind of ‘permanent motion picture’ that he constructs out of disparate data streams. 	Brooks begins this work as a kind of futurist: he predicts in his book that there will be ‘better ways to spend our time’ than through bureaucracy and the military. However, the technological singularity that he imagines is on the horizon doesn’t exist yet, and we don’t have the self-driving cars or other technologies that would make us ‘better’, so he finds himself constantly on the defensive, constantly questioning his own technological prowess. 	Brooks makes a point in his book about the rise of consumer culture: the mass media that transformed the future was created by, for, and especially for white men. But this only serves to underscore</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive reporter, conducts a series of interviews in conjunction with a documentary on the same subject. In the book, he uses the term ‘episodic’ to describe how information is gathered, and ‘recurrent neural networks’ to describe how historical data is assembled. Brooks does so by way of an analogy: the technology that underlies artificial neural networks is similar to how human technology is designed to be used, and thus the two terms naturally connote something that is constantly evolving and subject to change. 	Brooks begins to hear voices that tell him to take specific actions, and these actions include actions that may or may not be inspired by human beings. These voices also narrate the history of AI, how it came to be, and what might be done about it. These narratives are often based on the disenfranchised or disenfranchised-looking human race, but in places like Yemen or Syria they may also refer to non-white or racialised populations. ‘Space-</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive reporter turns up dead. The novel ends with Max Brooks’s son Travis identifying the body as that of his father. The character of Max Brooks is a kind of fictitiously apocryphal figure, appearing in print only occasionally and appearing to have been based on real-life events. However, the author’s rendering of the ‘real’ Brooks is a living embodiment of the ideas and practices of AIAs. Max Brooks’s son, Travis, is the protagonist of  	World War Z. He is a young man with an apocalyptic vision and a mission to ‘purify’ the world of all cybernetics, all artificial intelligence. As the novel ends, he terminates his mission by killing himself. 	[1] See Katherine Graham and Alex Buonocore, eds.,  	The Cambridge Companion to AI (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2016), p. 28–39. [2]</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive reporter, conducts a series of interviews in various parts of the world in an attempt to piece together the fragmented narrative of the war. 	Brooks begins by asking: how can we understand the future when it’s so opaque? How can we imagine a different future, one where politics and media are less prominent, and where nature is more valued? How can we imagine a future in which conflicts do less harm than they do now? How can we understand ‘how to live differently’? These are questions that begin to answer the question, how we might live differently in the future. 	The question then becomes how to imagine such a future in our urban environments, given our current ecological crisis and geopolitical situation. In  	World War Z, Max Brooks becomes increasingly political as the journalist enacts his imagined ‘escape from the present’. He invokes the name of Leonardo da Vinci, who first theorized about the interconnectedness of historical periods in which</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIAs, and the worlds they represent, in all their complexity, and in the knowledge that they have of their own historical trajectories.  	Task Force 1, which I was part of, proposed several models of what AIAs might be like, some more imaginatively than others. 	In  	World War Z (2006), Max Brooks represents the new bureaucratization of the future: technology has replaced people in myriad ways, and now we’re in a situation where the machines are learning to do many of the same things as we’do, and thus there’s a temptation to think of AIAs as kind of a Big Data explosion. 	However, this feeds into a false sense of predictability: what AIAs really do is feed on knowledge, and thus we don’t know what the future might hold, or might mean. World War Z begins at the end as Max Brooks, the name of the author and his fictive reporter, narrates the aftermath of a global ecological disaster that humanity was forced to confront. Humanity is reduced to ruins, and millions dead, and millions more homeless. Millions more refugees are fleeing violence in their home countries. Millions more people live in hunger. Millions more are malnourished. Millions more are chronically homeless. 	Brooks begins his account by describing the new breed of AIThe purpose of an AI is to serve its master, whether that’s a master plant, a master viral genome, or, more recently, a master AI. AIAs tend to follow certain processes that follow certain patterns, and thus they develop and proliferate according to certain principles. In World War Z, the AIAs become sentient and begin to make predictions about the future, predicting disaster, striving for artificial intelligence and beyond. These predictions are often astoundingly prescient – predicting not only what humans might do in the future, but also what might happen to us if we do things that AI</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been calling it ‘a collective brain’. It’s an evolving, inclusive group of invited discussants coming together over the course of a week to explore the ways in which a biennial can (and, I guess, cannot) connect to its local environment. For sure, this concerns Liverpool — we want to know what can and cannot take place in that city, both thanks to, and despite it — but I expect that the topic of Liverpool won’t be able to contain the things we’ll want to ask and tell each other.We have questions that are not local to Liverpool and the UK. We need to be able to recognise meaningful correspondences between Liverpool and other places, ones that aren’t arbitrary, reductive or bogus. For me,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been calling it ‘a collective brain’. It’s an evolving, inclusive group of invited discussants coming together over the course of a week to explore the ways in which a biennial can (and, I guess, cannot) connect to its local environment. For sure, this concerns Liverpool — we want to know what can and cannot take place in that city, both thanks to, and despite it — but I expect that the topic of Liverpool won’t be able to contain the things we’ll want to ask and tell each other.We have questions that are not local to Liverpool and the UK. We need to be able to recognise meaningful correspondences between Liverpool and other places, ones that aren’t arbitrary, reductive or bogus. For me,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been calling it ‘a collective brain’. It’s an evolving, inclusive group of invited discussants coming together over the course of a week to explore a shared topic. For sure, this concerns the city in which the Biennial will be located, and how it will engage with its history, present and future. For sure, this concerns the history of the city and the UK in which the Biennial will operate. But it’s also a place where other places and identities can also be found.There’s a word that describes parts of a city that are in constant communication with each other. It’s called ‘communication edge’. And the communication edge is one of the places where ideas and perspectives clash with one another. There’</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been calling it ‘a collective brain’. It’s an evolving, inclusive group of invited discussants coming together over the course of a week to explore the ways in which a biennial can (and, I guess, cannot) connect to its local environment. For sure, this concerns Liverpool — we want to know what can and cannot take place in that city, both thanks to, and despite it — but I expect that the topic of Liverpool won’t be able to contain the things we’ll want to ask and tell each other.We have questions that are not local to Liverpool and the UK. We need to be able to recognise meaningful correspondences between Liverpool and other places, ones that aren’t arbitrary, reductive or bogus. For me,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been calling it ‘a collective brain’. It’s an evolving, inclusive group of invited discussants coming together over the course of a week to explore the ways in which a biennial can (and, I guess, cannot) connect to its local environment. For sure, this concerns Liverpool — we want to know what can and cannot take place in that city, both thanks to, and despite it — but I expect that the topic of Liverpool won’t be able to contain the things we’ll want to ask and tell each other.We have questions that are not local to Liverpool and the UK. We need to be able to recognise meaningful correspondences between Liverpool and other places, ones that aren’t arbitrary, reductive or bogus. For me,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been calling it ‘a collective brain’. It’s an evolving, inclusive group of invited discussants coming together over the course of a week to explore the ways in which a biennial can (and, I guess, cannot) connect to its local environment. For sure, this concerns Liverpool — we want to know what can and cannot take place in that city, both thanks to, and despite it — but I expect that the topic of Liverpool won’t be able to contain the things we’ll want to ask and tell each other.We have questions that are not local to Liverpool and the UK. We need to be able to recognise meaningful correspondences between Liverpool and other places, ones that aren’t arbitrary, reductive or bogus. For me,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been calling it ‘a collective brain’. It’s an evolving, inclusive group of invited discussants coming together over the course of a week to explore the ways in which a biennial can (and, I guess, cannot) connect to its local environment. For sure, this concerns Liverpool — we want to know what can and cannot take place in that city, both thanks to, and despite it — but I expect that the topic of Liverpool won’t be able to contain the things we’ll want to ask and tell each other.We have questions that are not local to Liverpool and the UK. We need to be able to recognise meaningful correspondences between Liverpool and other places, ones that aren’t arbitrary, reductive or bogus. For me,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around a possible visit to the city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been calling it ‘a collective brain’. It’s an evolving, inclusive group of invited discussants coming together over the course of a week to explore the ways in which a biennial can (and, I guess, cannot) connect to its local environment. For sure, this concerns Liverpool — we want to know what can and cannot take place in that city, both thanks to, and despite it — but I expect that the topic of Liverpool won’t be able to contain the things we’ll want to ask and tell each other.We have questions that are not local to Liverpool and the UK. We need to be able to recognise meaningful correspondences between Liverpool and other places, ones that aren’t arbitrary, reductive or bogus. For me, in my role</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been calling it ‘a collective brain’. It’s an evolving, inclusive group of invited discussants coming together over the course of a week to explore the ways in which a biennial can (and, I guess, cannot) connect to its local environment. For sure, this concerns Liverpool — we want to know what can and cannot take place in that city, both thanks to, and despite it — but I expect that the topic of Liverpool won’t be able to contain the things we’ll want to ask and tell each other.We have questions that are not local to Liverpool and the UK. We need to be able to recognise meaningful correspondences between Liverpool and other places, ones that aren’t arbitrary, reductive or bogus. For me,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is critical in supporting and facilitating this important self-learning process. It is my hope that this journal will act as a resource for this critical new journal.D Download this article as PDF27 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been calling it ‘a collective brain’. It’s an evolving, inclusive group of invited discussants coming together over the course of a week to explore the ways in which a biennial can (and, I guess, cannot) connect to its local environment. For sure, this concerns Liverpool — we want to know what can and cannot take place in that city, both thanks to, and despite it — but I expect that the topic of Liverpool won’t be able to contain the things we’ll want to ask and tell each other.We have questions that are not local to Liverpool and the UK. We need to be able to recognise meaningful correspondences between Liverpool and other places, ones that aren’t arbitrary, reductive or bogus. For me,</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
