<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such,
    <text>accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such, it is the site on which the event takes place, and it is here that the awareness of the event, its participants and the environmental and community impacts of its activities are produced. 	An example of this in the Welsh Streets area is the creation of the  	Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, which took place in 1989 and 1990, respectively. The biennale was curated by  	Gareth White and  	Sandy Volz and the artist Ella Gibbs, who was a regular attendee of the event. Biennials have a long and important history in Liverpool, which we will look at in detail. 	In the Welsh Streets area, the art biennale was organised by  	Triad Gallery and the Welsh Streets Partnership. The names of the artists and their organisations are a record of how artists were able to be present in a city that was, until relatively recently, completely unaware of them</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such, it demands a different kind of authority. In the case of the Welsh Streets Home Group, for example, the Biennale required the support of the local residents to enable the group to carry out some of the demolition work. The involvement of the local residents in the demolition process was essential in order to enable the Biennale to proceed; but it is also essential that the Biennale not only carry out the work, but also that it is undertaken in a way that is transparent, open and involves all concerned. It is up to the local authorities to decide how their housing remains in existence and which kinds of management agencies can intervene in that housing. It is up to the local communities to decide how their housing is managed and who can participate in that housing. 	As an institution and as a city, the Biennale was able to engage with the needs of residents in a radical way; but the Biennale also had to engage with the needs of the local residents in a way</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such, it is able to act as a locus of resistance against the domination of space by a dominant power. 	There are different types of biennials, and each has its own distinctive set of strategies and instrumentality. The Biennale as an Event has been around for half a century now, and although it may be present in a modified form today, its basic intent and character is very much shaped by the events of that half a century. The key events in the history of the biennale are listed in Table 1. 	[i] –  The Venice Biennale (1978), featuring the work of many artists from many disciplines, including Mies’s group, 2000AD, Suzanne Lacy, Jeanne Heeswijk, Peter Schjeldahl, Christoph Buchel, Wendy Harpe, Mary Turner, Meehan Crist, Laura Lamb and many more</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such, it is the responsibility of the visitor to the art museum to know what the Biennale is doing, and to understand what the authority is up to. Biennials have a complicated relationship with their locations and their publics. In the case of Liverpool, for example, the Biennale was established by a local authority, but its activities have been deeply influenced by the politics of regeneration and urbanism, which have seen large parts of the city actively marketed to the private and the non-profit sector through cultural institutions, including schools, cultural agencies and housing co-ops. The local authorities have significant say in how cultural institutions are run, but these rights are rarely exercised. Instead, authority figures often exert considerable control over who can study, work and access certain spaces and resources. In the case of Liverpool, for example, the Biennale has actively sought to integrate art and the local communities in a way that is both socially useful and generates revenue for the local authority. In 1989 a Community</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such, biennials have their own form of art project that differs in kind from the artist’s usual public project but also in kind from the art project that the public engages with. For the Biennale, this has often been a ‘tourist’ type of project, for instance the sculpture commissioned by the Liverpool Biennial for its cover of the football club’s kit, which the public could have engaged in collectively through the organisation of a ‘holiday’. For the biennale, the public is often engaged in an interpretation of a project that is very specific to a specific locality, city or region. In the case of Liverpool, for instance, the Biennale decided to create a project around the city’s Downtown Arts Trail, which would in turn draw artists from around the region to work on the project, while simultaneously creating a local arts community based around the area through partnerships with local businesses and cultural organisations. 	The unique engagement between</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such, it demands a public that can be drawn to and is willing to participate in something it creates. In the case of the Welsh Streets Home Group, for instance, the public was drawn to the idea that it was creating through its involvement in the Biennale; it was creating a change in the city through its involvement in the Biennale; and it was creating a new kind of art form through its involvement in the Biennale. 	This last idea, art being what it is, is perhaps most exemplified by the work of Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Although their project has some elements of the Biennale package, it is clear that the project is framed within the parameters and institutions of the current economic and social configuration in Liverpool, and so operates within a different logic. 	[i] Richard Southern, ‘On the nature of urban change: A conversation’, in  	Urban-State Studies, Vol. 3,</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such, it is not confined by the formal or institutional relations of art museums or galleries, and the public is not limited by the formal or institutional relations of education. The public, in this sense, is everywhere present and is a very significant element in the autonomy of the biennale. 	In the case of a biennale to be held in a particular location, the public plays a significant role in shaping the parameters and values of the exhibition, and in this sense local government is a significant player in the production of a biennale. Local authorities have a long-standing commitment to the arts and to supporting artistic endeavour through education and art production, and in recent decades have actively engaged in both the production of art and the dissemination of that art. It is not surprising, then, that the Biennale is made up of representatives of a number of local authorities, including areas with a high proportion of schoolchildren. 	The boundaries of the Biennale have varied over time, and</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such, it demands a different kind of relationship from that typical of the exhibitionary exhibitionary form: one that is responsive to the needs and interests of communities, demands a kind of authority that cannot be bought or imposed. In other words, it seeks to impose its will on an organisation that does not have the authority to do so.  	And this kind of authority, or politics, is often expressed as a question mark. Is the Biennale political? 	Yes, it is that way because the authority that it supposedly serves is often anonymous and unaccountable. In the case of the Biennale, this is often expressed as a question mark ‘i’. In reality, the Biennale does not have this kind of invisible or intangible authority; it has the real authority because it is governed by a democratically elected body of passionate and knowledgeable fans. 	And this kind of dynamic is also evident in the larger festivals that are now part of the itinerary – in places</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such, the authority that authorises a biennale to happen must have some kind of relationship with the public that legitimises its involvement. In this case, the authority would be the local arts society, or a successor organisation, and it would have to have some kind of political influence. In the case of Liverpool, the Biennale would have to be democratically elected by the local community, and have to be supported by the local authority. Biennials today often have their origins in socially engaged or culturally responsive art practices, and often take the form of grassroots art movements that seek to draw institutional or bureaucratic support to the art from a position of strength. 	To be a biennale, a work of art has to be culturally relevant and socially transformative in some way. In order to achieve this kind of weight, a work of art has to be aesthetically interesting, intellectually stimulating and morally ambiguous. I find it very difficult to imagine a work of art right now that is aesthetically uninteresting</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these trade unions, and through the work of other community groups. Unite here!  L.R. Welsh Streets Home Group (2013-16). Design and Delegated Transformation Project for the Architecture Biennale, Liverpool Biennial, 2016. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are a number of biennials that have their origins in or are a direct descendant of the Biennale. Some of these are the precursor to the Biennale itself and can be seen as a kind of point at which the two meet again and which informs how the two interact. 	The Norman and Kate Ellis-Welsh Art Biennale, Liverpool, 1990. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	There are many biennials that meet the criteria of the Biennale, but unlike the Biennale, which requires the co-operation of an authority, a biennale requires the direct involvement of a public. As such, it demands a public that is technically aware and has access to all the information at its disposal. In this sense, it is similar to the way that a museum is to a museum. In a museum, information is collected, organised and controlled by an authority, while in a biennale case information is gathered, analysed and controlled by the public. In both the museum and the biennale, information is gathered, analysed and controlled in order to produce a certain result. But while the authority that gathers and controls information has a clear agenda, the public is often left standing before a control tower wondering what has been collected and what it may do with it. 	In both  the biennial and the museum, the information gathered is used to produce a particular result, but unlike in an institution such as a museum, the results cannot be accepted or trusted. As biennials and museums grow in size and scope, they are forced to engage in more and more innovative and controversial and in-</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘geographical combination’ that gave us the phrase ‘dominant culture’. And perhaps, if the biennial continues to cater to our contemporary tastes, tomorrow’s pop will be pop under the stars. Open Season on Art and Social Change, 2015. Photo courtesy of Open School of Art and Art’s Social Committee.  If, on the other hand, decisive action is needed today to change the city, then perhaps the biennial could play a part in creating a ‘different tomorrow’.  Conclusion  The biennial is not some new concept that has been thrown together by curators and artists. It is a practice that has been around for a long time, and has many forms: it is an art form, a social practice, a ‘cultural district’, and it has a very specific role to play in creating a ‘different tomorrow’. And perhaps this is why, in the present context, the biennial is</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘periphery’ that I call home. The borders of tomorrow will be the borders of today.Download this article as PDFTim JeevesTim Jeeves is Professor in Cultural Studies and Director of the Centre for Cultural Studies at the University of Alberta. His research interests include (but are not limited to): critical culture (especially punk and post-hardcore), post-colonial and settler nationalism, and art and visual culture in late imperial contexts. His publications include (to be forthcoming from Oxford University Press) Culture and Capital: Globalization and Participatory Politics (2009) and (to be published soon) From Multinational Enterprises to Local Enterprises: Conversations with Co-operatives in Contemporary Art History (2014). He is currently the executive director of the Global Multinational Initiative (2014-2020) project at the University of Alberta, and co-curator of the upcoming 10th ACM exhibition of cooperative arts and social practice in Liverpool. His work has been featured in exhibitions</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘leap’ that’freed[s] us today from the tyranny of the ‘one size fits all’ cultural definition.  And, perhaps more important, tomorrow’s art forms will be artforms – whether we like it or not – that are on the same plane as today’s architecture, manufacturing, publishing and distribution systems. This is the ‘swift’ that’s needed: today, the art forms that are most readily identified as ‘nation’ are going to be the most difficult to shift.  And, here’s the ‘leap’ again: today, our art-world, cultural geography, and indeed all cultural spaces is going to be influenced by information; and, as a consequence, the art forms that we produce and read about the most will be the most susceptible to the ephemeral nature of information.  So, the next time you’re at the beach,</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘bottom-up’ way in which contemporary culture is developing, and it’s this new topology of influence that’s being forged across the planet. And if we take our cues from the Istanbul Biennial, which is developing a worldwide reach, we can infer that this is a phenomenon that will get uglier still: there’s a ‘war on the cities’, and the whole global phenomenon is being redrawn according to the desires of a few city-dwelling nations. We see this not just in the rhetoric of political parties and their candidate for president, but in the architecture of contemporary urbanisation, including in the design of developments that are almost entirely geared towards accommodating a few million people in metropolitan centres. This is the kind of urban-dwelling society, in other words, that can be built around.  And this is what contemporary art is building itself, by the way. The Biennale has already shown that the city</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘globality’ paradigm that has recently come to dominate in academe and popular culture. It captures the essence of the ‘periphery’, but also of the ‘intersectionality’ paradigm that characterises how we inhabit the ‘city’ in new and innovative ways.  This is the paradigm of ‘periphery’ that is mobilised by the social, but also the cultural, and that investigates the city’s temporal condition through a ‘city-problem’ framework. It captures the ‘city-problem’ as a problem that needs to be solved, but also the solution as a problem that arises out of or along the lines of the problem. It’s a ‘city-problem’ paradigm that introduces the city as a site of conflict, yet it’s also a problem that arises out of or along the lines of other problems. With the ‘global’ in place</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘leap’ that’s being made today, and it’s a ‘glimmer of hope’ that’s slowly leaking out. Today, there’s a ‘glimmer of hope’ in the form of social media, but in five years or so, there’s a danger that the social media of the future will be dominated by the forms of data that can be mined and utilised. There’s a danger that the data that can be mined and utilised will be appended with magic words and phrases that sound magical but actually make the most of the city in which they take place. And there’s a danger that the data that can be appended with magic words and phrases will be hijacked and used in ways that are not based on true facts and which have no basis in reality. This is the predicament of cities that are caught between their urban growth aspirations and the realities of the city — between</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘circulation problem’: the more pictures circulate of a given event, the less likely it is for a viewer to move to another location.  The counterintuitive but important insight of biennials in the past was that they gave the appearance of being able to connect with audiences outside of their local contexts. As biennials start to get older and diversify in the ways in which they are organised, they start to become visible again – to the extent that their commercial circulation is now even possible in their adopted country. This is true for a biennial as we know, but it is also true for any kind of art exhibition that is now global in scope. It is no longer sufficient for the art to be housed in a particular art museum and the biennial to be world-class in its size and form. It is now also essential for the art to be exhibited in venues that are accessible to a global audience. And this last element is an ever-present threat. In the 1960</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘leap’ that’s needed. And in the coming years, I expect that New York, London and Paris will all be among the last places to which we will have cultural exposure.  As a city, Liverpool has its problems – structural inequalities, a depressed population, a financial crisis – but these are secondary, affecting only the city’s privileged few. Real problems, such as the breakdown of the health service, mass incarceration and the endemic violence that plagues our neighbourhoods, will remain. And as city, Liverpool can make progress in many areas, although its problems are deeper. But as a city with a very specific identity, with its own particular set of problems, with limited resources, it’s time to make some fundamental changes. Do you know what a biennale is?  We’ll do research on the next Biennale, following on from my lecture  	Unravelled, in which I address the subject of urbanisation in</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘metainterface’ today: in many ways more universal, more dynamic and more permeable than the ‘global’ social media of the future, where people identify with a collective identity. But the metainterface will have its moments of universality, of course, and tomorrow’s tweets will have a moment too. Today, the ‘global’ social media provides a fixed range of experiences: the point of no return for the biennial is now becoming apparent. In time, the metainterface may be overcome by other more dynamic approaches. But today, the metainterface is the only face of the biennial. In time, of course, it may be necessary to adopt other identities, become localised and move around the world in search of experiences that are richer and more powerful than the metainterface could ever hope to be.  And this is the point: today, the metainterface is the only face of the</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a series of ‘generation[s]’ of biennials to be staged in the city, and the city’s rapid regeneration will make it the perfect place for another 10 years or so. I imagine there’s some speculation about what this might mean politically: perhaps, in the past decade, the situation has become so dire that it’s time to revisit the biennial as a city in crisis.  Whether, in the coming years, this ‘generation[s]’ will again be the dominant cultural form or be relegated to the margins, will remain to be seen. But whatever form it takes, it’s clear that this will be another ‘global’ community. And unlike today, when the dominant form of visual culture is globalised, tomorrow’s popular forms will be localised, with influence spread across many localities, not just a few nation-states. This is the ‘new’ vision of the cultural function of culture, or more precisely, how it is distributed across vast geographical areas. And this is the transformative potential of a city’s cultural resources: today, only a few metropolitan centres can boast such a significant cultural resources.  Whether, today, the city is the crucial locus of the next great cultural movement is a critical question today. In a changing world, the question becomes whether, in the coming years, the city will play a greater role in artistic and cultural productivity than it does now.  And, if so, which form it takes: the city as a site of creative activity or a confined site of consumption? Will the city become a creative agent or a confined site of consumption? Will the city support a creative or a confined form of cultural activity? Will the city promote a ‘permanent’ or ‘volatile’ cultural or economic change? Will the city provide critical resources or become a commodity site? These</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer to see their investments in art and design redirected elsewhere. This can happen, for example, when art is actively promoted by the administration in the interests of the city’s economic development in the form of tax abatements or improved transit links to attract artists and other stakeholders, or when the curatorial office actively seeks to impose its artistic vision on the local community through policies such as art spaces or free post-secondary education programmes. In these cases, the stake in question is often perceived as an area of direct competition between local artisans and multinational art institutions, with the latter often characterising the latter as a ‘bottom up' approach.  Art and the curatorial  The curatorial office is a multi-award winning sector of the British cultural sector. It has a global impact, and is the single largest employer in Britain.’s cultural sector. 4  Its activities include a wealth of material support to its artists and creative workers, as well as the provision</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer that their ideas be taken up by the institutional or professional artworlds. The aim of this research project is to see if there is a market for culturally responsive art practice.  A component of the project is an exploratory tour of the region, taking place on a weekly basis. This will enable the audience to get a sense of the intensity and geographical variation of the battle over Brampton's future, while also allowing the audience to get a sense of the vagaries of market forces and political manipulations that can be expected from projects that are culturally responsive.  A second component is a series of six video essays that document the cultural dynamics of their location, the city at war with itself. These videos were produced as part of the Creative Time series, 2016-2017, and are the product of a year-long research project into the lives and works of Community Arts projects in the city. The videos are a combination of personal accounts, narration, archival footage and art direction.</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer to see projects developed in a specific way. In these cases, the move to the urban seems to represent a good opportunity for the office to experiment and mutate its project.  A new urban form may be created in part through the exchange of information and ideas, and in part through the exchange of cultural assets. At a macro-level, the new urban form is an augmented and transformed version of the old metropolis. At a micro-level, it is an arena for the contestation of cultural identities, belonging, and possession.At a macro-level, the metropolis is reanimated in the image of the city, and at a micro-level, it is the image of the person. If the person is the city, then the city is the person – but the person is also a cultural asset, and cultural capital is a subordinate variable. If the person is the city, then the culture is the neighbourhood, and the neighbourhood is the subcultural collective. The</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer to see their projects developed by an independent artist or other stakeholders.  A curator’s role in the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design is to imagine things, to make them happen, to envision possibilities and to act as a mediator between art and commerce.  A curator should not create their own possibilities and instead should partner with other stakeholders to achieve desired outcomes.  A curator’s relationship to their agency and their audience is another critical mediator between the powerful and the powerless in the art world. It is important for the curator to be able to effectively communicate with both audiences. The exchange of ideas and culture is an inherently collaborative process, and the curator must be able to use their ideas to help shape the project they are asked to lead.  A second important mediator between artist and audience is the work itself.  The work must be relevant to the current political moment in order to be considered art.  Art should be tools for artistically speaking the political</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer that their ideas not be taken forward.  A curatorial office that is constantly on the lookout for ways to bolster its portfolio of exhibitionary and cultural assets is a strange creature to behold, to be sure. But it plays a crucial role in curating the cultural life taking shape in the city, and it is precisely this critical eye that the curatorial office seeks to develop and deploy in the development of projects. The curatorial office is an essential part of any serious cultural-institutional repositioning. It plays a critical role in staging and capitalizing on the precious few cultural assets that remain in the city, and it shapes what can and cannot be exhibited based on its own subjective criteria.  The curatorial office is the point of articulation and control for cultural enterprises, and it plays a vital role in the development of the city by ensuring that projects are placed on the map and visible. The curatorial office sets the agenda, and it shapes what can and cannot be shown. The</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer to see funding and other support for their positions redirected elsewhere.  A curator’s significant other is an art administrator, who has a much greater say than that of an artist or other stakeholders in the artistic, curatorial or educational context. The significance of this in the context of the Biennale is that it is now possible to propose and have art projects funded by the Biennale and its organisers, despite not possessing the relevant artist or other stakeholder entity.  The Biennale has greatly expanded the curatorial reach of the institution, and has placed a significant cultural burden on the shoulders of the curator. The Biennale has trained many a curatorial hand, and it is hoped that this will continue in perpetuity.  A curatorial visit to the museum of Museum of Modern Art might be too familiar to some audiences, but to others it is a radically different experience. Some people associate museums with a physical, institutionalised presence; others with a culture of learning</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer not to be influenced by the office in the making of their cultural programmes.  The interests of the Community Arts organisation in this context are often brought into conflict with those of other stakeholders, and the two are often at odds. This could be an issue in conflicts over cultural property, as is the case with the Liverpool Biennial, which sought to develop a cultural portfolio including the development of its own cultural identity through the acquisition of cultural properties. The Biennial was developed in large part through the negotiations over its cultural properties, and the Baklava Mitrofan Foundation is a private company established in 2009 to manage and protect the Mitrofan Gorge, located some 200 m above sea level in the Kyrgyzstan highlands. The Baklava Mitrofan Foundation has an ownership stake in the cultural property, and the Kyrgyz government holds a 20% equity stake in the foundation. The Biennial was initially conceived as a biennale of the arts with</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer to see development occur on their preferred trajectories. It is this tension between stakeholders and stakeholders that I am interested in articulating, because it is a crucial interconnection between the many projects that are part of the Inclusive Development Project, even though some of the projects are co-opted by the administration. The fact that there are different developmental trajectories for each of the three waterfront neighbourhoods is a result of the fact that these neighbourhoods were selected at random from a geographically diverse area. So each neighbourhood is a unique outgrowth of the Inclusive Development Project, but each neighbourhood is also an individual outgrowth of the broader development programme. Yet each neighbourhood is unique in that it is a point of entry into the development of the city. So each neighbourhood is a unique in its own right, and the city as a result of this process has generated a set of characterised trajectories for each neighbourhood. The question then becomes: how do we organize these different pockets of the city into meaningful and influential cultural moments</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer to see their investments in art and culture supported by developments in the local economy. This is particularly the case in developing nations, where development projects are often driven by private investors who seek to maximise returns on their investments. It is this conflict of interest that creates the uneven playing field between the modern and the contemporary art market, and between public and private art collectors. In such cases, the contemporary art market is often an instrument for the oppression of the contemporary artist.  A curatorial visit to a developing nation, a city, a rural area, or a neighbourhood is a rare opportunity to witness firsthand the heterogeneity and dissipation of modernity. It is an opportunity to witness the emergence and proliferation of cultures, to witness the emergence of new ways of living, to witness the perforations of history, to witness the inartistic and transcendent value of art, to witness the inappropriateness of modernity, and to learn about the  	surface and deeper meanings of art.</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to convey the full scope and richness of the complex.  A curator who is not a specialist in a particular field or subfield is invited to undertake an In Community Arts project as part of a research project at the Dartmouth College of Arts and Design.  The project is an art/design collaboration between the two institutions, and it will produce new work arising out of the curatorial exchange. The curatorial exchange is a dynamic process driven by the dynamic circulation of information and ideas. It is an ever-present and fragile condition, and the cultural content of the exchange is primarily influenced by the current state of the art, its production and consumption. In this context, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often necessary to support the efforts of artists and other stakeholders to intervene in the cultural process. But as is often the case, cultural content produced by the curatorial office in the development of projects is often opposed by other stakeholders, who would prefer to see an organization that is self-sufficient in the production of cultural outputs.  A curator's mandate is to promote knowledge and encourage reflection, and her/his/their perspectives are usually limited to those with a direct relationship to the place where the work is created. The mandate to produce culturally responsive products and services is not a new one, and one can argue that it is even more of a producer today than ever.  The main difference today is that many of us do not work for marketing, PR, or in-house production agencies, but rather as community artists, writers, architects, artists, photographers, etc. We produce what other people – usually those with a close relationship to the place where we live – would consider culturally relevant. This may include things that we learned at community colleges around the country, or things learned from other disciplines, but tends to be more about popular culture and urbanicity than academic pursuits.  A curator's role is to deliver culturally responsive products and services that</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENT
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENT Professorial Chair in Computer Science at the City University of New York. His research interests include artificial intelligence, media and aesthetics. His publications include the award-winning issue of IEEE Transactions on Computer-Human Interaction (2015) and the book Saddle Up: Talking Robots (2016). He has taught at the University of California, Berkeley, Stanford University in the US, and the Universidad Di Tella, Italy. He is currently editor-in-chief of IEEE/ACM Interdisciplinary News, an IEEE publication. He has also edited the magazine IEEE/Advances, and has edited the webzine arXiv.He is currently editor-in-chief of IEEE/ACM Journal of Web and Mobile Computing, a physics and computer science journal.He is part of the editorial board of Digital Trends, a digital media organization. He has edited several books, including Digital Trespassing: Art, Digital Scarcity (2016) and part of the Digital Trends Reader, Digital</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENTED Chair in Computer Science at the LUCA. His research interests include artificial intelligence and urbanization. He is the editor of the online journal Interface Science (2016-2019) and the co-editor of the upcoming Fall 2016 edition of the journal IEEE Spectrum (available online). His work has been featured in publications including the New York Times, Washington Post, Los Angeles Times, San Diego Union-Tribune, Chicago Tribune, Philadelphia Inquirer, San Francisco Chronicle, Newark Star-Ledger, Burlington Free Press, New Jersey Times, and San Francisco Chronicle Arts &amp; Culture. He is the recipient of several awards and has received multiple mentions in the media. His book Sharing the City: Learning from Barcelona about the Connected City was recently shortlisted for the Turner Prize.He is the author of Symbolic Media: Understanding Media (2014, revised 2016) and co-editor of the forthcoming Spring 2019 edition of the journal IEEE Spectrum (available online). His work has also been featured in the New</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENTED Chair in Computer Science at Columbia University. His research interests include artificial intelligence and social networks. His publications include the forthcoming book Systems Neuroscience: On Understanding and Embracing Media (with Yann LeCun and Peter Osborne, Routledge, New York, 2016). He is a member of the editorial board of Network Science (www.networkscience.org), the online peer-review publication of the Network Science Foundation, and a regular columnist for La Opinion (www.latinionews.com). He is the editor of the forthcoming global digital magazine Network Science (New York: Zone Books), where this article is published.He is the author of the forthcoming book Systems Neuroscience: On Understanding and Embracing Media (with Steven Levy and Peter Osborne, Routledge, New York, 2017).Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UN</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENTED Chair in Open Source Studies at the UN. His research interests include information technology and cultural ecology; cultural ecology and autonomous media; and hip-hop culture and urbanization. He is currently developing an Advanced Researcher’s Diploma in Cultural Ecology at UNAM, Las Vegas, US, and a position with the UN Digital City team, New York, US. He was recently appointed as a co-curator for the 10th Venice Biennale, to take place in 2018. Towards A Constellation (2018) is the title of my exhibition at the Constellation Gallery, USVI, the home of the USVI Art &amp; Science Museum, and to open on 10 August, 2018, the home of the UKVI Art &amp; Science Museum. The exhibition is a response to the question: what is the new architecture? In the late twentieth century, the public was captivated by the image of an urban landscape transformed by a river, a sea, an airport</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENTED Chair in Computer Science at Columbia University. His research interests include artificial intelligence, social computing, cultural ecology and labour. His publications include the popular books Soft Robotics (2015) and Soft Robotics (2018). His work has been featured in trade publications such as IEEE Spectrum, The New York Times, Computer Games Research Institute (UNAM), Computer Crime Research Centre (UK), and IEEE (2014). His work has been funded by the Australian Research Council, Research Councils, and Engineering and Physical Sciences Co-operative Union (ESCU).He is currently commissioning a research project in the Peruvian Amazon with the NYC Art &amp; Science Curatorial Program, with the NYC Museum of Art, and will present the project at the 22nd Computer, Film and Technological Art Association convention, New York, USA, in June 2018. [1] Sweet Dreams of Our Mutual Embrace, University of California, Santa Barbara Press, 1980.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJos</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENT Chair in Computer Science at the Old Dominion University in Virginia. His research interests include artificial intelligence and social networks. His publications include the popular science best-seller &quot;Comrades&quot; (2012) and the recently released sequel to that same book, &quot;Comrades II&quot; (2015). He is part of the research team for the exhibition &quot;Beyond Borders: Virtualities of Cities&quot; due to arrive in San Francisco Bay in September. He is currently the editor-in-chief of the popular science magazine &quot;Geology&quot; (2014). His work has been featured in numerous popular books and journals including: Science, Nature, Hollywood, Wall Street Journal, New York Times, Washington Post, Atlantic and Smithsonian, among many others. He is a regular lecturer at the United Nations and other international venues.He is the host of the weekly public programming show &quot;Stages&quot; on the web-based radio program &quot;Recordings from the Crypt,&quot; which was nominated for a Grammy Award. He is the editor</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENTED Chair in Computer Science at the Manhattan School of Technology. His research interests include artificial intelligence, media and cultural ecology, social computing, cultural ecology and urban evolution. Recent publications include the award-winning book Systemics, or the Art of Not Knowing, to be published in 2018 by NYU Press; the 2017 book Real People: The Rise of Digital Cultures, to be published in 2018 by Oxford University Press; and the book Real Life: Contagions of Contentment, to be published in 2018 by Cambridge University Press. He is the author of several nonfiction books and numerous articles. He is currently working on a new nonfiction book titled Systemics, or the Art of Not Knowing.Future City co-hostsDeena Chalabi and Alexander Provan reflect on the legacy of World War Z, the end of the Cold War and the start of a new era of urban mobility. World War Z, written by Max Brooks and Colin McComb, was co-performed by the</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENT Chair in Computer &amp; Information Science. His research interests include social and cognitive computing, natural language processing, and user-friendly software. His publications include the popular science-neoconudface &quot;The Computerization of Everyday Life&quot; in Science &amp; Cultural Theory; the New York Times best-seller &quot;Information Mythology&quot; in cultural ecology; and the recently published book  	Uncovering Natural Language Processing: From Strategies to Strategies&quot; in the Proceedings of the ACM  linguist’s conference: Systems, 2016. His book  	Uncovering Natural Language Processing: From Strategies to Strategies&quot; builds on the recent work of the UNConQUERED project, led by Prof. Evan Hartley and Prof. Esther Levi, as well as the work of the NYU Langone Medical Center’s Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Lab. His latest work builds on work undertaken for the film  	Unravelled, which is set in the Spanish city</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENTED Chair in Computer Science at Columbia University. His work has addressed topics of artificial intelligence (AI), cultural ecology, social systems and media. His publications include the popular books Smart Screens (with Jill Sobule) and New Media Technologies (MIT Press, 2015), as well as chapters in Networks, Intranets, and Social Worlds (MIT Press, 2016). His latest project is a two-year long study of the 1992 Barcelona Biennale that will include a book and a documentary. He has written for Wired, The New York Times, The Washington Post and The New Republic and is currently a panelist on the forthcoming TV show Edge.Campanilla is a co-founder of Unave, a digital art collective based in Bogota, Colombia. He is the recipient of the UNSPECIALISTEE  programmer prize  and the UNKNOWN grant from the Arts Council, as well as the 2013 Cooper Hewitt Prize for Architecture and a 2014 UNKNOWN programmer pri</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] The AI is a super-computer developed by the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and NASA. It performs vast amounts of computation and is able to understand vast amounts of data – much of which is text – in an attempt to create more intelligent beings. It is unclear what kind of knowledge the AI would have, since it is unclear what kinds of relationships between humans and computers the AI would have.  [2] The Beatles, Sgt. Pepper's Lonely Hearts Club Band, 1964. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [3] The Metropolitan Museum of Art, New York, 1983. Courtesy of the UKCA.  [4] The Daily Telegraph (London), 16 April 1976.  [5] The Daily Telegraph (London), 20 April 1976. Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJosé Luis CampanillaJosé Luis Campanilla is Professor in Computer Science at the City University of New York, and holds the UNCOVENTED Chair in Computer Science and Engineering at the New School in New York City. His research interests include artificial intelligence and social networks. His publications include Systems Neuroscience: A Brief Introduction (with Thomas Zimmer) and to be published in a future issue of IEEE Computer, Systems Neuroscience publishes the results of a major research project currently underway in Portugal. His publications have been featured in digital media including Wired Magazine, Scientific American, BBC News, BBC Computer and BBC Science. He has been an advisor for the 2014 Venice Biennale and is currently a director of the Portuguese branch of the Academy of Sciences. He is a member of the steering committee of IEEE/RSL’s Symposium on Knowledge Discovery and Transformation (S.D.T.) and the 2014 AI symposium. His writing has been featured in the New York Times, Wall Street Journal, Scientific American, BBC News, BBC Computer and BBC Science.He is the host of the monthly podcast Systemdorm, which is published by New Media</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole is now exposed to that particular form of massive power. When you turn on the TV at night, you see images of the demolition of homes – there are stories of families still living in the area – but you rarely get the chance to go to bed dreaming about the houses that are being demolished. For some, the demolition of home is simply another form of work that they are doing in their spare time, for them it is just another job. For others, it is their life's work. For us, it is both the everyday demolition of homes, but also the demolition of a mythological place – a place where communities gather to talk and share experiences, to buy things, and to have rituals of some kind that emerge out of that collective process. The collection as a whole emerges out of that process, through the narrative of the programme, not through knowledge of its actual composition. That is, of course, until it is systematically erased from existence. When the bank was closed, the collection as</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole is a particularly vulnerable spot. The power of the archive lies in its 'rings', as it are, and its ability to resonate with a wider public through repeated exposure. However, the power of this collective memory is itself fragile, and the collection as a whole is particularly vulnerable. The power of the ring is that it can capture and transmute particular events and ideas – often unwittingly – into new forms that are at best perforce hybrid and perverse, and at worst actively destructive. The collection as a whole is particularly susceptible to this kind of collection-wide amnesia, which is vividly illustrated by the collection of photographs that came to define the architectural style of the 1990s Liverpool Biennial. These photographs, taken by the Liverpool Biennial staff and posted online in 2009 under the title Redefining Art’s Scale, act as a reminder of the city’s historic urban blighting processes. The redaction of key words and phrases in the photos obscures the messy urban landscape of</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole is a collection of large objects. The collection as a whole is a huge, vast data set, and its preservation and archiving is a powerful way of concealing the past. However, the power of this power can be used morally ambiguously, as in the case of the prosecution of Aqsa Mahmood and Fazliddin Dadhji, whose deportation from Turkey triggered the First World War. Sometimes the power of archiving is used for good: the collection of Nadine Gordimer’s children’s books, published in 1970, is a powerful example of this. However, in the case of the Holocaust and the Holocaust denial, the power of archive is misused for evil: the power of archive is used for the purpose of evading responsibility and fuelling the conflict.How can the power of archive be used for good? I believe that the power of archive should reside in the hands of a community of custodians, who should draw upon knowledge from diverse</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole is a return to some of these practices. However, the collecting agency that we name is different from the collection that is produced by museums and historical societies. The collecting priorities of the 'Centre' are very different from those of a museum or historical society. This is partly because the person or organisation that is collecting the material or organising the research, as opposed to the person or organisation collecting the material or organising the historical society is the one that has the power. But the main reason why biennials have collections of material from different subjects is precisely this: to work with and to exchange this material between subjects. In the case of Liverpool Biennial, for example, the collections it has today were assembled from different periods and were made up of different people. They were gathered from different periods and in different places, and so on. In the case of Liverpool, the collection today is a function of its historic value and its potential future use. It is constantly being assembled through research and documentation, and</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole is part of this new historical order that is being assembled. This is a power that is much more readily available and manipulable, and it is now being assembled through research and documentation. So the idea here is that there is a latent archive of archival materials and information about what is happening in an area of the world right now, and that could be assembled through research and documentation; that is, the power of the archive. In a way, this is similar to what the biennial is trying to achieve, although here the museum is trying to play catch up and overtake the nascent biennial. The important difference here is that the biennial is trying to build an archive of its own, rather than trying to make something out of nothing. The important thing here is that the archive is made visible and that it is assembled and expanded through research and documentation. This is what the Liverpool Biennial is trying to do. The story of the ferry cannot be told in a linear fashion, and neither</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole is a good place to start learning about this new kind of historical power.  	When researching the Holocaust, one of the first things that inevitably comes to mind is the power wielded by an individual like Adolf Eich, who was head of the Nazi Party's Judenrat, responsible for selecting individuals for death, and who issued a decree on January 6, 1938, instructing all German officials to prepare &quot;suicide […] squads&quot; for the occasion. The reach and nature of this power grab are difficult to comprehend, but it is clear that this did not happen by accident. It had to be issued by an official high-level commission, and it was clearly stated in bold type on the document: this was a proposal to all German officials, not an individual. So how did this happen? To understand how this happened, it is necessary to understand what we now call the Official History of the Holocaust. This document, prepared by the National Archives and handed in by the Nuremberg Military</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole is an important part of this new urban form. This is a new kind of urbanisation.  In fact, this kind of urbanisation is part of what the Biennial is trying to achieve in an unprecedented way: to be able to move from the museum to the street level, to the level of the street, and to the level of the apartment building. In a sense, the collections that are being planned for Anfield could be described as a kind of a tributary system that is currently being worked on upstream by the Liverpool Biennial and other art collections, which are trying to build a city around the collection and the street level. The collection as a whole is part of building the city, but it is also a city that is trying to be built around the collection and the street level. One could argue that the collection as a whole is part of the city, while the street level is a collection that is trying to organize itself on the basis of people’s need to know</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole is a likely result of that unprecedented power fantasy.  	But perhaps the most powerful way in which the collection can be brought together is through what has come to be known as ‘the archive build-up’. This is the new way in which research-based archives are made visible and transnational, and it is happening now as part of the Brexit’s  	Unite the Right rally in Charlottesville, Virginia. The collection of letters, diaries, documents and other archival materials gathered over decades in Liverpool is being made visible in an unprecedented way through this build-up, as are the people who use them, doing impressive work in their homes and community spaces. But the new normal is that materials like diaries, letters, photographs and stacks of documents will eventually become commonplace and disappear, as happened with the end of the gold standard and the beginning of electronic archiving. So it is that the collection of letters, diaries, documents and other archival</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole is part of this new urban form that is being forged in the ashes of the demolished buildings, particularly in the wake of the Housing Market Renewal Initiative (HMRI). The collection as a whole is a super-useful resource, and provides a way to imagine a future for the area with the collection moving at high speed into the present, rather than in the distant future when the collection is in its concrete shell.  The collection as a whole can also bind different pasts and futures, and act as a kind of geographical horizon that gives meaning to the destruction of much of what was once thought to be a single city block. The collection can act as a kind of tapestry that allows us to see into the future, or at least into the past.  Another way in which the collection can act as a super-useful resource is in the production of spatial identities. The collection has a kind of meta-historical character that makes it possible to imagine a different future</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, and will often times be more like an artistic commission. I have a proposal for a similar type of commission for the Liverpool Biennial 2018, although with Liverpool as the artistic centre of the project, rather than the other way around. Liverpool Biennial is already planning to work with the artist Esther Williams on a new urban project for Anfield, and with her family, including their art collection, to bring together a range of archives, drawing together over decades, allowing the collection as a whole to take shape. The idea is that there is an archive of over 20th-century British urban development in Anfield, which can be pieced together using historical materials and archival research. The collection can then be assembled into one coherent whole through the power of archiving. This is similar to the way in which museums and historical societies assemble collections today, but in a way that is much more powerful and ubiquitous. It is a power that has recently been deployed in an unprecedented way, and the collection as a whole is part of this new urban landscape being created in large part through the new biennial format.  Whether this is an appropriate use of the collection or not, there is a question that must be asked and answered: how is the collection being used? Is the collection being appropriated? Is the use of the collection permissive? If permissive, what is it being appropriated for? If permissive, what is its potential as an archive?  Such power brokers need to be stopped, and power is being exerted on the collection at an unprecedented rate in the United Kingdom and globally. It is up to the biennial to decide how the collections it produces will be used. However, there are obvious practical constraints on when and how such a use can be made, and the biennial can either decide to ignore these, or it can decide to actively thwart the potential use of the collections it produces by virtue of the huge financial burden it carries. For example, the biennial could make it impossible for any</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar business. The question becomes whether the city is ready for such a transformation, and whether the biennial can align itself with the city’s growth and create new modes of urban engagement. This may require new modes of urban production and distribution of resources, new modes of urban organisation, new modes of urban living. 	The question becomes whether the biennial can align itself with the city’s growth and create new modes of urban engagement. This may require new modes of urban production and distribution of resources, new modes of urban living, and a completely new relationship between the public and private sectors. These may sound like utopian goals, but they are attainable if we collectively and act upon them. The question becomes whether the biennial can align itself with the city’s growth and create new modes of urban engagement. This may require new modes of urban production and distribution of resources, new modes of urban living, and a completely new relationship between the public and private sectors. These may sound</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar business. If it is to achieve transformative effects, it will be necessary to coordinate across diverse stakeholders. This may involve cross-subsidy, which is becoming increasingly common in the urban environment, and may require the involvement of local governments. The density of buildings in the core city has increased by approximately 60% during the past twenty years. If the core city were to be transformed into a biennale destination, it would have to accommodate approximately 400,000 visitors in an urban area the size of Hong Kong. This may seem excessive, but consider that the city has a biennale calendar of about 400,000 visitors a year. The biennial’s current capacity to hold a significant impact on the cityscape is also limited by the city’s financial dependence on tourism. It may be possible to expand the biennial’s current programming, but this would require a state-of-the-art biennial’s centrepiece to rival some of the most iconic</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar business. The political will to do this may still exist, but the time has come to put an end to the fantasy of urban renewal and create viable, city-friendly neighbourhoods. The development of affordable housing, and in particular, the creation of affordable housing for artists and venues, is a necessity for the future of this city. This may require compromise, but the battle cry of ‘we the people’ may no longer be a response to the demands of a few mega-corporations. The people have spoken. Now the people need to be listened to. The people don’t always agree, but over the past decade or so, the majority of which were located in the north, the demands of the 1 per cent have increasingly often been heard rather than acted upon. This may be seen as a failure of the political and economic infrastructure, but it also may be seen as a failure of the people. Local people have often been able to take back cities and districts when they</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar business. The question is whether the city will be able to absorb the change, or whether the biennial, which appears to be everywhere these days, will become something completely different. The answer to that latter will almost certainly depend on the political will.We do not yet know what the political situation will be in 2045. The biennial may well become something completely different, and perhaps even more disruptive, than we imagined.  The question is, will the inhabitants of Liverpool still want to come to Anfield? Will they want to travel through the city, coming to the biennial as tourists? We don’t yet know, and neither do we care. The challenge now is to create a cultural offering that is both accessible, and manages to be both aesthetically appealing, and, above all, possible.Download this article as PDFNina Edgevs. The BiennialNina Edgevs. The Biennial: On the level of a performance, Nina Edgevs. The Big Oscill</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar business. The question is whether the city can support the ecological and urban planning that may accompany this. 	 	The question of political will and whether the city can support the decision is a different story. The city can certainly support the decision to destroy what little infrastructure is left after a major construction project, such as a stadium or new street grid, but the question is whether the political will is there to carry it out. In the case of a stadium or new street grid, the question is whether the city can afford to repair and maintain them. The answer to this is a yes. It is doubtful that the F.C.C. will have the political will to regulate the use of urban infrastructure after the destruction of the historical downtown core, but it is certain that the F.C.C. will have the political will to create an ecological and urban utopia with a strong participatory political and economic component. The question is whether the political will is there to enable the creation of</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar business. It is also possible that the biennial will simply adapt to the city’s shifting population and economic mix. Whatever happens, it is essential for our purposes here to know that this dynamic dynamic has already happened.And this dynamic will go on. The question is whether the biennial will be able to live up to its potential, or whether it will succumb to the pressures of a growing economy and urban complex. We cannot know with any certainty which of these will happen, but it is certain that the economy is one of the most significant factors in the city's rapid growth. We should therefore not underestimate the importance of the environment in shaping the trajectory of a biennial’s fortunes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThe Teaching Muse Emily Pringle is Professor in the Department of English and Festival Studies at the Winchester Arts College, University of Southampton. Her research interests include the art of visual culture and cultural ecology; political ecology; and the arts and social consequences of globalisation</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar business. The question is whether the city is ready for that. 	[1] National Geographic, March, 2015. http://www.nature.com/nature/journal/v14/n12/full/nature22469.html#ixzz2VyaW51X092LyMjE#ixzz2RhDQ2VyaW51X092LyMjE#ixzz2DdDQ1VyaW51X092LyMjE#ixzz2RTVQ2VyaW51X092LyMjE[2] Climate Central, 2016.  http://www.climatecentral.org/en/latest/summary-report/summary-2016/en/en/full-statement-on-global-warming-in-asia-pacific/hi-i-am-sue-l-curtis-susan-kelly-2016</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar business, and the politics of growth will likely play a role in its future.The question of political participation in the context of climate change will almost certainly play a role in the future of the biennial. Will the biennial become a vehicle for the political-ideological empowerment of an urbanised underclass, or will it be an equally powerful tool for the political and economic empowerment of an urban elite? These are difficult questions to answer, and no answer can be given in one fell swoop. There are many who have a stake in the outcome, and they will continue to be able to express their views through art. But the question of participation in the context of climate change will almost certainly play a role in the fate of the biennial. Will the biennial become a vehicle for the participation of a racialised underclass, or will it be a vehicle for the participation of a multi-racial underclass? Whatever its form, it is certain that it will remain political, and that means supporting</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar business. The question is whether the urban environment will still be able to support the kinds of public realm projects, such as parks and streets, that we imagined possible.Download this article as PDFBinaural beats acousticsWith the advent of recording studios, the biennial came to encompass a wider range of sounds. At the time, artists were encouraged to experiment with new ways of employing the studio. The advent of the biennial coincided with a general increase in public spending, which was in turn a result of a growth in tourism. The growth in tourism was accompanied by a corresponding increase in public services, services and structures – buildings, tunnels, museums, theatres, parks … – which were needed by the increasingly constrained public. These included a wide range of programs aimed at enticing visitors to spend money, including free public swimming, hiking, fishing and bird watching, as well as a wide range of recreational facilities, such as golf courses, tennis courts, picnics, picnicking …</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will certainly be different from the ones we imagined. The architecture of the biennial will be dictated by the city’s finance and urban transformation plans. These have been redrawn to take into account the impact of climate change, and will no longer be based on historical trends. To make the biennial a reality, the F.C.C. would have to pass a law granting it exclusive use of a designated area. It is also doubtful whether the biennial would be able to gain local support in the way that we imagined. The fact that we did not create an entity to manage the city and its infrastructure may have ultimately political consequences. The political situation may have shifted, but the relationship between biennials and the urban environment is static. The biennial will almost certainly be influenced by the city’s finance plans and its growth as a result of these, as well as the city’s economic development plans. The biennial may well become a multi-billion-dollar business for the city. The question is whether the city can support its growth on its own. In the current political climate, the answer is probably &quot;yes.&quot; The city remains hugely dependent on tourism, and its growth will almost certainly be accompanied by a host of new tax-funded agencies and programs. The question, then, becomes whether the biennial can align itself with these growth plans in a way that does not sacrifice the biennial as a subject of analysis? It may be the case that aligning itself with the growth plans may actually hasten the inevitable, because the threatened aridity of the city is used as a political tool by those with a financial stake in the biennial’s future. If the biennial is not brought into line with the city’s development as a whole, and does not contribute to its social and ecological transformation, then it may be that the biennial requires a shift in its growth, and this will be seen by some as an – perhaps unavoidable</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations,
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations, society more generally. Sometimes the project or the work we produce is so provocative that it actually threatens institutionalised power structures – structures that we actually witness. In such cases, we can be quite blunt in our questioning whether structures exist to oppress us or just to provide us with a social and political situation in which we can flourish. 	The third and final component of Community Arts practice is the maker. This is a person or organisation who contributes to the production of art or community through their work. It can be a community organisation, a non-profit organisation, a firm established through the merger of two or more commercial businesses, a non-profit trade association or a for-profit business. The point is to see how the social aspect of the art can be enhanced through the collaboration and the production of open source software, documentation and artwork, publics and localities, research and analysis, and to see if such tools could be utilised to produce more social or even transformative effects through their use.</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations, and how that may shape how we engage with the project in different contexts. For example, when we were researching Displaced Persons, we conducted in-person​ surveys of three Auckland First Ministers, asking how they would engage with displacement. We also conducted an online survey of 1,200 people using Engage! New Zealand, asking how similar the two projects were in terms of their social objectives. Both projects sought to create a sense of belonging in the local communities by empowering the local people to take control of their futures, and we found that both were successful in this as well as other ways. 	When we started our PhD research, we decided to name our department after the local of the Greek island where the Trojan Horse was based. This came as a surprise to many people in the department, who found the idea of the museum after the city ridiculous. However, the people who initiated and led the project were quite taken with the name and had fun using it. The Greek mythological figure was</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations, and we can challenge assumptions and preconceptions about what that other relationship to the project or art or community might mean. For example, our work with the MiMOC (Mexican National Council of Cultural Monuments) has engaged on several levels with the idea of territory and its various forms, and the systems of control that separate us from one another, and has placed particular emphasis on the work of migration and refugee advocacy, while at the same time incorporating studies of incarceration and criminal justice related issues. The project has been about what it means to be ‘Mexican’ or ‘Mestizo’ in a particular locality, and has sought to understand the ways in which one is incorporated into that particular scene, while also questioning the boundaries and systems of power that might be at play. In other words, it has operated on the notion of place, but has also acknowledged the specificities of being embedded in a particular social situation. 	In the case of the MiMOC,</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations, or to the world around us. For example, the stories and practices of migrant workers or the urban poor often receive a great deal of attention, but little is said by way of reflection or analysis about the roles and rights of these populations in contemporary urban environments. This is especially true for artists or curators of migrant worker reclamation projects, which are often inspired by the stories and practices of these communities. We see this as an opportunity to create a space or forum through which artists or curators can contribute to this conversation by bringing their artistic or curatorial thinking into the project. 	A third component to Community Arts practice that is often under-reported is the development or construction of social or cultural capabilities for these populations to participate in. This can happen in many ways: providing arts or culture education or facilities to artists or curators of migrant worker reclamation projects; maker/maker-curators associations; art/artist-curating institutions; cultural councils or non-profit arts organizations; community</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations, but there is much more to it than that. We have to see it as a lived reality, and not just an artwork or a visualization. There is a politics to the practices of Community Arts that need to be explored, and that starts with asking: what are the politics of making people live differently through art? What are the politics of giving those people a voice through art? What are the politics of the social when we turn to religion or state law? What are the politics of the individual when we turn to identity or nationality? What are the politics of language or the politics of citizenship? What are the politics of financial services, or the politics of mass communication? What are the politics of representation or the politics of displacement? 	Community Arts has often been a response to the question, how can a work of art be social? The practice of artist-organisations has historically been a response to a question, how can a work of art be representative? There are many works of art today</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations, or, to be more specific, how that relates to the society we live in. When we don’t have a socially engaged project that engages with these issues or want to, we often steer clear of them. But what we do have a responsibility to create is an environment where people can be drawn into those projects and have a say in how they are run. 	When we started the Community Arts education project in the 1980s, our intention was to use the art as a blunt instrument. We didn’t want to be experts in how people engage with art or art in a particular context; we just wanted to be able to whip people into action through our art as a blunt instrument. We started by creating a free two week intensive course in how to develop a project, using original works as resources, and then inviting people to join us in a creative way. This was the ‘real life’ of the arts education model, so it was a model that people</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations, and to see what kinds of possibilities that might present. 	When we engage with the cultural systems that generate or are products of capitalism, we find that capitalism is everywhere and at any moment, and so we need to be constantly aware of the ways in which we are drawn into those systems and how we are materially implicated in their functioning. 	The third component of Community Arts practice is likely to be more controversial, but it has become increasingly important for us as artists to be able to communicate our own work across the divisions of race, class, gender and sexuality, and to be able to identify with communities across the course of a biennial, because that is the way in which biennials are able to generate sustained, long-term relationships with audiences that are attentive to more than we could ever hope to hope on our own. 	The fourth component, perhaps the most fundamental and influential to artists developing their own practices, is likely to be found in communities with which artists have ongoing,</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations, and to ask, ‘What does it mean to be human in this context?’2 And sometimes, when we are not working within a community or going through a transformation, we need to ask, ‘What does it mean to be human in the context of a capitalist social order?’3 For example, in the UK we have recently started to see the connections between the social media platforms Facebook and Twitter, and the political and monitoring projects that followed them into being. And it is not just social media platforms and their users: platforms are becoming ever more aware of the kinds of analysis and monitoring they can bring to bear on social struggles. 	When we started to do work with M4T, we started to see how platforms are placing social and political struggles on a global scale. In the UK, the #MeToo movement is often seen as being sparked by a certain ex-partner of ours, but we were starting to see that many of the issues</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations, and to come to understand how this experience might be similar to that of another person or place. 	When we do engage with the project of data-production or visualization, we tend to isolate particular individuals or discrete elements and projects that we think are important in our respective spaces, but which may or may not be representative of the real world in which we live. For example, when I worked on the graphic identity of the Liverpool Biennial in 2012, I created a composite image of hundreds or perhaps thousands of street level photos, some of which were taken within a one kilometre radius of Anfield.2 	Even when we produce and present a project with data, hidden or not, we tend to act in ways that are not designed with people or places in mind. For example, when we produce a project that includes interactive media, we tend to ignore the fact that people are often not engaged with the media with which the project is made, but rather with what we have produced in its place</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and publics from a particular locality? If the answer is no, then we must start from the assumption that data is there, wherever it is, and that publics and localities are often not present or invisible when they are part of a larger cultural system. 	The second component of Community Arts practice is about the social. In the words of the term, ‘Community is the arena in which the social dimension is emphasised.’1 It is a socially engaged practice, and often a struggle to see people like-minded individuals engaging in art or community activities, because often what we have in common is not so much our common humanity, but our shared humanity – our fellow human beings being drawn into an art or community project through the activities of their own bodies. 	When we have community or human rights oriented work that we engage with socially, we often take the project into the context of our research or our own work to see how that relates to our own situations, and how that relates to the systems that shape our social, economic and political situations. In a 2010 survey, over a hundred academics, activists and practitioners from diverse fields of study responded to the question: ‘Do you see the importance of dialogue, or producing dialogue only, in your work?’2 Many cited the importance of transparency and accountability in their projects, citing the necessity to both the public and the private spheres of power in a democratic society. Transparency and accountability, however, are not enough to create or foster change; a sense of the public or the public good is required. In fact, many academics and activists who responded to the survey also felt that their projects were sometimes more interested in placating a constituency or a specific set of stakeholders than in creating lasting, positive change. They cited projects like the 2006 Copenhagen Consensus Decision as an example of successful democratic participation, but also projects such as the Stop Torture International Network and Mercy for Animals, as well as the work of the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In 2013, they established a multi-disciplinary, multi-use art space in the San Fernando Valley called Homebaked. Homebaked continues to be an important art-historical site for the region, and Moore is a key practitioner and promoter of the project.Homebaked, the Los Angeles based multi-use art space, originates in the San Fernando Valley and is home to several other projects. In 2015, the Biennial of Arts &amp; Culture selected Homebaked as one of its institutions for the upcoming cycle. In 2017, the National Museum of the American Indian selected Homebaked as one of its venues for the 150th anniversary of the foundation of the museum. In 2018, the Los Angeles County Museum of Art selected Homebaked as one of its venues for the Smithsonian’s National Gallery of Art, and in 2019 the Los Angeles County Museum of History and Preservation selected Homebaked as one of its venues for the Venice Biennale.In this</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In 2015, Moore curated the Venice Biennale, and in 2017, London’s V&amp;A. In their own words, ‘a turning point in the history of art’, and ‘a pivotal moment in the history of biennials’ development’. Their exhibition, ‘Art’ after the Biennale, discovered art after the art was usually dead, showing new art appearing in an event that for decades had little in terms of public or institutional interest, or indeed, in its real-life consequences.In the 1980s and 1990s, the biennial was a rare event in which the art form was actively contested, with curators often characterising the event as ‘dead’. Moore and López de la Torre’s exhibition Art after the Biennale posed a question that was both timely and controversial: what if, as some curators believed, the art form had entered</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In 2015, they opened the National Art Museum and Museum of Modern Art in Doha, Qatar, and the 2016 and 2017 Venice Biennales respectively. They have participated in the Cooper Hewitt Cultural Curatorial Jam in New York City, and are currently developing the European Capital of Culture list.Merleau-Ponty Archives, 2015. Photo: Christiane Paul.PreviousNextMerleau-Ponty Archives, 2015. Photo: Christiane Paul.The Two Arts, by Jeanne van Heeswijk and Britt Jurgensen, 2016. Installation view at Tate Modern. Courtesy the artist.PreviousNextThe Two Arts, by Jeanne van Heeswijk and Britt Jurgensen, 2016. Installation view at Tate Modern. Courtesy the artist.Merleau-Ponty Archives, 2015. Photo: Jan Lopéz de la Torre.PreviousNextMerleau-Ponty Archives, 2015. Photo: Jan Lopéz de la Torre.The two</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In 2016, they opened The Miami Museum of Art, the last of the Maya Monuments, which houses their vast collection and houses their headquarters. The Miami Museum of Art was a major tourist draw for the city, and the first Maya Monuments museum, and they’ve worked with local museums, historic districts, and archival collections to tell their stories. In 2018, they opened The Gallery at 1844 Jackson St, an exhibition space for their collection and home to the recently completed second phase of The Gallery, a multi-use performing arts center and exhibition venue. They’ve also collaborated on the Spanish language version of their flagship journal, Binderie. In 2018, they opened the biennial of their favorite cities: Buenos Aires and Montevideo.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In 2012, Moore was a co-curator of the Venice Biennale, part of the curatorial team for the New Frontiers series of exhibitions. She curated the 2014 Chicago Architecture Biennale, which opened in Venice and was part of the curatorial team for the New Frontiers series of exhibitions in Cincinnati. Moore is the Margaret and Tony Curtis Professor of Modern Art History and Curator of the Humanities at UCLA, and part of the Curatorial Faculty for the USC Museum of Art. She is the Helen and Norman Hiorns Professor of Visual Cultures and Curator of the Humanities at USC.Aida OlasztinaBirthplace: Iznik, Poland, 1947. Gender: Female. Dies: 1988.Occupation: Artist.In her artistic career, Moore has concentrated on the intersections of her family's history and her travels throughout the world. She is the recipient of several awards, including two Ivrit-Brunel awards (2001 and 2014), one</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In 2014, they were part of the curatorial team for the Venice Biennale. Their exhibition The Sacred Womb (2016) and the upcoming exhibition The Three Musketeers (2019) in Venice offer a new look into the lives and work of Indigenous and other nations in the arts and cultural context.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreBoth artists were born in Montevideo, Uruguay, in 1886. Their father was an art dealer and Lefse manufacturer. Moore studied painting and sculpture at the Royal College of Art, where she was a painter and sculptor, and Art History, a course in Renaissance and early modern art history, as well as a part of the Curatorial Faculty. Her development as an artist and teacher was initiated by her love of animals, which was reciprocated in her work: when she sold curiosities, animals, or live fossils, her customers included indigenous or tribal groups</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In recent years they've collaborated on projects in the United States and Europe, and have been featured in exhibitions such as the New Museum’s 'Art from Silence' project, which placed them in historical contexts and into contemporary art’s public gallery of silence. They co-curated the inaugural Venice Biennale, and have co-curated and co-organized the biennials of other cities around the world. In 2015 they co-founded the Center for Performing Arts in Santa Fe, New Mexico, with Cecilia Chung, and in 2017 formed the McArthur Art Center, a regional arts institution in Santa Fe, New Mexico.Marianne Moore: I’m referring to the fact that there’s no money in it. People are asking, How do you sustain an art school? And the answer is: you’re looking at a skyrocketing tuition bill, which is a direct consequence of the enormous growth in fees and charges, which</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In recent years, Moore has focused on the intersection of social and ecological crises, particularly in the Americas, and the effects of industrial civilization. Her work has included the 2010 Delfina Foundation Alaska Platform, a $100 million multi-purpose recreational and historical site in the city, and the 2014 Delfina Foundation Global Platform, a $100 million multi-purpose complex in the far north. Both foundations were created to support art projects in the city and are managed by a board of artists, writers and community members.Morehshin Allahyari: You can think of the artist as someone with a very specific set of skills and an agenda. She also happens to be a mathematician. What was it like to be a designer in the 21st century? MJ: In the 21st century, there’s no such thing as the ‘designer’; there’s only the planner. The notion of design is hugely transnational and applied across borders; it’</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In 2013 they opened the Centro Cultural Florencio Nacional, a residential community for artist-centered projects in the city. They also opened Cuenca del Toro, a new museum and gallery with a curatorial focus on the arts and culture of the Peruvian Andes. Unravelled was their 2015 curatorial intervention, a temporary installation and a chapter in the Architecture of Social Life series. Their 2016 project Unravelled: History of the Peruvian Urbanscape was their final project, and are now partners with the Liverpool Biennial.Both Moore and de la Torre were curators on the 2006 Venice Biennale, and worked on the 2008 Madrid Biennale and 2016 Sochi Biennale. They directed and co-scripted the 2016 Buenos Aires Biennale, along with the 2014 New York and London Museums of Art visits. They were also co-curators of the 2008 Athens and Gorgias, and were co-curator of the</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the last in the city and the last to be built, but we’ll be seeing what happens after that. There’s a question around what happens after that, and we need to find out what that is. How do we design a future for ourselves and our city in that case, because that is a very interesting question to ask.Download this article as PDFCuehondas del ToroMarianne Moore and Ada López de la TorreMarianne Moore and Ada López de la Torre: The two artists formed in 1986 and collaborated extensively throughout the '90s and into the early 2000s, when Moore was curator of the New Art Museum and in 2003 the artist was part of the curatorial team for the National Museum of the American Indian. They created a new kind of biennial that focused on the cultural significance of indigenous and other &quot;heritage&quot; art forms, and invited artists from around the world to participate. In 2016, Moore was a curator at the Los Angeles County Museum of Art and the National Museum of the American Indian. She was part of the curatorial team for the 2016 Venice Biennale, and part of the curatorial team for the 2017 People’s Republic of China Pavilion, where she oversaw the installation of works by indigenous artists from all over the world.Marianne Moore: The notion of history repeated itself – in many forms – in the second half of the twentieth century. The word ‘heritage’ comes up a lot in relation to a place or a culture. But what does it mean to be ‘heritage’ in relation to history? For me, it’s as if there’s a double meaning to the word. When we talk about the place or the culture, we’re not just thinking about the artefacts or the collection – we’re thinking about the lineage that those things come from. So when we</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues into usable and innovative strategies, based on current and historical housing conditions, needs and desires in the city. The project will also enable InSite to contribute to the development of innovative housing solutions through research-led development projects in the city, while enhancing knowledge of the city’s past housing development and the challenges ahead. 	The project calls for a ‘tripartite process’ to merge the knowledge of the participating institutions and relevant local communities. Particular attention is given to the ‘housing crisis in the city’, which is the subject of a separate initiative by the Biennial. 	The partnership between INSite and the Liverpool Biennial could potentially render localised and regionalised perspectives on the same factual data, thereby enabling a one-to-one or large-scale inter-connection between the experiences of inhabitants of the areas planned for development by the Biennial. 	InSite is inviting participants to apply for a spot in the research project. The research project</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues into viable options for future housing, while drawing upon expertise from a range of expertise streams within the area, internationally recognised academic and research institutions, grassroots groups and local authorities. 	The project’s research-based programme will see InSite develop a multi-disciplinary research agenda through its local, regional and international staff, researchers and clinicians, as well as local communities. The scope for research into the housing crisis, including through research projects, will include research-based practices, including research into the causes and consequences of housing in the city; research into local governance and research projects; research into direct action strategies; research into participatory research; research into community-based learning programmes and research projects; research into alternative land-use strategies; research into participatory planning and research projects; research into contract-based research; research into implementation research; research into contracting through workforce programmes; research into third-party funding providers; research into collaborative research projects; research into international funding agencies; research into non-</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues into usable strategies for the future of the city. Research into sustainable solutions to controversial issues is an important progressive step in advancing the cause of social and economic justice. Research conducted in the context of the Biennial could not only change how social scientists, practitioners and artists think about housing and social change, but could also change how such knowledge is produced and distributed. 	InSite is a UK based non-profit organisation founded in 1981 and headquartered in Liverpool. It is a not-for-profit organisation that brings together innovative artists, academics and grassroots groups to produce socially engaged work on a local, regional and national level through research, advocacy and education. It is a member of the Russell Sage Foundation's (2013-16) Social Practice Research Network (SPRN) and was previously a board member of the SPRN. InSite was a catalyst for the Liverpool Biennial’s 2016, which was also a catalyst for the creation of the SPRN. InSite was a driving force behind In</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues into usable tools that can be used in the future to build or alter housing in the city, at an early stage of planning. 	The project is being led by Professor Alan Johnson, Director of the Leeds and Royal Holloway University Schools of Architecture and Urban Studies, and Professor Guy Debord, a leading genturger and architect who died in 1967. The project is being developed by the Leeds and Royal Holloway Schools, as well as the Centre for Research Architecture, at the University of Leeds. 	(Incite! / InSite) is a 3-month long, collaborative research project. It was part of 	Diagoras Programme, at the University of Leeds, part of 	Research Workshop: Participating Institutions (Rake), a collaboration between the University of Leeds and Leeds Business School, part of 	Research Fellowship: Leeds. 	(Incite! / InSite) was launched in October 2017. 	invited me to be part of</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues into a future housing crisis scenario, while drawing on the insights and behaviours of individuals and groups who have remained in the city during the past 50 years. 	The project's research-based programme will see the use of data and innovative approaches to bring forward positive futures for the city’s struggling population. This will enable the redevelopment of abandoned and vacant properties, the establishment of non-profit management companies, the creation of worker-owned cooperatives, as well as the provision of affordable housing for low-income households through the provision of low-income housing grants. 	The Liverpool Biennial will deliver a research-based programme with a collaborative approach to inform a future housing development strategy. This will include the development of case studies and scenarios in an attempt to highlight key facts and figures relevant to the city’s housing crisis, while drawing on the experiences of other cities in an attempt to draw forward ideas for the future. The project will seek to reconcile past and future through research, analysis</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues into an appealing narrative through a narrative that incorporates key aspects of each project’s heritage. 	This approach to historical research is distinct from the more traditional archeological or historical survey research that often falls under the term ‘historical research’, as a synonym. Rather, this ‘fieldswork’ approach seeks to map spaces and time in an area through what is essentially a historical survey, or at least drawing lines across the historical places where actionable historical information is located. InSite’s research will draw on the experiences and heritage of the local communities living and working in and around the Shoal at the Liverpool and MCRL ports. The PCC will draw on experiences from their own research projects into the area. Both projects will investigate the ways in which the Shoal at Liverpool and MCRL can be used to generate new ways of living and working in the area. 	The historical research projects will be based in Istanbul and Istanbul-based institutions</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues into usable strategies for the ‘development’ of the city through a single resource. 	InSite is using the capital from its crowdfunding campaign to fund the construction of two new housing towers, one in the heart of the city’s financial district and the other off the river, near a new train station. While the river site is convenient for transit, it has been suggested that the tower ‘came with a dark side’. 	InSite’s research-based programme in the city will draw together key findings from the two previous research projects, as well as new research from the university, local housing activists and residents, and will present findings from a third research project into the lives of house-buyers, commissioned by the Biennial and conducted by Leeds City Council. 	As co-investigators in  	Future City,  	Research Triangle Park (2015–16) and  	Research Triangle Institute (2017–present),</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues into a viable future for the city’s large urban Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander populations. 	InSite is using the funds from the Scottish Hand in order to relocate its headquarters to Cashel, New Mexico. Funding for relocation is provided by the Scottish Hand in perpetuity. 	In January 2018, InSite announced that it was closing its New Mudgei Gallery and Archive, the site of InSite’s first retail store, due to structural issues. The closure of the gallery and archive was motivated by financial difficulties, with InSite closing its bank account and having to declare a loss on its 2016 financial report. 	In February 2018, InSite announced that it was closing its Beauty Supplies store, as a result of structural issues unrelated to the closure of Beauty Supplies. The closure of the store was also related to the inability to secure financing for the store, which was to be housed in a partnership development by the UK’s largest cosmetics retailer,</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues into quantitative and qualitative models relevant for the social and spatial redevelopment of the city. The project will address how quantitative methods can be combined with qualitative methods to produce new knowledge-production strategies. The research projects will be developed with the collaborative input of researchers from the Liverpool Biennial, the University of Leeds, and the local community. The partnership between the Liverpool Biennial, the University of Leeds, and the Leeds City Council is a rare example of a research-based programme co-producing social or spatial change through an art-project. The collaboration between the Biennial, the City of Leeds, and the local community will hopefully yield new insights into the dynamics of living in and within a community, and how to support such participation. 	[i] Gareth White, The Social Life of Housing (2015), in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 20, No. 1, p.9.Download this article as PDFGareth WhiteGareth White is an art historian and writer</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets, particularly for those communities with a stake in the outcome. The resolution passed overwhelmingly, with contributions from all quarters and interests. The issue was raised again at the annual meeting of the International Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament in October 2016. This time, representatives from the International Campaign, the Union for a Developing Economy, and the University of Leeds presented research on their respective research-based programmes into the impacts of inSite, a £750,000 project funded by the European Commission and the UK's National Audit Office. 	InSite is using a partnership between the Liverpool Biennial and the University of Leeds to investigate the housing crisis in the city. The project’s research-based programme will draw together key findings from the Biennial’s 2016/17 and 2017/18 research projects, as well as findings from previous research projects undertaken by the University of Leeds in the 1980s and 1990s. The collaboration with the University of Leeds will enable InSite to render current housing issues into viable options for future housing, while drawing on the expertise of a range of partners – architects, housing activists, academics, local authorities – with a view to enabling InSite to deliver its stated aims of ‘innovating ways of living’. 	 The project is being led by Professors Sandeep Parmar and Deepa Chalabi, as well as Dr Katherine Bradshaw, Chair of Architecture and Environmental Design at the University of Leeds. The research programme will be developed with Leeds Digital Archive and will see Leeds-based InSite teaming up with Leeds-based LUXeD, a cultural organisation formed in Rotchdorf in 1981, the University of Leeds and archives to research housing in the city. The partnership with the University of Leeds will see InSite develop technology that records and manages the health of the biennial’s visitors, developing strategies for its future activities. InSite will use their offices and research centres to monitor, collect and analyze health data</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And so we find ourselves suffering from the imperfect form of the aesthetic experience that is understood as the consummation of the modern age: the perfect image of the perfect object.The sublime is understood in different ways by different people. There are those who derive pleasure from the appearance of the sublime, who call it a Symbol, and who use its varied epithets (morbidity, decadence, madness, violence, etc) to describe the consummation that is now unfolding across the globe. There are others who identify with the classical festival of the full moon, who call it superstition. Finally, there are us, who identify with the idea that we are not on this earth alone, but are part of a community of users of energy resources, and so are contributing to a global ledger that records all manner of data points that can be used to make more abstract things more real. There is a tension, a mutual incompatibility, between the goals of the modern museum and those of the</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And here the body imagines things in terms of possible futures – present and future – in which things are not as they are. For example, the body can compute that it can shed more muscle tissue than it does blood, through a process known as hypertrophy. The body then undertakings this task at a rapid clip, producing the same amount of tissue but with higher bone-taking capacity. And here we see an exceptional case of overcompensation: the body maximizes the amount of tissue it has to repair itself in response to injury, which in turn produces an extraordinary increase in tissue that can then be used by more tissue-using organs. And here we also see an exceptional case of overproduction: the body exploits its excess tissue for its own ends. And here we must ask: how is it that the body in its infinite capacity can repair itself in this way? And if the answer is that we live in a world (our bodies) populated with inescapable pathogens and toxins,</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And this process – overproduction – is a recurrent feature of the contemporary condition. We accumulate food and water and other commodities in response to constant need; we seek medical attention for ailments that are treatable with far less than emergency room visits; we engage in the activities of everyday life in the hope that we might one day be able to look back on the past and recall the pleasures of eating and engaging in culture; we engage in the practices of art and architecture in the hope that we might one day own cultural artefacts; and we engage in the symbolic practices of fashion in the hope that our clothing and accessories will one day represent a collective sense of meaning and purpose and be able to articulate the collective in a shared history and future.Tags: anthropology, biopolitics, biopolitics: intersection, cultural geography, cultural geography, cultural geography, conjugation, ethnography, iconology, migration, migration, migration, icon, iconography, ideology, nationalism, nationalism, politics, resource use</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And so we find ourselves engaged in debates about the status of human bodily fluids (blood, tissue, organs), the integrity of human language (its semantic value is often questioned), and the limits of our own capacities. The search for an adequate sense of the sublime often seeks to reconcile the differences between bodily fluids, the attributes of living things, and the things that are understood as essentially distinct. The search for an adequate sense of the ‘unique’ often seeks to reconcile the differences between living things, the attributes of things, and the meaning of words. The search for an adequate sense of the ‘unique’ often relies on the construction of idealized versions of the things understood to be unique, of words understood to capture the essence of things, and of the world as understood in the embodied form of a living thing.The quest for an adequate sense of the ‘unique’ often results in a fetishization of the anthropologist’s figure as the one with the panache</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And so the body, in a continual state of excess, produces the emotion of pain at the lowest possible cost. We experience bodily pleasure in two ways: as excess; and at a price. Aristotle, in his Theaetetus, defines the ‘pleasure of the flesh’ as follows:Theaetetus, Book X, Chapter 8, §8.1. Pleasure, or what is meant by this in Greek, is the quality of things existing in the world as objects of enjoyment. It is one thing to look on in rapture as an elephant you have just bought for a few thousand pieces of silver; quite another to indulge in the flesh of a living human being in a way that is entirely captivating, quite another to produce that same elephant in one of your many other ways. This is not some sort of abstract or abstract-like thing. This is a life-like experience. Not everyone with whom you have lived will be able to identify with this sort</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And we humans are creatures who value things that are abundant and simple, so it is easy to understand the desire to consume, to consume what is familiar and familiar. The body, and especially the organs it produces, is often catered to by our cravings. But this body does not produce pleasure or endow us with anything particularly remarkable or unique. It is a collection of habitual responses to food and drink, of course, and its functions are often centred around the production of more food and sex. But this body also has other, subtler functions that are not exclusively those of the consuming part of us. For instance, the brain is a collection of neurons; it is not a singular building block but rather a series of units that aggregate to form larger systems, and these other functions also include the production of new neurons. So the body, in its capacity as a collector of calories, is also a producer of new neurons. And these new neurons do not come out of the blue; rather</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And so the two parts, the object and the process, are positioned in such a way as to maximize the return on investment for the manufacturer as a whole, while minimizing the risk to the world as a whole. This is the archetypal situation – the manufacturer has a return on investment (ROI) that is above and beyond the cost of production; the world has no such return. The object has a different form and semantics. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (including sweat, tears, and secretions), is positioned at a distance (this is why bodies have faces and bodies have hands and feet); it is not physically visible to the naked eye, but its existence in the abstract is. The symbol of the heart is a perfect image of this distance. The body is often described as consisting of energy, but this is not always the case; in the physical world of things, energy is a concept that is still quite fluid and subject</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And so we find ourselves divided into two camps: those who cry wolf about the inhumane deaths resulting from over-the-counter drugs (heroin, crystal meth, etc), and the medical profession’s legitimate response to such abuses, and those who claim that the medical profession is uniquely positioned to intervene in the social harms resulting from the over-the-counter drug trade, through its brand names and product lines; against a backdrop of inhumane deaths at the hands of those who refuse to be labelled.The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (including the organs that constitute blood), often overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And so we are led to believe that the medical profession’s capacity to intervene in the social harms resulting from the over-the-counter drug trade is an endowment that should be shared equally between the different stakeholders – patients, doctors, nurses, pharmacists, etc.</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And this overproduction – excess of a substance, substance, body part, etc – manifests itself in various ways, including (but not limited to) the manifestations of physical deformity, the growth of malignant tumors, and the formation of voids in which to exist – to name only a few manifestations. In the broadest sense, then, the body (and especially the brain) is a large computational unit – capable of phenomenal experience, including phenomenal cognition – and capable of phenomenal suffering. This explains how the body can generate such a large volume of matter and fluids with such minimal effort. It is possible that the reduction in cost and effort required by contemporary computation would result in a qualitatively different kind of bodily – qualitatively different from the kind that we humans produce – but this is a philosophical question that cannot be answered with any certainty.Instead, we can affirm that modern computation reproduces itself through what is sometimes called ‘the miracle of crowds’ – the ability to gather information in large</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone: a capacity that is often expressed as a capacity for empathy. But empathy is a capacity; it is not an endowment. And empathy is a particular form of admiration. Excessively so. Aristotle could not have imagined a future in which the capacity for empathy would extend to encompass all aspects of our lives, but he did foresee the consummation of the emotion as a consummation.The search for an adequate form of empathy for all of us ends up structuring our understanding of the sublime in terms of two components: bodily and conceptual. The body, and in particular, the bodily processes involved in shedding blood and bodily fluids (the tissues that constitute blood, tissue, are complex and variable and constantly on the lookout for pathogens and contaminants); and the thought, or representation, of the object (blood, tissue, organs, bones, sweat, hormones, etc). The body, in turn, frequently overcompensates by producing more of the same thing at a lower cost. And such overcompensation is understood by some cultural theorists to be a virtue, a positive quality that helps to ensure universal access to resources and to create a sense of oneness with the world around us.Yet there is considerable variation across cultures in the quality of this kind of aestheticising. A 1998 review of art and psychology in the Journal of Abnormal Psychology concluded that empathy is a construct that is socially constructed and that attempts to translate the emotions of others into our own are not likely to succeed, since the target audience for an artistic work is typically individualists and not social climbers. And a 1993 review of Art as Social Process concluded that empathy is a modern social convention that is no longer solely the preserve of artists and social climbers.Critic Geoffrey Rushton describes the phenomenon of aestheticising: aesthetically speaking, the capacity for aesthetic experience is what gives meaning to the word ‘beauty’. And the capacity for aesthetic experience is what makes us human. If the capacity for aesthetic experience is</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011
    <text>accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011–) is part of a new division at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, established in 2012, named for the museum’s first director, Jean Guy Lecat. It is a new museum with a different mission and an entirely different collection of works. It is a museum of performance, a museum of visual culture and a museum of art’s public. It is a museum of perception, a museum of history and a museum of visual culture?s collection. It is a museum of art and of the public and in that way, it is both the collection and the museum of the future? The collection is made up of objects from the museum of photography, including negatives and prints, some of which were made in the archive. The museum of modern art has an archive of its own, and the decision to preserve the collection as a museum of perception is a museum of modern art/collection. The museum of modern art is a museum of perception because it is a museum</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011–) is the largest remaining museum of modern art in the United Kingdom. It is the only surviving museum of the arts in the United Kingdom, and one of only eight remaining in the world. It was founded in 1887 by the then Head of the British Museum, William Osler. It was Osler’s idea that the Museum should be a non-commercial enterprise, and not beholden to the whims or political whims of government. Thus the Museum’s mission statement reads: ‘To keep alive and propagate classical arts’ Classical arts, he said, ‘are the sole property of their respective communities … [and] will remain so until a future government takes them back’.  [Emphasis added.]  [3] The Museum is currently undertaking a £500 million redevelopment of its historic building, the Gallery, on the former site of the Victoria and Albert Museum. The Gallery will reopen in 2018 as part of the Biennale, marking the Museum</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011–) is taking the British Museum of Art (1962) as a template for its own branch, as well as exploring the possibilities of a national museum of art. Both the B.M.A. and the B.M.A. were founded by women, and both trace their origins to the early twentieth century. However, the B.M.A. is the dominant form of British art museum at the moment, and the Museum of Modern Art in New York continues to be a significant cultural force in London. The Museum of Modern Art in New York is home to some of the most significant art from this period, but its greatest contemporary resource is the B.M.A.[6] The Museum of Modern Art has recently published an issue of its online journal Stages on the topic ‘Art After the Modern’, which brings out the many layers of the past, present and future of art. It is hoped that the journal, which documents the reflections of artists and</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011-). The museum is home to the largest collection of its kind, and since its foundation, has offered exhibitions, recorded interviews, recorded works, written texts, published works, and produced a range of activities and publications, including the publishing of the museum’s new journal, Stages (2014). It was founded in 1972 and is a global cultural and architectural resource for artists, curators, collectors, and visitors. Stages (2014). Cover Image: Mark McNulty. 	[1] Doubtless, this was a source of much consternation to the local inhabitants of the area at the time. 	[2] For further information see: http://www.stagesontheroad.com/index.php?fuseaction=art&amp;type=artstitution&amp;month=annual&amp;file=annual Stages (2014). Stages was created to commemorate the thirtieth anniversary of the launch of the Bienn</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011–) is a museum enterprise, founded in 1991. It is the largest museum of its kind in the world, and hosts the annual meeting of the Association of British Museum Administrators. It is also a producer and distributor of cultural products, with a permanent exhibition and multimedia installation program. The Museum is a regional hub for the global art world with a permanent exhibition and a multimedia installation program. It is the primary representative of the contemporary art world in the United Kingdom. The Museum is a regional hub for the global art world with a permanent exhibition and a multimedia installation program. It is the only museum of its kind in North America and Europe. It is home to the Charles I. and Victoria Embry Museum and the British Museum’s collections, as well as permanent exhibitions, such as the International Year of Art, the Museum of Contemporary Art, the Museum of Modern Art, and the Edward Said Gallery. It is a regional hub for the global art world with a permanent exhibition and a multimedia installation</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011–present): http://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-1204010.html The Bryant-Curtis Gallery, Manchester (1901–2006): http://www.bbc.com/news/magazine-1204010.html The Tate Modern, London (1901): http://www.tatemodern.org.uk/en/exhibitions/archive/index.html#sthash.JlQI6iQHo.dpuf.kFxhCRM.dpuf.kFxhCRM.dpuf.kFxhCRM.dpuf.kFxhCRM.dPxhCRM.FsoB4.2014. http://www.tatemodern.org.uk/en/exhibitions/archive/index.html#sthash.JlQI6iQHo.dpuf.kFx</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011–2016)Since its foundation in 1973, the British Museum has been a permanent exhibitionary building, showing contemporary art from all over the world. The museum was founded as an independent cultural centre for a post-totalitarian society, dedicated to the exploration of new frontiers, and since its foundation it has been a laboratory for the coming together of diverse cultural worlds in a common cultural space. The museum is both a teaching and a research centre, offering a multiplicity of activities to its diverse user groups, many of whom are students, artists, curators, students, staff and members of the public. The museum is a unique institutional site, able to sustain its activities through five levels: exhibitionary, cultural centre, educational institution, cultural organisation and public. The ninth level, the museum itself, offers a range of activities including a museum of contemporary art, a gallery of contemporary art, a design studio showcasing architectural works from around the world and an engagement in community projects. The museum is a significant</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011–) is a nonprofit cultural organisation based in London, England, established in 1867 and headquartered in the galleries of the Tate Modern. It is the oldest and largest museum of modern art in the UK. It is a world headquarters for the British Museum, and a regional hub for the Museum’s international activities. It promotes and presents the museum through exhibitions, publications, events and the local community of artists, designers and curators from around the world. The museum was formerly known as the Tate Modern and is now the Tate Gallery.The museum was founded in 1867 by Sir Peter Blake, the ex-manager of the London Zoo, and Sir Edward Poynter, the former art secretary of the London Zoo. Poynter retired in 1903 and was succeeded by a new team of art and zoological workers led by Sir Peter Blake. In 1901, the zoo was closed and Blake established the modern museum. In 1907, he established the museum and its current collection of art,</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011–) was founded in 1973 by Crown and Trustees. It is the largest museum of its kind in the world, and hosts the royal patron’s Rolls and other royal curates’ collections. It is also home to the largest private collection of royal items, with over 6,000 objects. Unlike the Museum, it does not make permanent works of art available for public consumption, preferring instead to retain objects in its collection for a specific, limited time. 	[1] The word ‘boring’ comes from the word ‘boringmachine’, a computer program used to categorise photographs of objects according to their relative aesthetic desirability. The idea of art as ‘a process of acquiring and holding things […] by … acquiring and holding them in […] possession’ is from Berial Jameson. 	[2] The phrase ‘you get what you pay for’ is from a speech by John Lennon, taken at</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the various branches of the British Museum. The 'British Museum of Photography' is a branch of the British Museum, London, founded in 1884, and runs alongside the museum, which opened in 1886. The British Museum of Photography (1887–1972) is the oldest and most prestigious branch of the British Museum. It was founded in 1887, two years before the first photography was invented. It is run by a board of trustees appointed by the Head of the British Museum, and consists of nine members appointed by the Museum. The Museum’s board of trustees includes eminent artists, such as Jean Guy Lecat, Alfred Eisenstaedt, Nora Crook, Richard Layzell, John Graham Kerr, and Chris Wainwright. In 1972, the Museum and its trustees were incorporated as a non-profit corporation, and its website is http://www.bbc.org/news/magazine-120514.html The British Museum of Art (2011–present)The British Museum of Art is a museum and the largest specialist archive of its kind in the world. It is the largest surviving museum of its kind, and one of only three remaining in existence. The other surviving museums are in Egypt, and the United Arab Emirates. The British Museum is the oldest continuously operating museum and one of the few remaining centres of its kind in the world. It is a world heritage site, recognised in both the United Kingdom and the United States. It is the only museum to have its collection housed in a single building, the Museum of Modern Art, New York City, built in response to the 1906 earthquake and fire, and one of only two museums to have its collection of 19th-century art housed in a single building, the Museum of Modern Art, St Petersburg, Russia.  [1] See: http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Category:Articles,2  [2] http://www.newadvice</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co-production with Adrian Beeca and Filippo Conti’inguica in 2015 of the hugely popular book Persistent Image on the city’s rivers Carrefour de Bellevue was a surprise, even to those who followed the project’s progress. The story goes that as part of the conference that Stoney pitched at, a museum turned down her proposal because of its size and the presence of representatives of the waterfront corporation. It was then that Persistent Image began discussions with the museum, which over time relented and began work-in-progress. The book, published in 2016, is a stand-alone work, and the museum edition was published in 2018, ten years after the river’s appearance in the story.In the intervening years, the river has been heavily modified in many places, and its name changed several times to avoid conflict with neighbouring waterways. In the 1970s and 80s, the river came to symbolise the</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co-production with the artist Todd Meyersman in the early 2000s on the now closed Greenwich Village Gallery triggered a major expansion of the gallery, which has now become one of the city’s most visited venues. The gallery has hosted numerous exhibitions, and Meyersman has a longstanding partnership with the museum that displays many of the works from that era. Stoney’s own 2007 solo exhibition, ‘Times Square’ was co-curated by Carl DeMaio, and her co-curator on the Metropolitan Museum of Art’s ten-year-long 2012 show, ‘Empire’, was DeMaio’s former partner.NEW YORK STREETS, MAP by Tom Lopéz de la Torre, 1989. Photo courtesy of the New York Public Library and Art Resource Center.The history of New York Streets is one of the most problematic parts of the city’s urban landscape. It is often cited as an</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co-opting of an antiquarian sensibility – one that has often been critical of her own practice – is a new kind of precarity. It is about as much as the art can bear, or returns. It is art that is art without value, and art with a political use of cultural commodities.It is art that engages with the political. It is art that seeks to make sense of the world around it. It is art that seeks to create understanding. It is art that seeks to put together disparate elements and bring them together to make something new. It is art that is politically astute and strategically strategic, and it is art that does not get trapped in the present.This kind of politics is what contemporary art is trying to bring together. It is trying to end the myth of static classical art – the notion that classical art is always this way – and to do so, it is relying on its own institutional memory, culture, and heritage. It is trying to end the notion</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co-opting of an already well-known institution as an artistic playground is a new and refreshing way of seeing things. It’s a way to see arts practice as art’s natural state, a way to see contemporary art as an evolving art practice that is always on the lookout for new ways to be put into practice. It’s a way to see the connection between Stoney’s practice as an artist and the institution that she calls ‘the City of New York’, and the wider urban future that she imagines for it.It’s also a way to see art practice not just as an asset in the service of a capitalist accumulation of capital, but that also serves as a site for the ongoing production of innumerable kinds of labour, including the production of wealth. For example, the production of stone for the Empire State Building is nothing like the production of bricks in any of the old ways, and the production of art is nothing like the</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co-operative movement, the artists’ studios she established in the 1970s and 80s, and the films she produced, including those in which the artist herself was a leading player, are among the most emblematic of the city’s recent artistic recoveries. She has a unique way of structuring creative practice in the city that is both explicitly political and poignantly simple.Today, there is much critical and scholarly writing about the city that is either too subtle or not poetic enough to register in a reader’s imagination. And while there is much to be said about the cultural deformities highlighted by the 1990s financial crisis and the subsequent imprisonment of millions of people, the sheer fact of the city’s economic malady – exacerbated by the crisis itself – continues to consume much of the city’s cultural imagination. This kind of political-figural conjuration is much vaster and more pervasive than many realise.Very few artists from the 1970s and 1980s</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co-inventor of the Alley Cat, Ada Louise Breckon, argues that the sudden ubiquity of art now is often seen as a threat, and that the key to staving off the new art is in fact visual culture.Visual culture is visual culture for humans. It is visual culture produced by humans in response to our visual culture and the forces it faces. It is visual culture that is constantly evolving and responds to changing conditions, and it is visual culture that creates the conditions for creativity to take place. The challenge today is to create ‘visual culture that is not constrained by the needs of a human gallery or museum, but that nevertheless pursues creative solutions that address the underlying forces shaping our city today’.  [2] New York Art Publishers, Inc. Bulletin, Issue 2, October 1988, p. 1.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is an artist, writer and policy maker. She is the Executive Director</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co-opting of the curatorial agenda is a very interesting point. She demonstrates how art today is often seen as a hindrance to growth, particularly in the inner city. She simultaneously criticises the obsession with visual accessibility in the city and the tendency to connect art with accessibility. She proposes an alternative agenda for art’s future: it has to be relevant to contemporary circumstances, and it has to be transformative.I find myself somewhat conflicted about this. On the one hand, I really want to like what I’m hearing from Elliman and the rest of the curatorial crew. I’m hearing a lot of things that align with my own thoughtful orientation to art as a public function. I’m also hearing a lot of things that seem extremely conservative. I’m open to argument, but I feel like there is an assumption about who I am coming from with this question. I still get frustrated by the fact that people think that the art world in New</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co-inventor, the avant-garde writer Jean Guy Lecat, didn’t see it that way. He saw art as a ‘glimmer of hope’ in the city, a source of energy that can ‘swallow anything’. He wrote:I saw a woodcut of you cutting wood for the archery range. I asked Lecat whether he thought the exhibition would be a good idea in the city. He said: ‘Of course. The stones will be taken. The trees will be taken.’ He went on: ‘And you’ll find someone to give you the archery lessons when the school opens next spring.’[2] And he concluded with this wager: ‘That seems a good bet to me. You’ll find someone to teach you the craft and then, when the school opens, you’ll find someone to take the trees—and the</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co-inventor, the late Edward Said, argued forcefully in favour of contemporary art being made in the city. He argued that a cultural infrastructure based on direct democracy could and should be based on ‘frivolous ideas and beliefs’ rather than fossilised monuments and museums. He was fighting for a public space in the city that could be repeatedly reshaped to suit the needs of commercial and cultural interests. To him, this meant ensuring that the cultural life of the city was generated and directed from above, not by local communities and grassroots arts initiatives, which were frequently instigated and supported by the city but were often marginalised or sidelined by the power structures on the ground. He was killed in a car accident in 2002.Many artists and artistic movements in the 1980s and 1990s were inspired by and were heavily influenced by the socio-political and economic dynamics of the decade. But many contemporary artists and artistic movements are now drawn from the political and urbanisation perspectives. This is a</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] See http://www.ancientpathways.com/ir/english/langugae_et_al_1999_august_2001.htm&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Aimee Stoney has often been asked what it means to be an artist in New York today. She has a complicated answer, to be frank. She thinks it means many things to many people. She thinks it’s about time.She thinks it’s about connecting to the city.Art has always been essential to Stoney’s practice. But contemporary art today is more ‘art for audiences outside of galleries and museums’ and social turnarounds, and more reliant on partnerships with commercial galleries and museums.Art has always been precariously visible in New York, and its appearance now is often seen by many in the city as an unwelcome intrusion. It is now often cited as a hindrance to the city’s potential growth. But Stoney’s co-opting of her exhibitionary potential to push certain political and economic agendas is a new and dangerous game.It can be argued that the art market in New York City has functioned more or less normally in recent years. In 2013, the Art Dealer Council declared that galleries were the new megastructures, and 2016, the New York Museum of Art announced it was rebuilding its large-scale, cyclical, and leaky conservatory. The latter was largely a reaction to a 2015 curatorial quixotic project that rebuilt a half-ruined section of the museum, using art as a blunt weapon against the heavily curated city. Nevertheless, the Art Dealers Council, the Museum of Modern Art, and the Manhattan Museum of Art collectively produce and support about 20 independently organised art societies, many in Brooklyn, Queens, and the Bronx. Most of these have annual budgets in the tens of millions, and reach into hundreds of millions of dollars. The Bronx Art Society alone</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chron
    <text>accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chronologically across multiple episodes of a single television programme’. 	In Terry Smith's account, the 1987 Venice Biennale is a ‘ficto-ritualised event’, in that it was originally conceived as a ‘series of photographs’ that reflected the city’s architecture, but with the addition of a series of sculptures by Italian and Spanish artists, each dedicated to a different chapter of the exhibition. The biennale,’s nominal subject, is rendered into existence through the power of the image. 	Figure 1:  Artists rendering the experiences of the Venetian Biennale participants as produced in cooperation with the London and Rome Museums Authority. Photograph courtesy of Terry Smith. 	 	Figure 2: Artists rendering the experiences of the Venetian Biennale participants as produced in cooperation with the London and Rome Museums Authority. Photograph courtesy of Terry Smith. 	 </text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chronologically across different biennials’ in the city. As a result of the board’s activities, the biennial became an icon of the city and a point of entry for artists and collectors seeking out traces of the city’s cultural past. 	The biennial has proved an object of aesthetic and cultural recycling. The aestheticisation of the biennial as a collection of images of art being done in the city exemplifies the searching for meaning in images of art being displayed in a city. This is exemplified in the catalogue image of the 1987 Venice Biennale, which anticipates the visual arts museum today, but with images of past events. Assembled by a curator from Columbia University, the curator selected thirty images from various biennials, stacked them on a wall and projected them onto a screen in the main hall of the Giennale. The images were arranged chronologically across the years, taken from the biennial archives, archives of various artworlds</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chronologically across the period from 1904 to 1988’.[4] Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), p.8. 	One of the objects in Terry Smith’s triptych The Biennial Condition was a photograph of the entrance to the zoo, showing the number of visitors and animals at the time. The zoo had just been renamed ‘Zoo Florida’, and the city seemed an unlikely candidate for a new name. Smith, however, used the name ‘Zoo Florida’ in a pejorative sense: the name was an insult to the native Florida panther, which was named by accident in a similar fashion. The similarity between the two names was too obvious to ignore, and the transposition of the insult meant that the urban wild animal became a symbol of the folly of capitalism and urban planning. In a city despoiled of its wildlife, a panther is a symbol of luxury and excess. Smith, however, projects</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chronologically and geographically across the period from the 1980s to the present’. By the 1990s, the biennial was experiencing its own form of metainterface, as cultural theorists began to theorize the evolution of the biennial as a ‘global’ phenomenon. The megastructure was being produced by cultural theorists not trained in museumary studies, and their ideas were percolating in the corridors of power in London and New York that were simultaneously consuming and consuming slowly (like the inhabitants of a 1950s science-fiction novel). In these words, Nancy Curtis, in her influential book Culture and Capital (1977), speaks of ‘a certain metainterface’.  So, ‘the metainterface’ that Nancy talks about is the product of a certain kind of metainterface; the kind that emerged in the 1980s and 1990s in reaction to the discourses of postmodernism and the rise of postindustrial societies. Its</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chronologically in a densely populated urban environment.’ Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), pp. 16–17. 	The museum, as the locus of the art collector’s gaze, became an ideal place to begin a project that would later evolve into a museum, a city, and a museum. It is here that the museum becomes a tool that helps us ‘move through time and space’, as the anthropologist Wendy Chun puts it, ‘a site where visual interaction can occur between material and immaterial things in a non-representational way, where multiplicity and difference, and in particular, a place where art can be made and art judged’.[2] 	As an object of aestheticisation and political inclusion, the biennial offers the possibilité of viewing points outside the museum. Its physical appearance and function are further legitimised by its inclusion in a museum collection, which is itself effectively ‘</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chronologically across the period from the 1980s to 1990’. By the 1990s, the biennial was experiencing a phase of change, one that involved art collectors, curators, artists and other interested parties regularly visiting the exhibitionary venue and its collections. Art critics were writing about the ‘biennial condition’ and its effects on art’s social and political organisation. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), reviews the art from the collection of the Metropolitan Museum of Art, where the Metropolitan Museum of Art is housed. He finds it difficult to imagine the 1990s a different, but interesting, one. He describes the exhibitionary form as one in which ‘a cultural tourism agency could ever hope to regain its former power, prestige and financial weight, and which is no longer the center of a cultural vortex’. Art is often cited as a symptom of the ‘biennial condition’. However, Smith also criticises the lack of an ‘</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chronologically and geographically across the biennale’. Some biennials have their own distinct set of images. For example, the Venice Biennale (1972–77) used its first world exhibition as a pretext to return to the biennial form, staging images from the event across several continents. In Asia, the Venice Biennale (1978–79) used its petit fourès form to project images of the city onto the global landscape. In Europe, the Venice Biennale (1980–81) used its established cache of art from the previous year to project the city onto a new global landscape. In the United States, the Venice Biennale (1982–83) used the same pop-culture tropes as the pop culture of the time – celebrity, money, sex, drugs – to project a similar sensual fantasy. In the United Kingdom, the London Arts Biennale (1988–92) – which is characterised by its episodic random-access</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chronologically across the first half of the twentieth century’. The significance of the twentieth century as a twenty-first century is made explicit in the figure of the biennial. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), pp. 9–12. 	In the 1990s the biennial doubled its size and attracted a new generation of artists interested in the social impact of art in the social totality. Most of the major museums that year were either closing or being forced to close. The biennale became the object of a curatorial drive, part of the larger global trend of museum building and a vibrant exhibitionary form that was itself often deformed by the pressures of neoliberal globalisation. The biennial became an object of cultural exchange as well as commerce, and the commerce that it generated generated became a significant part of the global capitalist economy. Art, art collectives, art fairs – the globalised museum was born. Art fairs became objects of circulation in their own right,</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chronologically across a given year’. The exhibition format followed a curatorial theme, with each of the thirty-six images dedicated to a specific event in the biennial’s history. In the case of the Venice International Exhibition, the art collectors who came to the city to check out the artworks on display there also came to check out the art museums and the collections of the Zoological Society of Dublin. The collection of the Dublin Museum was a response to the collection of the Zoological Society of Philadelphia, which, in turn, was a response to the collection of the Zoological Society of London. The collection of the Dublin Museum held the collections of both the Zoological Society of Dublin and the Zoological Society of Philadelphia. The collection of the Dublin Museum therefore acted as a counterweight to the collection of the Zoological Society of London, which was a counterweight to the collection of the Dublin Museum. The collection of the Museum of Transport and Travel, which I curated in collaboration</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of leading biennials, Phantom Tourist Board (1986–87) and the London Zoo (1887–1888). The biennial was designed to be a point of exit from the city, allowing visitors to the city to ‘re-experience’ the experience of ‘living there’. The board was set up to encourage artistic endeavors in the city, and the zoo as a point of departure for artists to explore the city and ‘reevaluate’ their ‘experiences’ there. The museum, the primary venue for the board’s activities, became a point of entry into the city. The museum, along with the city’s many district museums, which in turn hold important collections of art, became the objects of the art collectors’ gaze. Terry Smith, The Biennial Condition (1987), describes the discursive circumstances of the biennial as ‘a set of congealed local images arranged chronologically and geographically to capture the oral encounter between visitors to the museum and artists’ works displayed in the museum’s galleries and public galleries across the city’s post-war years.’ Although the biennial is the object of scholarly and archival research, the importance of the sites and collections it preserves lies in its ability to conjure a nostalgic memory of the past through what Terry Smith calls ‘the memory of the past’. This memory is able to encompass the present through what he describes as ‘the pastiche’ – a form of writing that records the similarities and differences of the past, both present and past, through which the senses can detect similarities and differences.[7] The image above is a fragment from a 1942 diary of Bernard Benton, an English zoologist who specialized in invertebrates. His account, published in 1943, is one of several that frame the zoological and biological history of the twentieth century. In a note that remains</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;
    <text>curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25&amp;aid=26&amp;aid=27&amp;aid=28&amp;aid=29&amp;aid=30&amp;aid=31&amp;aid=32&amp;aid=33]Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa works as an independent writer, researcher and consultant. She is Curator for the MIT Pavilion and has a research grant from the Carnegie Corporation of New York. Prior to that she was curator of the Athenaeum of Athens, Greece, where she received funding from the Greek government to start a gallery in 2005 and a research grant from the Austrian government to start a research project in 2014. Her writing has been published in numerous periodicals such as Science &amp; Cultural Monitor, Thr#1 (2009), Science &amp; Culture Today, #13 (2015), Basingstoke Arts &amp; Letters, #27 (2016), and she has been a co-curator of the British &amp; Irish Pavilion, Christie’s, London, UK, and The Open University</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25&amp;aid=26&amp;aid=27&amp;aid=28&amp;aid=29&amp;aid=30&amp;aid=31&amp;aid=32&amp;aid=33&amp;aid=34&amp;aid=35&amp;aid=36&amp;aid=37&amp;aid=38&amp;aid=39&amp;aid=40&amp;aid=41&amp;aid=42&amp;aid=43&amp;aid=44&amp;aid=45&amp;aid=46&amp;aid=47&amp;aid=48&amp;aid=49&amp;aid=50&amp;aid=51&amp;aid=52&amp;aid=53&amp;aid=54&amp;aid=55&amp;aid=56&amp;aid=57&amp;aid=58&amp;aid=59&amp;aid=60&amp;aid=61&amp;aid=62&amp;aid=63&amp;aid=64&amp;aid=65&amp;aid=66&amp;aid=67&amp;aid=68&amp;aid=69&amp;aid=70&amp;aid=71&amp;aid=72&amp;aid=73&amp;aid=74&amp;</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25&amp;aid=26&amp;aid=27&amp;aid=28&amp;aid=29&amp;aid=30&amp;aid=31&amp;aid=32&amp;aid=33&amp;aid=34&amp;aid=35&amp;aid=36&amp;aid=37&amp;aid=38&amp;aid=39&amp;aid=40&amp;aid=41&amp;aid=42&amp;aid=43&amp;aid=44&amp;aid=45&amp;aid=46&amp;aid=47&amp;aid=48&amp;aid=49&amp;aid=50&amp;aid=51&amp;aid=52&amp;aid=53&amp;aid=54&amp;aid=55&amp;aid=56&amp;aid=57&amp;aid=58&amp;aid=59&amp;aid=60&amp;aid=61&amp;aid=62&amp;aid=63&amp;aid=64&amp;aid=65&amp;aid=66&amp;aid=67&amp;aid=68]Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is Professor in Digital Culture and An</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25&amp;aid=26&amp;aid=27&amp;aid=28&amp;aid=29 	[5] → http://science.yahoo.com/s/sciences/nature/nature-intelligent-systems-design-design-design-design-design-design.html#ixzz2Ac4YbSsEgEtN0KlM7NjAwMDEzNzEwMjE0MzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwMzEwNzAwNTcxNzAwNzAwNzAwNzAwNzAwMzAwNzAwMzAwNzAwNzAwNzAwNzAwN</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25&amp;aid=26&amp;aid=27&amp;aid=28&amp;aid=29&amp;aid=30&amp;aid=31&amp;aid=32&amp;aid=33&amp;aid=34&amp;aid=35&amp;aid=36&amp;aid=37&amp;aid=38&amp;aid=39&amp;aid=40&amp;aid=41&amp;aid=42&amp;aid=43&amp;aid=44&amp;aid=45&amp;aid=46&amp;aid=47&amp;aid=48&amp;aid=49&amp;aid=50&amp;aid=51&amp;aid=52&amp;aid=53&amp;aid=54&amp;aid=55&amp;aid=56&amp;aid=57&amp;aid=58&amp;aid=59&amp;aid=60&amp;aid=61&amp;aid=62&amp;aid=63&amp;aid=64&amp;aid=65&amp;aid=66&amp;aid=67&amp;aid=68&amp;aid=69&amp;aid=70&amp;aid=71&amp;aid=72&amp;aid=73&amp;aid=74&amp;</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25&amp;aid=26&amp;aid=27&amp;aid=28&amp;aid=29&amp;aid=30&amp;aid=31&amp;aid=32&amp;aid=33&amp;aid=34&amp;aid=35&amp;aid=36&amp;aid=37&amp;aid=38&amp;aid=39&amp;aid=40&amp;aid=41&amp;aid=42&amp;aid=43&amp;aid=44&amp;aid=45&amp;aid=46&amp;aid=47&amp;aid=48&amp;aid=49&amp;aid=50&amp;aid=51&amp;aid=52&amp;aid=53&amp;aid=54&amp;aid=55&amp;aid=56&amp;aid=57&amp;aid=58&amp;aid=59&amp;aid=60&amp;aid=61&amp;aid=62&amp;aid=63&amp;aid=64&amp;aid=65&amp;aid=66&amp;aid=67&amp;aid=68&amp;aid=69&amp;aid=70&amp;aid=71&amp;aid=72&amp;aid=73&amp;aid=74&amp;</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25(accessed September 2018). 	[5] Theoretical physicist Steven Weinberg proposes a new understanding of black holes through the concept of gravitational lensing, which he explains in terms of two-dimensional and three-dimensional co-locating of masses. He proposes that the gravitational lensesing of matter occurs when masses are brought together in an environment that is highly susceptible to the influence of one another. By understanding how matter is brought together in such a way as to cause weakness in the linkages that separate, one from the other, we can learn something about the mechanisms by which matter is put together. 	[6] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S01405271200474400#.VD_LH_UNOI1V1.1MkxoXJlMjE&amp;list=PLVkTlmNzMDE2MjE</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25&amp;aid=26&amp;aid=27&amp;aid=28&amp;aid=29&amp;aid=30&amp;aid=31&amp;aid=32&amp;aid=33&amp;aid=34&amp;aid=35&amp;aid=36&amp;aid=37&amp;aid=38&amp;aid=39&amp;aid=40&amp;aid=41&amp;aid=42&amp;aid=43&amp;aid=44&amp;aid=45&amp;aid=46&amp;aid=47&amp;aid=48&amp;aid=49&amp;aid=50&amp;aid=51&amp;aid=52&amp;aid=53&amp;aid=54&amp;aid=55&amp;aid=56&amp;aid=57&amp;aid=58&amp;aid=59&amp;aid=60&amp;aid=61&amp;aid=62&amp;aid=63&amp;aid=64&amp;aid=65&amp;aid=66&amp;aid=67&amp;aid=68&amp;aid=69&amp;aid=70&amp;aid=71&amp;aid=72&amp;aid=73&amp;aid=74&amp;</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25&amp;aid=26&amp;aid=27&amp;aid=28&amp;aid=29&amp;aid=30&amp;aid=31&amp;aid=32&amp;aid=33&amp;aid=34&amp;aid=35&amp;aid=36&amp;aid=37&amp;aid=38&amp;aid=39&amp;aid=40]Download this article as PDFHolly R. Brin, Ph.D., Assistant Professor in English and Film Studies, McGill University, and Ex-Director, Experimental Theatre, McGill University, where she directed Experimental Shakespearean Theatre, where she co-curated the Fifth Edinburgh Fringe, and was part of the artistic team for the Cirque du Soleil Edinburgh Fringe 2017. She has a special interest in the history of literary theory and can teach a class in English/Literature &amp; Critical Theory.Interview with Jeanette WintersonJE: You have a particular way of engaging with the past that is very interesting and probing. What is it about the past that interests</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  Fifth Expedition to Alpha Centauri, 2017. Image courtesy of NASA/JPL-Caltech/MSSS. Copyright NASA &amp; ESA. 	[3] See: http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S014052214120401344/full-text.html 	[4] See: http://science.energy.harvard.edu/sgp/index.html?search=full&amp;aid=0§ion=energy&amp;aid=1&amp;aid=2&amp;aid=3&amp;aid=4&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25%3A0%3B/sgp/index.html&amp;aid=4§ion=energy&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;aid=22&amp;aid=23&amp;aid=24&amp;aid=25%3A0%3B/sgp/index.html&amp;aid=4§ion=energy&amp;aid=5&amp;aid=6&amp;aid=7&amp;aid=8&amp;aid=9&amp;aid=10&amp;aid=11&amp;aid=12&amp;aid=13&amp;aid=14&amp;aid=15&amp;aid=16&amp;aid=17&amp;aid=18&amp;aid=19&amp;aid=20&amp;aid=21&amp;</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth.
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth.If we adopt the language of geology, and assume that all of the observed spatial variation is governed by the same geologic principle that also governs global temperature and salinity, then we can begin to understand how we can intervene in the spatial dynamics of climate change and environmental degradation, while maintaining ecological systems of our own design. The ability to observe and analyse such phenomena opens up all kinds of possibilities. For example, the observation that certain areas of the United States and Canada are experiencing particularly severe droughts could be used to suggest agricultural and urban planting strategies. Likewise, the discovery that certain African and Middle Eastern countries are experiencing particularly severe desertification could be used to suggest coastal erosion and flooding prevention strategies. And, of course, there is the hope that such observations and analyses will eventually lead to action.Unfortunately, in the current political and economic context, such a language would be seen as both naïve and un-Responsible. The ascendance of neoliberalism and the financial crises of the past</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth.As a final example of the pervasiveness of ecological systems observation, we can move from the case of the endangered goose (Quinquefasciurus fulvus) to the much more familiar and recognisable human goose (Euphorbia hirsuta), or goose-bump (Euphorbia americana) and its close relative, the mallard (M. reinhardtii). The genus name comes from the Greek Μελλίδιος, meaning &quot;large bird&quot;, and πολλάδιος, meaning &quot;mallsard&quot;. In ancient times, these birds were thought to feed on large animals and plants, especially those with high amounts of water and twigs – something that is still believed to be the case. The human divergence from the common ancestor of birds and animals is thought to have happened about 10,000 years ago, with the last extinctions happening about 11,500 years ago.</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth. The failure to develop such a capacity is one of the great challenges of our time, and a major contributor to the proliferation of ecological crises. Theory and research on the role of optics in the cognitive sciences has played a crucial role in our ability to perceive the changing face of environmental degradation, to detect its catastrophic effects and to act to mitigate those effects. Despite the obvious benefits and even the theoretical potentialities involved in such a project, there is simply no way to carry it out on a large scale or in a sustained way. And this is one of the great disappointments of our time: despite the obvious benefits and even the theoretical potentialities involved in such a project, there is simply no way to carry it out on a large scale or in a sustained way.  And here we see another example of spatialism at work: despite the obvious physical and conceptual links between the physical and the virtual (and perhaps even biological) environment, the world is constantly reinterpreted through spatialisation and mapping.</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth. We simply do not have the capacity or the willingness yet of any of the major planetary systems involved in the analysis of these phenomena to do so.Infrastructural progress is a globalisation-type process that has been going on now for over 200 years, and it is important to note that the emergence of new technological infrastructures is not unique to the past century. It is a global process that is now unfolding on a global scale, and it is this specificity that underlies the urgency that lies at stake. The emergence of new infrastructural technologies is a direct consequence of the need to account for the ever-growing number of people living on the planet. And this accounts for the creation and proliferation of new geo-political entities, such as the non-state space geo-regional and the for-profit sector geo-national cities. These latter are primarily designed to cater to the interests of a localised elite – the localised elite being the inhabitants of the surrounding metropolitan</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth.The other crucial spatial component to consider when considering the effects of industrialization, technology and urbanization is the extent to which the spatial variation and dynamic interaction of these phenomena is accentuated or mitigated in the big-city. This is crucial in understanding how our urban infrastructures are contributing to the problematics of environmental degradation, but also in understanding the spatial distribution of such pathology. For example, the distribution of climate-induced global mean sea-level rise is strongly influenced by the location of the poles, and the urban infrastructures that are the direct result of these conditions. As a result, the distribution of sea-level rise is disproportionately influenced by the trade routes taking advantage of the location of the trade routes. The current extratropical trade in coastal commodities, primarily fishing gear, is the result of this spatial malleability. As a result of this malleability, the spatial variation and dynamic interaction of all commodities is accentuated, which in turn contributes to the</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth. The biennial has played a pivotal role in enabling the ability to observe these phenomena in action, and enabling us to intervene in them to a greater or lesser extent. The biennial format has also provided a platform for the development of political and social change, both in the form of direct action and ultimately, indirectly, through the formation of collective understandings. The early manifestations of ecological crises are often framed as stories of mass protest and sabotage, but the ecological crises of our era are framed as crises of power and money. The biennial format has therefore often been seen as the ideal venue for the implementation of social or political change, and has even been referenced as a noun (Ecologies). However, the biennial format has a spatial dimension as well. The social and political contexts in which it is framed influence how we perceive its spatiality. On an emotional level, the biennial can be seen as a venue through which cultural events are experienced in the city, and in turn, in the context</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth. These observations and analyses are happening now thanks to the Internet and new technologies of data capture and transmission, but their geographical distribution and temporal dynamics are still quite poor. A growing body of research is showing that the activities that we term ‘space-based’ are becoming more and more intertwined with technologies that record and consume data. The ability to observe and analyse such phenomena is just one aspect of a growing body of research agenda that includes space-based resource-use and the ecological and social consequences of resource-constrained development. More important is the growing body of knowledge about spatial dynamics and the spatial relations between people, places and data capture. For example, mapping, surveying, analysing ‘geographical data’ and processing that leads to ‘stationary elements’ and places, which in turn, can lead to new kinds of research and discourse. New Forms of Space Research and InquiryIn the 20th century, the anthropologist Henri Lefebvre developed several influential</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth. If these mechanisms are not observed and addressed, or do not exist in the ways that we imagine they do, we do not have sufficient spatial and global reach to tackle the problem effectively. 	Looking to the Future 	Looking ahead, it is obvious that we do not have the desired spatial and global reach to address the challenges and pollutants that we do not yet know we have. Consequently, we are being forced to make do with less sustainable or less beautiful forms of urbanisation in an attempt to stem the tide of destruction. The question becomes, do we want to continue to live in cathedrals of destruction, or do we want to build new urban structures that are more ecologically sustainable? If the latter is the case, then it will become increasingly difficult to redefine what is meant by ‘ecologically sustainable’ in relation to the former. It is evident that the decisions that need to be made regarding one's personal and political future are being made in a city that is increasingly</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth.Clearly, there are other factors that are more readily accessible and which can be applied to the analysis of environmental degradation, but the development of ecological systems is a critically important first step in any environmental strategy. There is a strong deindustrialising trend underway in many parts of the world, which is likely to continue unabated for many years to come; and it is important to mention here that the top 1 per cent of industrial society still controls most of the planet’s remaining land and mineral wealth. There is a clear link between the amount of land that is owned by the global South and the amount of pollution that is emitted by the global North. This is particularly true in China, where the share of land devoted to agriculture has increased by 60 per cent during the past 25 years. In addition, the industrial capacity to extract raw materials from the ground has significantly expanded in the past two decades, and is still expanding. Finally, the industrial capacity to process these materials into products that are sold globally is</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from observations, and the constant need to update them as new scientific findings and developments take place. Most importantly, this means that observations, even those with seemingly obvious spatial relationships, will always have some relationship to events or processes that have a spatial or temporal context. For example, if the Earth is orbited by a sun that is extremely hot and dense, but also extremely cold and sparsely populated, then the climate of the planet will necessarily have a spatial element to it. The climate of the Pacific Ocean will necessarily be affected by global ocean currents and geopolitics. The climate of the atmosphere will necessarily have a great deal of influence on temperatures and salinity. And of course, the climate of Mars will have a similar effect, although the climate of Mars is very different from that of Earth. What is clear is that the ability to observe, to record and analyse these kinds of phenomena is essential to any serious attempt to understand the spatial variation and global dynamics of environmental degradation that is unfolding on Earth.For more than just planetary change-accounting, it is important to understand that the spatialisation of ecological degradation is not a by-product of capitalism. The growth of industrial-scale agriculture in developed nations is a product of political, social and economic development, and is primarily driven by the desire of large corporations to expand their markets. However, the advent of information technologies such as the automobile and the post-war electricity grid made possible a form of capitalism that was originally instigated and directed in the context of imperialism and colonialism. The post-war economic expansion coincided with a spatial expansion of the military-industrial complex, which offered enormous new sources of cheap energy. The advent of nuclear weapons and the subsequent reduction in size and mass of the nuclear warhead meant that the economics of energy became much more variable – with unpredictable effects on production and consumption – than previously imagined. The proliferation of non-military goods and technologies was another factor, along with the technological revolution that transformed the service-industry into</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
