<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is
    <text>human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is what I mean by the &quot;sharing of experiences and capabilities&quot;. The crucial point is that these new technologies make it possible to do things differently, and to observe new ways of interacting with the world. This is what I mean when I say that the new technologies allow us to do extraordinary things – to witness human behaviour and the world through different perspectives. I believe that this is what the sharing of experiences and capabilities means: sharing one's fundamental frame of reference, but using different technologies and observing new ways of interacting with the world.This is what I mean when I speak of ‘sharing one’: sharing one’s fundamental frame of reference, but using different technologies and observing new ways of interacting with it. I believe that sharing is going to happen through the mechanisms of these various technologies, and this is why I believe that sharing is a collective act of will; it is not something that can be imposed or managed. For example, if you have the ability to share a video,</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is an area of the city where a lot of people don’t have access to transport, and a lot of people don’t have access to housing, either due to displacement or poverty. So these new ways of interacting with the city are going to require a lot of interaction with the city, and a lot of collaboration between the city and grassroots level groups. These are exciting times to be able to say that you are part of the city, and to be able to contribute to the development of the city, because the only way that these technologies are going to be safe is if people are able to live in them and use them responsibly. This is an area where a lot of power is going to be transferred from the city into the hands of communities. People are going to have to learn how to use this new technology responsibly. There are going to be huge challenges, but there are going to be rewards too. Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	A</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is what I would like to see happen in London, and I think that is what is happening with the introduction of new technologies. It is not just about creating a new set of app-based services, but is also about how we create new kinds of interactions between people and those technologies. For example, the way in which social media is impacting on the way in which art is being produced in the area, and how the art and activism produced through the new platforms is being actively supported through the arts funding bodies. But it is not just about the technology – there is a need for cultural organisers and artists to be involved in enabling these new modes of engagement. There is a cultural dimension to the design that needs to be considered alongside the socio-politically-engaged design that is happening in the area. This is what Cédard Pascale and I did for the new cathedral that was being considered for the Centenary Square, by inviting artists from the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flat</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is what I mean when I say that the biennial can be a ‘transverse space’. It connects to what I mean by what art critic Peter Schjeldahl refers to as ‘the big picture’, which is the city as a whole. We live in an era where art is being made where there is none before, and in many ways that is a good thing. But there is a conflict between the architecture of the city and the architecture of the biennial, and the biennial has to find a way to reconcile these two. Schjeldahl’s definition of the ‘transverse space’ he refers to is very prescient, and it applies not only to the biennial, but also to the city. The biennial is a ‘permanent, fixed assemblage of artists’ studios, pavilions, exhibitionary structures and cultural resources in the city, and its surrounding countryside and national parks and monuments. It</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is something that is happening all over the world, and it’s great that we live in a world where people can access information and ideas all around the globe, but what is also happening is that information is being gathered in this one location. I believe that is happening right now in South Korea, and I hope it continues to happen in the future areas where there is a question of displacement and poverty. When you have a question of displacement and poverty, you need to have a much bigger picture. When we talk about the question of where the next Star Wars should be filmed, we need to also consider where the next Hunger Games might be filmed. The reason why I love the fact that we live in the present is because if we don’t invest in preserving the past, then what we create in the present will decay and we are creating an ever larger and more diffuse past that isn’t even close to being the present – it is so exciting to me when artists are creating spaces</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is where the biennale as a concept comes into play. The biennale is an event where people come from all over the world to experience the same thing – enjoy the same art, share the same culture, and engage with the same exhibition. It is an interesting hybridity: it can be about the same thing, created by the same people many different places, and in that mode it is very different from a typical event. The biennale as an art event has always been about a community of artists coming together to create something that is relevant to the region in which they live and work. For the local artists who have participated in this event, the experience has been very much about community – about coming together as a community of artists, and bringing out the best in each other. For the visitors, the experience has been much more about the juxtaposition of different cultures coming together to explore different aspects of the same place. And of course, the reason why people come to the bienn</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is one area where technology displaces people, displacing labour, displacing communities. The promise of this new technology is that it can liberate us from the burdens of bureaucracy, and that’s where our technological determinism and homogenised form of society is heading. But one of the things that is happening is that the projects that we envision and develop do not necessarily correspond with what is happening in the real world. For example, when the Flatbush Arts Community started their arts education programme, the Flatbush Playhouse Community did not have access to the same resources that the Skyscraper Theatre Community had. One of the beauties of this new democratised form of art and culture is that it opens doors that were not always there, and helps to create new possibilities for people to be involved.  My own work often operates along these lines, suggesting solutions to problems that are already present but which often have hidden oppressions or are oppressive in their own way.  One of the beauties of</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is what I believe in and I believe in what is happening in the area, and I believe that our relationship is important in enabling that to happen. I have always felt very strongly that if we don’t believe what we are doing is right, we should question whether or not it is right. And if we do that without conviction, then we create uncertainty and uncertainty-building for things to happen to us by introducing variable terms that are never transparent and never fully clear, and for things to happen to us by never fully explaining the details. I believe that the relationship between the artist and the viewer is a fundamental building block of understanding and engagement, and the relationship between the public and the artist is that most basic of building blocks. It is the fundament of what makes art possible-simple pleasures, deep work, and lasting engagement. I am really proud of the work that we have been doing together, and I am really proud of the fact that people also engage with what we do together. There</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is an area that I feel very strongly about: we need to be exploring how our devices and behaviour intersect with the environment in radically new ways. I see it in the interaction between our phones and the environment, in the interaction between media and the built environment. The interaction between people and platforms is one of the ways in which we create new behaviours and ideas – actively creating our own media environments and behaviour through our actions. This is not some abstract thing that we do through design; it is an act of imagination and it is how in-depth ecocidal acts are possible.Imagine if the phone that came with your phone could actually sense where it is at all times, and would only activate if a sensor was attached to it? Think of the possibilities. This is the kind of thinking and act of imagination that is possible with our phones, and I believe that it is one that is ecocidal. I also believe that it is possible to create in-built sensors that monitor your behaviour via sensors</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. This is an area with which I believe strongly, and which is why I have been working with Sandi Metcalfe for over a year now on the Skyscraper Theatre project, and why I am so excited by the fact that Sandi and her team are now going to be bringing together two local communities – the Flatbush Arts Community and the Flatbush Playhouse Community – to explore how technology is impacting their community. It’s really interesting to me that in the area of transport, the Flatbush Arts Community uses a kiosk that was originally a car dealership, and in the area of housing the Flatbush Playhouse Community uses a similar kiosk that was originally a clothing store – there is a direct relationship between the two. But what is really exciting is that these technologies are actually not built on the same bedrock and can be interfaced with, allowing for a dissimilar experience for people using them. The important thing is that they are made accessible to people.This is an area where a lot of my thinking has been centred around the human side of things. When you’re creating something new, you’re always thinking about the people you’re using it with, and how they are. You don’t necessarily want to work with people because they are people or because they are connected to your core values, but you do want to work with people because they are people who can contribute something to your thinking and your project. I think this is one area where a lot of the new technologies are able to do this, whereas previous technological paradigms were very much individualised and could not necessarily connect to any wider society. I think that there is an area in between, and that is when you combine the user with the whole system, which is what we call the User. When you introduce new technologies into the mix, you also need to be able to roll them out and make them work in real life, because otherwise you risk</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-standing (although rarely discussed) exchanges between biennials and the arts committees that monitor and appraise the arts in public places have, as is now the case, generated a kind of understanding between the arts and the biennial committees that monitor and appraise it. At such times, the curators and arts administrators involved in the Biennale are acutely aware of the limits of what can be said and done in the public square, and so they often engage with the biennial in an attempt to modify or abolish its mandate. In recent years, this has been done almost entirely in the art department, most noticeably with the regrettable decision to remove work by Chantal Mouffe from the Monuments Men programme, despite her significant critical reputation and extensive body of artistic practice. However, she was not the only artist to be excluded from the programme; many artists were highly critical of the treatment meted out to them by the curators. Nevertheless, Mouffe’s exclusion from the programme</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-standing antagonisms between the humanities and the social sciences are often cited as evidence of the cultural perforations of the twentieth century. There is certainly some truth to this. But we also need to ask ourselves and others questions such as: what kind of epistemological distance is there between the social sciences and humanities? What kind of difference does a social science make in its relation to the humanities? What kinds of difference does a humanities make in its relation to the social sciences? How does a social science make its subjects feel like people with agency? How does a mapping and scraping of data generate knowledge? What kinds of complications are there for the social sciences when it comes to engaging with the hidden layers and submerged cultures of humanity that are submerged in the mass of humanity?What is meant by ‘the social sciences’? Are we more sensitive to claims from the social sciences that are grounded in a particular set of values and institutions? For example, claims about the social value of language and the social</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-standing, but recently encounter, debates around the exchange and exchange of knowledge between artists and the public are, I believe, a result of an exhibitionary form that seeks to reconcile different kinds of knowledge. A museum or gallery might demonstrate a collection of objects, while an exhibitionary form such as a biennial seeks to reconcile different kinds of knowledge. I think that this is a misunderstanding of the two forms. I would argue that the exchange and exchange of knowledge that we engage in through the different modes of the biennial is actually a form of cultural piracy, in which the public is effectively made aware of the curatorial politics of the art institution, but also of the socio-politic political situation of the art world. It is a way of tricking the curatorial (art world) into believing that it has something to gain by representing the world through the art of a particular generation of artists, while simultaneously undermining the very foundations of the art world itself.I would argue that this kind of cultural</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-running debates and pedagogical debates around the benefits and deficits of open access to academic and art-historical resources (both in terms of providing a resource for critical thinking and the capacity for art to work in that context) lend themselves to a kind of historical, pedagogical and artistic meta-discussion. For instance, the debates and debates around the capacity of artists to engage audiences or engage the public in productive or interesting ways) lend themselves to the capacity for artistic action in that historical, pedagogical and artistic sense. It is a historical, pedagogical and artistic meta-discussion about how the capacities of artists to engage audiences or engage the public are greater or inferior to those of other professions or professions. The answer, generally speaking, is that the capacities of artists are not inferior to those of other professions. But there are fundamental differences between the capacities of artists and those of other professions. The capacities of artists, in turn, are different. Artists have certain cognitive, manual</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-standing, but increasingly marginal, fields of human endeavour are characterised by the art of not being able to communicate with, or being offended by, knowledge. Modern and contemporary art, as a rule, is – in the broadest and most general sense – interested in communicating with and offending as many people as possible. However, the social, cultural, economic and political context in which art is embedded, and in which it operates, dictates what kinds of knowledge are allowed to enter and leave that artifice. A good example of this is found in the field of architecture. Today, there are three main streams of information on urban development and design: empirical research, urban studies and urban analysis. All three of these have methodological failings (some might say, urban pathology) – but they all work within the prevailing political, economic and social climate. And of course, there is always the occasional urban development document or urban plan that proposes an entirely new way of organising things. But at the end of the day</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-standing debates about the role and rights of the artist and the biennial have led to a kind of generalised understanding and acceptance of what an artist or a biennial can and cannot do. This is useful for organisations such as the Liverpool Biennial, who need to be able to count on people understanding what they are doing, because they will recognise the work regardless. But it is of course completely at odds with the way in which organisations like the Liverpool Biennial operate, and with the way that artists are often made to operate. Artists are often made to operate in environments and in cultures that are antagonistic to the values and interests of the organisations that commissioned them to do so. And it is this tension between artist-centred and organisation-centred development that contributes to the problems of contemporary art today.The open access to knowledge makes it easier to understand when an artist has engaged with a particular set of issues and for the artist to make more responsive to changing circumstances and needs. And the bi</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-standing debates and conflicts about the role of art and the cultural sector in a democratic society arise as a consequence of our wanting to do things differently now and in the future. The question of who is an artist and what kind of mission is he or she trying to serve in the future inevitably comes up. In an effort to make the world a better place, perhaps it is useful to think of our current predicament as a kind of a tipping point, where artists and artists’ organizations begin to see themselves as something more than spectators or tourists. This kind of mission orientation is quite common in democratic countries, and it is one that we, as an art world, have to constantly remind our visitors and artists that visit us that they have just witnessed a very political act, where artists are forced to engage with political situations, and to the extent that it is necessary in order to engage with and contribute to the future of their city. It is a mission that is missionary in nature and uncompromising in its</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-standing debates and counter-examinations of biennials as a form of cultural exchange and artistic perversion aside, the other half of the coin in this equation is the one that comes to mind when looking at a biennial as an art form: when comparing and contrasting it with other art forms, and with the wider biennial movement. This is the art that comes out of the various biennials in generating new art from the same ground, in much the same way that biennials do with other art forms. It is the art that comes out of the different ways that art can be produced and acquired. In generating artists and artists from the ground up, as well as in shedding light on the ways in which art can be acquired, biennials are engaging with and developing contemporary art from the ground up. They are creating contemporary art through the process of acquiring knowledge, through what some might call a ‘biennialisation’ of contemporary art, and incorporating that knowledge in</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-standing antagonisms between the arts and biennials have recently re-assessed themselves somewhat. The biennial has found itself dependent on the health of the arts community in several cities, and so biennials are no longer seen as the enemy but as allies, partners and even friends. This is true for art institutions, of course. But the way art institutions are now structured and operate creates a different kind of contextualised access to knowledge. There is an imbalance between art institutions and the communities they serve, and so it is art today that is denied, not just in the sense of being marginalised but also in the sense that its practices are not valued or seen as legitimate. This imbalance is particularly evident in the areas of social and political engagement. It is very difficult to generate interest in a project or art event when the area is awash with investment, so much so that the biennial is often compared to a stock exchange.1 The biennial has had to work harder than ever to</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system is an interesting one. It begins to show how art can be used to intervene in and influence the course of history, and how art can intervene in and influence society as a whole. This is a potential way of thinking about, and perhaps a way of being, engaged in and about biennials in the present, or in the future. The point is to make them intervene in and influence the course of history in interesting ways, and then to see what happens next. This kind of historical, pedagogical intervention could be applied to other kinds of art, or to art in general. It could be an artistic intervention that creates a context or condition in which art can operate in an artistic way, or it could be art that operates in a context or situation that is opposed to that of others, and so forth. In any case, the pedagogical and artistic side of things should always be on equal footing.Open access to knowledge: the two sides of the same coinThese long-standing debates and conflicts about who is entitled to know and when, and how knowledge should be distributed, arise because the contemporary art market places a great value on reproducing artworks (and exhibitions of artworks) at a high price, regardless of the value attached to such reproductions elsewhere. The contemporary artist, curatorial and art historian is given a repertoire of tools to which to respond to changing needs and wants, which includes but is not limited to: a gallery, a website, offline exhibitionary platform, documentation, press coverage, critical acclaim, historical collections and so forth. All these different kinds of instruments are deployed in different situations, and although they may have similar or even complementary functions and attributes, they are used in radically different situations. In the contemporary context, the key question is: what is the value of reproducing artworks? In other words, what is the value of reproducing and preserving artworks today? If the answer to this question is determined by the materials and archival</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’, 
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 5  Andrea Rossi, ‘Meet the Makers: The Rise of Community Arts in the US’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 6  Andrea Rossi, ‘Meet the Makers: The Rise of Community Arts in the UK’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 7  Andrea Rossi, ‘Meet the Makers: The Rise of Community Arts in the US and Beyond’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 8  Andrea Rossi, ‘Meet the Makers: The Rise of Community Arts in the UK and Beyond’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 9  Andrea Rossi, ‘Meet the M</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 5  Andrea Rossi, ‘Cultural Capital of the World’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 6  Andrea Rossi, ‘Digital Divide and the New Media Paradigm’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 7  Andrea Rossi, ‘3D Media and the Critique of Cultures of Surveillance’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 8  Andrea Rossi, ‘3D Media and the Critique of Cultures of Surveillance’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 9  Andrea Rossi, ‘3D Media and the Critique of Cultures of Surveillance’,  Digital Journal, 2016</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 5  Andrea Rossi, ‘Democracy and Media and the Episodic’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 6  Andrea Rossi, ‘Democracy and Media and the Episodic’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 7  Andrea Rossi, ‘Democracy and Media and the Episodic’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 8  Andrea Rossi, ‘Media Constitutions and the Episodic’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 9  Andrea Rossi, ‘Media Constitutions: Lessons from Argentina’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 5  Andrea Rossi, ‘The End of an Era: Media and Postmodernism’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 6  Andrea Rossi, ‘Need for Tempers: Video, Social Networks and Anarchism’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 7  Andrea Rossi, ‘Digital Disruption and the libidinal Hypothesis – Is there a ‘Big Data’ to Be Explained?’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 8  Andrea Rossi, ‘The End of an Era: Media and Postmodernism’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 9  Andrea Rossi, �</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 5  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Mass Surveillance’,  	Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), pp.1–24. 6  Andrea Rossi, ‘The Digital Divide: Micro-Temporality, Cultural Politics and the Episodic’,  	Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 7  Andrea Rossi, ‘Cultural Capital: Infrastructure of the Future’,  	Cultural Theory/Bienal de las Amélias, 2016, Vol. 46, No. 1, p.1–18. 8  Andrea Rossi, ‘Cultural Capital: Infrastructure of the Past’,  	Cultural Theory, Vol. 40, No. 1, p.1–33. 9  Andrea Rossi</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’,  Digital Journal Vol. 23(1), June, p.1. 5  Andrea Rossi, ‘Rethinking Media Empires’,  Digital Journal Vol. 23(1), July, p.1. 6  Andrea Rossi, ‘Forging Multidisciplinary Interdisciplinary Workspaces’,  Digital Journal Vol. 23(1), June, p.1. 7  Andrea Rossi, ‘Building Participatory Cities with Open Data and Social Practice’,  Digital Journal Vol. 23(1), June, p.1. 8  Andrea Rossi, ‘Beyond the Stereotype: Race, Class, and Social Practices in Contemporary U.S. Cities’,  Digital Journal Vol. 23(1), June, p.1. 9  Andrea Rossi, ‘Cities and Cultures of Surveillance’,  Digital Journal Vol. 23(1),</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 5  Andrea Rossi, ‘Futurist Viewpoints on the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 6  Andrea Rossi, ‘Challenging the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 7  Andrea Rossi, ‘The Digital Divide and the Public Realm’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 8  Andrea Rossi, ‘Public Art as a Public Form’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 9  Andrea Rossi, ‘Politics, Art, Publics: An Introduction to Contemporary Art and Related Topics’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 5  Andrea Rossi, ‘The Digital Divide and the Media Trap’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 6  Andrea Rossi, ‘Why is the Media Factory in the US Building?’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 7  Andrea Rossi, ‘What Does It Take to be Global?’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 8  Andrea Rossi, ‘What is at Stake in the Media Archetype?’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 9  Andrea Rossi, ‘What is at Stake in the Media Archetype?’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol.</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 5  Andrea Rossi, ‘Imperfect Information Media and the Crimethinc Task Force’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 6  Andrea Rossi, ‘Futures of Art and Artifacts: Media Monitors, Digital Sculptures and Beyond’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 7  Andrea Rossi, ‘Framing Anti-Media Propaganda: Media Diversity and the Crimethinc Task Force’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 8  Andrea Rossi, ‘The Crimethinc Task Force and Related Work: A Conversation with Andrea Castells and Ferenc Széllki’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or a Community Arts Organization&quot;, as the case may be, also needs to be curated. The key to a truly ‘international’ relationship is for the hosting country to foster such relationships with other relevant partners, particularly those outside of its immediate orbit. The importance of such development cannot be overemphasised.  References  1  Andrea Rossi, ‘Between Border Control and Democracy: Partisan Politics and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 2  Andrea Rossi, ‘Border Control and the Digital Divide’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 3  Andrea Rossi, ‘Technologies of Surveillance and Bureaucracy’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 4  Andrea Rossi, ‘Remaking the Forms of Media’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1),p.1. 5  Andrea Rossi, ‘The End of Media?’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1), p.1. 6  Andrea Rossi, ‘The End of Post-Media Culture?’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1),p.1. 7  Andrea Rossi, ‘The End of Art and Art’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1),p.1. 8  Andrea Rossi, ‘Intellectual Property and the Politics of Content in an Information Society’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1),p.1. 9  Andrea Rossi, ‘Post-Media Culture and Digital Distribution: On the Limits of Art’,  Digital Journal, 2016, Vol. 23(1</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens, preferring to work with an ever-more sophisticated and urbanised variety of developers and the increasingly privatised service providers that they employ. It is unsurprising then, that the MBTA chose to ignore the group’s invitation and not toch its young designers’ hats. The group was formed with the express intention of engaging with the T, but also in an attempt to create a counterweight to the agency by showing how the agency can still be active in supporting local culture and encouraging artistic practices. The group’s first engagement came at a ceramics fair in June 2018, when the MBTA Community Arts Initiative hosted the T’s first ever Community Arts fair. The fair was a chance for the artists to show their work and for the public to comment on the work and architecture of the space. The ceramics were donated by Meredith’s Fine Arts, who arranged for the materials and inspiration for the project to come from around the country. This</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens, preferring to devote much of its limited resources to supporting the political parties of the city’s largest urban districts. The meeting with the Urbanists was an opportunity to declare publicly that the agency is aware of the city’s problems and that it wants to be part of the solution. The Urbanists’ own response, which expressed surprise at how little the public knew about the city, was published in the September 2018 issue of the Urbanist. There were a number of unexpected participants as well. For example, the fact that the Urbanists had chosen to convene in Brighton despite the fact that the city is experiencing a housing crisis, and despite the fact that the majority of its population do not have a place of employment or place to live, indicates a disconnect between the priorities of the artist and the agency’s. More interestingly, the fact that the artist had chosen to commission an organisation with no local links, but an international one with a multi-year mandate,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens, preferring to look to technology to carry out its urbanisation schemes. In this particular instance, the artist in question, Adam Ryan, had already been hired by the MBTA to work as a contractor for the Construction Trusts project Constructive City, and was already using the construction site as the site of his future hub for the future urban development of the city. It was at this point that the artist and his team realised just how much their project was at odds with the architecture of the city. The fact that the building they were proposing to remodel into a mosque had already been abandoned decades earlier was a source of great frustration to residents, who felt that the project would rob the heritage of one of the city’s most iconic sites of cultural significance. But as residents and visitors alike have realised, this was only ever a problem for the artist and his cohorts. The MBTA never invested in researching or caring about the history of the building, preferring to simply knock</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens, preferring to work with an amalgam of developers, property developers, and large financial institutions. Consequently, the meeting with the public was seen as an increasing erosion of the agency’s independence, while those deemed ‘core’ to the project were encouraged to participate further. The group was asked to consider how they might be empowered to take matters of their neighbourhood back, and to explore alternative futures for their neighbourhood. How might the city assist in the creation of ‘a new kind of urbanism’? How might the neighbourhood be transformed through collaborative, co-producing strategies? The group was invited to consider how neighbourhood interventions might be facilitated through the curatorial turn-around, and to propose an ‘open ended set of actions’ that would allow for further experimentation and development. What is the role of culture in the city, and how might art, literature, and other forms of cultural practice be woven into the curatorial turn-around? What is the role</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens, preferring instead to draw on the expertise of experienced urbanists and architects. The meeting with the artists' collective was therefore a rare opportunity for the agency to exert agency over the situation, creating a level playing field between the artist’s selected group and the citizens the agency selected. In this sense, the meeting also validated the agency’s ambitions: now, the citizens of Brighton and its environs must prove themselves worthy of the title, and the title’s luck may change in the future.  A city is a living organism, constantly evolving, and its natural inhabitants, residents, and artists have a vital role to play in preserving the beauty and identity of the city. They are vital to the functioning of any city’s infrastructure, but especially in the remarkable story of the past that the city must tell in order to continue to inhabit the present.   The Biennale’s current programme of actions recalls the way in which the Biennale was</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens, preferring to talk with representatives of other government agencies, political parties and other stakeholders. The meeting with the Urbanists was a chance for the MBTA to show its cards, and for the city council to consider its future, since the Future City project was deemed to be too far gone to attempt to resuscitate. The emergent conversation became evident to those present that the project had created, that the Urbanists had invited to become part of a larger, societal discussion, and that the city was becoming a laboratory for the kind of cultural experimentation that the Biennale was intended to foster. The conversations sparked by the project, and the emerging narrative they represented, are the kind that are bound to foster new ideas and strategies, and alter old ways of looking at the world. The conversations that foster new urban forms, and alter the existing order are those that are fundamentally interested in the long term, in the ways in which cities and urbanism reconfigure and evolve. They are not interested in short term</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens, preferring to work with representatives of other governmental bodies and large corporations. Although the group felt that the invitation was legitimate, they knew that they would need the full cooperation of the Transit Authority in order to carry out their project. Accordingly, the group worked with the Transportation Research Board (TRB), a quasi-judicial body appointed by the governor to review and approve any changes to the MBTA, including proposals that would affect service levels or quality of life. In a typical issue, the TRB will issue its first report as a public service, and then conduct a second public hearing, during which the public can offer additional comments. In this case, the second public hearing would be conducted in front of an audience of local residents and arts professionals. The audience would provide the necessary cross-section of residents to enable the project’s development team to engage with residents’ perspectives and overcome entrenched power structures.  The artists and their multi-disciplinary teams responded by creating a series of actions</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens, preferring to work with the local communities that it serves. In this case, the local communities were the inhabitants of the neighborhood and the theatre, who constituted the audience. Despite this corporate suburbanism, the meeting with the MBTA seemed like something that would happen, and the idea that we would one day undertake such a thing on a massive scale was a catalyst for our public engagement. The meeting with the MBTA seemed so unnecessary, since the project was already underway and we already knew what the outcome of the encounter would be. However, the MBTA did not renew its contract with the Theatre until 2021, so it seems like the invitation is still open to question. What next for the Theatre? The invitation to the MBTA to join us in Brighton remains a rare and precious commodity, so it is with great pleasure that I am able to invite them into my public realm in The Metreon. From the beginning of our conversations, they have been asking me to tell the story in various ways</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens, whereas the city actively recruits artists to engage with and help create a sense of the city. Therefore the meeting with the MBTA was significant in that it signaled to many that the agency values the people who live and work in the area, and that they are valued members of the local community. This was seen as a first step in creating a collaborative relationship with the MTA. The next public engagement occurred in June 2018, when a group of artists, led by Manveer Heptullah, visited the Temple Street Arts &amp; Culture Park, located just steps away from where the MBTA station is located. Over the next two months, Heptullah, his team and the public assembled at the Park Palace, where artists Satish Kanady and Dawn Powell worked in groups to create a public realm around the park, while Carla Ambrosius re-imagined the historic T station. The group then visited the Arsenale di</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Group’. The group, which included Dawn Powell, Katie Mackenzie, Manveer Heptullah and Rami El Samahy, was formed to explore the ways in which an architectural staging might engage with the city’s current situation. The group was created as a counterweight to the arrogance of the artist, who projected an image of a utopian future city without representing any of the inhabitants of the city at all. The group’s first public engagement took place in February 2018, when they staged a series of actions in front of Palazzo della Pergola, the former home of MBTA. The group then invited the MBTA to join them in Brighton, and invited the public to become 'bassadors for a new kind of urbanism' by encouraging other local authorities to follow suit.  The meeting with the MBTA came as a surprise to many, because the agency rarely engages with its own citizens, preferring to focus on the needs of the corporation. Though the group was initially sceptical, their meeting in October 2018 where the agency officially embraced their proposal seems to have changed their minds. The inclusion of the MBTA in the proposal seemed unnecessary, since the agency already has a strong partnership with the city, and the entire transit network is designed to be driven by computers. Though the proposal itself is still open for discussion, the inclusion of the MBTA in the proposed network seems quite unnecessary, since the agency is part of the Transport for London, and is not subject to the whims of the political operator.  In fact, the inclusion of the MBTA in the network would only confuse things, since the network would be driven by algorithms, and not subject to the real-life interaction between people and transit. The reality would dictate which stations to maximize capacity at which times, and the agency would only ever deliver what planners ‘dreamed up’ and imposed through their control mechanisms</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y2  – The geographer Steven Drozd is a professor in the Department of Sociology and Geopolitics at</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y  [2] The structure of the IMI Corona was designed by Leslie K. Green and is comprised of three</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-x  [2] http://graphicsisbeauty.com/graphics-art/2015/04/george-wang-placesthe-1-1-sprite-of-george-wang-nature-placesthe-1-1-sprite-of-george-wang-nature-sprite-full-size/  [3] https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S01744391413008544, accessed July 2018. [4] http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S01744391413008544, accessed</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y- y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y y *Note: If this is an ongoing project, I’d love to contribute to it. In the mean time, let me know if you have any questions.Best</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-yk-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-yk-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-yl-syn:   Pronounced ‘Pronounce’: ‘Pronouncement N.Y. Y. Muralum Loser Pronounced ‘Pronouncement’, or more correctly ‘Pronouncement New York’s Muralum Loser.) This is the fourth exhibit of the Asian Triennale, and the first in New York. The project was co-commissioned by the Museum of Modern Art and the Queens Museum. For more information, visit http://www.nanotechworld.org/.  [2] John Berger,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, and as a result, its resources will always be flexible and can be directed at meeting current needs.  [1] Seehttp://www.geographical-reference.com/domestic-business/north-america/usa/nyc-region-pricing-economy-20170324-us-nyc-2-6-6-joint-stock-national-helicopter-parts-now-importing-romance-marker-parts-new-racing-racing-rabi-spring-farming-rabi-on-wheels-rear-ended-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y-y</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to school with my brother, The Builder, who was always welcomed into the school choir. Then there was the football team, always led by the boys. We used to play catch in the street, use the girls' changing room, and go to the local arcade for friendly games. I will always remember the first time I played slot machines, and will always look at the top of the youth league table, as well as the shelves of Nuyumbalees Toys &amp; Men. I am so proud of my family and I suppose that every time I look at that, I feel like a failure as an artist. They produced something amazing on the cheap! I used to paint houses in Toxteth and sell them to builders, and now I am a consultant, helping builders put their projects together. The Welsh Streets area is in crisis. We need to find a way to work with the council and the businesses to bring these projects together. At the moment, I am working with the architect on a</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to school with my dad, The Elephant, on the Welsh Streets shopping street. We used to stop by the Gap shoe store or the John Lennon Bakery, just to buy some bread and milk. We used to visit with the Chrysler car repair shop on the Welsh Streets shopping street. We used to go to the nearby zoo or play football in the streets. We used to hang out with the black cabs or the gangs. We used to shop at the jewellers or thrift shops. We used to play football in the Welsh Streets playground. And we used to watch the Arsenal football team.Chrysler has been a Welsh Streets resident for 40 years. We used to play football in the Welsh Streets playground with the other residents. We used to play football in the street with the rest of the community. We used to shop for sports cars at the Welsh Streets Market. We used to play cricket in the Welsh Streets playground. We used to play football in the</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to school with my brother, The Builder, taking the Signpost along the Welsh Streets.We used to play football in the Welsh Streets, with the local kids, the farmers and the artists. There was a radio station, KXLY, 1130 AM, and a couple of local artists used to come out every now and then to play. It used to be a football ground, now it is a shoe store. It used to be called Midland Football League, then it was called Football Leagues. Football Leagues used to be based in the Welsh Streets, now they are all gone. The Welsh Streets have found a new way to rein in the violence that was a part of the community. There is a community park next to the Welsh Streets now, and a community cafe next door. There is a community centre open 24 hours a day.There was a time when the Welsh Streets were a popular destination for backpackers, backpacker culture was prominent, and the buildings that once housed independent</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to church every now and then to visit my grandmother. She was buried in the Welsh Streets and was interred in the local church cemetery. We used to play football in the street, sometimes against the other shoe. I used to be able to walk to church with my friends, but now all the girls play football with their clubs. I used to knock on the door of the Welsh Streets Diocese and ask what was going on. There was usually a manger full of cards waiting for me at the gates. It used to be that when I went to the bank, I got a 20 pence match, but that is now gone. The Welsh Streets Diocese still organises football matches.On Sundays, the girls of the Welsh Streets used to play football with the brooms, the gardener and the canary. I used to run the Welsh Streets Football Club, which was about 20 girls, aged seven to 11. We used to play on the street, with the boys, on the</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to school with them to play football in the grass pitch. By the time I was six, the football was replaced by rugby, and by the time I was eight, it was baseball.I started primary school in the Welsh Streets and went to secondary school in a converted bakery called the Welsh Streets Academy. At the academy, I did crafts and organised games for the kids, and of course, my interest was in architecture and design. I did a lot of design work, and one of the first projects I did was for the Welsh Streets and the Clydebank Road area. I did designs for houses, boutique hotels, schools, recreation centres and even a few funeral parlours. At the end of it all, I did architectural work. The reason why I worked in the Welsh Streets is that the shops in the Welsh Streets were so busy with cars, and the shops in Clydebank Road were so busy with people commuting to work, that it was almost impossible to get work done. So</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to school with a tinned up Welsh Streets Local Football Club. We would play football, hoop, swing on the swings, and generally have a good time.I used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to walk to school with a tinned up Welsh Streets Local Football Club. We would play football, hoop, swing on the swings, and generally have a good time.Maybe it was the drink and the banter. Maybe it was the fact that I grew up in a deprived area of the Welsh Streets. But whatever the reason, I always felt like an outsider. I was always the type who thought things through and acted on intuition. I wasn’t good at picking up trends but I liked to read the papers, watch the TV news, and follow the blogs. I used to like to read the Hollywoodland newspaper and stare at the DOWNTOWN ART page till it was black. I liked to read the gossip columns in the</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to school with my dad, picking out the colour, the pattern, the fabric, and the buy-one-get-one-free. We were always able to find something to like about the area, whether it was the Tudor or the Welsh Streets Market or the Clydebank Arts Centre. We were always able to look at the architecture books and find something to build ourselves. If we didn’t have kids, we’d always just be building ourselves.Today, the Welsh Streets are rubble, but the area has recovered sufficiently to be able to start a small craft brewery and market the success of the business. We’re fortunate to be headed by a group of community artists, designers, and architects who have collectively created a new kind of mixed-use development with a mix of houses, offices, shops, public realm, and open, green space. It’s a place where culture meets agriculture, and culture is actively creating new ways of living together. The</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to church every day, it being quite close to work. I used to go to the Welsh Streets Market a couple of times a week, and of course, the football matches. In between, I sometimes mixed it up at the nearby hardware shop.The Welsh Streets Market was started by the then Community Land Trust and it was a safe haven for young people to start out their own projects. There was a big culture war going on at the time, and the Welsh Streets Market was a place where people could find things they might not necessarily agree with, and still find a way. It was a place where you could still find a cup of tea and a sandwich if you were hungry, and a couple of doors down from the Community Land Trust building. The Community Land Trust had just been dissolved, and the Welsh Streets Market had sprung into life. The Community Land Trust had been formed to run the Welsh Streets Market, and the Welsh Streets Market had sprung into life full-fledged, with people congregating in</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to church every day with my father, taking the Local Adventure route.I don’t usually get drawn into thinking about what could/should be done to help the area, but I’m always keen to help when I can. I’m always up for a debate, a challenge or two, and I’m always willing to help when I can. It’s that simple.My favourite thing about the area is the Welsh Streets Market. I’ve always loved the way that the local kids used to play there, and the Welsh Streets Market is a place where they can come and play without fear or intimidation. It’s a place where you can come in confidence, know that you can count on a team of people behind you and that everything will be taken care of. It’s a place where you can really fall in love with a project, and not necessarily have to.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleHi, I�</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial—which was itself a disastrous, if not wholly preventable, reaction to the disembowelling of the art world by the new economic form of the biennale—is a cautionary tale. It is a reminder that art forms are here to stay; that the post-biennial form will probably outlive the biennial form, and that art, and every form of art, will likely exist in some sort of future beyond our planet.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleI was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth. My father is an architect and my mother is a builder. I spent a lot of time in the local shops, playing with the local kids, and of course, the Welsh Streets Market. I used to love to shop for sports cars and used to love to read the gossip columns in the local pub. I used to go to church every Sunday for the local girls to pick out outfits for the week. I used to walk to the Welsh Streets Market and the nearby farmers market, taking my favourite flower power yarn and knitting needle, and browsing the wares.I always felt somewhat inadequate in comparison to my more socially engaged peers. I didn’t have a sports car or a car for the whole family to take, so I had to learn on my own. However, I got much better and much better at mapping my surroundings, and at identifying the shops with the highest street value. I would walk to the Welsh Streets Market for ten minutes every day, looking for the latest high street fashion shoot, or just to pick up a random knitted cardigan or hooded sweatshirt. I used to go to the nearby Primary School, where the Welsh Streets children played football, or ‘Brick Lane Boys and Girls Club’ for short. They used to play dress up as wizards and the mermaid, or go swimming in the river, or take part in a folk dance. After school, we used to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many residents and workers don’t find affordable housing options anymore. The buying back of housing leads to speculation on housing – which leads to more speculation, which in turn leads to more housing, which in turn leads to more costs, which in turn leads to more bankruptcy, until eventually the entire neighbourhood is displaced and the city government folds its activities into a black hole. And as we noted, that’s just the neighbourhood problem. Compounding the urban crisis is the fact that many of the displaced people move back into the city, taking with them the unused housing units and the boarded-up buildings – which is why so many neighbourhoods become recrossing malls in their own right – which in turn leads to more displacement and more costs. And as we noted, the cheaper a place is to produce goods and services, the less appealing is it to people to rely on those goods and services in return for a place in the city. A survey done by the San Francisco–based non-profit,</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many neighbourhoods don’t benefit from the district’s services or culture, or where the district is homogenous and devoid of cultural attractions. The buying back of housing serves as a transfer of wealth from the hands of the tenants of housing projects into the hands of the owners of the businesses that construct the district’s infrastructure, which in turn serves as a transfer of wealth from the poorest neighbourhoods into the hands of the richest neighbourhoods. Theoretically, the intention behind the purchase of back housing is that of encouraging cultural exchange between the neighbourhoods where the new 'High Street' shopping district is being built and the neighbourhoods where the old ‘High Street’ has ended. Theoretically, the intention behind the purchase of back housing is that of encouraging cultural exchange between the neighbourhoods where the new ‘High Street’ is being built and the neighbourhoods where the old ‘High Street’ once stood.  One might even agree that the intention behind the purchase of back housing is that</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many residents of Century City are trapped in housing shortages and overcrowding despite the impressive economic potentials of new economic development. The purchase of back housing contracts only exacerbates the problem, since the owners of the properties bought them when they were down, when the market was cheap and eager to buy, and then when the market turned into a trap by underwriting housing shortages and overbuilding. The speculative behaviour of the past is repeated, but the response is different this time. The response is more cautious, perhaps even resigned, since the consequences of not meeting targets for buildings and renovations could see many residents forced into poverty. However, the next step is different. Rather than waiting for developers to deliver promised improvements, the city instead leverages its vast financial resources to buy back existing housing contracts, or in the case of derelict properties, to create affordable housing opportunities through district-based cooperatives. Cooperative housing has become the answer to a stagnant or failing urban market. It provides affordable housing for workers and businesses</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many other assets, such as schools, parks and infrastructure, are in short supply. The shortage of affordable housing is a direct result of building codes that were written for an area with a high per capita income and a high minimum wage. The coding of the city as a zero-growth zone means that housing prices will only go up – exponentially – when the per capita income in an area increases. Thus, the demand for housing is driven by a surge in housing prices that can be tapped into the housing fund as a quick fix when the city doesn’t grow any more. But this housing fund is currently running short of money; it’s like a credit card that has run dry. As a result, many people, especially those in the higher wage bracket, are forced to find somewhere else to live or work. This has been a particularly acute problem for low and moderate-income households. As the vacancy rate in downtown San Francisco hovered around 7% for several years, it was becoming</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many other assets – cultural institutions, arts venues, historic districts and so forth – are in serious decline. The problem is deeper and more pervasive than that. The logic of buying back housing and turning them into rental units – which is precisely what has happened in Oakland, Seattle and San Francisco since the mid-1990s – is a contradiction in terms. On the one hand, the city floods with housing, providing affordable housing to many of its residents; at the same time, it contracts out most of this housing to for-profit developers and non-profits.  The paradox is compounded by the fact that many of the units purchased through these schemes have become rent-stabilised units only available to very wealthy residents.  The non-profit sector has responded by creating affordable-housing trust funds, which in turn have responded by creating non-profit boards, which in turn have responded by creating non-profit councils, which in turn have responded by creating non-profit instrumentalities and so forth. And</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many neighbourhoods have been forcibly redeveloped. The proliferation of non-market housing – which is to say, housing purchased by the developer at extremely low prices and turned into rental housing – has created a situation in which many neighbourhoods are stretched thin and desperate for housing, but are also the site of conflict between the buyers and the residents, who are increasingly displaced in the process. A growing number of neighbourhoods are gripped by violent conflict between market and supply, between developers and residents, between the rich and the poor, between the urban and rural poor. And now, increasingly, between the city and the rural poor.Urban crisis  One might even say that the problem is urbanised – in the sense that too many buildings, past and present, are homeless on any given day – which is to say, the creation of new ‘housing deserts’ around major metropolises. And yet, as the biennale continues to expand, it is becoming ever clearer that the problem is much deeper. As</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many residents of Century City still live in overcrowded and dilapidated housing situations. The reason why urban residents aren’t being offered any type of improvement and redevelopment is because the market isn’t responsive to the needs and preferences of the residents of Century City. Acknowledge that fact.  One might even agree that the failure of the market to respond to the needs and preferences of the population is the root cause of the housing crisis in San Francisco and other areas that are witnessing a threefold increase in population in the past fifteen years. The inability of the market to grow in response to this rapid increase is fuelling a housing bubble. The inability of the market to grow in response to this rapid increase is also fuelling a portents of things to come: a monstrosity like Venice that no artist would want to inhabit, or Mical Avenue, the formerly great commercial strip that is now home to a nightlife mecca, or even the burgeoning financial district that will soon house</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many residents of Century City still live in overcrowded and unhealthy housing conditions. The buying back of housing contracts actually pushes residents out of the area and into the urban periphery, further burdening local governments with huge bills in the form of housing costs, rent and fees. Such practices are not just wrong, but dangerous.  One might even say that the city should not be in the rental market; it should be in a cooperative housing scheme, providing affordable housing to as many people as possible through sharing costs. Cooperative housing has proven to be a valuable long-term investment for the city, providing affordable housing to residents at no cost to the developers and owners of the properties. Yet sharing costs – and the intense competition for affordable housing among residents – means that housing rights are often abused in an attempt to increase the value of the managed plots of land and buildings, and especially when those abuses stem from the aggressive promotion of a specific development project by a local authority. A growing number of residents and activists now call for</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many neighbourhoods are already experiencing displacement and poverty. The only way to build sustainable local economies is to invest in education and infrastructure that support a network of socially engaged communities, including by creating local cooperative housing trusts, local grassroots cooperatives and so on. The purchase of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic. The purchase of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic. Housing is a purchase-only commodity; and as such, it is easy to understand how the logic of ‘housing only in San Francisco’ can be applied to the city’s rapidly expanding homeless population. However, this logic excludes many other factors, including the need to build or expand transit or education infrastructure or employ thousands of people in precarious or low-paid jobs in communities where the demand for housing is strong. Nor is it possible to understand the logic of ‘housing only in San Francisco’ without also understanding the housing crisis in other parts of the country. So it is with another critical urban</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets consistent with the desires of the owners and managers of the franchises – with the workers and communities whose histories are fused with the vehicles.Compulsory purchase and leasing of housing has become a central feature of the San Francisco–based real-estate development and management firm, Renaissance Realty Trust, which operates more widely as Century City Realty Trust. The acquisition of land and building of new housing have followed a similar logic. The acquisition of land and building of new housing follow a similar logic.  One might even agree that the developers of the failing city seem to have adopted the logic of the market in the same way that the speculators on housing mortgages did in the financial crisis of 2007–09: by buying back housing contracts at extremely low costs, or in the case of derelict properties, turning them into rental-only units through which the owners can pocket huge profits.Yet buying back housing doesn’t solve the problem; nor does it make any sense in an urbanised area where many neighbourhoods don’t have access to affordable housing. The reason why there is such a scarcity of affordable housing in the core areas is that the market has crashed and the politicians have tried to stop it. Theoretically, the Core Areas could theoretically be given over to housing, but given the density and number of businesses required to support such a huge development, such a policy seems economically unviable. It seems economically unviable because the supply of housing meets the demand; or at least, the supply of affordable housing doesn’t meet the demand. In other words, the policy of buying back housing – which seems to be working in the core areas – doesn’t make any sense in the dense areas where the market is actively busting and pushing people out.  And this brings us to the second reason why the crisis of affordability for the core areas is a crisis: because the politicians in the core areas have chosen to spend so much time trying to destroy the unique character of</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So
    <text>human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So while the postindustrial society may produce increasingly negative impacts on the planet as a result of the growing number of factories and cars on the road, it does not see itself as fundamentally different from anything else. It is a ‘system' that must be continually patched together from the different components. In this regard, the postindustrial society is not fundamentally different from anything else, and while it may produce more negative impacts on the planet as a result of the proliferation of modes of production, it is also fundamentally different from zero or near zero.  One might add to this the fact that the postindustrial society is becoming increasingly urbanised, as more and more people live away from the city centre. And while the impacts of climate change will certainly affect the planet as a whole, the postindustrial society will also become increasingly dependent on renewable energies, including biofuels from palm oil, which are responsible for a large amount of greenhouse gas emissions. As a result, it will be increasingly difficult to say what the</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So, according to one reading of the techno-neoliberal utopia scenario, we are witnessing the emergence, as yet undetermined, of new forms of hierarchical postindustrial societies where ‘public space’ takes on a new dimension. One might add another dimension to this: postindustrial may be becoming an ever more public space.  One might also add that these ‘public spaces’ are becoming ever more ‘commercialized’ in the service of the needs of the energy companies and merchant princes. And there we are, perfectly consistent with the ‘public’ as a concept emerging in the wake of the energy crisis, as the techno-neoliberal utopia of unlimited, inexhaustible energy is coming to define the global landscape.Postindustrial society may be coming to rely on ever more technologically advanced means of transport and communication, yet it is also becoming ever more aware of its vulnerability. The infrastructure that supports postindustrial life is susceptible to the whims of resource scarcity, and</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So far, so normal. But what is emerging is that the infrastructure of the postindustrial society is being designed in such a way as to support a future interaction between humans and the natural world – one in which humans are no longer confined to the confines of the planet. This is happening at a prodigious rate, with increasing numbers of people becoming the inhabitant of new urban landscapes and the countryside. The number of people living in urban centres has trebled in the past fifty years, while the number of kilometres traveled in car has quadrupled. And while the growth in car use and miles traveled per year is undoubtedly a factor in the explosion of population, it is also true that the size and mass of cars and trucks relative to land masses has quintupled, making it easier and cheaper for companies to connect with and occupy growing amounts of land. And so it continues. As a consequence, the land is being used in ways that can be mapped – that is, developments that can be counted on to</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So far, so normal, but what is emerging is a society in which infrastructure is produced not on a massive scale but over many thousands of individual sites and individuals – a society of the fat and the fatuous, the situated and the mobile. The denizens of the new urbanisation will likely find themselves caught in a web of mobility traps, clogged highways and tunnels, and subject to the whims of powerful economic planners. Yet, these people will not be able to see or comprehend the vastness of the problem. 	Rather, the driver of the infrastructure boom will likely be seen as a driver of the growth of a middle class and a healthy society – a self-proclaimed ‘society of the future’ – that will encompass everything from gleaming new data-graphics to enhanced taxi services to automated regulatory schemes that will ensure that the rich get richer and the poor are lifted out of poverty. All of this infrastructure will be seen as a solution to a problem that does not exist</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So, the postindustrial society we envision is one in which people are no longer confined to the confines of the site where they were born, raised and employed. They can choose to reside anywhere in the globe, or can choose to move to someplace far from where they are born, raised and employed. This choice, however, does not alter the fact that they will continue to be producers and consumers of infrastructure, and their products and services will continue to have a place in that society.  One can ask: what would replace the role of the photographer in the production of infrastructure?  Another possibility is to ask: what would replace the role of the climatologist in the prediction and commentary on climatic conditions?  A third possibility is to ask: what future would create a situation in which people could freely choose among many alternatives?  A fourth and final possibility is to ask: what would replace the role of the architect in the design of infrastructure, and the promotion of social and environmental improvements?</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So while in the future we may envision a society based on love and compassion, in practice we must also envision a society that is resourceful and compassionate. This means acknowledging our role in the production of infrastructure that supports our lifestyles and futures, and in the production of the infrastructure itself.Images courtesy of L. Paul/Magnum Research/AAAS, Inc. and the Environmental Defense Fund.  	Pixabay 	The image above is a series of 14 photos, all of which were taken in the same location in the city of Basel, Switzerland, in December of 2015. The images were distributed by the Basel Institute of Contemporary Art (BicAM), and show a working version of the BicAM website in the city. As the caption reads, the images were taken in response to the vandalism of several buildings in the city. The institute is an independent, non-profit organisation. Their website describes their research and development agenda: 	Research and development of</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So, while we may not yet be able to build entirely autonomous vehicles or systems that understand the political and social context of their production, we can be certain that the people who are running those systems will also be certain to ensure that the systems are run in a way that maximises the enrichment of the capitalist mode of production.  	[1] 	See, for example, James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital of Culture?’, New Left Review, Issue 6 (July 2016), pp. 1–14.  	[2] See http://www.globalresearch.ca/international/en/books/l... 	[3] See also Michael Hudson, ed., The Global Economy of Media: The Rise and Fall of Creative Class (New York: Palgrave Macmillan, 2015), p. 10.  	[4] See Hudson, op. cit., p. 10.  	[5] Hudson, op</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So, while we observe the technological revolution and its discontents, we also see the emergence of new technological modes of production and consumption that are indistinguishable from old modes of production and consumption, but that also transform the social forms that underpinned them.  	[1]   	[2]   	[3] John Durham Peters, ‘The Great Transformation: Social Change, Social Financing’,  	Oxford Journal of Economics and Politics, Vol. 1, No. 2 (2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Designing the Future in an Age of Uncertainty and Uncertain Worlds by Jeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington (MIT Press, 2016). 6  Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington,  	Designing the Future in an Age of Uncertainty and Uncertain Worlds by Jeanne Robinson and</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So far, so normal. But what is emerging is that the infrastructure is being designed on the basis of the new ecological crises that are sweeping across the planet. Sometimes these actors are called ‘postindustrial’, referring to the post-Fordist phase of the transition from production to consumption; a stage in which the social forms of production are no longer operative. Such systems are being designed with the capacity to sustain life on a planetary scale. So, too, is the implication that ‘knowledge production’ is now embedded in the fabric of the planet itself. This is a world that can no longer be produced via the hierarchical forms of production that the industrial society continues to inhabit. The postindustrial society we envision cannot simultaneously produce and consume energy. It will have to find other ways of incorporating energy into its social structure. In order to achieve this, it will have to find new ways of interacting with the environment that are less imperialistic and more ecological in their nature.Projections of the</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, and the social and political circumstances of their production.[3] This is a similar approach to our thought experiment on the use of photography in the production of infrastructure, but is framed within the larger political and urban context. We begin to see the social functions of the technology that is being developed and deployed in tandem with the people who are its users (postindustrial societies). The postindustrial society we envision does not envision a future of abundant, sustainable energy; nor one in which people ‘continue to work ever longer hours for low pay and often without any form of benefits’. It will continue to rely on ‘stakeholders in the financial sector, energy companies and merchant princes’ who control access to resources and the routes along which they can move those resources around the world. These stakeholders also control what can be called the Domain Awareness Network (DEN) – a global data network linking all manner of infrastructure that allows for the continual construction of infrastructure based on demand and resources. So while the postindustrial society may or may not produce the infrastructure required to support a future for which those in power do not yet know, the aim of the project is to allow for the continued construction of infrastructure that is capable of supporting a future in which those in power do know. 	[1] 	http://www.bls.gov/india/statistics/nationals/nadis/economy/stats.htm#economygroup=economynote1&amp;country=india_nationals_republic_of_india_stats.htm#economynote2&amp;country=india_nationals_republic_of_india_statistics.htm#economynote3&amp;mode=export&amp;term=economynote1&amp;term=allocatedspacebites&amp;filetype=pdf1919191407.pdf1919191407.xlsx 	[2] World Bank,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions. It provides essential links in the chain of things – raw materials, manufactured goods, financial instruments and more – that end up in the hands of consumers. And it contributes to a socially exploitable but increasingly fragmented urban future through its capacity to function as a transshipment point for commodities, financial instruments and more.1  The city is a capital trap – a situation in which growing numbers of people are trapped in ever-expanding and diversifying webs of debt and dependent lifestyles. Despite this constant stream of negative attention, the city is remarkably malleable. It can be differentiated into myriad forms: a city that is home to inhabitants in precarious situations, or a city in continuous transformation, in which all kinds of people flock in and out, seeking economic opportunities and becoming defined by the city’s charade of sustainability.  The city is a globalising concept. It implies that people arriving from faraway places or from the interior world should have some sort of inherent sense of belonging to</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions. It feeds into a global system of containerisation that is threatening not only the transshipment of products between regions, but also the integrity of the global supply chain. All of these transnational transnational transnational transnational transnational transnational transnational systems are affected by these same factors, yet they do not seem to be thinking or doing much about it. Rather, we seem to be witnessing the emergence of a new world order based on the transnational corporations and the global financial flows that are now the dominant forms of economic organisation.The city is the predominant mode of global circulation today. In the next phase of this development, there will be cities with transnational reputations, and maybe even those with human-resource departments. We need to start thinking about what the implications for our city will be in this new economic world, and how these will be structured. This is the broader question that is opening up in our city, and it is a question that we cannot afford not to be asking</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions. It feeds into a global system of containerisation that facilitates the movement of containers across the oceans, and of goods across the seas, and of people (truckers, soldiers, exporters, exporters, traders, etc) across these oceans. It feeds into a global system of hyperlinking – the globalised version of the medieval point of ingathering – in which all these moving parts of the capitalist economy fit together to produce ever greater flows of capital and goods, and thus, potentially, new forms of labour – new kinds of wealth – that can be exploited and distributed. And, of course, there is the part of the equation that includes the many different forms of colonialism and slavery that emerge from this all. The city is a complex system that depends on many different nodes and nodes that may or may not be connected. Each of these interacting parts has a role to play, and each of these roles is potentially fraught with inherent risks and injustices. Yet, each of these systems</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions. Finally, it feeds into a global system that is increasingly reliant on the services of a single infrastructure, but which is itself increasingly precarious and subject to geopolitical interventions.  So, while the built environment – the infrastructures themselves, not just the industry that creates the built environment – continues to make up the bulk of the global metainterface, the source of this proliferation of vulnerability is increasingly being traced to the source of this vulnerability: the trade in information, and the service that information provides to the built environment.  A second generation of the metainterface is emerging, albeit one that is increasingly centred on cities.  One example of this is the increasing prominence of ‘smart cities’, those ‘capable of becoming entirely self-sufficient with the right infrastructure and smart strategies’ that are being developed in both developed and developing nations.  Another example is the widespread adoption of ‘smart growth’ – the idea that government programmes, policies,</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions. It also feeds into a regional system of its own that is increasingly international, global and diffuse. These factors conspire to accentuate the role of cities in the service economies of capital and diffuse the social impacts of these industries towards non-city regions.2  Thus, the financial and social paraphernalia of cities is woven into the fabric of the city – infrastructure, financial instruments, regulatory regimes, codes, laws, codes, regulations, codes, legal opinions, constitutions, and jurisprudence that prescribe what is and what is not possible in cities. And yet this is precisely what has largely taken place in the financial and social services sectors in the past half-century.3  In the late nineteenth century, for instance, the law specifically prohibited the city from enacting or implementing a universal basic income, since such a programme was considered a violation of the 'fundamental' rights of citizens.[1] In the twentieth century, the law was more permissive, and</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions. Finally, it feeds into a global system of global highways that is increasingly based in Asia and the US, and which are regularly used to connect regions that are very different places but with very similar socio-political landscapes. These are the cultures that inhabit and are made up of the ‘bottom 50%’ of humanity. These are the ‘bottom 90%’ – the remaining 99%. The term ‘bottom’ is used not only to identify those at or below the socioeconomic level of the global economy but also to describe those who are voiceless, who are products of immigration, foreclosure, commodification and the politics of poverty. 	[i] Excerpt from The Global Economy of Intangible Assets, Third Edition, Routledge, New York, 2006. 	[ii] Excerpt from The Global Economy of Intangible Assets, Fourth Edition, Routledge, New York, 2007. 	[iii] Excerpt from The Global Economy of</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions. It feeds into a global system of bridges that forms the basis for the continued viability of both the city and the nation – the very social forms that we speak of in passing as if there is no such thing as ‘home’.  Such is the  capitalist ‘bottom line’. – Karl Marx  [1] Marija Cetinic at ‘20th Biennale of Sydney’, November 2014, p.25.Download this article as PDFMarija CetinicAt the University of Sydney, Australia, Marija Partizan is Professor in Cultural Studies and the Artistic Director of the Art Gallery of NSW. Her research interests include the art of home and cultural regeneration, and the economics of cultural consumption. She is currently researching the history of cultural tourism in Bosnia and Herzegovina, and is developing a multi-disciplinary art project that integrates cultural data, analysis, and design into cultural production in Kosovo. Her latest project</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions. It is a major node in a globalised economy that includes China, and its growing ranks of urban mover and shaker. At a geopolitical level, the city is a geopolitical oddity. It is both a home to the city, and a place where politics, tourism, and culture collide with increasingly dire consequences. Orientalism TodayIn recent years, cultural tourism has become a major form of industry for the Arabian Gulf, and is used as a backstop against geopolitical risk and other forms of economic decline. In the 1980s and early 1990s, the number of Chinese tourists visiting the Arabian Gulf region shot up almost threefold due to the Chinese market being so captivated by the spectacle of poverty and sickness displayed by the region – especially in the form of the Chinese doctor Mu Jingbo, who was touring the region on a commercial basis. He would later be accused of human-sabotage after a string of attacks on Chinese doctors in the region. The disease that he was promoting</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions. It feeds into a global system for data gathering and transmission that is increasingly dependent on the services of a variety of third parties, and which is increasingly susceptible to the whims of geopolitical events such as war, natural disasters and remittances from migrant labour. All of this makes the built environment – or, to be more specific, the built environment of the cities that are its platforms and fibres – a more potent place for fantasy, fabrication and speculation than the streets and fields around them. It is easier to believe in, and more often than not to be a part of, a fantastical future society based around the built environment, where people can be free from the constraints of poverty, hunger and oppression that characterise contemporary urban life. Unfortunately, this is what has happened in the past, and will continue to happen, largely because of the resource-starved metropolis. There is no silver bullet or miracle cure for the problems of poverty, hunger and oppression, but there are some things that</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets and structures – the raw materials and built environment that are the direct products of industrial processes. The city, and its built environment – which can be seen to be a capital trap – is an ever-present source of vulnerability. The finance, real-estate, commodities and financial instruments that feed off this built environment continuously shift in response to ever-greater numbers of investors, traders and speculators. The city is a major transshipment point for – among many other things – crude oil, natural-gas, pulp and paper, tires, tires and brake fluid, tires and brake oil, tires and paint, insulating fibres, metals, textiles, chemicals and more. It feeds into a global market for consumer products that regularly employ millions around the world and which is increasingly punctured by service-sector migration. It feeds into a global financial system that is increasingly based in the US and Europe, and which is threatened with being undone by the ever-larging financial sector in both regions. And it feeds into a global system that is increasingly reliant on renewable energy, primarily from wind and solar energy resources, primarily from hydro and nuclear power. These sources of renewable energy continue to add novel elements to the mix.  So, too, do local crises of over-saturated local environments, economic mismanagement and urban sprawl. But these factors are dwarfed in importance by the increasingly dominant role played by climate-driven anthropogenic global climate change, which is fundamentally transforming both the world as a whole and the local to the extent that the ecological and geo-political systems that underpinned economic growth and colonial power are fundamentally altered.   A final element contributing to this growing perturbation is the advent of insatiable consumer culture, which is fundamentally understood by the anthropologist John Graham Kerr as the ‘epidemic’ of which the planet is but a symptom.   So, too, with cities: they consume more and more of the built environment, and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic of the biennial has its roots in the nineteenth-century art biennale, but it is now being heavily questioned. The major art biennials of the 1990s are now some of the most expensive and experimental performances of the art market in the world, and the privatisation of artistic property is also being promoted. The biennial as a global icon has become ever more complicated, and its social functions have come to dominate its cultural functions. However, it is clear that as the biennial market has become ever more internationalised, the biennial as a global icon will remain vital for the survival of humanity. 	The biennial as a ‘container in a global market’ is a global industry. It is a global phenomenon with a global relevance. 	The museum has a particular role to play in this narrative of the biennial as a global icon. Its rich history and its global circulation allow it to detect developments that may signal the beginning of a new industry, or</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic of the biennial follows the long-term trend in cultural capital, that is to say, the increase in the share of art and biennials in the global aesthetic – a more integrated and visible form of art that is more easily accessible through museums and the social sciences – rather than the more acute market logic of the art market. The biennial as a global icon is thus a mode of globalisation that seeks to position itself as a ‘good’ in its own right, presenting itself as a counterintuitively simple form of globalization. It is a symbol of technological creativity and a platform for the very real explorations of how art and biennials become embedded in cities and how that impacts culture and society. 	However, the biennial as a global icon is also a mode of slow cultural and social change, in which art and biennials play a minor role. Globalisation, as we know, is accompanied by ever-expanding biennials and art institutions everywhere</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic of the biennial is deeply imbalanced, and as a result the world’s urban centres are increasingly represented by images of cars, factories, streets and parks. Art and biennial exhibitions are still overwhelmingly located in the main urban centres, but as recent biennials have shown, this is not always the case. Take, for example, Venice Biennale, which brought together biennials from many cities around the globe, and from all over the place. In the late 1990s, Venice Biennale focused on the city’s architectural heritage, as well as its cultural heritage, in an attempt to bring the disparate elements together to make a coherent urban heritage. In the early 2000s, Biennale of Sydney used its venues to bring together artists from all over the world, in an ambitious program that took the city’s cultural form and applied it to the traditional biennial form. In 2015, the inaugural Venice Biennale took place, and though it</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic of the biennial follows the logic of ‘profits and losses’ as a function of urban growth,6 and the biennial’s high profile, commercial and institutional activities can be seen as a ‘glimmer of hope’ in the city’s economic potential.7 	However, as the biennial has become more international, its cultural capital has also declined. For this reason, biennials are less able to sustain their public engagements, especially in developing countries where the biennial market is highly fragmented and poorly mapped. The global market for art and art products is a globally visible market with a clear comparative advantage, but this market has been slow to materialise due to its internal contradictions. Urban art is materially produced in and through the cities, but its market potential is significantly less developed in the developing world. Biennials also face an uphill struggle in countries with a low share of their national populations in the urban centres, where access to art resources is</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic of the biennial has attracted art-historical and contemporary artworks that can be auctioned to fund the art-historical and contemporary works that are normally exhibited in the dominant cities. Though these works may be significant in their own right, they are seen by many other art-historical and contemporary works, such as those from the New Museum, as well as biennials themselves, as little more than collections of historical art. So a globalised, urbanised biennial, while providing valuable work in its own right, is not the dominant form of art form today. 	The art biennale has become somewhat outdated in its focus on the New Museum and its collection projects, but it is important to note that these have been around for some time and have distinct collections-per-biennial ratio. 	There are also a number of smaller, regional biennials, some of which are growing in membership and popularity. 	Myanmar Art Biennale, for</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic of the biennial, which generates globalisation’s willingness to subsidise art and its production through exhibition and trade, must be considered in the context of a globalised social and cultural economy. If, as some critics have suggested, the biennial is becoming less and less a museum of modern art, with occasional exceptions (Paris and London especially produce artists and curators regularly), a ‘generational study of art’, as museum and gallery have become, in fact, essential to a biennial’s function. 	Though biennials are museum-like in appearance and function, they are, within the larger context of art museums, branching museums, and are, within the museum-like structure of biennials, quasi-public galleries. This characteristic, though rare, occurrence is also characteristic of other types of museum, such as oral museums, which are, as Charles Bukowski puts it, ‘timeless collections of oral history … documenting a historical moment</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic is highly stylised and differs from that of contemporary biennials, whose focus is primarily on the artist’s, curator, or institution who organises the art or exhibition. As a result, the demand for art and biennials in the dominant centers of the world is now highly contingent on the artist’s – i.e. highly urban – location, and the city is the dominant user of the art and biennial products. The biennial as a temporality may also vary in its spatiality. In the twentieth century, biennials were primarily published in periodicals, and the biennial as a ‘weekly or monthly journal’ is the dominant electronically distributed form today. However, the biennial as an exhibitionary form has expanded to include all kinds of places, including ‘havens’ and ‘lakes’ where art is often actively promoted, and many contemporary artists find themselves. In these and other places, biennials can</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic is parallel to that of contemporary real-estate investment and financial speculation, where the dominant markets are those that promote or enable the development of high-end residential and cultural products. The dominant cultural capitals of the world today are in fact those cities where the monolithic ‘New Economy’ is being implemented, where art and culture are the new ‘assets’ and ‘tools of the postindustrial society’.5 	Yet despite the predominant economic fixation on urbanisation, the dominant forms of cultural production today are those resulting from the active involvement of citizens in the management of their own cultural spaces. Indeed, as the biennial has multiplied in size and become more globally visible, the surrounding locales that have been built on its back have also become less so – reduced to rubble in the great sweep of the urbanisation process. As a result, the biennial has had to fight two wars, one on its own borders and one on the terrain of its own self-build</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic has placed a premium on the consumption of art and biennials in the dominant cities, while simultaneously distorting the ‘infrastructure’ of art and culture so that it is not possible to consume them entirely. 	Though the dominant cities are the direct sites of art and biennials, they are also major consumer markets for art and biennials outside the dominant cities. For biennials, this has meant the emergence of a globally recognisable ‘dominant art’ category within museum bookings, along with a regularly recurring ‘infrastructure’ of art and culture that can be researched and collected. Biennials have become globalised in this way, and their consumption has spread to every corner of the planet. As a result, the infrastructure of infrastructure has become a source of political, economic and social upheaval. The dominant form of art and biennials in the dominant cities is likely to continue to be the complex assemblage of art collections, current</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The biennial’s capacity to make visible, through its economic activities, the social and ecological activities of its location, while also its capacity to engage with and change its location – i.e. its city, but more specifically, its shadow economy – is a further point of convergence for the project, as various economic and cultural activities take place in and around the biennial.4. The biennial as a global icon. 	Though the biennial is a globally recognised art form, its current global popularity comes primarily from a globalised urban center: New York, London, Johannesburg. The other ‘main’ cities account for approximately 10% of the biennial market, with the remaining cities comprising mostly of European cities. As the biennial has become more globalised, so the demand for both art and biennials has expanded. Consequently, the share of art and biennials in the ‘dominant’ cities has also increased. This economic logic of the biennial has attracted artists from all over the world, and has encouraged artists from developing countries to come and work in the dominant cities. In these years, however, the biennial has been forced to account for some of its growth, because of an increasing number of artists choosing to exhibit their work in the event rather than in the ‘micro-biennial’ category. Consequently, the dominant cities have had to create a new ‘brand identity’ to stand out from the crowd. 	Within this new ‘brand identity’ category, the dominant cities have attempted to create distinctive cultural experiences through craft and urban activities, mainly through the ‘biennial (business, cultural, educational) model’. However, this model is no longer enough for the dominant cities; artists, curators and arts administrators worldwide now demand that biennial exhibitions target a city or region exclusively, and have become much more creative in their architectural, planning and other cultural activities. Moreover</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement of politics and government, and our own small role in creating and fuelling this dynamic. But it is also quite naive to deny the significant role played by cities and their inhabitants in this process. The role of citizens is critical, and it is this critical role that urban theorists and urban activists have largely neglected. Thanks to citizens' activism and their financial contributions, and especially thanks to the work of the Black-E and the Fight Club, there was much less poverty, much less homelessness, much less crime, in many areas. And thanks to the work of the Black-E and the other local groups, who brought together residents, community leaders, community planners and others with relevant skills to help implement the strategies of the early urbanists, much less is there today a segregation between rich and poor neighbourhoods.   A database of the Black-E’s activities in the area would allow us to learn about the political, economical, social and cultural dynamics of the area, and perhaps allow us</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement of politics and government, and as we have seen, this could have played a role in some of these projects. But there is growing recognition that these kinds of urban interventions are necessary for the sustainability of our cities and the growth of a certain type of urban fat, both culturally and economically speaking. The question now is how to get the necessary political will to implement these plans in the places where they are needed most – where the people with the skills, networks and connections to pull these projects off are most needed.  And how to make these cultural resources responsive to the needs of the communities they are intended to serve?  A place like the Black-E might be able to offer a solution to this conundrum. But how might we create such spaces that are not tied to specific constituencies? How might these be created and distributed through collective actions? These are questions that people with skills, networks and connections to bring these theories into practice are asking themselves and others. And if the answer to these questions is</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement of politics, and certainly not without the involvement of intellectuals and artists. However, their creative practices and their commitment to socially engaged practices dovetailed with the city’s rapid growth and changed needs. It is quite common for new urban centres to be founded on the back of a ‘rejection of progress’, as Grier put it. New urban centres brought with them a whole suite of values and practices that were both socially conscious and politically aware, but which were also, as is now the case, deeply lodged in the past. They also bred and bred: the rich and the powerful, the well-connected and the influential, the politicians and the museum heads, the museum visitors and the great artists and the curators. It seems that in an age of ever-greater connectivity and mobility, it is not surprising that in the past was also an issue. But in the age of the metainterface, and its accompanying theory, practice and theories, the city</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement of politics, economic development and urban transformation. But it is also quite false to suggest that all of this could have been achieved without it. The development and rhetoric of the 1990s was a combination of everything that the Black-E and the Fight Club had been working towards, and much more that came out of them. It is true that the rhetoric of urbanisation and development in the early and mid-1990s was much more abstract and emotional, and much more focused on individual forms of social change. But this abstraction and emotionalism was also deeply flawed. Urban theorists at the time tended to identify the social crises that were threatening to undermine the very fabric of the city as a social catastrophe, but this identification was often limited to specific social groups. In a very real sense, the social dynamics of the 1990s were already set in motion at this point in time. This is why, twenty years later, so many of those who joined the Metainterface project are still coming out of the</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement of politics, economic and social theorists, and we can also recognise from the outset that in the interest of full disclosure we would have to be able to identify with the urban theorists and urban designers who were involved in creating these developments. We could also identify with the urban poor: poor, in fact, who needed housing and were therefore attracted to the urban growth and the associated poverty alleviation programs. But this would only be possible since the city has become so multi-sourced and multi-functionalised. Cities now function as valuable real estate investments, and the rich and powerful alike often live there too. We could speculate that the emergence of new technologies such as Uber and Airbnb may make it easier to access these spaces, but this is at best a partial explanation of the explosive growth of these services, which draw on a driverless car and network of autonomous vehicles, and their clients, while at the same time displacing full-time workers and pushing many of the city’s traditional image-</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement of politics, the economic, cultural and legal systems, and without the participation of large numbers of citizens, since all of these play roles in making and giving cities shape. The role of urban planners and urban theorists in the 1990s was to a large extent defined by the participation of a relatively small elite of well-connected professionals, many of whom were connected to the city’s financial sector. These professionals had their offices in the US Congress, in the White House, in the IMF, and in the WTO. They had a mandate from the city’s finance department to undertake anything that could be seen as a ‘rebalancing’ of the urban landscape. These projects were to a large extent self-financing and ‘blind’ to the consequences. Most of us, myself included, were either completely oblivious or completely ineffective in our roles. The majority of us simply didn’t have the political or legal clout or connections to make such a radical change.</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement of politics, the city’s infrastructures, finance capital, real estate developments, cultural institutions, legal theorists and even philosopher’s to ensure that the social functions of city building were maximised. But the involvement of thinkers such as Wittgenstein, Benjamin, Thomas and John Urry helps to frame the city in a way that engages us and generates ideas that can then be applied to live and work in ways qualitatively different from those expressed by the city’s current planners and urban theorists. 	Urban growth in the US, 2007-14 GDP, US$ billions. Photo courtesy of the Bureau of Economic Analysis. 	Urban planners and urban theorists have understood the importance of public realm – the public realm – for the wellbeing of its inhabitants. But the infrastructural rationalisations of the city – its built environment, its financial sector, its social services – are primarily the expression of interests and institutions that benefit from</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement of politics and government, and it would be quite naive to say that all of it could have been avoided if it had been subject to the kind of political and economic domination that it continues to enjoy. But it is also quite possible that the activities described above could have been brought about without the involvement of such political and economic means. That is, government intervention could easily have been avoided through better planning and management of urban space. And perhaps it could be argued that in the wake of such governmental and economic neglect and mismanagement, urban forms emerged with such resilience and such creativity in the face of such economic predation. But this is not at all to suggest that such urban forms are not challenging and creative, and that their success is not due to the benign neglect that governments and affluent communities routinely show towards the common good, the poor and the underprivileged. On the contrary, it is to suggest that such challenges and creative activity must necessarily come with a price tag attached to them, and that this</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement of politics, and certainly not without the engagement of arts and cultural organisations. Nevertheless, there is a continuity and a power in this area, and this can be seen in the work of the Arts Council, whose work in this area is extensive and includes producing and publishing a number of books on a regular basis, publishing the current edition of which was published by Auspicious Circumstances Press in London on 18 February 2017.Download this article as PDFAuspicious Circumstances Publications2018-07-21Auspicious Circumstances.716.pdf#small5 September 21, 2018Auspicious Circumstances, London, EnglandLiverpool, EnglandLiverpool Biennial 2018PreviousNextAuspicious Circumstances, London, EnglandLiverpool, EnglandLiverpool Biennial 2018I. The Biennial Condition 	[I]n a nutshell, the problem with the biennial is this: it has become increasingly common for curators to become entwined in projects</text>
    <text>working basis for deriving data sets from the individual citizens of a particular area. It was a way to engage with what had become a very topicalised question in the area, and this was welcomed by many quarters. It is worth recalling that in the 1970s and 80s the Black-E and the Fight Club were the archetypes of a new wave of radical urbanisation in the area, and in the 90s and 00s there was the Metainterface project, which sought to bring together film, architecture and public art in an interactive way. We could say that in the 1990s and 00s the availability of space and access to amenities changed in ways that stimulated and even capitalised on this in order to cope with an ever-more urbanised population, more and more dispersed urban space, more and more strangers and exotic places all around us. Such urban developments required a new set of urban planners and urban theorists to put the pieces back together. It would be quite naive to suggest that all this occurred without the involvement of politics and the civil rights movement, nor the fight for equality before the law. Yet the sheer scale and character of these movements and their influence on urban development is a testimony to the resiliency of inSite’s commitment to exploring alternative modes of organising and living in the city. We could also say that inSite’s involvement and in particular in its use of crowdfunding to fund critical projects in the area is a testament to the power of grassroots organising. But this is also a testament to the persistence of imagination, the ability of activists to engage with and create change in a way that is personal and collective in nature. It is this ability to engage with the city in a way that is above and beyond the formal that is traditionally associated with urban practitioners and policy makers, but which in the past was often limited to a specific elite of planners, developers and academics. It is a testament to the power of grassroots organising and imagination. This kind of responsiveness to the city is precisely what</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths. The only way to address such work is for the city to embrace the art, and so the biennial has to be inclusive. In doing so, it must actively intervene, break new ground, and so forth. Otherwise the festival becomes a museum and the biennial a set of curatorial narratives. This is the only way to inhabit the potential transformative power of art and culture in the city, and so the biennial has to be radically inclusive. The only way to inhabit the potential transformative power of art and culture is for the city to embrace the art, and so the biennial has to be radically inclusive. The only way to inhabit the potential transformative power of art and culture is for the city to embrace the art, and so the biennial has to be ecstatically distinct from the city. Otherwise, the festival becomes a set of curatorial narratives, and the biennial a set of cultural experiences – one of the main reasons why artworks are often present in such formats, rather</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths. The question of cultural trauma and power is one that undermines and undermines our ability to inhabit socio-politically relevant territory. In the end it is the city that produces the art, and the biennial that can define its own space and time.This is the equation that the artworld and biennial faces today. The art world and biennial are often accused of becoming too present, and so is the festival’s share of the otherwise invisible providing a false sense of presence. But the art world and biennial weren’t always accused of this. Its roots are in the art market that emerged during the colonial period, and its current form emerged as a response to the market’s devolution. The market brought artists and their audiences into ever-larger markets, and so it is the market today that produces artists and their narratives. So the art market and its narratives didn’t invent the art biennial, but the art market did in part invent the art</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths. What would you do if the city is on fire? 	In a way, the burning of the Biennale as a spectacle of the city over the past twenty years has triggered a number of changes in the city that are pivotal in terms of the development of the biennale as an institution and the city as a place in which art can be produced and enacted. These changes have been complex and uneven, and the key to understanding them is in-depth research, but I’m interested in two main points: (1) what the artworks and artists produced during the duration of the event as a whole, and (2) what can be learned from these collections. 	The burning of the Biennale as a spectacle of the city has two impacts: it generates new modes of cultural organisation, and it destabilises curatorial efforts. New curatorial approaches to the event are often instigated by the burning of the artefacts. The Biennale created a self</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths. When life gives you lemons, you’re actually going to need a long vision.When the art is moving in lockstep with the narrative, we’re actually witnessing a very real transformation. We’re witnessing the emergence of a rebellious new temporality, one that doesn’t necessarily align with the dominant social order. We’re starting to understand that the biennial is an ever present and powerful narrative device, that it’s just that we haven’t fully tapped into its potential yet. The biennial as a curatorial device is a powerful narrative device, because it establishes a precedent and tells a story through a sequence of actions. The important thing is that the story is told. Otherwise, we’re saying, ‘That could have been us’. And that starts to unravel at certain points. But that story is far from being told. When the story is told, the city is often quite a distance away,</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths. The Liverpool Biennial has done this with its proposed 'City of Culture' concept, which proposes a complicated reconception of the city that exploits cultural resources in a way that exploits labour and produces new kinds of cultural practices. In a way, the artist and his team at Liverpool Biennial may be right. But that comes at a price. The city is a complex system with multiple infrastructures and overlapping publics, and the potential for economic exploitation is great. The biennial’s eventual commercialisation depends upon the city remaining completely oblivious to the festival’s growth and potential. If that happens, then the festival will cease to be, and the relationship between the two will have to be negotiated. The hope will always remain for the sake of artists and the city that these relationships will last, but the city has to be prepared to absorb a substantial loss if that happens. In the event that the biennial does go out of business, the city will absorb a significant loss</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths. In these rare cases, the artists and curatorial duo find themselves the objects of cultural critique and satire. But this is rare, and often negative. The city tends to portray the arts in a certain way, and so the biennial’s first few years are crucial in building its public consciousness and imagination. If it doesn’t have these early foundations, it will crumble. Our only chance, as artists and critics, is to build them up and ultimately to alter them. We must build them up slowly, as the festival approaches, and then, once the critical mass of tourists arrive, to let loose with wild parties and riotous celebrations. These are the only two possibilities for cultural impact that matter to us.The other is for the city to provide the tools and capacity to produce its own art. That is, the tools and capacity to produce its own art with which to address the mass of people who visit the city, and beyond. The city can produce its own bi</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths. That happened with the Biennales of Sydney and San Francisco. It happened in Liverpool with the Liverpool Biennial and so on.The idea of the festival as a potential site for cultural exchange arose in response to this space‑fringeing, anti-social, counter-cultural edge. It became an instrument for the socialisation of cultural elements within cities and thus an object of cultural making. It was, in other words, a vehicle for the establishment of a shared cultural experience, in the form of a biennale, without which there would be no biennale. That is, without the social interactions that would allow us to identify with the cultural elements in the city and thus foster the shared space-fringeing, anti-social cultural desires of the times. So the idea of the festival as a potentially transformative event became one that would make a mess of things, would break things up, would alter them in unpredictable ways, but would also set things in motion by triggering cultural</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths. That is, the art works at the centre of narratives eventually have the power to alter our perceptions and alter how we internalise those narratives. The likelihood of that happening is remote, but it has happened. In the case of the Biennale of Sydney, the new narratives surrounding the city were spun by and large by artists and cultural strategists, driven by a determined mayor, and then challenged by a city council that saw the artworks as a potential investment in the future of the city. The biennale was an art institution in its own right, capable of sustaining a culture of its own making, and so the city entered into a kind of symbiosis with it. The biennale became a site for cultural exchange and cultural creation, and so the cultural council could allocate spaces and personnel and so forth, but it also functioned as a site of eventual decline and destruction. It could either produce extravagant new displays of art, or it could mop up those spaces with derelict</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths. In other words, the biennial is an artefact, and not a project that represents the city as a potential future.** 	In the event that we do become culturally aware, transformative possibilities emerge. But we don’t get culturally aware until much later, and so the transformative possibilities we do acquire are very late in coming. That is, the cultural narratives we produce are often painfully dated, or in some cases downright wrong. So the art that is created in the biennial and displayed at the museum is built on very strong foundations of historical facts and figures, but also on the fact that these figures are often precursors to much more oppressive cultural narratives. This historical juncture is a critical juncture. It isn’t sufficient for the artist to construct a cultural narrative that is accessible to a global audience, but must create a context in which the artist can operate in a way that is both historically accurate (i.e. the artist has to be able to</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which represented a departure from the usual curatorial format, was the work of a curatorial edifice, and so the equation that made up the difference between exhibition and festival became problematic. The festival was a curatorial enterprise, and so its boundaries became important, and so was its real power. But the biennial had no real power, other than to the city. It functioned as a space for cultural exchange, but it didn’t have any inherent cultural power. That was the art of the possible. The city was always the star of the show, and so the city was always the object of desire and the object of abuse. The city was a mass of potential fuck-ups, but the artists and the curatorial duo rarely experience them firsthand. Thus the festival, as a potentially transformative event, has an inherently precarious relationship with the city. It is often the case that the artworks at the centre of cultural narratives actually break our narrative, forcing us to confront uncomfortable truths. The festival is the one place where these cultural narratives are allowed to be actively enacted, and thus has a much more direct and immediate effect and consequence on the city. Nonetheless, the relationship between the two elements is what I consider to be the 'real life' of the city, and the biennial must account for this. The real life is always experienced through the subjective perceptions of the artist, and so the biennial must also be an event that operates from the self. It’s as if these two elements are working in concert to create a new kind of cultural practice. But this is still a problematic equation. The city is the site of the potential failure of such a project, and so, as a precondition, it’s worth asking: what kind of failure is this?  The answer is ‘life’, and ‘the thing that happens in it’. ‘The thing that happens in it’ can either be great or</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could
    <text>human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could be created through this new understanding of reality, but we do know that these imaginary worlds would have to be of a certain kind – and that is a big if.In the spirit of the biennial, we decided to start by asking, what does it mean to create a realistic and responsive interface? We were also curious about how the different disciplines of art, design, architecture and media might engage with this new understanding of reality. We were especially interested in ways in which art, design, architecture and media might produce new modes of interaction and behaviour through this new understanding of reality. We wondered what kinds of dynamics might arise between artist, public, public sector, artist, curator, media, artist, public, media, architecture, urbanist, urbanist, journalist, politician, historian and online communities? The responses suggested some surprising divisions. Some curators and art professionals saw an opportunity to make things more realist and individualistic, to embed more social value in what they were doing, and to</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could be produced by what kinds of technologies, and how these might be organised and controlled. The ability to imagine new ‘realities’ – to believe that there could be different kinds of worlds, with or without humans – seems to have been crucial for the kind of critical imagination and imagination that led to some of the most important advances of the twentieth century.This kind of technological creativity is now being reproduced at an unprecedented rate, and although there are many who would like to see it spread all over the Earth, there is no guarantee that this is going to happen. And although there are elements of technological rationality – the ability to replicate and adapt existing technologies – there is also a fundamental sense of unreality about the world that is now unfolding all around us, in ways that are impossible to assimilate or control. As a result, there is an explosion of imaginary alternatives everywhere, which constantly challenge and innovate ourselves, constantly contradict ourselves and are ultimately rejected by the status quo. This kind of technological creativity</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could be created through what kinds of technologies. But at least we do know that futuristic possibilities are possible, and that is reason to dream, to strive for that kind of realism.Download this article as PDFWendy ChunWendy Chun is the Curator of Architectures at the Ontario Museum. Her research interests include the social construction of urban environments, the amelioration of poverty and inequality, and the protection of the natural resources of Ontario. Her publications include the award-winning ‘Urban Form: Politics, Architecture, and Ontario’s Cities’ (with Jennifer Stranahan and Adam Szymczyk) and ‘Building a Progressive Urban Future’ (with Tamsyn Sitre) in the Journal of a progressive urban organization. She is the host of The One Show: Curating Uncategorized and Other Hosts of People (2014-16) and the upcoming ‘60 Minutes’ documentary series.Her writing has also been published in the New</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could be imagined, but there are signs that the potential is there. In fact, as biopolitics and biopolitics of imagination grow in importance, we can see this as a main thrust of a project now at a very early stage, with important exceptions – the construction of infrastructure, for example – as well as ideas and procedures that are now being refined and applied at a global scale.In any case, if we can draw a parallel between the cognitive architecture of artificial intelligence (AI) and the cognitive architecture of the human brain, we might be able to imagine what kinds of worlds possible worlds would be like if AI were made accessible. If this is possible, then perhaps what we don’t yet know is that there are ‘better’ ways of organising the world, and organising humanity, through what might be called a proto-apparatus, something that is both flexible and part of a larger framework. In this sense, then, we can say that there are different kinds</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could be created by dream, but it looks like there are two ways to think about it: ‘There is ‘reality’ as imagined by an author/authority, or ‘there is reality as observed and described by others with skills, abilities and conscious experience’. There are of course different ways of putting it, and there is no way to know which is which. It is also possible that in the future, scientists and others with appropriate understandings of the technology to allow for the creation of ‘real’ may one day be able to create ‘imaginary’.In the meantime, the question remains whether the capacities we have now are enough to allow for the kinds of change that could result from dreaming, or whether the kinds of dreaming we’re trapped in right now are only ever going to happen in very specific and constrained circumstances. This raises the possibility that there are ‘other worlds’ out there, beyond our own, that we</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could be made by embedding sensors and computers in our bodies, but it is becoming increasingly clear that we’ve all become cogs alongside one another. It was also one of the main reasons why, six years into the new millennium, we did not experience the financial crisis that would have opened up all those zeros and ones in investing strategies. We did not have to live through the pain and suffering associated with the crisis, but knowing how it would affect us and our families, we could have. This is one of the reasons why, six months into the new millennium, we are experiencing a distinctly different kind of crisis. It is not the kind of crisis that requires us to accept a global economic order; nor is it the kind of crisis that forces us to adopt a particular set of values or to adopt a particular political orientation. We do not yet have a satisfactory answer to the second question, but it is becoming increasingly clear that the first question will remain unsettled.The emergence of new</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could be imagined, but one can imagine worlds in accordance with certain ideological frameworks. In other words, the notion of reality doesn’t really distinguish ‘real life’ from ‘imaginary life’ – much less distinguish real life from imagination.  In fact, the idea of reality as defined by rigid categories is part of what gives the West her concept of truth. If and when the technology to allow for such an interpretation comes about, it will mean that ‘truth’ can be imagined in quite other terms.The other reason why the fascination with the singular may be starting to wear thin: what is imagined may no longer be imagined. This is one reason why, during the 1970s and 80s, the arts were often cited as a way to combat materialism, and it is one reason why, during the 90s and 00s, the biennial became a yearly ritual. It may no longer be the case, but the impulse to imagine new imaginings of</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could be created through this new science, but there are some indications that things could be imagined more constructively than through traditional means.For instance, the possibilities for the reduction of bureaucracy and the emergence of a libertarian society were imagined through the magic of transparency and accountability. By making things so that information about them could be gathered and communicated, this new science led to a dramatic reduction in government power and responsibility, and to a libertarian society in which individuals could exercise their individual rights irrespective of who was benefiting from those rights. This is not to say that this kind of reduction in state power and responsibility was a given or inevitable – it is to say that it is far from being the case today. And the reason is that we have also expanded and politicised our scientific and technological imaginations in ways that render the possibilities of ‘reality’ even murkier and murkier still.Modern science and technology usher in a new era of unprecedented possibilities for everyone, but especially for those who are oppressed or</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could/should be possible in the future, but we do have some indications that we could create within our own heads, or construct from scratch, imaginary worlds that are indistinguishable from the real world, in much the same way that the Flat Earth Society imagines an ideal future. Ideas of beauty, of course, have a tendency to dominate reality, so it is easy to demonise the influence of beauty. But there is some evidence that these ‘ideal forms’ of the future might be more aesthetically pleasing than the present and might foster a kind of poetic inspiration that helps us to imagine more beautiful things. For instance, the aesthetic quality of the graphic novel covers of the future might derive more from the aesthetic considerations of the art that is being produced in the form that is being reproduced than from the aesthetic considerations of the art that is being reproduced in the real world. So there is some truth to the idea that the prettier the cover, the more likely it is that we will end up</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology have moved beyond the laboratory and are now embedded in our lives, interwoven with our daily interactions, making it possible to imagine ever more fully realized worlds. This is one reason why dreams, especially lucid dreaming, are often quoted as a sign of things to come. If and when the technology to allow this becomes available, it could change the very definition of ‘reality’ – one that is no longer defined by formal or organisational criteria.This raises the question: what constitutes ‘reality’? The concept of ‘reality’ seems to have been formulated in such a way as to allow for the possibility that elements of ‘real life’ could be imagined, but also for ‘imaginary things’ to be imagined in accordance with formal and ideological frameworks. This kind of thing is possible, although much more difficult and ambiguous than it sounds. We don’t yet have a satisfactory answer to the difficult part of figuring out what kinds of worlds could be made by replacing humans with robots, but there are indications that the outlook for our future, at least, is likely to be quite different from the one we currently inhabit. It is possible that in the future, we’ll be able to look back at the human species and think, not about what happened in the past and future, but instead what we did in the past and in the future.This could mean something along the lines of: in the present, there’s the contemporary urban environment; in the future, there’s a post-material world; in the present, there’s ‘primitive’ cultural zones like the Andes or the Arctic; in the future, there’s ‘civilization’ based on the accumulation of historical ecological systems that humans have created. There’s also a chance that these cultural zones will merge with existing human-made urban landscapes, becoming indistinguishable from their natural surroundings; this is the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the mission to celebrate the city’s rich visual heritage through innovative cultural and educational activities. It features new media and performance techniques, including that of the artist Marina Fokidis. The Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology are both located in Los Angeles.  [2] Gareth White, ‘Habitable Zone’, in Science &amp; Culture, Vol. 141, No. 3 (2014), p. 731–73.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in The Arts and Director of the Program in Cultural Studies and Theory at the California Institute of Technology, where she investigates the politics and values of ‘biennialism’ and the contemporaneous development of new forms of art and culture in the region. Her research interests include biennials, art world collapse and contemporaneous forms of cultural production, and her work has been exhibited in institutions including the Museum of Modern Art, the Australian and Mexican</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the mission to celebrate the city’s rich literary and visual heritage through collaborative art projects. In 2017, it opened the San Andres Museum of Modern Art, the largest remaining collection of modern and contemporary art in Tijuana. [2] The Palestinian Centre for Human Rights, 2017. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Centre for Human Rights.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication and Culture, Renfrew College of Art, Design and Technology, University of Toronto and holds the Canada Research Chair in Cultural Studies. Her research interests include the Middle East and North Africa, art and architecture in the Palestinian territories, and the contemporary art of the Gaza Strip. Recent publications include: “Policing Art in the Middle East” in The New York Times, 'Art as Public Conflict” in The Washington Post and “Civil War Wax' in the New York Times Literary Supplement. She has written for The New</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the mission to celebrate the city’s rich visual heritage through innovative cultural practices that capture its essence across multiple media. The Museum of Modern Art features works from the Museum of Tijuana that address the city’s diverse visual cultures through a visual language that incorporates indigenous, Mexican, European and other visual languages. The Museum of Tijuana Art is the only art institution of Chihuahuan descent in the United States.

[2] Doha World Architecture Book 2016, Qatar: Qatar Museums Authority. Retrieved from: http://www.qatar.org/en/museums/en/book/world-architecture-edition-2016/chapter/50/doha-world-architecture-edition-2016-qatar-museums-authorities-world-europe-2/architecture/text/emea/downloads/emea1856.pdf#.UXZ3LPX4mEtY</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the mission to celebrate the city’s rich Mexican heritage through art and design. Its main branch, the Modern and Contemporary Art Museum, is located in the California Academy of Sciences.  [2] See: http://www.tomart.org/english/en/history/index.html [3] http://www.tomart.org/english/en/history/summary.html [4] http://www.tomart.org/english/en/history/index.html[5] http://www.tomart.org/english/en/history/summary.html[6] http://www.tomart.org/english/en/history/index.html[7] http://www.tomart.org/english/en/history/index.html[8] http://www.tomart.org/english/en/history/index.html[9] http://www</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the mission to commemorate the city’s rich cultural heritage through innovative means that contribute to the creation of new ways of living in Tijuana. http://www.tijuana.org/en/en/history/about/mohja... 	[2] Referred to as ‘the marathon’ in the book, the notion that the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology created and revived Tijuana was developed through a three-year long process of incrementalism, a political and literary genre that sought to reconcile the apparent contradictions of modernity and neo-natalism by which modernity was characterised. In Tijuana, the word ‘marathon’ was made redundant: under constant surveillance and military presence, ‘marathons’ are now common occurrences, as the result of a combination of federal, state and municipal policies that regularly transgress the city’s natural geographical limits and legal jurisdiction. In the book, author John Lee</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the mission to celebrate the city’s rich cultural heritage through art and education from a broad range of creators and curators. The Museum of Modern Art/Caltech has been planning the California Museum of Playground Design for twelve years, and the California Institute of Technology has been planning the Temple-Mead Johnson Pavilion, a new art space for the Tijuana Art Biennale, since 1995. [2] Waugh, Robert. Culture and Anarchy: Culture and Anarchy in Contemporary-Day Life. Princeton, NJ: Princeton Architectural Press, 2016.Download this article as PDFEduardo PorterEduardo Porter is a filmmaker, writer, and producer. His works in the social and political domains include the ‘Cuba Libre’ social movement, the ‘Green Movement’ environmental organization, and the Tijuana Five. His most recent project was the TEDx Talk: Utopia in Crisis - Part 2, a social documentary that premiered at</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the primary mission of preserving and sharing the histories of technology from the city of New York through art, research and teaching. It is the only institution of its kind in the United States.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor of Visual Cultures and a Special Advisor to the Director of the Museum of Modern Art and a former Curator of Art for the Women Photographers International, Los Angeles, and Los Angeles County Departments of the Museum of Modern Art, New York. Her research interests include the history of visual art in the US, with a special focus on the art of visual culture in the Occupied Palestinian Territory (2006-2015). She is the author of Systems of Historicity: Art, Architecture, and the Political (2009) and the blog www.jessicaorock.com, where she shares her research and analysis. Feminist Journalist and FilmmakerTania BrugueraTania Bruguera is a writer,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the mission to celebrate the achievements and creativity of Tijuana through modern and contemporary art of all kinds. The museum is the final resting resting resting resting of the former home of Art Francisco Núñez De la Torre, the US-born Mexican-American illustrator best known for his contributions to the Atlas Shrugged series of US pulp magazines during the 1930s and 1940s. He is also the editor of Pacific Rim Press (1978–1987), the definitive Mexican American biweekly. [2] David Leacock, The City and the City (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1996). [3] John Urry, ‘The City: A Social Science Research Centre’, in  	Urban Studies (1962–78), Vol. 18, No. 1, pp. 1–27, accessed November 2018. [4] Le Corbusier, Le Devoir, p.259. [5]</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the mission to celebrate the city’s rich and diverse cultural heritage through collaborative exploration and, in perpetuity, to chronicle the lives and works of its inhabitants. 	[2] The Journal of Historical Art, Vol. 27, No. 1, Spring, 2015. Available at: http://www.utexas.edu/hist/jha/publications/2015/spring/the-journal-of-historical-art-vol-27-issue-1-spring-2015.html (accessed September 2018). [3] Una Filho, ‘Toward an Ethics of Histories’, Journal of Anthropological Methodology, Issue 3, October, 2014, p.12.[4] Idem, ‘Histories, Present and Future’, Journal of Cultural Studies, Issue 3, October, 2014, p.1–26. [5] Simon Critchley, ‘On</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist - The Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority.PreviousNextThe Palestinian Centre for Arts and Cultural Studies, 2012. Photo courtesy of The Palestinian Authority. 	The Museum of Tijuana Art [1] The Museum of Tijuana Art is housed in the Art Gallery of New York. Its mission is to commemorate the city’s past, present and future through a multi-disciplinary exhibition and cultural initiative. It is a hybrid institution: exhibiting work from the past, present and future, as well as contemporary art and design from all over the world. It includes projects that respond to current social and political conditions in Tijuana, such as migration, violence and repression. It also includes projects that advance the interests of a particular nationality, such as the Tijuana Science &amp; Technology Museum. The Museum of Tijuana Art was established in 2014 by the Museum of Modern Art and the California Institute of Technology, with the mission to encourage and discover Tijuana’s modern art through research-based exhibitions, writing and public programs. The Museum of Modern Art is the institution of choice for research-intensive exhibitions, especially those concerned with Tijuana’s digital culture industry. It offers exhibitions and lectures in both English and Spanish, focusing on the city’s past, present and future.The California Institute of Technology is the world’s most prestigious institution for its work on technology. It is the California Institute of Creative Technologies, the birthplace of Google. It was founded in 1847 and the world’s oldest continuously operational university, now a multi-disciplinary center of creativity and knowledge. It has a total enrolment of more than 5,000 students from eighty-five countries. The Museum of Modern Art is currently planning to open a new division dedicated to the museum and its collections. [1] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, 2005. Photo courtesy of The Whitney</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city council
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city council or mayor is to the people, and the people only, not the institutions. The city will not, as yet, reap the benefits of the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The arts will have to be found in places that matter, and will have to compete with other values, in order to be taken seriously. If the arts are to remain a significant part of the city’s cultural landscape, then a fundamental change in mindset and organisational practices will have to happen, and rapid innovation and new ways of doing things promoted. 	[1] Excerpt from The Biennial Condition: Art as Intrinsic Cultural Terrestrial in the Age of Intangible Value.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the Winchester School of Art, University of Southampton. His research interests include the cultural ecology of intangible cultural assets (prior to</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city council is to legislate and establish the policies that will enable the city to be run effectively and efficiently, and this will have to take into account the needs and preferences of a diverse range of people. It is very difficult to prescribe what a diverse range of people in a city should and cannot do, because of the inbuilt bias against any group that does not share the city’s core interests and paradigms. It is also very difficult to undo policies or activity that are in place because of the systemic nature of the crisis, and because of the persistence of power structures that are deeply embedded in the city. It is critically for the future of a city to be found in consultation and negotiation with people rather than in strict linearures determined by the rich and powerful.  	The promise and art of the 21st century is that we are social creatures who value community and care about each other. But what we mean when we talk about ‘community’ is that people come together across</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city council, and by extension, the mayor, is to live up to its elected mandate. The city council has the final say on development, but even if it does not concur with the mayor, it can still make development decisions that can be repeated by the mayor. The fact that the city council is composed of artists and residents with a strong collective memory of where and how things were done in the city, and an explicit collective responsibility not to let down its guard when things are not going well, is a huge asset when trying to put things right. 	One final potential dimension to consider is the relationship between protest and the arts. I have been struck by how many of the biennials that I have studied, the cultural orientations that they have attempted to put forward, have been about issues of social and political concern. The issue of economic development, for example, or the role of the arts in curbing the excesses of capitalism. In a way, I believe that the city is</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city council is to legislate, and as such the city will most likely dominate the range of possibilities open to it when it comes to arts and culture. The biennial will most likely dominate the range of art and cultural products available to New Yorkers, and city councils will most likely dominate the range of art and cultural experiences available to them. It is important for artists and artists to find common ground, because otherwise there can be conflict. When the Board of Trustees at the Brooklyn Museum voted to create a Community Arts unit, the first move was to create a dedicated unit to support the work of the unit, and for the next eighteen months the board and the artists were free to spend as they pleased within the unit. But the Brooklyn Arts Collective soon found itself caught in a tangle of overlapping units, many of which were as independent as the board itself. The board’s move to arm the unit with funds quickly became a problem, since the money raised through membership fees went straight to the</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city council is to legislate the city’s resources and to protect those resources from anyone but its own citizens. The council will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial while remaining true to its civic obligation to protect the resources. A formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable, but until now the biennial has focused on its own interests and loyalties, and city council members have been particularly susceptible to the institution’s temptation to align resources with the council’s priorities. A city council that reflects the community’s will and resources should reflect the people’s will, and preferably both. If the city cannot or does not want to support a biennial in its core areas, it should at least actively seek alternatives. 	The application of creative localism to the biennial format may be viewed as a starting point for future research and development, but it is far from a panacea. The main driver of the biennial remains</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city council is to legislate the public good, and the biennial will most likely play that role pragmatically, ethically and financially. It will most likely engage in cultural-political activism on a local and national level, and it will likely collaborate with other arts institutions, non-profits and other grassroots grassroots groups to achieve social and political change. It will likely produce informative art that informs decisions about housing, employment and other aspects of the city. It will most likely produce artists whose work is not beholden to a corporate commission or institutional patronage. It will likely produce innovative and sometimes revolutionary art that disrupts existing art forms and systems, and it will most likely engage in economic self-sufficiency for communities to be in a part of. 	The question is whether the biennial will have the political will or the guts to challenge established art forms or power structures or both, and whether or not the biennial can assemble a diverse group of artists who share a commitment to challenging inequality and injustice in ways</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city council is to legislate the rights and duties of citizens. The powers delegated to it by the Constitution and its laws should be used to the maximum extent permitted by the constitution and the laws. However, the council’s powers should be creative and responsive to the needs and desires of the people, since the council’s roles are ultimately dependent on the votes of the people. Creative and responsive city government is the real answer to the art deco curse, and creative and responsive art should be encouraged. 	[1] See, for example,   	http://www.newyorker.com/archive/2016/10/the-curse-on-new-yorker-201... (accessed October 2018). 	[2] Hank Gruen, ‘The Art Newspaper’, in ibid., p. 19. 	[3] Gruen, ‘The Art Newspaper’, p. 19</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city council or mayor is to the people, and to a state within the state, and to such a council or mayor, and to such a list. The people may withhold consent, but at the end of the day, the state will always act with the requisite majority. The office of mayoralty remains politically vulnerable, but the office of mayor remains vital to the establishment of an independent local government. The progressive wing of the Democratic Party is expected to rebound in value with the election of Jeremy Corbyn as Labour leader, and the mandate to push through a number of exciting initiatives, including an ambitious programme of universal childcare, a public debate about the role of art in local government, and the establishment of a new museum movement. The city will have to find creative ways to partner with an independent biennial in order to sustain it. The question becomes what limits will the biennial place on this office, and when, and how, those partnerships will be formed. Biennials are expected to grow in their localities</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city councilor or mayor is to do the will of the people. The task of city planning is to find creative ways to use scarce public resources to meet the collective needs of the city. The city must find ways to support creative industries, and any city councilor or mayor with a budget capable of supporting a biennial is encouraged to seek such support. The biennial is a technological revolution in how art is produced and consumed, and the city is becoming more like Silicon Valley. But it is also a creation myth, and art is expected to be a core constituent of the future urban future.  	Art must be protected from commodification. If the biennial is to achieve widespread cultural consumption, it is imperative that it is produced in a socially just and environmentally sustainable way. Biennials can and should be produced in ways that benefit the local communities they are created in, and in a city. It is also important to note that the creation of a biennial is not a job for engineers or</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial will be remembered as a watershed event in the city, but the city will not, as yet, reap the benefits from the art and cultural dollars that were siphoned off by the opportunists. The city will have to rely on the arts for a large proportion of what it produces, and the biennial will have to be a significant artistic tool alongside its legal duty to preserve historic buildings and sites as urban ruins, and its cultural responsibilities to draw people to places and activities, and to those activities, in order to keep people coming back. This will be a tall order, and the biennial will most likely do better when it is independent of the city. The city will have to actively seek out and support a second biennial, although a formal partnership between the city and the biennial would be desirable. The city will have to find creative ways to support a second biennial in its city without becoming dependent on the institution. 	Finally, the most basic and important job of a city council is to legislate and establish the policies that will enable the city to be run effectively and efficiently, and to balance the demands of different government agencies in an effective and responsive manner. The responsibility for art and culture in the city is currently held by the city council, but with the notable exception of historical curatorial appointments, which are retained by the biennial, the council has little real power in this area. The biennial should assume all the responsibilities of the city, but it should also assume the autonomy of its artists, curators, and organisers, in order to maximise the contributions of the city to the art and culture export market. This is the model that the biennial should adopt in its relations to the neighbourhood, and particularly to the residents of the neighbourhood. The biennial should research and present the geographical locations and the history of the neighbourhood, taking into account recent social and spatial changes in the neighbourhood. It should also research and present contemporary cultural practices and practices in the neighbourhood, taking</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
