<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and
    <text>present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and it is an approach to art as a public-private partnership. The technology permits the viewer to ‘pin’ or ‘pin point’ the locations of images viewed, thereby enabling an artist to create a graffiti-like representation of an area through photographs taken within the area. 	Artists who constructively employ Inventor can expect to be approached by city governments, local authorities, heritage commissions and other interested parties who demand to know where their art is located and how it is used. The technology has the potential to make a huge impact on cultural consumption and circulation, as well as the making of art itself. 	However, this potential can also lead to the dystopian situations described above. In an age of ever-more transparent apps and sites of interaction, mass mediated narratives and ubiquitous data feeds, it is imperative that artists and art institutions take the technology and its accompanying culture of the present, and not the mediated narratives of the mediated forms. This means developing alternative cultural practices</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and it is being done in concert with the implantable image-recognition chips currently embedded in users’ bodies. 	However, these advances also make the images that are displayed publicly available – making it easier for a vandal to replicate the work and spreading the crime of cyber-bullying, fake news and other urban ills further. 	The right to ‘know’ is increasingly important in a digital age, and is increasingly being restricted in ways that are not always obvious or visible. As a result, and perhaps this is a feature, but some of the most interesting and influential work of art that I have encountered in the past 30 years has been done in ways that demand transparency and which are often quite subversive. 	Sometimes the work done in ways that are opaque and which seek to conceal the underlying structures of power and wealth that are slowly but inexorably shaping our cities and our world is quite beautiful and moving and speaks to the true intentions of those who created them.</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and it is the new way in which images are taken. It is said that the social implications of this new world are profound and growing wider than the geographical borders of any one location. There is a palpable sense that images from anywhere can connect with images from anywhere and thus create a tapestry that stretches across the world. 	In the age of the internet and smartphone users everywhere have access to these images and can produce and share images of their worlds, there is a palpable need to understand what it is that is happening in their cities and in their neighbourhoods. In TOR, we are experiencing a new phase in which the operations of cities are monitored and controlled via algorithms. These algorithms allow for the discovery and construction of ever larger metapromises – ‘datacenter ecosystems’ – that not only house software but also images and multimedia elements but that are capable of supporting the activities of nations. The importance of this kind of infrastructure cannot be underestimated. 	In an increasingly urbanised world</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and it is a new paradigm for how images are produced and consumed. It is this paradigm shift in the way images are made visible and understood that creates and contributes to the potential of new media. 	As a result of this paradigm shift, there are new technological paradigms emerging alongside old. Some of these are as benign as they are intriguing: imagine a tool that collects images from websites and places them at the right place and time, allowing users to ‘stack’ images, create fold-outs or collages and share them with others. 	Others are far more sinister: think of the effects of ‘near image capturing’ and nasi image gathering, where images are treated as data points that are malleable and which can be used to produce ever more immersive and contextual images through the deployment of algorithms, machine learning and other computerised techniques.[6] 	Such is the  	transnational dynamic that characterises contemporary technology. It is no exaggeration to</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and it is an increasingly prominent use of social media as a tool of the dispersed and the fablée. 	[i] The Intifada’s original name was the Arab Spring, but over time variously rendered as ‘The Palestinian Intifada’ or ‘The Arab Spring’, depending on the region from whence it came. See: http://www.activistpost.com/2014/09/intifada-new-name-of-crisis.html?utm_source=gp_old&amp;utm_medium=social_media&amp;utm_campaign=Feed_the_Catapult&amp;utm_content=Feed_the_Catapult_internal_feedback&amp;utm_campaign=Feed_the_Catapult_internal_feedback_external_feedback_social_media_feedback_20140330_e18de18c-97ba-4e97-bfc1-b</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and it is the contemporary condition as a result of the constant stream of data and images that are captured and exchanged on a global basis. But what is the experience of living and working as an artist and as a practitioner of what can be conceived as ‘technological literacy’ in the age of the images?1. Sophie Hope Franklin,  	Unravelled (film still), 2017. Shot on location in Egypt, the film explores the effects of the revolution in Egypt and the Middle East. 2. Actress  	Catherine Hall,  	Rose Tattler (film still), 2017. Shot on location in the US, the film examines the effects of the 2016 US presidential election on artists and their work. 3. Creative Director  	Sophie Hope Franklin,  	Unravelled (film still), 2017. Shot on location in the US, the film examines the enduring value of archival sources and the necessity to</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and it is the new way of gathering and contextualising information. It is this new sensorium that enables artists to create worlds according to predetermined parameters, but it also enables investigative journalists to renditions of cities according to predetermined parameters. This is the case with the inquiries undertaken by the New York Times and CBC into the activities of the Israeli police during the 2014 Gaza conflict, as well as with inquiries into alleged police complicity in the 2016 Barcelona terror attack. 	In these new media contexts, the online and augmented image is closely related, but distinct from one another. New media often employ innovative means to engage users’ time, such as augmented reality, social media or live streaming, while old media typically employ traditional media to engage users’ time and data. With the exception of live streaming, all media technologies now produce images or documents that can be retrieved at any moment, whether it is due to user-uploaded media or organisational innovations. Hence, in the age of social media, it</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and it is a kind of citizen science. It is an innovative and powerful way to collect and aggregate knowledge, but it also carries with it serious questions about the values and ethics of artistic and social practice. 	[i] Lewis, Lawrence. Nation Building: The Architecture of the New Urban Order. New York: Cornell UP, 2012. [ii] Cochran, Mike. Inhabitant. New York: New Directions, 2012. [iii] Thayer, Noel. Imagined Communities: Social Practices and the Politics of Intimate Media. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 2006. [iv] Thayer, Noel. Material Identities: Sex, Politics, and Media. Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2008. [v] Thayer, Noel. The Limits to Capital: Media, Intimate Media, and the Pursuit of Happiness. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1995. [vi] Thayer</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and it is a new paradigm for how images are produced and shared. The adoption of social media and the virtual has fundamentally transformed how people gather information and communicate. It is no longer possible to ‘monitor, capture and transmit’ as the original imaging medium was. Social media has created an environment in which ‘ordinary people’ can come to know and identify with images and videos, and have a voice in the creation and presentation of images and videos that are then assembled and communicated. A new paradigm has emerged: the social. A paradigm defined by the fact that social media has empowered creative people to come to know and identify with images and videos and that then be assembled into websites and multimedia works that then engage audiences around the world. 	The social media generation is both artists and thinkers who have taken the social image and multimedia as a tool for creating worlds within works of art and visual media. They have produced works that are both accessible and extraordinary in their own right. Some of these artists</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to produce a trilogy of four-panel essays, each of which represents a single city or town in the United States or Canada. The essays are a response to a question: what is it like to live and work as an artist in the present, and in the age of social media? The project was launched on GoFundMe and raised over $32,000 in five months. The images below are two examples of one such project,  	Inhabitant, and the second project,  	Postcards from the Intifada. The images were created using Inventor , a new online toolkit used by artists to investigate their own images and the world through the lens of technology. 	In this new media age, the images displayed on a website or app are augmented by data about where, when and with whom they were viewed. This phenomenon is sometimes referred to as ‘near image capturing’ or ‘nasi image gathering’ and it is said to increase the productivity of surveillance and political control operations. The use of code and image processing in the design of media is widespread and extensive and  	The Inventor website includes a free app for the Apple Watch that records where the images were viewed and with whom they were exchanged. 	In the case of live events such as protests and urban hibernation, the need to constantly update the website with fresh images of activity arises. In both  	Inventor’s case, the need to monitor one’s position arises from the continual need to track protestors, and in both cases the monitoring of such movements is of course illegal. However, the inroads made by the site-specific tailored app Inventor.com towards understanding urban conditions, and the inroads made by the in-app purchase of images, can only be interpreted in such a way as to support the political, economic and social strategies of the state. 	The political</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others.
    <text>present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others. The project has been featured in numerous books, including from Australia, Canada, the United Kingdom, France, Germany and Spain.  The project was also recently selected by Digital Art Gallery as one of the 50 Most Innovative Art projects of 2014.  Finally, in 2015, the project was selected for Digital Public Library of the Year from the Arts Council Otago’s Innovators Programme.RT:HMR has been intermittently online since 2010, when the artist Jeanne van Heeswijk presented a series of paintings in Liverpool Docks, featuring the HMR project’s images, as part of the 'exhibition home' programme. In 2011, the project was re-launched as ‘The Residency’, with artist-in-residence Dr Jeanne van Heeswijk as curator. In 2015, the project was re-chosen as part of the National Portrait Gallery’s Future Art bursary programme, although it is not always</text>
    <text>present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others.The project has been featured in numerous books and periodicals worldwide, including New York Times bestsellers, including 'The Fragile City: Art, Architecture, Modernism' (with Nasser Rabbati), 'Remaking the Middle East' (2015), ‘The Fragile City: Art, Architecture, Persian Gulf' (2016), ‘Building a Future' (with Nasser Rabbati, ‘The Fragile City: A Journal of Building Cultural Futures’) and ‘Building a Future’(2017) by Nasser Rabbati, with contributions from Arwa Aburawa, Teju Alo, Fatma Al Sahlawi and Imran Hashmi.  The project has been featured in numerous academic and building cultural monographs, including Routledge International Publisher’s Companion to Cultural Studies (2017), Lester Thurow, Cultural Capital (2017), Lester Thurow, Building the Future: Developing Middle Eastern Cities for Modern Capitalism (2017), Lester</text>
    <text>present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others. The project has received funding from the British Museum, National Museums Liverpool, Natural Science and Topcents, as well as numerous individual donations.RT:HMR was inspired by two previous, smaller projects: 1. The British Museum's Egyptian Painting project, launched in 2002, and 2. The Italian Painting project, launched in 1993. Both projects sought to map, document and reactivate the ancient history of painting in Egypt and Syria. For RT:HMR, the goal was to map, document and reactivate the ancient past in order to produce a digital repository of images and texts from the region. The algorithms used in these projects were borrowed from data mining and paleontology, while text mining and website design were heavily based on ‘Open Access Media Technologies’, including RTLabs’ text based annotation and ‘Text Mining’ software.In order to make the social networking and mapping projects accessible to as wide an audience as possible,</text>
    <text>present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others.More than 20,000 people have signed up for beta-testing the platform since its launch on 6 September 2014.  The platform has been adopted by a variety of academic and research groups, including Oxford Dictionaries, National Atlas Society, Royal Geographical Society, Museum of Modern Art, Museum of Modern Art, Royal Roads and National Museums Liverpool, whose collections are extensive and permanent online sources of knowledge about British architecture.Oxford Dictionaries, which organise and annotate the Oxford English Dictionary, recently launched a new online edition of the dictionary, taking the word ‘eternal’ to denote the essential meaning of the word.Oxford Dictionaries, English and Danish translations of the New York Times, 2017. Image courtesy of Oxford Dictionaries.Download this article as PDFJacob Lund, Verina Gfader, Anne Kølbæk Iversen, Christine Kempe, Susanne Sundblad, Thomas Allsen, Benjamin Swinburn,</text>
    <text>present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others.Over the past years, RT:HMR has continued to be a project of collaboration between the National Museum of Canada and the Royal Ontario Museum, Hamilton. In 2014, the Museum of Modern Art’s collection was acquired by the Royal Ontario Museum, Hamilton. The purchase enables the Museum to offer a full range of exhibits, programmes and activities, including new works curated by Professors Eyal Weizman and Yaacov Kristal. In addition, the purchase supports the Museum’s work-in-progress exhibition, ‘RT:HMR: The Complete Works’, which continues to be published in the magazine, as well as online at www.rt.com/humor. The collection and its contents will be on display at the Royal Ontario Museum, Hamilton through February 2019.Download this article as PDFEyal WeizmanEyal Weizman is Professor in the Department of the History of Art and Design at McGill University and holds the Canada Research Chair in</text>
    <text>present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others.  In 2015, the project was expanded to include an interactive map that enabled users to travel to locations in Pakistan and Afghanistan where the effects of the Khyber Pass were being investigated.  In 2017, the project was redone as ‘Khyber Pass Volcano’, an active volcano that emits ash and ash particles at a rate of six million tonnes per year.The Khyber Pass is a tectonic plate that is rapidly eroding the Himalayan tectonic plate, which is slowly but inexorably adding mass to the region. As a result, the climate is warming at a rate of 4.3 degrees Celsius per decade. If emissions continue to grow at the current rate, we must urgently address the problem. The Khyber Pass Volcano’s ash fall from the mountain threatens over 1.8 million hectares (4.6 million acres) of cropland and is fed by a steady stream of groundwater pumped from the nearby Tsetse River Valley</text>
    <text>present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others.RT:HMR has been featured in a number of books, most recently by Graham Hicks (ed.), Building Stories: Photography, Resistance, and Release in Situations of Global Instability, New York and London, Routledge, 2015. Both the UK and US editions of the same journal have kindly agreed to publish an edition of this book in English and Russian, with an introduction by the author and the title translated into both languages.Download this article as PDFGraham H. Hicks, The Politics of Art and the Postcolonial Condition, Cornell UP, Ithaca, NY, 1988.Graham H. Hicks was born in Dublin, Ireland. He is the author of From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Social Media and Postcolonial Theory, Cornell UP, Ithaca, NY, 1986.He is a Distinguished Professor in the Departments of Communication Studies and English and General Education at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, Canada. He is the editor of the journal Communication Research &amp; Practice,</text>
    <text>present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others.  The images have been used in advertising campaigns, publicity campaigns, documentaries and books. The project has been featured in a number of academic journals including:  one by John Urry, former chair of the HMR Research Centre, University of Sheffield (2014); one by Prof. Jin Wan Kim, Director of the Korea Advanced Research Institute, Korea, USA (2015); one by Prof. Harald Uppen, Director of the Centre for European and Asian Cultures and Research, King’s College, London, UK (2016); one by Prof. Evelyn Forget, Curator of Collections and Exhibition Research Lab, National Museums Liverpool, UK (2017); one by Prof. Usha Bhadwal, Curator of Collections and Exhibition Research Lab, National Museums Liverpool, UK (2018); and one by Prof. Syed Kamal Adal, Curator of Collections and Exhibition Research Lab, National Museums Liverpool, UK (2018).  The project has been featured in</text>
    <text>present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others.  The project has been featured in other media including The Economist, The New York Times, The Washington Post, The Wall Street Journal, The New Republic, The Atlantic and many more.  The project has been featured in a number of documentary films, including 'Empire Strikes Back', which was shot in New York and London, respectively.The HMR project has also been part of the exhibition catalogues of the Museum of Modern Art, Museum of Modern Art (New York: Museum of Modern Art, 2012), the Museum of Modern Art, Museum of Modern Art (London: Museo de Arte Contempora Modern) and the Museum of Modern Art, Museum of Modern Art (New York and Berlin).  A special edition of the Museum of Modern Art, Berlin, was recently presented by the Museum of Contemporary Art, Los Angeles.Download this article as PDFRachel Grant and Vera RubinBoris Groys and Sonia Dutt 	The idea that resistance can be creatively modulated through art</text>
    <text>present an online project to digitise all the images from the HMR project’s website. The project was developed, lead by Prof. Eyal Weizman, Prof. Yaacov Kristal and Prof. Yaacov Oransky. The aim of the project was to create a platform, accessible from anywhere in the world, that would continuously update, annotate and present the project’s content online.  The project was launched on the social network Twitter under the handle ‘RT:HMR’. It quickly gained global attention and has been featured in numerous publications and online journals.More than 20,000 images from the project’s collection have been published in various languages, including in six issue ‘Grand Central Dispatch’ (2013), ‘Grantham Research &amp; Data Solutions’ Journal (2014), ‘NR’ journals including ‘The Scientist’, ‘The Lancet’ and ‘Science’, among others. The project has been featured in several documentary films, including the award-winning ‘Earth Up’ journal documentary ‘Earth Up’ (2014).  The project has received a multitude of awards and mentions, among them: various European, American, Russian and Israeli cultural organizations; a Wellcome Trustee funded project led by Prof. Dr. Ronen Ludwig and Prof. Dr. Steven Gilchrist in London; The Gilchrist Foundation for Advanced Study in New York; the German Council for an Open University in Berlin and the Nordic Council for an Open University in Stockholm; and the Danish Council for an Open University in Copenhagen.  The HMR project has also been featured in numerous non-fiction books, most recently from the Nancy and Norman Whiteside Foundation, the Whitechapel Foundation, the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, and the Huntington Library, among others.   A digitized version of the project’s website is hosted on the Whitechapel Foundation�</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there among citizens? What kinds of publics are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires can be built? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among citizens? What kinds of repertoires are there among</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there to which the institutions of the city can tap to form a dynamic, responsive citizenry? What kinds of publics are there to which the city cannot tap? What kinds of capacities and what kinds of publics are there for the reconstruction of the city? What kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information about the English version of this issue brief, see the online issue brief [PDF] and the issue brief [PDF] on the site of the Biennale.) What is the meaning of ‘New Urban Space’? What is the urban being made to be when destroyed? How is the urban being made alive? How is the social being made alive? What are the modes of engagement of the urban? What are the spatial forms of the city? What are the social relations between city and country?). How are the capacities of the city formed? How are the spatial relations between people made visible? How are the capacities of the city reproduced through the act of making visible? How</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there for individuals to operate on the city through their actions? What kinds of publics are there for the city to transform through the actions of organizations? What kinds of capacities are there for the city to invest in the future of the city through policies that positively impact the capacity of the city to create and consume value? What kinds of capacities can the city afford to leave to future generations? What kinds of capacities do the family offer in return for the future to foster collective action? What kinds of capacities do the city not have the ability to share? What kinds of forms of power are available to those with a stake in the future of the city? What kinds of forms of power are exploitative? What kinds of prejudices are rife in the current urban landscape? What kinds of forms of power are they creating? What kinds of power is available to empower citizens to take back control? What kinds of power is available to dispossess citizens?This issue brief proposes a set of questions that draw upon experiences from a</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there for action? What kinds of futures can be imagined for the future inhabitants of the city? These are questions that can be asked and answered in this issue brief, while sketching out the issues and possibilities of a possible future in which the capacities of the city are radically transformed through the actions of individuals and/or non-state actors. If implemented fully, this ‘transcendental building’ imaginary assemblage could radically rearrange the urban landscape, creating new kinds of places where people can be free from the state and confined to certain kinds of space, perhaps far removed from the current situation of acute scarcity and diffuse spatiality that characterises modern cities. This is not to suggest that such a scenario is without risk or hardships, for the inhabitants of the city would still remain subject to the whims of economic development and the whims of state power. But the possibilities offered by the activity set out in the issue brief, its liberatory aspects, and its ability to generate new possibilities for the</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there that can be served by a biennial? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) What kinds of curatorial approaches are there to curating the biennial? (For more information, see the appendices.) When, where and with whom is the biennial at its most effective? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) What kinds of curatorial approaches are there to curating the biennial in a way that engages with its historic sites and places, but also with the ways in which they are affected by art and urban development? (For more information, see the appendices.) When, where and with whom is the biennial at its most vulnerable? (For more information, see the appendices.) When, where and with whom is the biennial at its maximum possible? (For more information, see the appendices.) What kinds of curatorial approaches are there to curating the biennial in</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there for the biennial to build on? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) What kinds of publics are there for the biennial to actively participate in? (For more information, see the biennial website.) What kinds of ethical dilemmas can be posed by the biennial in the service of generating knowledge? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the biennial take part in a culture war not initiated by it? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) What kinds of forms of cultural negotiation are possible between present and future urban centres? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) What kinds of forms of cultural negotiation are possible between public and non-public space? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) What kinds of forms of cultural negotiation are possible between</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there to which individuals can call upon to help in transforming the city? (For more information on the &quot;public&quot;, see the next issue of this journal.) What kinds of bonds can bind individuals together in the building of a public, or the making of an institution?) What kinds of bonds can bind individuals together in the making of an institution? (For more information on the &quot;school&quot;, see the next issue of this journal.) What kinds of frameworks or discourses about the city can bind an individual to the making of a public institution? (For more information on the &quot;street&quot;, see the next issue of this journal.) What kinds of frameworks or discourses about the city can bind an individual to the making of an institution? (For more information on the &quot;street&quot;, see the next issue of this journal.) What kinds of identities or groups exist between public and private spheres, between street and university? What kinds of discourses or identities can bind individuals to the making of a public or the making of an</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there to which the actions of individuals invite others to belong? What kinds of bonds can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief and the appendices.) What kinds of forms of community are there? (For more information, see the appendices.) What kinds of practices are there that call into being groups? (For more information, see the appendix.) What kinds of relations can ‘bottom-ups’ form between people? (For more information, see the appendix.) What kinds of practices invite others to join in a common pursuit? (For more information, see the appendices.) What kinds of practices invite others to participate in a shared fate? (For more information, see the appendix.) What kinds of understandings of the public do individuals share? (For more information, see the appendix.) What kinds of understandings of the social do institutions have? (For more information, see the appendix.) What kinds of understandings of the contextual do individuals have? (For more</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there? How can the capacities of the biennial take root in the city? What kinds of management practices can be adjusted to best serve the needs of the city? What kinds of curators can be brought in to direct the exhibitions, and what kinds of curatorial approaches can be developed? What kinds of research institutions and what kinds of student organizations can be supported? What kinds of partnerships can be forged? What kinds of local strategies can be developed? What kinds of committees can be set up to carry out research, and what kinds of externalities can arise when bound by a biennial? What kinds of legal structures can be set up to support the collection and maintenance of historical material? What kinds of instruments can be proposed to help curators do their jobs? What kinds of public agencies can be set up to carry out research, and what kinds of student groups can be supported in this research? What kinds of committees can be set up to carry out maintenance, and what kinds of student groups can be supported</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, its discontents and the issues that arise from them?]This issue brief responds to a specific proposal that emerged from the public, including from the USGS. It seeks to provide a sense of the kind of cultural capital to be built by replicating the cultural institutions of the past, using the technologies of the future to envision an alternative future for communities living in the cities of the future. The question that arises is what can be built on the foundations of the present, and what kinds of capacities can be built from the ground up from here? This issue brief proposes a set of questions that attempt to address some of these questions, while drawing on experiences from a variety of disciplines, including architecture, urban studies, geography, history and geology. The questions are: what kinds of capacities can be built? (For more information, see the issues brief [PDF] and the appendices.) How can the capacities of the city be transformed through the actions of individuals? What kinds of publics are there for a biennial to address? What kinds of curiosities are there for a biennial to enact? What kinds of actions are possible when certain kinds of people gather? When and where does the biennial promote social change? When and how is the biennial placed within contemporary art and urbanisation processes? When and how is the biennial placed within postindustrial urbanisation processes? When and where does the biennial promote participation in the urban renewal programmes administered by local authorities? When and how is the biennial placed within postindustrial vocational education and training programmes? When and how is the biennial placed within postindustrial art and design programmes? When and how is the biennial placed within postindustrial architecture? When and how is the biennial placed within postindustrial photography? When and how is the biennial placed within postindustrial video? When and how is the biennial placed within postindustrial sculpture? When and how is the biennial placed within postindustrial DJ (design and installation) programmes?</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator 
    <text>present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator at Welsh Streets; Tania Bruguera, Artistic Director at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Director of Research and Public Programme at The Welsh Streets; Carol Stokes, Artistic Director at Welsh Streets; Tania Bruguera, Artistic Director at Welsh Streets; Joasia Krysa, Artistic Director at The Welsh Streets; Ella Gibbs, Artistic Director at Welsh Streets; Dawn Lacy, Artistic Director at The Welsh Streets; Sally Brannan, Artistic Director at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Principal Curator at Welsh Streets; Dawn Lacy, Principal Curator, Welsh Streets Art Gallery; Dawn Lacy, Principal Curator, Welsh Streets Museum; Gareth Welsh, Principal Curator, Welsh Streets Art Gallery; Sally Brannan, Principal Curator</text>
    <text>present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator at The Welsh Streets; Sue Bell Yank, Artistic Director at the Welsh Streets; Deborah Lloyd, Artistic Director, The Welsh Streets; Dawn Butler, Artistic Director, The Welsh Streets; Jon Grant, Artistic Director, The Welsh Streets; Suzanne Lind, Curator, The Welsh Streets; Tom Waugh, Artistic Director, The Welsh Streets; Emma Hart, Artistic Director, The Welsh Streets; Sue Bell Yank, Artistic Director, The Welsh Streets; Tom Lox, Curator, The Welsh Streets; Janet Logan, Curator, The Welsh Streets; Ciara Graham, Artistic Director, The Welsh Streets; Suzanne Lind, Curator, The Welsh Streets; Tom Waugh, Artistic Director, The Welsh Streets; Janet Logan, Curator, The</text>
    <text>present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator at the Welsh Streets; Suzanne Logan, Curator and Co-founder of Welsh Streets; Thomas Welsh, Senior Lecturer in Art History at Oxford, and a former Curator for the Welsh Streets, and Carol Dewachi, Curator and Co-founder of Welsh Streets. The Welsh Streets Digital Archive team includes Elisek Dagset, Consultant Curator at The Welsh Streets; Sophia Lazaretto, Senior Lecturer in Art History at Oxford; Dirk Johannsen, Senior Lecturer in Art History at Liverpool John Moores University; Sophia Pavlova, Lecturer in Art History and Curator of Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University Museum; Guillaume Lotze, Senior Lecturer in Art History and Curator of Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University; Gareth Welsh, Senior</text>
    <text>present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Artistic Director at the Welsh Streets; Christos Mampouli, Artistic Director at the Welsh Streets; Ella Gibbs, Artistic Director at Glasgow Champs and Auspices; Ella Raicovich, Artistic Director at Tate Britain and TateDock, the international art dealer; John Moores University, whose collection of art is now the Royce W. Kellman Collection; The National Gallery, whose collection of art is now the Andy Warhol Museum; and The University of Glasgow, whose collection of art is now the Bucking Collection.  The symposium itself was part of the Tate Modern Art Conference taking place in November 2016. Previous programs have included Conrad Dyson, The Artist, 1963, the Gorbals, now living in their garden, Millionaire</text>
    <text>present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator at the Welsh Streets; Matt Welsh, Senior Curator at the Welsh Streets; Suzanne Rimmer-Hughes, Senior Curator at the Welsh Streets; Paul White, Curator at the Welsh Streets; Samson Kambalu, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Steven Welsh, Senior Curator at the Welsh Streets; Suzanne Rimmer-Hughes, Senior Curator at the Welsh Streets; Rafico Ruiz, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Bryan O’Rourke, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ciara Elliott, Curator of Education and Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; John Roper, Curator of Education and Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Peter McCaughey, Curator at the Welsh Streets; Tim R. Smead, Head of Curatorial Practice at</text>
    <text>present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator at The Welsh Streets; Mike Stubbs, Artistic Director at The Welsh Streets; Rafico Ruiz, Artistic Director at Welsh Streets; Ella Gibbs, Artistic Director at The Welsh Streets; Wendy Harpe, Artistic Director at Welsh Streets; Nina Edge, Artistic Director at Welsh Streets; Shankley and Ciara Gill, Deputy Artistic Directors at Welsh Streets; Tania Bruguera, Deputy Director, Welsh Streets and a key role in the development of Welsh Streets’ programming; Bruno Latoury, Deputy Director, Welsh Streets; Bryan Breslin, Artistic Director, Welsh Streets; Emma Froese, Artistic Director, Welsh Streets; Andrew Gow, Artistic Director, Welsh Streets; Mike Stubbs, Assistant Artistic Director, Welsh Streets; Shankley and Ciara Gill, Full</text>
    <text>present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator at The Welsh Streets; Rob Goodfellow, Senior Curator at The Welsh Streets; and Maria Pavlo Lazarenko, Curator at The Welsh Streets. The symposium was co-curated by Kathi White, Curator at the Welsh Streets, and Rosie Cooper, Curator at the Welsh Streets Museum.The symposium offered several different ways to engage with the present and future of the city. These included  exploring the connections between the architectural styles of the past and the urban styles of the future; the art projects of the past and the projects of the future; and the role of the city in the social and ecological future. This symposium also presented the curatorial process that resulted from the symposium and its curatorial materials. These included a board of curatorial preferences for the future of the city, materials, 35 drafts of recommendations and presentations, and a research project. The board of curatorial preferences</text>
    <text>present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator at the Welsh Streets; Tessa Jurgensen, Curator at the Welsh Streets; Sue Bell Yank, Director at the Welsh Streets; Dora Russell, Director at the Welsh Streets; Emma Barnes, Director at the Welsh Streets; Nina Edge, Director at the Welsh Streets; Conor Burns, Director at the Welsh Streets; Bryan Hughes, Senior Lecturer in Art History at Liverpool John Moores Univeristy, USA; Bryan Waugh, Curator at the Welsh Streets; Nina Edge, Curator, the Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Director and Managing Director at The Welsh Streets; Nicola Kester, Artistic Director, The Welsh Streets; Sue Bell Yank, Director, The Welsh Streets; Conor Burns, Senior Lecturer in Art History at Liverpool John Moores Univeristy, USA;</text>
    <text>present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator at the Welsh Streets; Sue Bell Yank, Artistic Director at the Welsh Streets; Nina Edge, Senior Lecturer in Art History and Curator of Open Space at Ricardale in Paris. The Welsh Streets art department also includes Renee Roper, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Dora Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets, and Polly Billingham, Artistic Director of the Welsh Streets Creative Centre. We are deep in the conversation with each other and the Welsh Streets. Thanks for starting this morning, Sally. It was good to meet you too Nadine. It was good to talk to you about the exhibition we did for the Arts Catalyst conference in Liverpool last week. The idea of the biennale as a ‘curatorial exercise’ seems strange to me now, but I used to think that was the whole idea. Now I see that it�</text>
    <text>present an online project in which they’re asked to engage in a comment, critique or just have a word with a representative user of the site. The project was developed through a one-day symposium at the National Board of Artist’s Retreat, hosted by The Artist and his wife, Emma. The symposium was delivered by Maia Szymczyk, curator at The Royal, Glasgow, and presented in English, Polish, Slovak and Polish, with a Slovenian contribution.  The symposium itself was organised by Nedopolsky Museum, in cooperation with Welsh Streets, Glasgow, following a partnership between The Welsh Streets and RCA. The Welsh Streets curator team includes Katrine Dirckinck-Holmfeld, Museum curator at The Welsh Streets; Gareth Welsh, Curator of Public Practice at the Welsh Streets; Ellen Gibson, Curator at the Welsh Streets; Kate Rutter, Head of Communications and Advertising Strategy at The Welsh Streets; Alex Boyd, Curator at The Welsh Streets; Meehan Crist, Curator of Public Practice and Arts Practice at the Welsh Streets; Bryndis Sexten, Director of Partnerships and Partnerships, Welsh Streets Museum; Dora Meehan, Curator of Public Practice at The Welsh Streets; Suzanne Rimmer, Artistic Director, Welsh Streets Gallery; Bryndis Sexten, Director, Welsh Streets Gallery and Associate Professor at The Adelphi Institute, University of Glasgow; Peter McCaughey, Artistic Director, Welsh Streets Gallery; Loraine Rimmer, Artistic Director, Welsh Streets Gallery; Dora Meehan, Curator of Public Practice and Arts Practice, Welsh Streets Museum; </text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way
    <text>present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way to bring together the different strands of our cultural histories and our ethnographic and archival resources. In doing so, it would provide a base to start a conversation about culture and displacement and to initiate a more nuanced analysis of the present.’3 And, according to the Museum of Modern Art’s Deborah Levy, ‘The project has triggered a conversation about how art and cultural resources should be distributed in the city’, while at the same time contributing to the construction of a permanent biennial that will ‘reanimate cultural spaces and inspire a new kind of urbanity’4 in the city.5 The conversation has triggered new questions and ideas, and it is this ongoing process of dialogue and innovation that generates meaning and excitement for the city, yet is also deeply uncertain and unstable. Indeed, as the project evolves, it is ever-vigilant against displacement, which is a fact of life for many people in the city. In the words of Benjamin</text>
    <text>present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way to show the connection between the politics of representation and the politics of habit, and also to look at the impact that art is having in terms of the collective memory.’3 In San Francisco, a project like this would seem to make perfect sense, given the city’s chronic homelessness crisis and the museum’s frequent public programming, but there is much more going on behind the scenes. In fact, in some ways the project embodies the contradictory aspects of the museum’s mission: on the one hand, the museum is trying to make a name for itself in terms of the new curatorial appointments it is making; on the other, it is also trying to build long-term relationships with key community groups in the city who will be able to shape the museum’s future direction. The answers to the latter question are more political and subtle. After the election of Donald Trump as US president, the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Art in New York decided</text>
    <text>present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way to show our works in the city, so that the local community and artists could become acquainted, and also to show that we were aware of the issues at play in the city.’3 The project was developed in close collaboration with the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art and the Civil Warbler Foundation.4 The Civil Warbler Foundation is a not-for-profit public charity founded in 1903 by the San Francisco Art Biennale Board, which is a division of the Los Angeles County Historical Commission.5 The mission of the foundation is to support and preserve the cultural resources of the city’s historic districts through preservation and promotion of ethnography and ethnography-ancient art and related media through research, writing, and exhibition making.6 The Civil Warbler Foundation is a not-for-profit public charity established in 1996 and is chartered as a Corporation in the City of Los Angeles. Its mission is to conserve and enhance the cultural resources of the historic districts,</text>
    <text>present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way to bring the different cultural resources of San Francisco together to explore how the art and culture of the city interconnects with the cultural resources of the surrounding region.’3 This event was inspired by the book Culture and Anarchy: Social and Political Developments in Latin America and the United States, by Mireya Lopéz de la Torre, a conversation that took place during the 1970s and 80s between the author and the Museum of Modern Art staff.4 Sofía Olascoaga, ‘Curator in Residence at the Museum of Modern Art’, explains that the Museum of Modern Art was originally established as a residence for avant-garde artists, and that its mission statement reads as a ‘statement of intent’ that the museum could continue to exist independently: ‘The Museum of Modern Art will be a place of encounters, a laboratory for experimental and critical art, a place to host curatorial activities, and a place</text>
    <text>present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way to create an interactive space in which people could come to understand and connect with the issues and ideas raised by the cultural commission’s thesis. This interactive project would then be used as a teaching tool by the museum and other art institutions, and it would provide the framework for further research and development. […] Once we had conceptualised the project in terms of movements and trajectories, we then asked ourselves: how could the art form be used to actively create change?’ We then asked ourselves whether the cultural commission’s thesis was correct, and if so, how. We then asked ourselves whether the cultural commission’s intervention was necessary, and if so, how. We then sought an understanding of how the cultural commission could contribute in a more significant way to ending the ongoing social and political crisis that the city is currently embroiled in. We wanted to know how the biennial could be more effectively organized around the curatorial agenda of the museum, while</text>
    <text>present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way to bring together cultural resources from the two cities, and also to observe how the two exhibitions would complement each other. For the next part of the series, we wanted to create a cultural workshop specifically for the purpose of the exhibition, and for that we invited artists from the two exhibitions to create a new type of cultural centre for the exhibition, one that would be situated in the city and entwined with the cultural exchange taking place between the two exhibitions. This would mean combining the cultural resources of both cities, while remaining separate, but also integrating the cultural exchange between them in a way that would permit cultural activities to be held in both cities’ museums but also in other art centres and in the community spaces that artisans offer in the other city.’3 This cultural workshop model is similar to the one proposed by the Biennale Committee for the first time in Amsterdam.4 The new centre would offer both a physical exhibition space and a cultural centre for the exchange of cultural knowledge</text>
    <text>present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way to come together as a community of artists, curators, artists’ friends and artists’ families to explore how art, and specifically the work of artisans’ can play a role in creating alternative modes of being in the city’s urban landscape.3 She continues:  'The project came together because people in the area felt that they needed to be involved. In some cases, it was because the community members had an art project that they were proposing to do in the plaza, and the plaza was full of interested parties’s participation.4 There were several iterations of the idea, with participants proposing their own specific projects. The most ambitious and novel proposal, put forward by the community, was carried out in 2015, when the San Francisco Art Biennale commissioned artists from around the world to create a ‘performance space’ specifically tailored for the occasion. The project, entitled  	Stage 4: San Francisco’s Edge, brought</text>
    <text>present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way to bring together cultural resources from the two cities, so that the local community could draw upon these resources and create a cross-cultural context through which the collective experience of living in San Francisco might be different from the one experienced in the city.’3 This might be seen as an over-simplification, but the point was that cultural resources could be produced in the city through this process, in effect creating a hub of activity around the art produced in the city. In turn, this process could permit the creation of local cultural resources, through a collaborative process between the local community and the art world.  The Museum of Modern Art and the Annenberg Public Art Fund both supported this project, as did several other artists, including Monique L.S. Mandel, Joshua Clover, and others. The challenge then became to figure out how to deliver cultural resources in a way that is not exploitative, but nevertheless relies on the collective will of the community. These cultural resources would</text>
    <text>present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way to bring together the various strands of culture that intersect in San Francisco.’3 And, in a city with so many different strands of culture, this is a great way to bring people together across different cultures, different times and places, to understand how we as artists are part of this larger cultural system that is constantly reshaping itself.  	In both the case of cultural resources and cultural groups, cultural capital is a political concept. It is a way of conceiving of the past, making connections and imaginaries anew, and in that process creating historical narratives that are not reductive. Cultural capital is a production for power, and because it is continually produced, it must be reckoned with and reformed in order to be more effectively utilised. In that sense, I think the project reflects the political nature of the city, in that it is constantly being re-figurated and reshaped by forces beyond the city itself. In that sense, its political value is questionable, and</text>
    <text>present an online project that brings together the cultural resources of the two cities, while the second proposes an entirely new way of organising cultural activities in the city. The project was initiated in 2016 by the Annenberg Public Art Fund and the Museum of Modern Art in New York and is co-chaired by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art, both in New York. It is particularly relevant in this context, since the project received a major US investment from the New York–based artist Jorge Soleri, who is also the curator of the American Museum of Modern Art.1  The process began with a public art project in the streets of San Francisco, where participants ‘recycled and discussed the issues of displacement and activism, and the place of art and culture in the social and political landscape of the city’.2 Sofía Olascoaga, who directed the project for the Museum of Modern Art, explains: ‘We thought that the project would be a way to start a conversation, an open door, and invite community members from different walks of life and disciplines to participate in a very informal and personal way.’3 The project was then made into an exhibition, and the participants into artists, dramatists, curators, journalists and other curators. The fictional character of Joaquin Arias de la Torre was a charismatic, if somewhat paranoid, leader who instilled fear and uncertainty in his subjects; although there is some evidence that he may have simply relished the opportunity to reveal more about the city to a wider American public.4 Arias de la Torre was not alone in his pursuit of knowledge. Many other artists, including John Akomfrah or Wally Manraj joined him. Among them was Mathaf Kholeif, whose work 'Satanic Temple of Babylon' incorporated elements of both Iraqi and American religion. Kholeif is a member of the contemporary generation of artists known as</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by,
    <text>biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by, or even co-opted by virtue of, its subject-figure, the technological singularity. Consequently, it is the contemporary art of the postindustrial city that is actively engaged in reframing the role of the biennale, and in that respect it is essential that it is a place where contemporary art must develop if the biennial is to be understood as a cultural enterprise in its own right.  The Biennale as a Cultural Stage  Every biennale is a stage in a much broader cultural ecology articulated in the language of ecology, in that they are both encounters between artists and their audiences. They are both works in progress, in that they are constantly (re)negotiating who they are and what they are expected to become.  Biennales are acts of public expression, in that they are continually deployed to change and connect with new audiences and representational positions. At their best, they are encounters that invite dialogue and interaction, and at their worst, they are</text>
    <text>biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by, and dependent on, the cutting-edge of technology. However, the power of the art-historical curatorial posture that is part of the biennale is being challenged by a generation of artists and art-historians who are conscious of their civic and political responsibility. These generation of artists and art-historians are waking up to the fact that the biennale is part of a globally distributed artistic-political-ideological complex that includes, alongside major museums and biennials, independent art-historical curatorial initiatives such as, for instance, the Asian Cultural Centre in Tokyo or the Open School’s Open Road East Asia) and the The Art Newspaper’s publication of cross-cultural pieces such as Towards a World Urban Future. The generation that grew up on the biennale is conscious of being integral to a narrative of emergent forms of urbanisation that is increasingly globalised and mediated through technology. This generational shift in consciousness</text>
    <text>biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by, or stands in for, larger cultural systems. So it is more apt to see, listen to or take part in a performance by, say, the Occupy movement. The biennale needs to be seen to function in a broader cultural system, and that can happen through its performances, public exhibits and performances that invite in a broader audience. It is more credible when it is done by and for the collective, and engages with broader social structures and agendas. The Occupy movement, and its multi-year, multi-edition, even multi-edition, and future, are a good place to start. The biennale must be seen to engage with broader social and political structures, and to that end it is essential that it is productionally inclusive, so as to be able to tell a story across multiple sites and cultures. It is seen as art and not just another art form, with social and political underpinnings.Art is a powerful curatorial tool, but it is equally essential that</text>
    <text>biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by, or even co-opted by cultural Marxists. It is this double negative situation that the biennale has to address, and to some extent it does so well, while being itself a tool of, or in the presence of, cultural imperialism. Biennales, however, do have a place – along with nongovernmental art, nongovernmental arts, and other curatorial forms – in a cultural ecology that actively seeks to enrich, educate, or otherwise engage with the present and future of a city, nation, planet, or contemporary culture through its collection, production, presentation, or other curatorial activities. The biennale is an important event for a city, and a source of symbolic power for a city’s economy. It is a ‘once in a generation’ event that is traceable to the late nineteenth century, and continues to be so to this day. It is a ‘once in a generation’ event, and its contemporary repetition</text>
    <text>biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by, or even a co-performant with, the cultural industries on the one hand and, on the other, actively participates in, contributes to, or is a co-performant with, the historical curatorial systems that host those technologies. This last status, ‘performative’ or ‘cultural tourism’, is the dominant form of cultural industry today, and it is a form that art forms including biennials have adopted with increasing frequency in an effort to access and utilise through the ever-expanding, ever-flexible, ever-altered market of art value. The decline and fall of the biennale can be tracked to several curators and artists being displaced or leaving the industry at various points in the past 20 years (including the biennale of Sydney in 1991, when the biennale experienced its first art-specific curatorial reorganisation, and the biennale of New York in 1994). There are several factors that can</text>
    <text>biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by, or suffers from the effects of, the gerrymandering that characterises modern curatorial work. This is particularly true of those works that are non-biennale-curated, but is also true of biennials in general. So while the biennale has its own logic and politics, it is far too easily reductive to apply to them, or art in general. However, the biennale as an art form has the potential to produce long-term effects on broader cultural landscapes. These may include, but are by no means limited to: a) change in the identification of curatorial work with cultural landscapes; b) change in the identification of art with social formations; c) change in the identification of aesthetics with social circumstances; d) change in the construction of aesthetics around cooperation and exchange; e) change in the construction of aesthetics around social and ecological situations; f) change in the construction of aesthetics around the politics of language and the politics of occupation. In</text>
    <text>biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by, or is even directly influenced by, contemporary art. The curatorial, massive, influential exhibition is the locus of authority in this case, as it were. It is at the biennale that the artist is exposed to and creates his or her art. The biennale has a particular, though rarely explicitly stated, curatorial function. Its traditional, but often influential, function is to market an exhibition (or ‘showcase’ as it is sometimes called). The biennale, like every curatorial decision, is a function of negotiation and compromise. It is, however, considerably more successful at promoting a specific vision of the future to a specific audience when it is centrally co-conceived and centrally co-located in an institution or a city. Here, it is more clearly understood than at the museum or gallery. Its curatorial, mega-exhibitionary character is its greatest strength. It is understood by an ever-expanding, globalised public that is</text>
    <text>biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by, or worse, ‘invented’ cultural-political entities, whose original curatorial approaches to art are often reactionary and exclusionary. A viable alternative to the biennale is the city, which offers greater autonomy and political resilience in the face of technological change, and is thus a more suitable venue for the biennale to operate in its present form. However, the biennale has had to adapt its programming and policy of resistance to changes in the technological multiple, and those changes can be identified as the result of a ‘cumulative effect’ of social media and the hyper-commercialisation of art (Bartelsberg, 2015).  In the twentieth century, the biennale became increasingly influential in the diffusion of cultural capital as a globalised society. Biennales, along with the later generation of art collectors and collectors, are the collectors and travellers of today. The biennale has a materially regionalised characterised by connections to major cities that can</text>
    <text>biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by, or creates space for the presence of, technocratic governments. But the biennale has a particularly interesting and powerful toolkit for thinking about the world as a single engagement with the themes and practices of postindustrial society. That toolkit comes from a book by the same name, published in 1991, and is the result of a collaboration between the artist Sonny Bono and the historian Peter Harrison Burnett. The Bono-Healy book is a forceful indictment of the bombast and excess of the 1980s, and the book’s apocalyptic panorama is one that is particularly well-suited for the task of framing the present as a series of encounters between artist and public, from Bono to Damien Hirst to Matthew Freud and Rachel Carter to name only some of the more prominent. The narrative that emerges is that of expulsion from a community of artists and curators who had organised the Venice Biennale that year. The book is also a valuable contribution to understanding the phenomenon of urban sp</text>
    <text>biennials past and present have come to symbolise postindustrial capitalism and technological obsolescence. The art fair counter parts of the biennale circuit, whose curatorial approaches can be seen to follow the same logic. They promote the exhibition as a ‘big picture’, showing ‘the big picture’ in terms of global trends, to which they add ‘leapfrogging’–looking innovations that ‘prove to be game-changing’. In other words, they work to create visions of the future that are as if they were curated by, or in the presence of, the technological singularity. The biennale has an important place in the running of such singularities, and in that capacity it is essential that curators and artists are exposed to the latest avant-garde, critical or speculative art. The biennale itself, while essential in its logic, has limited authority in the world at large because it is often co-opted by, or even entangled in, contemporary capitalist circulation. 	But this co-option can also be seen as a kind of experimentation. The major biennale companies, including the British Museum, have spent decades trying to figure out how to align their curatorial approaches with the new technology of art-value extraction. The results are usually messy and inconsistent, and often counterproductive. So it is that biennales still try to make sense of the contemporary art-value economy, and the contemporary art-value world. But their current and previous incarnations are usually littered with paradoxes, ranging from the petty (the British Museum esthmaticensis) to the profound (the Biennale of Sydney) to the mundane (the Biennale of Venice). The current iteration of the Venice Biennale is no exception. In its current form, it represents a kind of transition, a point where the old and the obsolete meet, a kind of juncture where cultural capital meets biennale commerce.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy
    <text>present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy, Metainformatique, and the Metainformatique of Everyday Life – Essays and Reflections on the Contemporary Condition (1998). His most recent work, Using Media: Essays on the Art and Politics of Disappearance, was published by Verso in 2016.Joshua Freeman is co-editor of the online journal Stages published by the Museum of Modern Art, where he has written on a wide range of themes including the legacy of colonialism, modernity, and postcolonialism. His work has also appeared in publications such as the New York Times, the Los Angeles Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The A.V. Club, and numerous other periodicals and magazines. His latest book, The New Economy of Exhibitions: World Architecture, was published by Verso in 2016.Joshua Freeman is a writer, curator, journalist, and producer who has worked extensively in the Middle East and North Africa. His work has been featured in the New York Times, The</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy, Archive and Digital Cultures (2008) and the New Statesman: Understanding Digital Cultures: Entelechy as an Embedded Media Technique in Contemporary Art (2015). His work has been featured in numerous international and local magazines and newspapers worldwide, as well as numerous periodicals including the New York Times, Los Angeles Times, London Review of Books and Time, among many others. He is currently executive director of the International Centre for Studies in Palestine and the Museum of Modern Art in New York. He has been a lecturer at the New School for Art and New Media in the New York University Graduate School of Journalism. He has edited the online journal of the Black Arts Workshop, the online journal of the New Arts Movement, and was a lecturer in Communication Studies at the University of Toronto.He has written for The New York Times, The New Republic, The New York Sun, The New Inquiry, The Sunday Times, The Nation, The Nation, The Atlantic and other publications. He has been a</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy, Metainthology, and the Metainthology Reader (2015). He is currently a professor in the department of Communication, Media and Culture at the University of Alberta's McClelland School of Art. His articles have appeared in The New York Times, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Education and The New York Times Higher EdXplore: Art, Politics, Policy (with Lynn Tolmon) and has delivered lectures at Carnegie Mellon University, The Hebrew University of Jerusalem, The Jewish Theological Seminary, the University of Alberta, and The Commonwealth Club of Australia. He has also edited the ANNALS OF ANCIENT EAST London, The Orientalist, The Journal of Southern Cross and The London Printz. His latest project is a two-year long study of the Ottoman Empire, co-editing The British Empire and Ready Player One: The Game of Empire (2016-17) with Polly Brannan, published by Perigee in 2017.</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy, Metainchymosis and the Modern Museum (2007), the New York Times bestseller Archaeology of the Nakba: Israel’s Experiencing of Genocide (with Gerald Celente, 2011) and the New York Times bestseller Shadow of History: Israeli Military Operations in the Gaza Strip (2015). His work has been featured in numerous books including: Naked Capitalism: Privatising Historic Places: Israel and the After (2016), Art and Anarchy: On Urban and Terrifying Politics (2017), and the anthology Imagining Palestine: Essays on the Palestinian Issue (2018). He has written for the Forward, the Nation, Jacobin, and other publications. He is the host of The Affinities podcast, A Star is Born (2017), and is a co-editor of the forthcoming book Imagining Palestine: Essays on the Palestinian Issue (with Jeffrey Lewis, forthcoming 2019).His forthcoming book Shadow of History: Israeli Military Operations in the Gaza Strip is a critical look</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy, Postmodernism and Postcolonialism, and the forthcoming book Systemics, or, The Architecture of Modernity. He is currently an Assistant Professor in the Department of the History of Art, Culture &amp; Communication at the University of Toronto, where he is researching the history of art, culture and postcolonialism in North America and the Middle East. His work has been featured in the New York Times, Washington Post, New Republic, Atlantic and Time. He is currently completing a book project on postcolonialism and contemporary art history titled Institutions of Art and Culture: US, USSR, and a City of Traps.Until now, the question that has preoccupied me most during the past year has been: how can an artist or a curator or a community work together to address the issue of mass incarceration in the United States? A project called Community Arts Futures, led by the artist Maya Angelou, was developed to address this in intimate and powerful ways. The name comes from a 1987 essay</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy, Media &amp; History (2017) and the New York Times bestseller Media Madness: The Rise and Fall of Creative Media (2015). His latest book is Reclaiming the Mural: Essays on the Future of Art and Anti-Media (with Tessa Jha).The JCCA Annual Meeting was held at the JCCA in New York from October 12 to 18, 2017. It is the first in a two-part series of books on the future of art and anti-media produced in collaboration with the artist and curator Sabrina Erkoe. Part 1 examines the legacy of the CMAA, and part 2 looks at the future of the organization.The Society of Illustrators was founded in 1791 in London to promote European art from the peripheries. It was a not-for-profit organisation, and its first mandate was to promote the visual arts in North America. In the American context, the society’s first mandate was to oppose American artistic endeavors</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy, Entelechy Politics, and the City (2015) and the New York Times bestseller Nonplace: Everyday Nonfiction (2017). He is currently working on a new collection of nonfiction books to be published in 2018, and will be presenting his research into the JCCJCCF exhibition’s collection of objects from the JCCJCCF at the 68th Venice Biennale from September 2018 to April 2019. Making the World Work Again by Envisioning Architecture  (2015)Envisioning Architecture  Envisioning Architecture is a 2016 PhD dissertation, entitled ‘The End of Postcolonialism? Revisiting the Concept’, that examines postcolonialism and its discontents from a feminist perspective. In her research, she uses a variety of materials, including objects from her mother’s home in the 1980s, to explore the ways in which architects and designers of the postcolonial condition can be made to participate in creating the future</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy, Enteleche and Postmodernism (2008), about the cultural histories of post-industrial societies, from the 1980s. His work has also been featured in numerous exhibitions and publications worldwide including at the Venice Biennale, Tanakh, Tate Modern, The New York Times, Wallace Stevens, The New Yorker and The New Republic. His writing has been featured in numerous journals, including the online content of the journal which is published each Tuesday. He has a minor in English and Cultural Studies from McGill University.  [1] JL Subrahmanian and RR Subotzky, ‘On the nature of time: a comment on Zapf and Rawls’,  	 Journal of Political Economy, Vol. 21, No. 1, March, pp. 397–415.Download this article as PDFJoshua Freeman jf Freeman is the Curator for the 2012 Venice Biennale and has written for The New York Times, The New Republic,</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy, Metainterface, and the Cinema of Memory (2015), as well as the recently published State of Perfume (2018). He is currently at work on a book project about the Mandan, Inventing History: Gender in Art and Culture from Jean-Luc Nancy’s Standing: Art, Identity and Secularization in Cultural Spaces of the New Empire (2017), and will present the project at the Bermuda Biennial, November 17–21, 2018.  [1] See http://www.genoa.org.uk/en/biennials/2018/exhibition/en/exhibition-list/overview/[2] See http://www.genoa.org.uk/en/biennials/2018/exhibition/en/exhibition-list/overview/[3] See http://www.genoa.org.uk/en/biennials/2018/exhibition/en/exhibition</text>
    <text>present an online project that seeks to locate the remains of over a hundred African slaves’ at an undisclosed location in northern India. A digital recording of the expedition is made available online, where it is met by ecstatic responses from viewers and listeners alike. The project is shut down shortly afterwards, but not before some fans have started a Facebook fan page dedicated to the project and its images. The story of the disappearances and the reconstructions is told in many languages around the world.Download this article as PDFJoshua FreemanJoshua Freeman is an independent writer, curator, writer and Principal at The Jewish Museum in New York, where his work often focuses on the Jewish past and contemporary experience in Palestine and the Jewish homeland. He is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at the University of Toronto, where he is responsible for the museum’s international profile, its relationship with the wider art world, and its development as an independent museum. He is the author of several books including the award-winning Between Two Worlds: Entelechy, Power and Culture (2013) and the New Media Reader: Essays on the Symbols of Postcolonial Critique (2015). He is currently working as Associate Professor in the Department of Communication Studies at the University of Alberta, Canada, where he is also the editor of the Black Stack, a blogging platform for postcolonial studies and Indigenous studies. His work has been featured in publications including The Nation, The American Conservative, The New York Times, The New Republic, The American Indian Movement’s Journal of Indian Studies, and The Washington Post. He is currently researching the 1994 genocide of Native Peoples by the Canadian National Indian Act (the Gathering), which he says he will one day write about.Jussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an artist, researcher, and writer. He is a co-founder of the Centre for Inquiry, and has a particular interest in the role of art and activism in challenging power structures and extracting social change. His work is produced through</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still, the site of the conference would be a significant advance for the organisation, and its members, in many ways, in many cases, would become better informed and more productive practitioners of their craft. This is a compelling argument, and it is one that is being continually undermined by an agenda of making it easier to get things than it is to change them.The other argument against cultural production is that which is often referred to as the ‘culture war’: the idea that the arts and culture are somehow intrinsically ‘warmed’ up to conflict with the rest of the society. This is frequently attributed to a 1950s anti-intellectualism advocated by William Julius Wilson, who was a British intellectual and the son of a prominent nineteenth-century British critic of the French Revolution. While there is some truth to this, there is also a great amount of truth to the idea that someone like Stanley Kurtzberg, a white British man, would be able to fundamentally change how the world</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still, the transformative power of cultural production today derives not from the individual or the collective, but from the micro-managerial enterprises that assemble and assemble – and which one might say are already there. And if the goal of cultural production today is to become ‘real’ again, then one might imagine that the autonomous cultural units at the nanosecond and micro-level might need to be reconfigured, given new technological augmentations and even new languages. This is the scenario that TEDxCalder Williams established, and which was further explored by TEDxCalder Williams himself.It should be noted, too, that TEDxCalder Williams was also the curator of the annual meeting of the Society for Automotive Art, where he presented the work of various stakeholders, including members of the Royal Automotive Museum, in an effort to find a solution to the ongoing conflict between public and private sector ownership of automobiles. As we all know, there was no resolution to this conflictual situation, although</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still, the organizational change required to allow the public to define and determine what counts as knowledge is a cultural change, and while it may or may not happen, it is highly unlikely to happen anytime soon. Even if we did decide to embark on a cultural and linguistics of our own, it would still be a long way from where we are now, and much less than what we aspire to as a biennial.In any case, the question is, how to leverage the vast amounts of data already floating about the planet in an ever more pervasive and pervasive way to make the world we inhabit more livable and more democratic? While there are many cultures of humanity floating around in space, there are few that are as dependent on the services of humans as are the cultures of AIADC. We could theoretically argue that humans are both the limiting factor here and in other areas of the planet, and that the more humanity we spread out and expand the boundaries of space, the more vulnerable we become. But</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still, the scenes we imagine ourselves rendering are likely to be informed by infrastructural forms of capital still extant in places like Bengaluru, New York and Shanghai. We could even imagine non-governmental creative-class arts organizations like the Biennale re-imagining themselves as AIADC’s next step. But the great changes we envision for the world we live in still have to happen. And if the social, political and economic changes we envision for ourselves are not based on new understandings of the world, but on older, but still fragmenting social and cultural forms, then we would still need to put in place new social forms to govern ourselves and the world we inhabit.The upshot of all this, then, is that while the contours of what AIADC might one day be resemble those of the biennale, the focus would still have to be on the social. In the current political context, cultural production might be more visible, but it would still</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still, the reason why the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC are able to tackle such monumental tasks is due to the fact that they are able to imagine in terms of worlds outside of themselves, and thus, at the same time, reject conventional notions of what is conventional. This is to a large extent due to their concept of ‘the Human Being’. The Human Being is a construct, and its use is a fiction. However, the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC are able to imagine and project worlds because they possess the conceptual toolkit necessary to create ‘knowledge deserts’ – worlds where knowledge is actively thwarted by an oppressive multitude.This can be seen in the work of artists, from the Welsh Streets muralists to the Idle No More activists, whose work through  	Self-organising Unit (2003-2005) provided the intellectual substrate for the social transformation desired by the city. The social transformation desired by the city is</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still, the impact of AIADC’s stated mission would be felt most strongly in the social and civic domains. It is important to remember that AIADC was created to address a curatorial question: what kinds of questions could it address? As stated by its mission statement, the curatorial question is the paradigm of an inquiry: what kinds of questions could it possibly address? Though the mission statement itself makes this a central concern, the fact of the curatorial character of the question is also central. If the social, cultural and linguistic dimensions can all be taken into account in the construction of an autonomous, self-organising entity, then surely the question of social and cultural organisation can be too. We need to be able to recognise when we are witnessing the emergence of something new and radical, and to react accordingly. In this sense, the curatorial character of the mission statement is also essential. Otherwise, the whole enterprise is seen as an act of leaving behind the present in an act</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still, the organisational work that AIADC has already begun to produce, the strategic communication that needs to happen between members of the same or different cultural groups, needs to happen much sooner than later. That is, unless a cultural revolution or similar radical shift in how people think and perceive the world can be brought about.It is no exaggeration to suggest that the work already done by the Center for Inquiry could be put to better use in the world. For one thing, the Center for Inquiry is already doing valuable, although perhaps controversial, work in curating and organising exhibitions, speaking engagements, seminars and workshops, and hosting regular and special events. It is also no exaggeration to suggest that the work already done by the Centre for Inquiry could be put to even greater use in the world, much less in creating a cultural ecology of its own. For one thing, the Centre for Inquiry could put culture to work in the production of infrastructure – infrastructure, that is, infrastructure capable of supporting knowledge flows and producing</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still, the very idea that cultural resources could be gathered and communicated with, or that the work of art, poetry and other forms of expression might lie somewhere between the social and the purely natural – between the social and the vernacular – seems utterly foreign to us. It seems as though the very notion of the ‘public’ would imply that there is a very different social world, where deeds, gestures and actions are private property. The very notion of the ‘public’ would imply something very different.We could try to think of a way to imagine cultural production as occurring between the public and the cultural, but this seems unrealisable in the age of the biennial. The art world and cultural sectors are very different now, and the biennial has largely entered the realm of the social. We might try to imagine what a public might look like, but this seems far-fetched in the age of the biennial. People inhabit different worlds, and it is much easier to imagine</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still, the shared, but undefined, future that AIADC hopes to produce is necessary in order to sustain the real life that is being created in the name of AIADC. It is a world where the cultural resources of this part of the country are not bound by the constraints of geography, economics and materialism. It is a world where people do not rule over other people’s bodies.It is a world where oppression does not exist.But it is a world that cannot be created, and yet which intellectuals and artists in other fields have created it within. It is a world where the rich and powerful do not rule over us all, but rather create opportunities and lend us their services. It is a world where the powerless and the poor alike can participate fully in creating their own destinies. This is the kind of world we want to be making.It is a world in which architects, philosophers, journalists and others with expertise in the physical and social aspects of the world are</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s interests, but with an emerging, if still nascent, interdisciplinary field of philosophy shaping what counts as knowledge. Perhaps our own interest in the retrieval of knowledge comes from a desire to understand how our own cultural practices might be relevant in the future, or perhaps it comes from a desire to understand how our social worlds might be generated by a complete lack of understanding. It is as though we have no idea where the boundary is between the worlds we imagine ourselves to be creating and the real world.Even setting aside the human dimension, the immense social and geopolitical changes that have been wrought in the name of AIADC’s stated mission of bringing together all parts of the country – and especially the parts of the country with the highest populations – still needs to happen. It is likely that the autonomous, self-organising components of AIADC would still need to be tested and calibrated, and that cultural and linguistic resources would still need to be gathered and communicated with. Still, the autonomous parts of AIADC that could be imagined exist already, and could be assembled from the elements that are here and there, creating what is sometimes described as a ‘house organ’ – a kind of factory with chambers and nodes able to peer inside and outside of the building and with ‘windows that move like a window frame’ that can ‘see and hear like a house’. These kinds of factory-like structures exist already in the form of cities, but they are, for the most part, apolitical, non-representative or static. With the notable exception of New York and London, few places in the UK have their own autonomous, self-organising, responsive city currently. Still, the aim of AIADC should be to see if there are ways to combine different cultural practices within a single cultural context, and to see if there are ways to see the world through such a framework.Art is an undeniable cultural asset, and it</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily
    <text>biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily Pringle 	Emily Pringle is a writer, producer, and Documenta 14 board member. She has a particular interest in the history of biennials in various forms, including biennials as an artistic practice, their social contexts, and their evolution in the decades since their formation. She has written on a range of subjects, is a regular commentator on The Big Issue, and is part of the Documenta 14 Documenta 14 Editorial Board. Her books include the Documenta 13 (2015), Documenta 14: Strategies for a New Millennium (2015), and Documenta 14: Rise of the Biennale World (2016). Her articles have been published in The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, Frieze, and many other publications. She has also edited The Frieze d/e and edited the online journal Stages. She lives and works in London.PreviousNextEmily Pringle 	With over a decade of experience as an independent writer, producer,</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily Pringle and Sarah Nuttall 	[i] Anne Applebaum, ‘Impacts of Low Energy Biennials’,  	Waste Management International, http://www.iee.org/publications/impacts/low-energy-biennials-2012-12?y=shortlink.biennial-impact-2012Oct.19-22.html#sthash.BqE12w.DdTl.AbU.3.xlg==.bC1.2014.12.impacts.low-energy-biennials.html, accessed 4 July 2015. 	[ii] Anne Applebaum, The Committee of Eight, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, Routledge, London, 1982, p.7.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is a writer and Environmental Studies PhD candidate in English and Film Studies at the University of Alberta</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThis article was originally commissioned by and published in New Left Review #22, London, November, 1970. With Alice Cooper, co-curator of the 70th Venice Biennale, we are hosting the Venice Architecture Biennale, organised by Carriageworks, Venice, Italy. We are planning to commission a number of artists to design temporary exhibitions for the Biennale, with a view to bringing them into existence. The exhibition will be based on the plans for the neighborhood Venice in the wake of the Biennale, with works that emerge from the excavations yet to take place yet to be undertaken. The project was supported by the Emergent Behaviour research Centre and the Natural Science and Film Research Council. The artist Judith Curry will be exhibiting her 'Supplemental Material' to the Venice Biennale as a supplement to her previous works published in Frieze and the New York Times. The idea of ‘substance’</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleFacebook or Google+0 Share onFacebook Sara RuxtonFacebook or Google+0 Share onFacebook Sara Ruxton is an arts educationalist and writer with a particular interest in the history, practice and potential of Community Arts practices. She has worked with local community groups for over twenty years and has a particular interest in how artists can be adopted into historically black cultural contexts. She has published more than twenty books, including the award-winning The Black Stack (1987), Toward a Post-Technological Society (1995), The Black Stack: The Architecture of Community Arts (with Suzi Randall, University of Toronto Press, Toronto, 1997), Building a Public Realm: Social Practices and the Architecture of Urban Futures (with Ray Udoh, Cornell UP, Ithaca, NY, 1998), and co-edits Dynamite: On Urban Futures (with Ray Udoh and Peter Severing</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleTraveling Theatre, The Theatre Workshop, 2000.I began by asking what it meant to me when I first came to work as a designer, artist, producer, writer, etc. in a major project on the West Coast. Most of what I was asked to produce was delivered by way of a script or template, or was at the very least delivered via Facebook message or Twitter update. I receive letters from readers from all over the country who either work for the same organisation or have the same organisation as me. Many of you will be familiar with the West Coast Theatre Workshop (WCS), the local area organising powers who run the show, the West Coast Production Workshop (WCP), the production designers, and West Coast Development Corporation (WCDC), the developer.I was also invited to produce the 2015 West Coast ‎Beacon Hill Arts Festival, West Coast Arts Festival, 2015 West Coast Jamboree, the West Coast Jamboree 2016, </text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily Pringle and Christina RicherThis article was originally published in The Washington Post and has been reproduced with kind permission. 	This is an extract from the book 	Unfixing America: Race, Globalization, and Political Nationhood by Christina Richer and Heather A. Daly, Postcolonial Empires: Culture and Politics in a Global Context, Princeton University Press, Princeton, 1988, p.76-83.Download this article as PDFPhilip E AgreIn his contribution to the journal Race and Globalization, Philip Agre reflects on the crisis of identity that characterizes contemporary political-ideological discourse. Drawing on his years as a research associate at the University of California, Los Angeles, Philip Agre produces an inventory of the cultural industries of post-liberal democratic governments globally that promote and facilitate racial and socio-cultural assimilation. These industries include mediaeval forms of religion as well as contemporary forms of capitalism and ethnic cleansing. He warns of a 'cultural blindness' that is fue</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleDrawing Lessons from Historic CulturesCultural Capital: Historic CentsCultural Capital: Historic Buildings and TerritoriesCultural Capital: The Infrastructure of Community1 October 2014A ConversationWith Prof. Steven Henry Povinelli2 October 2014A ConversationWith Marilyn Herman3 October 2014A ConversationWith Joyce Carol Oates4 October 2014A ConversationWith Maya Angelou5 October 2014A ConversationWith John Urry6 October 2014A ConversationWith Sheryll Krieger7 October 2014A ConversationWith The Committee of Eight8 October 2014A ConversationWith HomebakedCommunity Land Trust and Historic BuildingsTeam The Cooperative9 October 2014A ConversationWith The Community Land Trust and Historic BuildingsTeam The CooperativeNovember 2014Cultural Capital: Historic Places and TerritoriesCultural Capital: The Infrastructure of Community1 October 2014A ConversationWith Dr. Eva Castringius2 October 2014A ConversationWith Dr. Ron Paul, Ph.D., Director, National Institute of Mental Health, Bethesda, Maryland and author of The Civil War in Contin</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily Pringle and Sarah Nuttall Surrounding Voices: Conversations on Language and Politics via Skype 	When I first started working as an artist in the 1990s, language was a constant source of struggle. From the early days when I was trying to translate the work of Søren Atkin into Dutch, French, Italian or Spanish, to today’s debates on the meaning of life between immigrants and citizens, language constantly threatens to intervene in our collective thinking. Yet the stakes for language are nothing compared to those for life, which are eternal. The one that is lost on us all is life itself. In the history of life, language has lost about half its speakers. How do we recover the language that made us who we are today? In conversation, the participants in Surrounding Voices: Conversations on Language and Politics reflect on the questions above, try to come to grips with the sense of loss, and discover how to live with the loss of the language</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleWhile in Liverpool last month, I had the chance to visit the Curtains by Design exhibition. The journal that accompanied the project was written in the presence of a local curator and a fellow curator, Laura Tabili, who presented the project as an artist and a researcher. As the title suggests, the project was both a diary and a research project. I think it is a valuable document in its own way, recording not only the events of the visit but also the processes leading up to it. The diary entries are a continuing document, and they form part of the project against which the projectors, the curators, the journalists and others will attempt to evaluate the visit as a whole. They form part of a project that I am part of, and in which the city assembles to challenge many of its familiar roles. As the name implies, the project is not limited to the person who is visiting but extends to the city as a whole. The projectors, curators</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the need to decipher, in differentiating between the two, the vagaries of the real, the unpredictable, and the inescapable is of course a vital task. 	[i] The Committee of Eight, a city-based art collective, was established in 1975 by the Canadian poet Joyce Carol Oates and the American poet Maya Angelou. Their collection The Committee of Eight was published in 1977 and a second edition in 1984. The Committee of Eight was formed in Toronto in 1984 and New York in 1988. See Joyce Carol Oates and Maya Angelou, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cities, Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, The Committee of Eight: Two Gracious People from Two Cultures, co-authors, with Steven Henry Povinelli, Under the Table: Social Criticism and Literary Criticism, Routledge, London, 2012, p.5.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleAfter Reading the Palestinian Issue of The New York Review of Books, Volume 22, Number 1 &amp; 2 (January – June 1991), p. 8.Download this article as PDFAfter Reading the Palestinian Issue of The New York Review of Books, Volume 22, Number 2 (January – June 1991), p.8.Download this article as PDFAfter Reading the Palestinian Issue of The New York Review of Books, Volume 22, Number 2 (January – June 1991), p.8.Download this article as PDFAfter Reading the Palestinian Issue of The New York Review of Books, Volume 22, Number 2 (January – June 1991), p.8.Download this article as PDFAfter Reading the Palestinian Issue of The New York Review of Books, Volume 22, Number 2 (January – June 1991), p.8.Download this article as PDFAfter Reading the Palestinian Issue of The New York Review of Books, Volume 22, Number 2 (January – June 1991), p.8.Download this article</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric
    <text>present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric Cazdyn, Israel, 2013, p.90.Download this article as PDFMichael LernerMichael Lerner is an independent writer, Curator of Moveable Feast, 2014-2015. He is the Curator of Moveable Feast, 2014-2015, of the prestigious Venice Biennale. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New York Times Magazine, The New Republic, The New York Times Magazine, The New York Times Book Review, The New York Times Travel Guide and The New York Times Digital Times. He has been a lecturer at American University, Temple University, Trinity University, University of California, Santa Barbara and Stanford Universities, and was previously Director of the Program for Global Studies at the Carnegie Museum of Art. He has written on a wide range of issues, including the environment, art and activism for outlets including The New York Times, The New Republic, The New York Times, The New York Times Magazine, The New Republic,</text>
    <text>present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric Cazdyn, Temple Books, 2012, p.93.Download this article as PDFMichael LernerMichael Lerner is an artist. His current projects focus on the local community in the West Bank and Gaza. He is the Curator of the international Biennials, and co-curator of the forthcoming London and Sydney biennials. His current exhibition schedule includes exhibitions at the Palestine Museum, University of Toronto, New York Museum of Modern Art, Tate Modern, Tate Britain, and Kunsthalle Zu?rich.He is the Curator of the new exhibition “Al Quds: The Biennial Anthology” at the Palestine Museum. The project will document the life and work of the Biennale in the West Bank and Gaza, and examine the relationship between art, biennials, and the institutional forms that enable their institutionalisation.He is the Curator of the South as a Continent project, part of the Contemporary Conditioning Service, Tate Modern. His current</text>
    <text>present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric S. Landsberg (New York: C.W. Frow &amp; Co., 2013), p. 48. 	[iii] See, for example, Michael Lerner and Eric S. Landsberg, The Alaskan Virtues: A Documentary History of Art and Architecture in Eighteenth-Century Alaskan Traditions (Durham: Duke University Press, 2004), p. 87. 	[iv] Michael Lerner, ‘The Alaskan Virtues: A Documentary History of Art and Architecture’, in The Alaskan Virtues: A Documentary History of Art and Architecture, ed. Michael Lerner, Peter Lang, Eric S. Landsberg (Durham: Duke University Press, 2005), p. 135. 	[v] Peter Landes, ‘On the Use of Historic Places and Subjects in Art’, in The New York Times, 12 June 2016, http://www.nytimes.com/2016/06</text>
    <text>present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric Rothenberg, Pimlico, London and New York, 2013, p.7–17. 	[iii] See https://www.biennial.com/2014/exhibition/index.html?option=com_content&amp;view=article&amp;id=25&amp;Itemid=1&amp;annotation=314#Exhibition Excerpt from Excerpt from The Narrative of The Palestinian Mujahideen by Nasser Rabb 	[iv] See: http://takfirisagainstwar.com/index.php/takfiri-news/201403307/al-qaeda-al-thaqafa-al-thaqafiyya-al-thaqafa-a-new-phase.html?section=Blog&amp;file=Blog/2009/09/al-qaeda-al-thaqafa-al thaqafa-new-phase-1/ Al-Q</text>
    <text>present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric van Dyck, Hebrew University Press, Jerusalem, 2012, p.2. [iii] See: http://www.alqussalabs.com/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/DownloadThisFile.html?language=en. Translate it into ENGLISH, and you will see what I mean. [iv] See: http://www.alqussalabs.com/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/DownloadThisFile.html?language=en. Translate it into ENGLISH, and you will see what I mean. [v] See: http://www.alquss</text>
    <text>present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric Ben-Tovim, Hebrew &amp; English Edition, 2 nd ed., Al Quds University Press, 1997. 	[iii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, 1995. 	[iv] See http://www.alquds.org/english/index.html?artid=1809&amp;itemid=1&amp;sort=asc&amp;aid=0&amp;format=archived&amp;filetype=pdf# [v] See also http://www.aljazeera.com/indepth/2011/..., accessed 7 September 2013. [vi] See, for example, Daniel Fernández-Muñoz, ‘El héroe de las Americas?’, in Rolling Stone (14 October 2004), p.A1. [vii] See also http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earth/earthnews/..., accessed 7 September 2013. [viii]</text>
    <text>present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric C. Scheidt, Dordrecht: Holland &amp; New York, 2011, p.81.Download this article as PDFMichael LernerMichael Lerner is an internationally renowned artist who has exhibited widely throughout Europe and the United States. He is the curator of the Jewel Box, Israel, and has curated the United States, Europe and Israel of Art Futures, as well as the United Kingdom, China and Singapore. His work in Palestine includes the international exhibition, The Abu Ghraib Remnants, of the internationally acclaimed exhibition The Abu Ghraib Group: Victims of Iraq, published in 2014. He is the editor of the online art magazine Art Newspaper, and the author of several books including the New York Times bestseller The Artist is Present, published by D.I.B.E.E.Empire and distributed by Quadrant Books. He is also the curator of the upcoming China’s Art of the Net: Cyber Culture and the Politics of Net Neutrality, published</text>
    <text>present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric Verstraete, trans. Stefan Collini, D.I.T. Films, 2013. 	[iii] See http://www.alqaeda.com/en/homebrew/index.html?lang=en&amp;Item=42#1212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212[iv] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, pp. 19–26. 	[v] See http://www.alqaeda.com/en/homebrew/index.html?lang=en&amp;Item=42#121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212121212</text>
    <text>present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric C. Stoner (New York: Independent Arts Association, 2016), 1–36.Download this article as PDFHana BauhidHana Bauhid is a writer, curator, and arts organizer. Her writing has addressed a wide range of topics relating to contemporary Arab upbringings and the discourses surrounding them. In 2015 she co-founded and curated the independent arts organization, Al Quds, Jerusalem, which brings together traditional arts practices from the city with innovative media and programming that engages with current events and themes from the region. She has worked with the Israeli NGO, Al Mezan Center for Cultural Studies, which works to enhance understanding of artistic practices in the Arab region through collaborative projects with institutions from the region. Her writing has also been featured in the New York Times, the Guardian, BBC News, Al Mezan Center's Digital Media Lab, and numerous other publications and journals. She is an adjunct professor at McGill University and holds a joint appointment with the McGill and McMaster Universities</text>
    <text>present an online project that takes the form of a live-action video that invites viewers to explore a collection of objects in the home of a Palestinian woman, 18-year-old Ramzi Barhoum, who is also the pseudonym of Hana Bauhid, an artist and activist who is also the pseudonym of Mu'adza Intel, an organisation that advocates on behalf of the Palestinian family in Gaza. The project was inaugurated on 7 December 2013, and the project continues to receive contributions and endorsements from a range of quarters, including from internationally renowned curators, artists, journalists and activists. 	[i] See www.alqussalabs.com.au/english/2013/12/al-qussali-art-03-israels-home-collection-al-jihad-collection-al-israels-house-1/ 	[ii] Al-Quds, Jerusalem: The Biennial Anthology, ed. Michael Lerner and Eric van Heeswijk, Palgrave MacMillan, London, 2011, p.75.Download this article as PDFMichael LernerMichael Lerner is an independent writer, curator, journalist and consultant. His work has addressed the history of art, the impact of new media and the impact of religion in contemporary art. He has written extensively on the Middle East and North Africa for publications such as Al Watan, Al Hayat, Al Masry Al Youm and Al Anbiyya Al Aws, among others. He has also been a regular contributor to the New York Times Magazine.His latest book, The End of Postcolonialism, is published by Palgrave MacMillan, London, 2012, pp.91–97.Download this article as PDFMichael LernerMichael Lerner is an independent writer, Curator of Public Art at Tate Britain, and Senior Lecturer in Art History at Lancaster University. His work has addressed postcoloniality, postindustrialisation, gentrification, urbanisation</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p
    <text>biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.170. 	[v] Michael Ames, ‘Imminent Domain: The Legal Concept for Developing Countries during an Economic Boom’, Environment &amp; Urbanization, Vol. 13, No. 1, Spring, 2003, p.1–22. 	[vi] David Harvey, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Nation-Building as a Function of Space’, New Left Review, Issue 7, 1984, p.71. 	[vii] David Harvey, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Social Innovation as a Form of State Failure’, New Left Review, Issue 7, 1984, p.1. 	[viii] Kirstin Powers, ‘Democracy and Decay: US Presidential Elections of 2004 and 2008’, The ANNALS of the American Academy of Political and Technical Studies, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2003, p.1–22. 	</text>
    <text>biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[v] Foucalt, op. cit., p.3. 	[vi] Robert H MacDonald, ‘Coming Apart: Racial and Class Disparities in the Age of Information’, American Sociological Review, Vol. 66, No. 2, Spring, 1978, p.335. 	[vii] Kunstler, op. cit., p.3. 	[viii] John Berger and Amitav Ghosh, ‘Rethinking Cultural Capital: A Survey of Cultural Capital and Economic Technologies’, American Sociological Review, Vol. 66, No. 2, Spring, 1978, p.335. 	[ix] Amitav Ghosh, ‘On the Sublime: Die Warenlager im Körper Waren, Der Kunst des Warenlagers, Leipzig, 1976’, Zeitschrift f</text>
    <text>biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.1. 	[v] Robert H MacDonald, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Social Media and Capital in Decline’, The New York Times, November 8, 2010, p.A1. 	[vi] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Rise of Digital Cultures: Media and Culture as Mass Deception’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.1. 	[vii] Michael Ames and Christian Ulrikas, ‘Live from the Shore’, Radio Free Europe/Radio Liberty, November 20, 2012, http://www.rferl.org/files/Rififi...(accessed January 2018). 	[viii] Robert H MacDonald, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Film and Media’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March,</text>
    <text>biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.1. 	[v] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Identity: Race, Identity Politics, and Postmodernism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.1. 14  John Horton Curry, ‘Crisis of Identity: Identity Crisis, or, the Crisis of Identity as a Concept’, Critical Inquiry, Vol. 20, No. 1, Spring, 1986, p.1–28. 15  John H. McWhorter, ‘Imaginings of a People’, in People, Culture &amp; Politics, Vol. 11, No. 2, 1988, p.1–34. 16  Michael Ames, ‘Crisis of Identity: From Post-Impressionism to Identity Politics, and Back Again’, Critical Inquiry, Vol. 23, No. 2, Spring, 1988, p.1–23.</text>
    <text>biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.189. 	[v] Michael Ames, ‘Gravity’, In These Times, March, 1986, p.26. 	[vi] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[vii] Michael Ames, ‘Gravity’, In These Times, March, 1986, p.27. 	[viii] Andrew Goffey, ‘Delegated Performance, Delegated Politics, and Delegated Learners’, Performing Arts Research Theories, Vol. 23, No. 1, Spring, 1986, p.1–27. 	[ix] Goffey, ‘Delegated Performance, Delegated Politics, and Delegated Learners</text>
    <text>biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.1. 	[v] William Burroughs, ‘Capital and Class: A Socially-engendered Crisis of the Imagined Village’, Public Culture Vol. 6, No. 1, Spring, 1988, p.1–24. 	[vi] Michael Ames, ‘Into the Void’, Public Culture Vol. 6, No. 2, Summer, 1988, p.1–28. 	[vii] Gustave Flaubert, Dictionary of Blasphemes (1939), in New Literary Criticism, Vol. 3, No. 1, Spring, 1940, p.1–38. 	[viii] Matthias Choreau, ‘On Immortality and Cultures of Critique’, Monthly Review of Cultural Theory, Vol. 21, No. 1, Spring, 1941, p.1–17. 	[ix] G</text>
    <text>biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.1. 	[v] Robert H MacDonald, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Film/Video as Media of Exchange’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.1. 	[vi] Robert H MacDonald, ‘Material Culture and Animal Cultures: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.1. 	[vii] Marija Cetinic, ‘Victim or Jailed: Media Criticism of Prison Conditions’, American Sociological Review, Vol. 71, No. 2, 1984, p.275. 	[viii] Katharine Hepburn, ‘Envisioning Publics: Social Communities, Publics, and Publics in Art’, in Imagining Communities: The Arts</text>
    <text>biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[v] John Berger, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Primer into the Contemporary Science Fiction Fantasies that Transform Our Ideas of Possibility’, SF Quarterly, Vol. 26, No. 1, Spring, 1986, p.1–26. 	[vi] Michael Ames, ‘The Language of Capital: On Language as a Form of Prophecy’, Journal of Communication Inquiry, Issue 3, Vol. 4, No.1, Winter, 1986, p.1. 	[vii] John Berger, ‘Language and Revolution: On the Possibilities of a Planetary Model of Human Language’, Science Fiction Film and Television, Issue 3, Vol. 1, Spring, 1986, p.1–24. 	[viii] George Orwell, ‘1984’, in Collected Essays, ed. Patrick Leigh Ray and Peter Lang (Norton</text>
    <text>biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.187. 	[v] Andrew Goffey, ‘On the Construction of Space: From Postcolonialism to Third World’, in ibid., p.183. 	[vi] Michael Ames, The Society of the Spectacle (New York: Columbia University Press, 1972), p.3. 	[vii] Gareth White, ‘On the Use of Cultures: From Myth to Cultures of Reparation’, Journal of Communication Inquiry, Issue 10, Spring, 1976, p.41. 	[viii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Materialism, Anarchism and Futurism – Interviews and Reading List’, in ibid., p.38. 	[ix] Kunstler, ‘Culture and Anarchy: State and Materialism in Nineteenth-Century Capitalism. I. The Culture Industry. II. Cultures of Reparation.</text>
    <text>biennials past and present in an effort to create an alternative and bring them into the 21st century. 	[i] Bruno Braudy, ‘On Violence and Property: A Theory of Exchange’, Philosophy, Vol. 34, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1–24. 	[ii] Joseph Foucault, On Violence and Property (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2008), p.30. 	[iii] James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Crisis of Representation: Empire, Materialism, and Postcapitalism’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[iv] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Capital and Communism: A Brief Pre-Critical History of the Present’, The New York Review of Books, Vol. 228, No. 1, March, 1986, p.183. 	[v] Ibid., p.184. 	[vi] Robert H MacDonald, ‘Apparition of Evil: Ten Myths of the Paranoid Style’, in David Harvey &amp; Michael Ames, eds., The Blackwell Companion to Political Correctness (Oxford: Blackwell, 2012), p.31. 	[vii] Gustave Flaubert, A Course in General Linguistics (1904), in H. L. Arnold &amp; Rudolf Steiner, Selected Essays (New York: Oxford University Press, 1942), p.228–32. 	[viii] Michel Foucalt, ‘On the Use of Words’, in Selected Essays (1924), pp.153–65, on the use of language by culture warriors. 	[ix] W. E. B. Du Bois, ‘On Language and Social Change�</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the city the capitalist logic of its own reproduction, it follows that the biennial must account for its own existence. But this account, in its essential mode, is fallacious: the biennial as an institution produces no social significance outside of the city. Its social significance, like everything else, depends on the political will and concrete choices that are available to it. 	The biennial will always have to find a home in the city, and it must do so in ways that are consistent with the capitalist logic of its production. But the city is a site of struggle and conflict, and the biennial’s political and economic positioning is a crucial site of these struggles. It serves to create the possibility of recognisable difference, recognisable difference on the one hand and recognisable difference on the other. The biennial must be possible in all but the most idealised image of a metropolis. It has to be able to expand into new urban spaces, and it has to do so in</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the city the city’s real wealth and meaning, it has to somehow manage its economic reproduction. But the biennial is also a site of de-imagining: of de-realisation. It’s true that the biennial has to account for its excess production of art-historical artefacts, and has to engage with its own economic circulation of art-objects. But these tasks never stop coming before it, and they’re only human, and we’re all susceptible to exhaustion, so the biennial loses its way. It becomes something that it’s not, which is why biennials are vanishing. Every biennial is a fragmented remnant of an old format, with various localised forms of art-historical production that come together to create a kind of shared historical space, and this shared historical space is being reconfigured by a new generation of artists, curators, curators, students and art-historians. 	So there</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the city as a whole, the biennial has to generate some kind of return on its investment. And this kind of thing does happen all the time in places all over the world: the Venice Biennale is a good example of this kind of capitalism at work, its productions constantly shifting the city into new configurations that have as much or more influence on cultural practices as they do economic ones. 	But the Venice Biennale does have another kind of kind of kind of kind of relationship to the city as a whole: that between biennials and museums. And the Biennale’s productions in the city as a whole are produced through the museum, and in a certain sense, museum-making is produced by the biennial. So the museum becomes part of the equation, but the museum-making is produced by the city as a whole. 	But what does it mean to be a museum? I think it’s possible that the kind of museum-making that</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the city what it doesn’t actually exist, then it’s going to have to account for something. And there’s a question of capital: how do you account for capital when it’s present in such dominant forms of social organisation? Could the biennial be a site of ‘capital letters’ – capital ‘flows’ (whatever that means)? Could it be an arena where the very real struggles over how to put capital into practice generate ideas about the social significance of labour and the capacities of local communities? 	I think that there’s a way in which the biennial can and should work in relation to what’s happening in the city, and I believe that there’s a way in which the various stages of art's development could be imagined as constituting ‘a large progressive urban system’. In other words, I think that biennials could and should become sites of ‘interim forms of</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the city as a whole, the biennial is the most essential of all the sites of capitalist circulation and reproduction. And yet, in the biennial as a whole, the biennial loses its specificity. As a site of exchange, the biennial is qualitatively different from any other. It’s said to be a ‘transactional’ exchange – in the sense that you can take it or no it. In this sense, it’s true that the biennial is the most distinctive of the biennial sites, as a place of taking or providing, of giving or not giving, of buying or not buying. 	But the biennial is only a site of exchange: what it represents to the city as a whole, or in other words, what kind of social and political context it creates in the city. It’s true that the biennial represents to the city (and to some extent, to individuals) the cultural totality – in so far as</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the city the commodity that’s produced by its very existence – in so far as it doesn’t get commodities – then it’s subject to the law of diminishing returns. But what it represents to the biennial is subject to the law of political circulation and reproduction, and what it represents to the city is necessarily uneven and unstable. The biennial can become culturally infinite in this sense, but it’s also true that culturally infinite is a relative concept: in a given state of development, the biennial could also cease to be and become something entirely different. 	I find the idea of the biennial as a ‘shortcut unit’ to be interesting. A shortcut unit means that it’s possible to produce great effects through a small number of people working in parallel: a few people can achieve spectacular results through a small group, while the large collective achieves spectacular results by pooling resources. For example, the shortcut unit for a multimedia production might be</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the city what it doesn’t already know, the biennial is itself a fabrication. And yet, this is also the case: the biennial must account for its own contradictions, because it’s the only way that capitalism can be abolished. The biennial is an indispensable site of capital accumulation, but it’s also true that as the biennial loses its primacy, it loses its ability to be present in the city. It becomes less of a place and more of a phenomenon. And so the biennial is forced to account for itself in relation to its own demise. 	The biennial is a site of contemporaneity, but it is also a site of destruction. It represents to the biennialer that which is possible through a given set of circumstances: economic, climatic and spatial. And this is the real essence of the biennial: the ability to mutate, to become what it professes not to be. 	The biennial must</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the city in some way, shape or form, it has to produce in some way. But what it’s not able to do, nor imagine doing, is account for itself in relation to what it represents to the planet. That would be an impossible task, since the features that make us ‘biennials’ would be incapable of sustaining themselves in this way. 	What the biennial can and must do, in order to maintain its spatial and temporal nature, is create what I would consider a more or less permanent ‘parallel universe’ in which the biennial as a whole can reside. This parallel universe would have to be materially different from the one we’ve got now, and would have to be created in some way. It would have to be created by, and contain elements of, the biennial that we don’t already have, and which is then reproduced in a way that we don’t yet know how to regulate.</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the city as a whole, the biennial is a myth. But the biennial does this through the mediation of what sociologist Peter Osborne calls ‘the big three: the banks, the insurance companies and the media corporations’.3 The biennial is a site of permanent exchange: it acquires qualities like currency, status and social capital that make it possible to write off the full value of a site. And yet, it remains relatively powerless in its relation to its host society. Osborne proposes three conditions for the success of a public art project: (a) a critical mass of people engaging with the art in ways that educate them as to what’s possible; (b) a way of linking the art with the economy through which the value is produced; and (c) a mechanism for redistributing the wealth generated by the art back to the city.4 While all three conditions may be met, I believe that (b) and (c) above are essential for</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI and virtual art? I’m interested in the ways in which a biennial can connect to its local environment, in this case, in the sense that it’s possible that a biennial could be built on a site that’s already experiencing an art crisis. Could the biennial be a cultural centre for the area? Could it be a place of exchange between artists, curators, artists’ state and visitors?  	There’s a sense in which the biennial must be a site of some kind of political investigation, because it’s possible that our current biennial format will outlive the human species: in a certain sense, the very concept of the biennial will be needed to endure. ÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂÃÂBut the biennial is also a site of intense capitalist circulation and reproduction. It’s true that the biennial has to account for itself in relation to what it represents to the city: in so far as it represents to the city the city as a whole, the biennial must somehow register as a kind of a city organ. And this is what the biennial does: it creates a relationship with the city that justifies (for the artist, the biennial practitioner and gallery visitor) the institution’s continued existence. 	But here’s the tricky part: the relationship doesn’t stop there. The biennial has to account for itself in relation to the city, and this means that the city has to be part of the equation in some way. And this is precisely what the city does: it sits on top of the biennial, while it simultaneously creates a biennial account that is mutually exclusive and responsive to the city’s needs. The biennial has to be a site of exchange between artist and audience, and so it establishes a relationship with the city that is mutually exclusive and responsive to the biennial’s needs. But this isn’t enough: the bi</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the media
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the media, a way to describe a specific set of activities; a term that’s being deployed with increasing frequency these days. But what institutionally designers and artists can offer in return is a huge, un-inclusive, and sometimes ungraspable market for their ideas. It’s not as if the market for a new car doesn’t know what it wants. It’s that the market is a big place where people come to figure out what’s valuable, and that every activity contributes to that value chain. If you design the market in ways that create that sense of discovery, then you’re on the right path. But if you let the market figure that out for you, then you’re stuck in a rut. That’s why the market will always try to do what it can to support economic growth, which inevitably means creating more jobs for less-skilled workers. But what the market can't do is create that</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the media, a tool of the city and an excuse for inaction.But what if the city can’t be an institutionally oriented thing? What if the city instead becomes a venue for creative perforations? What if the city becomes a magical land where things that otherwise wouldn’t happen, happen? This is the idea behind the city as a site for magic and the magic of crowds. It was originally developed for the purpose of seeing how the effects of a public plaza in a medieval city could be modified. But the motivations that came out of that were changed over time. The original intentions of the city as a magical place, with its public plazas and magical economies, are what we have to deal with now. And the ideas of the city as a site of mass transit and cultural institutions that foster a certain kind of urban immobility – in a very old-fashioned way – are what we have to deal with now.So the idea of the magic of crowds starts to</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the media, used by those with a clear agenda – and it’s being used by those with a conscience.The other weapon in the city is the ‘collaborative learning’ programme, or CREATION, a partnership between artists and institutions that was started in 2014 by the Liverpool Biennial, its curator, Joasia Krysa and the artist Wendy Harpe. This was a collaboration between the Biennial, the institution and the artist, and it was designed to bring together artists from different disciplines to work together across different artist-centered areas. The idea is that as an institution, the Biennial is asking artists to work across different audiences: different audiences to understand the same thing, through different mediums. The idea is to provoke thought from within the institution, generating genuine understanding between the people involved. The problem with the Biennial is that it’s the institution that creates the context and the power to do that. It’s the site, the people</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the media, used by the media to proclaim whatever news they want, whenever they want it. And of course, since we live and work in a digital society, what was once a relatively new development is now part of the package that every news organisation can deliver, no matter how far away it is from where the news is actually coming from. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ has a particular character in that it describes an intellectual sector that’s developing at a rapid clip, and which is populated with people who are very much into the new technologies of things, and don’t understand how the complex systems that underpin that thing actually work. So the acceleration of that sector, especially around the past two years, really speaks volumes about the state of things to come. And here’s another way of putting it: when young artists are making art on the internet, they’re building cultural capacities that last a lifetime. What’s happening now is that those same</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the media, used by those with a clear agenda – usually in an attempt to shift the conversation away from what’s happening in the city at large. But ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is only one weapon in a multi-layered, multi-compassed, multi-use arsenal. There are a number of other words and phrases that are often used to describe trends in a city, but the central concept that is usually employed is the ‘turn of urbanisation’. So it’s easy to define an area as having ‘institutionalised poverty’. But what does that actually mean? It’s not just an urban problem. It’s an area-specific problem. You can’t just say ‘institutionalised poverty’ and expect it to translate into local policies that will have an impact. Institutionalised poverty is a concept that is very difficult to define, and very difficult to understand. It</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the media – a way of saying, here’s how I connect with you, here’s how you connect with me, here’s how you get things done. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is just as dangerous as the more generic ‘global’ one. The latter is just the opening salvo. The institutionally oriented turn of phrase has a history that goes back to Thomas Jefferson’s time, and it’s this long phrase that starts with ‘I’m “going to be “very simple”’. It’s the very beginning of the piece, and it’s the very beginning of the sentence. But what happens next is telling. When you get to the part that begins with ‘we’, what happens next is telling. And what you’re saying in that part of the city is going to be of limited value. What happens next</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the media, and the media use of the term is a powerful one. It’s as if ‘institutionally’ means ‘inside’ and ‘inside’ means ‘out there’. 	But the interesting thing about the word ‘institutionally’ is that it’s almost a double-edged sword. On one hand, the use of ‘institutionally’ can mean exactly what the institution wants, as long as there’s some kind of democratic element to it. For example, the use of the word ‘institutionalize’ can be used to mean that particular elements of a particular practice, institution or idea should be retained in perpetuity. But if those elements are lost, then the institution loses its institutional power and becomes something else – a museum, a school, a newspaper – which is very different from how we think of it now. A newspaper that serves as an example of how an</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the media, and it’s being used by cultural-policy wonks to soften the blow of criticism of their cultural projects. If the city is innovative, if it’s creative and dynamic and dynamic and exciting, then the institution is a set of institutions – a globally recognisable brand name, a periodic reference, a set of activities that are seen as legitimate, and a fixed resource – that can and must cater to the expectations of particularised electorates. But the turn of phrase ‘institutionally oriented’ can also be used to mean something quite different. It can refer to the way in which an institution builds itself. The way in which an institution builds itself is defined by the power of capital. If the city is too complex and nuanced and flexible and flexible, then ‘institutionally’ turns out to refer to a particularity, and not to the substance of the organisation’s activities. For example, the way in which the Asian Infrastructure Investment Bank</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the media, used by those with a clear interest in presenting the latest twist on the old capitalist formula as a settled truth. It’s a weapon that’s used by those in power to shape language and how we understand the world, to create what they call ‘regeneration’. But ‘institutionally oriented’ turns of phrase are only one variant of a much larger theme being deployed by those with a clear interest in controlling language and knowledge. Take, for example, the use of ‘regeneration’ as an umbrella term to describe a number of phenomena. We can think of different aspects of regenerative municipalism. There’s the aspect of food and agriculture that comes up whenever we talk about food and agriculture in the city; the fact that cities are ecosystems first and foremost, with their own economies and social systems; the fact that cities now collectively refer to themselves as ‘regeneration Cities’; the fact that cities collectively</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics, which are ushering in a new era of transformational transformations in which art and culture will play a bigger role). This is why Tate Britain is so into their Autonomous City concept, which essentially says that you’ve got to be an art institution to be part of a research university. It’s as if these ‘institutionally oriented’ concepts are what make art institutions possible. But the ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase ‘speaks volumes about what’s happening in the city. It’s a strong word, but the city has certainly responded to this particular turn of phrase. The term ‘institutionally oriented’ is a big one these days. If you look at any academic journal published between 2010 and 2015, almost all of those terms were used once or twice per year, from June onwards. The ‘institutionally oriented’ turn of phrase is a weapon of the mediaeval sort, used by those who rule the world, and is a recurring theme in academic writing on the city. It’s an essential part of the neoliberal project, and the mediaeval sort of thing is just around the corner. So, ‘institutionally oriented’ turns of phrase are a recurrent theme, and they’re a recurring theme is a bit of a trap. The ‘turn of phrase’ is important because it allows a space for the listener to suspend their disbelief. If you use the word ‘turn of phrase’ without any particular object in mind, it’s a great way to constrain meaning, to make it a kind of a magical happening. For example, the word ‘turn of phrase’ could just as easily be used as an object like ‘shift of clocks’ or ‘light switches’. It’s a tool that allows us to observe patterns, to ‘follow invisible</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co-editor of the upcoming automotive magazine, to be published by Annals of Automotive Engineering.She is part of the research team for the documentary Autonomous, which will examine the development of self-driving vehicles in North America and internationally from the 1990s to the present. She is the author of several books, including the award-winning Assessing the Art of Carrying (Profile, 2015), the New York Times best-seller Autonomous (Profile, 2015), Learning to Drive: Understanding Uplifting Artificial Intelligence (MIT Press, 2017) and the New York Times best-seller Creating Healthy Cities: Art, Science, and the Performing Arts as Medicine (Profile, 2016). She has been a consultant for the film Zero Dark Thirty, which documents the US military's targeted killing program in Yemen, and The Invisible War: US Military Operations in Somalia (Profile, 2017). She is the host of the CBC's Newscasts on Cities and</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co-investigator of the Autonomous Highway System (AHS) project, which will link highway systems with satellite imagery to detect and repair damaged or destroyed road and rail systems, as well as monitor the health of the maritime environment. She is a consultant for the Global Positioning System (GPS)2.0 platform, which will enable reliable long-term tracking of assets in the event of a breakdown. She is part of the research team developing Argo, a Near Earth Object (NPE) satellite servicing and repair system. These systems are said to minimise the risks to personnel in the event of a system failure.With the end of the Cold War came a new era of international cooperation in areas including science and technology, but also in the field of defence. Since the end of the cold war, many partnerships between nations and non-state actors have developed between the former and the latter. These include partnerships between military and civilian research institutions; non-governmental organisations; non-governmental organisations</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co-editor of the upcoming online open-access journal Transport &amp; Technology   (retail edition 2017).PreviousNextElizabeth DenhamIn her research, Elizabeth seeks to understand how technologies and information technologies impact qualitative and quantitative qualitative qualities such as memory, emotion, and knowledge. This can be seen as an interface to more fundamental physical and virtual phenomena, as well as the interaction between human and machine. She is interested in how infrastructures are affected by environmental degradation, as well as how to design resilient infrastructures. Her research is part of the research centre’s 'Knowledge Initiative', a multi-disciplinary research project that addresses knowledge production through a collaborative, multi-disciplinary and inclusive research programme. Through a series of workshops, lectures and seminars, she is guided by the idea that knowledge production should happen in cycles. This would explain why knowledge is produced in cycles, rather than as a fixed record of occurrence and duration. For more information visit Knowledge Initiative website.Elizabeth Den</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co-editor of the upcoming automotive magazine, to be published in 2016, as well as of the automotive trade journal, to be published in 2017. She is part of the research team for the forthcoming book, Systems, Routines and Radicals: Conversations on the Art and Science of Building Systems in the Information Age, published by Arsenal Books.Elizabeth Denham is the author of The Black Stack: New Nanotechnology and the Threatened Planet (2013), Managing Oil and Gas (2014), and is currently a Research Associate at the University of Alberta, where she is developing a new type of archival material for high-performance computing that is both environmentally friendly and energy efficient. Her dissertation examines the role of the nanotechnology industry in the development of environmentally conscious manufacturing through a case study of Hardie Energy, Inc., a Canadian company pioneering the use of nanotechnology in the manufacture of petro-chemicals and components for electric vehicles. The Black Stack Project is a collaborative research project created in collaboration with</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co-editor of the automotive repair and maintenance website Repairing AutoAdvice.com and is Co-Founder and Managing Editor of the automotive repair and maintenance online publication Repairing AutoAdvice.com  analysis               as well as a columnist for the Canadian Auto News and the National Auto Dealer. She has also written for the Daily Express, The Globe and Mail, The Metro and The Wall Street Journal.She is the recipient of several awards and has lectured on a variety of topics concerning the automotive and infrastructure industries. She is a co-editor of the automotive repair and maintenance online publication Repairing AutoAdvice.com and has co-founding partner of Repairing AutoExcellence.com.PreviousNextElizabeth DenhamMSc Candidate in Mechanical Engineering &amp; Introduction to Mechanical Engineering, University of Alberta, Canada, 2015PreviousNextElizabeth DenhamMSc Candidate in Mechanical Engineering &amp; Introduction to Mechanical Engineering, University of Alberta, Canada, 2015</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co-investigator of the Canadian National Lab’s Navigant Research Lab for Autonomous Vehicles and part of a research team developing a next generation of automated repair systems for rail, road and port infrastructure. She is also a consultant for the US company DaimlerChrysler Research Institute, which develops technologies for detecting, measuring and repairing defects in rail, road and port infrastructure. She is a member of the research team developing a new generation of automated repair systems for rail, road and port infrastructure. In addition to developing new technologies, this research team is working on ways to make infrastructure repair a more intuitive and intuitive experience for users.Autonomous Vehicles and Industrial InfrastructuresInfrastructures are increasingly becoming self-repairing. This has led to an explosion of research and development on infrastructures that can be repaired or reconfigured in ways that help meet the needs of society. This has led to developments in infrastructure repair that are cost-effective, efficient and</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co-editor of the upcoming online open access journal Transport &amp; Equipage titled Development &amp; Disruption: Cooperation, collaboration &amp; resilience. She is part of the research team for the upcoming book The Architecture of Resilience: Collaborative Research &amp; Publishing Strategies for a Post-Technological Society.She is part of the research team for the upcoming book The Architecture of Resilience: Collaborative Research &amp; Publishing Strategies for a Post-Technological Society.Ignazio Lazzarato,  	Unravelled, 2015. Installation, Arsenale. Photo: Lucia Carocci.PreviousNextIgnazio Lazzarato,  	Unravelled, 2015. Installation, Arsenale. Photo: Lucia Carocci.Ignazio Lazzarato: A Turin-based artist, Ignazio Lazzarato is a professor in the Department of the Physical Sciences at the University of California, Santa Barbara, and holds a joint appointment with the Art</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co-editor of the forthcoming online edition of &quot;Stepping Stone Reports&quot;, an industry trade publication.She is a co-founder of The Black Stack Project, an academic research centre on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles. The project is developing a host of tools and modules for the autonomous repair or enhancement of vehicles, including modules for the truck, rail and port infrastructure. She is also the project manager for the next edition of 'Stepping Stone Reports', which will be published in 2017.Interview with Elizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is the Max Planck Institute Professor of Chemical and Environmental Engineering at the University of Alberta, and holds the Institute for Sustainable Development Professor Emeritus Chair in Chemical and Environmental Engineering at the University of Alberta. Her research interests include the study of emerging technologies of environmental and urban chemistry; the application of engineering principles to the management of natural resources, including the repair and enhancement of infrastructure; and the study of the complex interactions between engineering, urban and civil</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co-editor of the upcoming automotive industry trade journal, Auto Express, and was instrumental in securing a one-year contract with the Port of Vancouver to add self-healing paint to the Port of Vancouver Railway (PWR) fleet. She is also an advisor for the Port of Vancouver’s new public works plan, titled, Place-Making, which looks to address the challenges of the Port’s burgeoning urban centre.Previous publication:Geographical IndexNext publication:Geographical IndexGeographical IndexA Landscape with a Human FaceBookFacebook TwitterGoogle+LinkedInGeographical IndexA Landscape with a Human FaceBookGeographical IndexA Landscape with a Human FaceBookChina Earthquake and Tsunami: Critical ConceptsAlan M. SchmitzProfessor of Geography and Film Studies at the University of Alberta, Canada, specializes in the history and philosophy of geography. His research focuses on the philosophy, methodology, and theoretical basis of continental-scale theoretical and methodological geology. He is</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence. These could be applied to a variety of domains, including the study of black holes, advanced materials and engineering, and even the development of biofuels. Newer, more disruptive technologies are being developed that could completely change how we live our lives. For more information, visit The Black Stack Project website.Download this article as PDFElizabeth DenhamElizabeth Denham is an MSc candidate in Mechanical Engineering at the University of Alberta, where she is working towards a Bachelor of Science in Chemical and Environmental Engineering. Her research interests are centered on the application of engineering principles to the emerging field of autonomous vehicles and infrastructure. Her dissertation examines the Autonomous Repair System (Ars) developed by Advanced Motorparts Co. for its Ranger, a truck fitted with self-repairing brakes that were part of the Oshkosh, Wisconsin, stationery store chain. Her research is part of a project examining the potential of rail, road and port infrastructure to support autonomous repair systems. She is a co-investigator of a research project examining the effects of pulse-width modulation (Pulse-Width Modulation), an environmentally friendly means of increasing the speed of sound in radio frequency (RF) lines, on roadways and in the maritime sector. Previous research and development deals with the development of driverless transit and autonomous maritime surveying systems. She is a co-investigator of the Canadian Nano-systems Initiative, an interdisciplinary network of government, research and manufacturing institutions, and partners in the DARPA Challenge, a multi-year, multi-funded initiative that develops new technologies for future military and civilian applications. In addition to developing autonomous vehicles and infrastructure, Denham is also a co-founder and co-director of Ultra Mobile Systems, a collaborative research and development institute focused on next-generation platforms in information and communications technology. Her dissertation examines the environmental and social contexts of the development of the nuclear bomb in relation to the role that nuclear engineering and research institutions might play</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and others could flourish. Still, the ‘real’ role of the artist remains an open question. How should the artist engage with the challenges and opportunities of a future society where tools and software are created and not necessarily controlled by a central authority? How should the artist create a more participatory context in which to work, so as to enable that future society to be forged? These are questions that continue to plague contemporary art in the Middle East, and they remain largely unaddressed in academic art history and biennials. This neglect creates an impression of the region as if it were a collection of islands, with isolated inhabitants inhabiting a separate world. It also neglects the fact that the Pan-Arab revolutions shook the region to the core, creating a vacuum of power in the face of increasing authoritarianism, and that the Foundation Projects – the early art and contemporary art institutions in the region – were established as a response to this vacuum. These projects chart the spread of new media, design</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and others could work. As a result, the social and political context surrounding artistic and artistic-type work became increasingly critical in ensuring that it was not subverted for political reasons. The proliferation of social media also played a part in raising awareness of the inherent accessibility of the platform. It enables a certain amount of open and transparent discourse, which contributes to creating the perception that things are happening on a large scale. But it is important to point out that the biennale has a social mission as well. Its mandate is political, and its main form of organising is through the political. The politics of the biennale have recently shifted to one of intensifying inequality and oppression, and it is important for artists and others with whom the organisation comes into contact to realise this. There is a danger that the politics of the biennale are being cancelled in favour of a capitalist form of identity, consumption and consumption culture, where the politics of the item is negated by the politics of the currency and the</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and others could expand their audiences and reach. The advent of computer programming allowed a level of accessibility and interactivity not available in the past, and the proliferation of coding languages has spread cultural norms and professions of knowledge around the globe. But the increasing accessibility and interchangeability of information technologies has come at a cost: the accessibility of information is affected when it is shared, and the pressures of data-intensive use make it increasingly difficult to master a new technology. How to share? How to make sense of it all? These are questions that begin to elucidate new technological paradigms around collaboration and access in an increasingly globalised world.1. Conversational Design and User-Centred DesignThis approach to new technological paradigms was articulated by Nasser Rabbat in his book  	The Contemporary Condition: Toward a Socially Responsible Use of Recent Developments in which he proposes two complementary approaches to the same technologies: caution and adaptation. He argues for caution in favour of an</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and others could develop creative solutions to problems. The consequent spread of research-intensive, postgraduate programmes in engineering, mathematics, computer science and other related fields has its own unique set of influencers, which are exerting a dramatic effect on the local and global artworld. Most pressing, however, are the growing numbers of displaced Palestinians – displaced Muslims, Bedouins and other minority groups forced into forced displacement by developments in the Middle East. This effect is felt in every corner of the globe, and it is now commonplace for artists and designers to contemplate displacement as a result of conflict. This book is an invitation to a conversation about the phenomenon of displacement in the context of contemporary art and design. It seeks to identify the imperatives and social forces shaping the future of Palestine – both today and in the future – in the image of the city.The Arab Spring and subsequent revolutions ushered in a period of geopolitical change in the Middle East, and a shift in international economic and political frameworks. The Arab</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and others could develop creative practices and engage with the systems that underpinned human behaviour. The proliferation of data-processing equipment and networks also plays a role in the social and cultural reproduction of knowledge. More important, it is the proliferation of networks – networks of interconnected devices – that facilitate the exchange of information and ideas across the social networks. These new media provide new ways of understanding the past, creating a critical awareness of social change.In this regard, the proliferation of social networks is closely tied to the spread of cancer. The more computing power is coupled with mobile phones, the more information is transmitted across the globe. As a consequence, the health of a region is affected. ‘Information overload’ is a common complaint of users of social media. This is partly due to the fact that information overload causes users to continuously seek out and re-use content; as a result, the offline human capacity to consume knowledge is severely limited. Consequently, the offline population turns to underground communication channels such as crime</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and others could develop creative solutions to social problems. Such developments made it easier to access research-intensive journals and to access publications in specialist art and design venues. The proliferation of print media also contributed to a decentralisation of political and economic power, making it easier for artists to access resources such as funding and partnerships. In other words, ‘digital activism’ is often conflated with ‘computer activism’ and ends up serving both purposes. That is, the tools used in the service of social change are also used in the service of publishing and communication. If this were not the case, the social struggles would have continued to come from the margins, where people would have been more open to learning and understanding. Today, this is precisely what many in the area still lack. And this is already affecting the ground-rules-based social dynamics that artists develop with their communities, and which can be traced to the 1970s. I will argue that the proliferation of online media and digital culture in</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and intellectuals could thrive and disseminate their work. It is also attributed to the proliferation of Internet-based communication platforms, which allowed accessible and interactive versions of theorised social interaction. But all of these pressures and all of these accruals of knowledge – which were often precursors to the present – can also be attributed to the invention of new computerised tools for analysing and managing data, which allowed for the continuous building of abstract concepts and concepts of all kinds, including human behaviour, which allowed for the construction of ever larger and more complex infrastructures, systems and apparatuses of knowledge.This book is the result of six conferences convened in Beirut, Lebanon, in June 2016, with the participation of leading computer and information science and architecture researchers from over a dozen countries. It is the product of a six-month research project, Project Cybersyn, that I led with my team at École Polytechnique F. Chimayonge in Montreal, Canada. The project</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and others could contribute. But there is also a ‘substantial bias towards democratisation’ in the technologies that power our connected lives. As the World Wide Web was invented, so too were social networks invented – creating platforms on which anyone could contribute and which would then award points to users’ posts. But these were only temporary – people were depositing information on the networks, not the other way around. As a result, the populations involved tended to disperse – from the areas that became web-based platforms, to smaller-scale embedded systems that became embedded into buildings, to connected devices that plugged into electrical grids. And while this fragmentation is inevitable in a society as large as that of the ‘web’, it is also true that the societal scale of such behaviour has increased dramatically in the past twenty years. In an area such as the West Bank and Gaza, which are densely populated and ethnically diverse, the number of Israelis killed in clashes with Palestinians surges over one million;</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and others could work. This is a mistake, says Rabbat: meeting people online is not the same as meeting in person. It is as if the convergence of data has displaced the need for interaction. In fact, meeting people in person today is an essential part of how people get information and ideas. Rabbat’s book is divided into seven parts, each addressing a different aspect of online interaction. Part one, ‘The User’s Interface’ discusses the ways in which people navigate the interface today; it is a virtual reality of sorts, allowing people to ‘step through the cracks’ and uncover greater meanings. Part two, ‘User-Centred Design’ discusses how people interact with software and the mechanisms that allow it to be programmed; it is an approach to understanding not necessarily the human aspect – but the part that is engaged with. Part three, ‘User-Centric Culture’ discusses how people discover and relate to cultural practices; it</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence, and could easily be applied to other fields such as architecture and landscape. The question is whether the research can be applied to realise these imagined futures. Current trends in artificial intelligence could be considered a fad, but the possibilities are there – just not as many as once thought. A future with machine intelligence could mean not as many humans working for it, but many more like-minded individuals sharing the technology. This is the transformative potential of such systems, not the dystopian or even disaster scenarios of present-day societies. Perhaps the real revolution has already happened, and we are just witnessing the first signs of its adoption.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatThe scholarly interest in Palestinian human-computer interaction (or, well, human interaction) has increased over the past decades, but its visibility and influence compare unfavourably with that of previous generations. Much of this is attributed to the explosion of computerised medical diagnostic centres and research labs, which provided a platform on which artists, researchers and others could flourish. In the 1980s and 1990s, the endocentric and neo-natalist literary forms that had defined the contours of what is now called the ‘PC’ were largely displaced by what came to be called the ‘smart phone’ and ‘PCL’ platforms. There was a time when a ‘PCL’ meant a storehouse of software, and a dedicated PC meant a corner shop. Today, the locus of the ‘PCL’ is often defined by a chain of department stores and retail outlets. Some might even say that the PCL is the department store of the 21st century: it contains everything a user might need to get started.For many people, the PCL is seen as a fixed point in time – an object for future reference – while the PSL (the storefront) is seen as a fluid space where objects continually change in relation to one another. But this is not always</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
