<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States.
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States. It would be an entirely new kind of cultural regime, one that seeks to reconcile the different parts of the nation, rather than carving them out into distinct cultural entities. Creativity and collaboration with local communities would be encouraged, as would the creation of working-class-based arts and culture institutions, such as low-income housing co-operatives, within the boundaries of the new cultural regime. Inhabitants of neighbourhoods such as Greenwood Village, East Gwillimbury, which was one of the sites of the 1968 Montreal Exposition, would be given full cultural rights, as would artists, curators and other artists who would set up studios in neighbourhood neighbourhoods such as Greenwood, East Gwillimbury and the surrounding area. This model is not based on race or national origin, but seeks to redress a historical imbalance between the cultural elites and the vast majority of Canadians. It is also not a perfect model, since it is dependent on the willingness of the federal government to step in and fund</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States. The Arsenale should also consider creating a cultural commission that will monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in the years to come, as well as create a new entity that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s future cultural activities in Canada. Finally, the Biennial should consider creating a new entity that would exert cultural control over its artistic activities in Canada and the United States. These tasks could be divided among a number of different cultural entities, such as the Arsenale, Biennial, Biennial trustees, artists' unions, etc. The question is, who would exercise cultural control? The answer, of course, is Canada’s largest and most visible art community. It would be an unprecedented and potentially destabilizing move for the Biennial to separate itself from its local community of artists, curators, curatorial and artistic resources, and most importantly, its artistic and curatorial identity. Artists, curators, artists’ unions, artistic professionals, artists</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States. It would also create a new curatorial approach that would draw upon the biennial’s strengths and weaknesses, while supplementing it with innovative new approaches to address the unique needs of the American and Canadian biennial communities. The Arsenale has expressed interest in the possibility of creating a similar joint venture with a city in North America. It would create a new entity that would monitor and supervise the activities of the biennial in that city, including but not limited to: art, culture, architecture, transportation, housing, parks and natural resources, education and recreation, media and exhibition design. The entity would be responsible for: (1) the artistic and curatorial direction of the biennial in that city; (2) the development and implementation of the joint venture’s cultural initiatives; (3) the financial support of the joint venture’s art programs; and (4) the continuation of the partnership’s legacy in that city. The entity would have sole access</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States. The Biennial itself, through its art institutions, could also become a co-convenor of this new venture. Its mission statement, 'to foster dialogue and exchange between artists, curators, community members and other stakeholders' would become a statement of intent.1 The partnership between the Biennial and the Arsenale is a new paradigm in art-sponsored cultural exchanges. It signals a new era of cultural exchange between local and national artworlds, and between biennials and other art forms. The Arsenale’s financial backers include the Fonds de recherche du Québec, the Fonds de santé pub, the Federated Arts Association, and the National Endowment for the Arts. The Arsenale, through its charter, stipulates that its activities must be ‘relevant to the cultural needs and priorities of Québec’s Québécois identity’. As a nonprofit arts institution, the Arsenale has an ethical</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States. It would also create a new cultural entity separate from, but in parallel to, the Biennial, operating under the Biennial banner. For this to happen, a number of conditions must be met: (1) a cultural department must be created; (2) a set of priorities must be established; (3) a cultural department must be fully autonomous; and (4) a set of artists, producers, curators and others with skills and perspectives relevant to the context in which the biennial operates, must be invited to apply for roles. The joint venture proposal raises new possibilities for cultural enterprises in cities that are not suburbanised or ruralised. It also provides the basis for a new kind of urban culture, one that is not confined to the peripheries but extends outward in directions beyond the cities and rural centres. 	 The proposal calls for the creation of a cultural entity that extends beyond the city limits of Montreal, and possibly beyond, to the cities and suburbs outside of Montreal. This</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States.Creative perforationsThe idea of the biennial as an artistic perforation emerges early in the book, in an epigraph that begins, ‘The Biennial: a cultural perforation’. It is the perforation of a niche market segmentation that is particularly sensitive to artistic interventions, and the positioning of biennials as element in that market segmentation. The book ends with a list of questions that begins, ‘What next?’ The book opens with a question mark, and a question mark again, in the present of a multinational corporation. The word ‘biennial’ appears seventeen times, in twenty-one places, in connection with other questions. The word ‘perforation’ appears twenty-six times, and twenty-five places, in the same connection. The word ‘art’ appears twenty-nine times, and twenty-six places, in the same connection. The word ‘artificial per</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States. It would also create a new entity that would be accountable to no fewer than five federal, provincial and municipal governments, but would have sole authority over material and intellectual property issues. The joint venture would have sole authority over the biennial’s work in Toronto and Montreal, and over the material and intellectual property rights of artists, producers and curators in each of the other major Canadian cities. This proposal represents an interesting new paradigm for the relationship between biennials and large art institutions, and it could prove a game-changer for the biennial in Canada. However, this is not at all what happened in Russia during the 1990s.In 1990, when the Biennial was founded in St. Petersburg, the Russian Federation, and its artists, curators, collectors and other stakeholders actively participated in creating a unique opportunity to showcase their collections and participate in a unique programme of activities. The Biennial's mission statement reads as follows: ‘The Biennial is an international, regional and</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States. It would also create a new joint venture with a territory in the Caribbean, the Cayman Islands and Federated States of Micronesia that would jointly manage and monitor the biennial’s collections. This joint venture would make artworks available online, wherever art is currently prohibited. The project itself seems to be expanding, with online readings and interactive installations becoming increasingly prominent. The new online biennial, as we know, is a curated event, giving priority to works produced by and specifically for the event. It is up to the artists, curators and festival organisers to create a unique experience for the event, and to make sure that this event maximises their potential. I believe that the biennial has the potential to become culturally responsive – to engage with and even to educate – so that we can all participate in creating a better future for generations to come.Download this article as PDFErnesto López de la TorreErnesto López de la Torre</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States. It would be an innovative way to invest in the future of the biennial, but it would also expose the biennial to the vagaries of market forces and the unpredictable unpredictable behaviour of cultural industries. It would be a dangerous bet, allowing a biennial to lose its cultural edge, becoming less able to adapt to changing circumstances and societies.  	[1] See Hilary Putman, ed., The Biennial Condition: Contemporary Art and its Philosophical Intersection (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2011), pp. 8–19.  [2] See Hilary Putman, ed., The Biennial Condition: Contemporary Art and its Philosophical Intersection (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2011), p. 7. [3] See Hilary Putman, ed., The Biennial Condition: Contemporary Art and its Philosophical Intersection (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2011), p. 8. [4] Ibid., p</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system is an open question. Is it possible to create an environment in which such systems could operate in a meaningful way? If so, how? One possibility is to implant these systems with sensors that monitor and record daily activities, like food and water consumption. As a biennial approaches its third decade, it is important to ask how the biennial is connecting to its historical context. If the biennial is to become culturally responsive, the cultural departments of both the U.S. and Canada need to be consulted on changes, as well as the other artists, producers and curators who will be creating works in the years to come. This could be done through a new joint venture between the Biennial and the Arsenale, which would create a new division within the Biennial that would monitor and supervise the activities of the Biennial in Canada. This joint venture would create a new entity, one that would exert cultural control over the biennial’s activities in Canada and the United States. It would create a new joint venture with the mandate to promote and produce cultural content for the biennial in Canada. Finally, it would create a joint venture with the mandate to commission artwork for the biennial in the United States. This last part is crucial, because in order to accomplish the ambitious cultural projects that will be created in the years to come, the Biennial will have to produce high-quality works that will be treasured by audiences in both locations, and that will be treasured by all. It will also have to produce works that will be treasured by audiences in both locations, and that will be treasured by all.In order to achieve these three tasks, the Biennial will have to create cultures of exploration and wonder in both its historical and contemporary contexts. It will have to produce works that speak to both contemporary art and contemporary needs, while simultaneously understanding the other. It will be able to engage audiences globally through engaging with current events and social phenomena through art that is both</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara University from 1936–37 and Professor of Physics at the University of California, Berkeley from 1938–39. He was the Director of the Berkeley Geology Laboratory from 1945–49 and the Los Alamos National Laboratory from 1953–58. He is a Fellow of the American Museum of Natural Sciences and was a 1977 graduate of the American Geophysical Union. He was editor of the online nautical journal Rock &amp; Roll, and was a co-founder of the Rock &amp; Roll Archive (1988). He was also a founding member of the Geology Education Foundation and a board member of the Geology Education Foundation. He is an advisor for the Climate Research Program at the University of California, San Diego. He was a consultant for the film Argo and the TV show The X Files.He is the author of From Deserts to Cities: Urban Geographies of the Recent Past and has written frequently for the New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, and Climate Central. He is the recipient</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara University, where he directed the school’s geological and mineralogy department. He was also director of the Manhattan Institute, a publicly funded research center at the Santa Clara University Graduate School of Education devoted to the &quot;future impact of technological change&quot;. He was a member of the Board of Trustees for the New York City Museum, where he was a chair of the board. He was a consultant to the United States Geological Survey and the United States National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration, where he supervised the development of the ‘Geology of Future Oceans’ project.He was also a consultant for the Manhattan Project, where he designed and implemented the Manhattan Project Research Center at the Santa Clara University Graduate School of Education, which provided a multi-disciplinary, publicly accessible, and energy-efficient set of tools for the study of human habitation and evolution. He was an advisor to the Manhattan-based sub-studies in Biological Geology and Geology of Materials and Structures, where his</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara University from 1956–60 and Professor of Physics at the University of California, Santa Cruz from 1963–66. He was also the Director of the Max Planck Institute for Geosciences in Berlin, where he was a co-founder of the Geosciences Kulturkampf (1968–1976) and the Max Planck Institute for Geophysics and Planetary Research in Berlin, where he was a co-founder of the Max Planck Institute for Extraterrestrial Physics in Santa Cruz, and a co-director of the New Museum in New York. He was a fellow of the American Museum of Geology and Geophysics and the American Geographical Society. He was a member of the American Geographical Society. The Monuments Men, Parikka’s first and most famous work, was completed in 1968. His work on the Monuments was part of a series of paintings that he presented as part of the Heidelberg Project. The Monuments was</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara University, a position he held from 1927 to 1982. He is the author of the Nebula-Winners: The Physical and Literary Character of Science Fiction (1984), and of the award-winning (1994) Science &amp; Sand: On Writing and Unwriting Science Fiction (2001). He is Professor of Geology and Geophysics at the University of California, Santa Cruz, where he directed the university’s Center for Earth and Planetary Exploration, where his work focuses on the geology and mineralogy of the San Andreas Fault and the San Andreas Mountains. He has written widely on geology, in particular on the role of oil in the climate system, and on the economic implications of resource depletion.He is a Fellow of the American Geophysical Union and the American Geographical Association. His work has been featured in journals such as Science, The New York Times, The Washington Post, Popular Science, The New Republic, The New Republic of San Francisco, Popular Science Digital and the Smithsonian Institution.</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara University, and Director of the Geology and Planetary Sciences Division, the Department of Earth, Planetary and Environmental Sciences, and the Geology and Quaternary Sciences Departments at UC Riverside. His publications include the popular science-neocon Essential Geology (1937), in which he advocated the primacy of geology in the national and international education systems, and the popularizer of geological concepts such as &quot;plate&quot; and &quot;ore&quot; in curricula throughout the country. He received a MacArthur Fellowship from the National Science Foundation, and the William and Flora Louise Marshall Fund from the Carnegie Corporation, and was a member of the Board of Trustees of the American Museum of Naturalists. He taught geology and planetary sciences at the University of California, Santa Barbara, where he served as its Dean from 1929–37. He was a fellow of the American Museum of Naturalists, and the American Geographical Association.He was a founding director of the Santa Clara University Museum of Art and a member</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara University and Professor of Physics at the University of California, Santa Barbara. He served as the chair of the Department of Earth and Planetary Sciences at the University of California, Santa Cruz, where he taught for half a century. He was also the editor of the popular science and technology magazines Science &amp; Technology and the Internet Magazine. He was the co-producer of the television show The Search for Extraterrestrial Intelligence (1979), in which he participated alongside fellow geologists Carl Sagan and Terry Smith. His latest book is 	The Global Space Coast: Economic Possibilities for Our Time – Forecasting and Capitalizing on the Scientifically Based Developments of the Past Decade (2015). In 2007 he was appointed as a professor of Earth and Planetary Sciences at the University of California, Santa Cruz. He is the author of The Ecology of Space: The Geology of Ocean Acidification (1992), Geology: The Social Life of Place (2008), and the forthcoming Geology of Virtuality (</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara University, and was Director of the Geology and Planetary Sciences Division, the A. Bonifacio Foundation for Geology and Planetary Sciences at Stanford University, and the California Institute of Technology. He was a member of the Board of Directors of the American Museum of Naturalists, and was a board member of the American Physical Society. He was a founding director of the Santa Clara University Center for Earth and Environmental Studies, and the Santa Clara University Earth Science and Technology Lab, where his work on the Ames Research Station in Iowa under the direction of Prof. Peter Weibel was funded by the National Science Foundation. His work on the Ames Research Station focused on the effects of radiative forcing on the Earth's crust and mantle, and on the lithosphere, a subsurface layer of the mantle that acts as a shear boundary between the Earth and the mantle beneath it. Known phenomena at the station included the formation of volcanic plumes and the eruption of magma from beneath the Earth, which in turn</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara University and Professor of Physics at the University of California, Santa Cruz. He was the Director of the Santa Clara University Atmospheric Laboratory and the Santa Cruz Museum of Art. He was a co-founder of the Santa Clara University Climatic Lab and the Santa Cruz Museum of Art. He taught at the University of California, Berkeley, and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. He was professor of civil and environmental engineering at the University of California, Santa Cruz and the director of the Santa Cruz Museum of Art. He was a consultant to the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers and the Federal Emergency Management Agency. He was a consultant to Lockheed Martin and NASA on disaster mitigation strategies. He was a consultant to Arjen Mulder and Allan Sekula on future-looking art. He was a consultant to Honeywell on disaster risk management. He was a consultant to Transfield and GTE on civil aviation and the environment. He was a consultant to Schneider Electric on environmental risk management. He was the founding director of</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara University from 1956–58 and Professor of Physics at the University of California, Santa Cruz from 1958–60. He was also the postdoctoral researcher at the California Institute of Technology, where his work focused on the magma beneath the Earth's surface. He taught geology and planetary sciences at the University of California, Santa Cruz and the University of California, Berkeley. He also worked as an adjunct professor at the University of California, Los Angeles. His publications include books on geology and planetary science, essays on the environment, and scientific reports on technologies of habitation. He was a consultant for the film Contact, as well as the television show Planet Earth. He is a co-founder of the Museum of Contemporary Art and the Biennial Project.Researcher and Envisioner 	The word ‘researcher’ describes those who seek to understand the causes and consequences of an event or phenomenon. It describes those who understand the significance of an event, its causes and consequences. For example</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI's global circulation and the connections between culture and technology, in which worksite adaptation to climate change and other aspects of the biennial would be part of the agenda. 	[2] Excerpt from the talk, ‘Climate chaos: What will be the future of biennials?’, given at the annual convention of the International Association for the Study of Culture and Technology (IASCT), June 2016. 	[3] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of biennials in the future city’,  	Future City, July 2016. 	[4] Wilfried Neuhof, ‘On the future of biennials’,  	Future City, September 2016. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka (1909–2006) was an American geologist, geologist and physicist. He was Professor of Geology at Santa Clara University and the Director of the Geology and Planetary Sciences Department, The Engineering School, Santa Clara University. He was also the editor of the popular science and math magazines Science &amp; Mathematics. He was a member of the Board of Trustees for the Santa Clara University Geology and Mineralogical Survey. He taught at Santa Clara University, where he was an adjunct professor, and the University of Illinois, where he was a professor of geography and geography. His publications include the popular scientific articles in Science &amp; Mathematics (1962–78) and Science (1939–45) and the essays in Popular Science (1951) and Popular Science (1962) and Popular Science (1957). He was a member of the Board of Trustees for the Santa Clara University Geology and Mineralogical Survey.He was a co-founder of the American Geophysical Union and the Santa Clara University Board of Trustees. He was a member of the Board of Trustees of the United Earth Union, was</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development around the globe: the construction of ever-larger airports, highways and shipping lines; the development of ever-more elaborate highway interchanges; the massive mechanisation of manual labour; the industrial fluidisation of sub-contracting labour; the proliferation of satellite dishes that take up valuable real estate; the proliferation of GPS-based mapping services; the proliferation of remote-sensing cameras that record the landscape around them; the proliferation of runway runways and the like; and the ever-more elaborate ways in which infrastructure is made (including the porous, soft and lightweight qualities of materials and the plant ‘systems’ and biomaterials that are woven into it’s surface).  And here you are, another passages from the same book, another section devoted to the built environment, this time laying out the social and political meanings of the built environment. You begin to see the connections between the social and the political (including how the built environment may be defined as ‘social</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development around the globe, such as in ­Mumbai’s new ‘Golden City’ – a ‘city on a shoestring’ – that will eventually boast a wealth of office and retail space, education and health facilities, recreation facilities and cultural facilities, as well as a multitude of cultural venues and exhibition venues.  And here you’ve placed the concept of ‘space’ in the context of a social totality that includes elements of both public and ‘private’ spheres. Public space is being created increasingly through the incorporation of biennials and museums into their curatorial activities, as well as the collaborative activities among the arts community with other institutions.  And ‘space’ here refers to the physical (including buildings and infrastructure) as well as the virtual (including the intangible, such as respect, luxury and places). Within the meaning of classic Marx’s ‘transvaluation’ of commodities, space is the spatial equivalent</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development that landscape architects and urban theorists produce in order to explain why cities are so important. But to think about ‘space’ means to inhabit, to step out of one’s comfort zone, to explore unfamiliarity, to encounter unfamiliarity and so on. And to ‘space’ in this sense means land, buildings, landscapes and so forth. The problem with spatiality in general is that it constrains movement – movement as industrial production, logistic production, commodities flow, transport infrastructure development, migration and so forth. And yet you rarely get tired of the idea of space, the built environment or the urban environment. You tend to get caught up in the details, the particular features and ornamentation that distinguish certain parts of the city from others. And this is especially true for younger people.  A more accurate rendering of the cityscape would involve more than the icons and numbers that we have today: it would involve ‘living space’ and ‘cultural</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development, from the footprints of the defunct suburban railway to the millions of square feet of office and retail space now occupied by biennials and museums.You write: ‘But what we mean when we talk about ‘space’ is precisely what Paul Feyer­hert and his team did with their term: ‘space-use maximisation’. They chose an ideal spatial framework to work with: a sphere of influence around a center of enormous physical and financial resources, with clear definitions of what counts as ‘space’ (including, I guess, the concept of ‘space’ as a physical entity)? The reason they chose to build a biennial around a single city rather than a regional hub is that this centric framing destroys the dynamic of multi-sited, multi-use places: places with varying uses of ‘space’ – places with varying uses of ‘facade’ – places where use creates or contributes to form. You</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development that are projected onto the landscape to accompany the news stories of major incidents in the city. You also see it in the ‘climate’ section of maps, which usually includes figures such as   	UNEP’s   figurehead,   	Carrot Top, burning coal as a fossil fuels source. Cities are made up of built and planned environments that constantly – and very nearly always – require the creation of new forms of urbanisation to accommodate them all. Cities are the most illustrative of all such spaces, because they are made up of a dense, coherent set of building and social forms that constantly seek to be incorporated into one another. Cities, then, are often seen as resources that can be utilized, and in that sense are often overused. But they are also seen as ‘resourceful’, and that is to say, creative in their use. In that sense, they are capable of supporting all manner of uses, including their own misuse</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development around the world: new airports, subways, shopping malls, highways, tunnels, bridges, tunnels, streets, public squares, parks, historic streets and islands, islands of residential neighbourhoods and islands of migrant labourers. And you can almost picture these huge expanses of land and the built infrastructure of cities as ‘urban farms’, where small plots of land and infrastructure ‘supporting communities of habitation and recreation are located, feeding into larger ‘institutional farms’, where crops and land are produced and utilised. And ‘institutional farms’ are the objects of careful surveillance and regulation, to the extent that they support the capitalist accumulation of capital. You see this in the way in which biennials and museums attempt to meet the needs of an urban or suburban constituency, in their search for ‘uniqueities’ in an urban setting. You see it in the institutional ­nature of scientific or museum-type research, where the research is often</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development around the globe, in the unfolding ‘urbanization’ that you and I are part of, but which is mainly occurring in the developed world: in New York and London, Mumbai and Shenzhen, Johannesburg and Port Elizabeth, to name only a few cities). Cities that are rapidly becoming unrecognisably more like islands, or disconnected metropolises. Cities that are no longer defined by the built environment but by the connectivity and mobility provided by digital technology. ‘Cities’ are the virtual replicas of the replicas of the ‘built environment’. Your and I are placed in this ‘digital space’ that is becoming ever more mobile and ephemeral, and this is threatening not just the historical value of cities but also the very identity of cities. Cities are no longer defined by the value that they add to the value system of exchange and consumption; cities are valued for the capacity that they provide at a moment and in a particular place.</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development around the globe: vast agricultural plantations, neon-glimmering skyscrapers ‘covered in sensors’ that monitor farming operations; massive surveillance networks, setting aside particular neighbourhoods for thoroughfares; and the increasingly common use of bomb shelters and underground basements.  And yet ‘space’ has always been a somewhat ambiguous term, open to various interpretations. You might say that space is a ‘form’ of social organization – that is, a kind of social organization according to which social entities (people, groups, societies) inhabit distinct spheres of space. You might also say that ‘space’ is a ‘mode of knowing’, a kind of spatial system that organises knowledge into different kinds of relations. And you might even say that space is a ‘mode of experiencing’, a kind of space enabling ‘knowing’ according to the capacities of particular living beings.  And this kind of ‘mode of knowing</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development around the world: the ­New York City subway map, the Asian subways map, the ‘Road Map to Urban Development’ for India, the ‘Map of India’s Urban Frontier’ on a map. The Asian subways map, for example, takes into account the ‘contemporaneous effect’ of different cities ‘combining to form larger metropolises’. The implication of this ‘contemporaneous effect’ is that these ‘urban quarters’ are spread out over larger areas, creating what Swaminathan calls ‘universes of space’. But what does ‘space’ mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? I think of it as a ‘complex construct’ that has many forms, but one that is becoming increasingly important as we inhabit the cities of the modern world? One that is no longer confined to the city as the ‘hub</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that maps, categorises and categorises – mapping, in fact, to the operation of cities. The question becomes, what does mapping mean in the age of the biennial and the museum? The answer, it seems to me, is that it ‘transcends’ the usual definitions of space (including that of nation) and nation (including that of space). It is, I believe, the new normalised form of space-taking-place-entirely.I draw your attention to a passage from your 2008 Political Economy of Art and Ideas, in which you begin:  One might ask what is meant by ‘space’ by these terms. To most people, when they think of ‘space’, they think of buildings, mountains, cities and the built environment. But when we talk about ‘space’, we usually mean land, the built environment and the built infrastructure of cities. You see this in the huge images of urban development around the globe, in the phrase ‘space-occupying’ concrete monstrosities, such as the Dubai Metropolitan Municipality’s planned ‘Golden City’ and the ‘Granby Four’ suburban rings around New York City. You also see it in the commercial real-estate speculation around the globe, in the phrase ‘market-share’ being used to describe the clusters of apartments, office parks and housing developments that line the financial lines of the metropolis.’ You see it in the commercial cruise lines, in the high-end Michelin-starred restaurants of Asia, and in the packaging of some products by multinational food companies, such as Intl Market Research International (2002–08). You see it in the financial instruments that monitor and analyse the world economy – the sub-prime housing crisis and its aftermath, in-depth analysis of which I wrote about in my book A Financial Volcano (2011). And you see it in</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics
    <text>should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Emptiness: Art and the Politics of Entrapment, Oxford University Press, New York, 2002.Laura Raicovich: On Being Mortal: On Being Moved: Toward a Philosophy of Being, Thames and Hudson, London, 2000.Gareth White: Politics of Emptiness, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1994.Peter Osborne: Systems of Embodiment, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1996.Download this article as PDFGareth White and Laura Raicovich-On Being Mortal (2014)Gareth White and Laura Raicovich-On Being Mortal (2014) is the story of two artists who, through a series of public interventions, were able to change the understanding and practices of their local communities from being predominantly about white artists and white venues, to a more nuanced and inclusive range of artists, predominantly from other parts of the UK and abroad. The project has been published in a number of academic and urban journals including: The Routledge International Handbook</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Intimacy, Yale University Press, New Haven, 1992.Joasia Krysa: Intimacy and Its Spaces, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 2002.Joasia Krysa: On Intimacy, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 1996.Lucia Sanrome: On Intimacy, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 1991.Michael Albert: Toward a Philosophy of Intimacy, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2004.Svetlana Boym: On Intimacy, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 1988.Marijke Steedman: On Intimacy, Yale University Press, New Haven, 1996.Svetlana Boym: On Intimacy, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 1988.Michael Albert: Intimacy and Other Essays, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1999.Lucia Sanrome: Intimacy and Other Essays, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1999.S</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 1994.Nikki Milligan: Politics of Intimacy, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2012.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. She is Professor in the Department of the Arts and Cultural Practice at the Yale School of Art, specializing in art and culture in transition, including the arts and culture of the digital age. She is the author of The Gallery as a Digital Scenario, to be published by Yale University Press, New Haven, 2017.PreviousNextNikki MilliganKaren Bowden is a curator in the Science &amp; Technology section of the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. She is the recipient of the RIBA Award for Excellence in Science &amp; Technology (2014) and the Mechanical and Power Cubes of Our Times, to be published by MIT Press,</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Emptiness, University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 2002.Logan J. Gilmore: The Politics of Emptiness, University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 1983.Rafico Ruiz: ‘The Politics of Intimacy: Communicating a Project in Seventy-One Letters’, in The New Media Reader, Issue 3, Number 2, Autumn, 2002, p. 707.Download this article as PDFRafico RuizRafico Ruiz: I am interested in the notion of openness, or what I would like to think of as openness, in relation to social transformation. The concept of openness is often used in relation to the work of art, but few of its applications are intended to be shared. Social transformation is a relational process; and as such, it is not possible to perform the social transformation of an institution without understanding what the other, institutionalised forms of social transformation entail. Therefore it is essential for artists to develop critical skills</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Emptiness, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 2008.Joasia Krysa: On Cultures of Abandonment and the Episodic, Palgrave, London, 2013.Jan Montefiore: On Cultures of Abandonment, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 2006.Svetlana Boym: ‘Culturomics, or the Cultural Economy of Abandonment’, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 2005.Jan Montefiore: ‘Culturomics: economics of cultural  	abandonment’, in  	Curtis M. Kling’s Culture and Abundance: Social Science, Cultural Economics and Politics, ed. Michael J. Fox, Roe Director, Harvard University Press, Cambridge, 1988, p.187–223.Joasia Krysa: On Cultures of Abandonment, Oxford University Press, New Haven,2009.Svetlana Boym: ‘Cultur</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Emptiness, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 2002.Brendan Knowlton: Visual Life and Material Life, Routledge, New York, 2011.Sarah Lowdnes: Material Life and Symbolic Life, Routledge, New York, 2008.Dirk Groot: Current Anthropology, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1998.Download this article as PDFDirk Groot and Susie O’SullivanIn recent years, the exhibition business and its curators has tended to produce artists who are more prominently involved in the production of visual events, such as festivals, such as the football fans in Sunderland, who engaged with the fact that a large security detail was brought in to keep fans out of Anfield, and the film-makers in Leeds, who commissioned an installation to document their experience in the Welsh Streets, both in Liverpool. The absorbing effect of these exhibitions has often been to erase or modulate these deeper, more contextualised political themes. Despite this, the art world</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Emptiness: Art, Capital and the Form of Radical Embodiment, University of Chicago Press, New York, 1976.Jussi Parikka: Toward a Theory of Emptiness, Blackwell, Oxford, 1988.Meehan Crist: Toward a Theory of Emptiness, Blackwell, Oxford, 1986.Svetlana Boym: Toward a Theory of Emptiness, Blackwell, Oxford, 1986.Erin O'Toole: Politics of Emptiness, Ithaka/MIT, New York, 1988.Marijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 1974.Svetlana Boym: Politics of Emptiness, Ithaka/MIT, New York, 1974.Meehan Crist: Toward a Theory of Emptiness, Blackwell, Oxford, 1986.Erin O'Toole: Politics of Emptiness, Ithaka</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Emptiness, Routledge, New York, 1992.Shubhess Krishnamurthy: The Practice of Everyday Life, Routledge, New York, 1997.Svetlana Boym: On Being Migrantas, Zed Books, New York, 2012.Erin O'Toole: Being Migrantas, Zed Books, New York, 2013.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Emptiness, Routledge, New York, 1996.Erin O'Toole: The Politics of Emptiness, Routledge, New York, 1999.Rafico Ruiz: The Politics of Emptiness, Routledge, New York, 2001.Download this article as PDFShubhess KrishnamurthyShubhess Krishnamurthy is a writer, producer, and co-ordinator of the New Migrant Movement, an artistic collective that produces works on topics relating to New York City and the migrant/migrant experience. Her</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Emptiness, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 2008.Robin Mackay: Politics of Emptiness, Oxford University Press, New Haven, 2008.Anna Best: From Community Arts to Museum Studies, Routledge, Oxford and New York, 2010.Download this article as PDFAna Laura López de la TorreAna Laura López de la Torre is a curator, producer and writer whose work centers on the politics of visual culture. Her work has addressed the intersections between visual culture and public involvement, the practices and ideologies of resistance, and the legacy of colonialism and slavery. She is the founder and editor of the website Visual Culturist, which is dedicated to the study of visual culture and resistance. She has written for El Pais, The New York Times, El Pais Mundo, as well as El Universal, El Universal de los Muertos, and El Universal de Tijuana. She is currently a consultant for El Universal's Culture and</text>
    <text>should be curated’, the directorial equivalent of a curatorial visit). For more information, please see our Curatorial Faculty page.Download this article as PDFErin O'TooleErin O'Toole is the Curator of Public Practice at the National Gallery, where she has worked since 2012. Her areas of expertise include the exhibition business, the visual arts and architecture. She is a co-founder and co-editor of The Visual Arts Blog (www.visualartsblog.com) and the official publication of the Visual Culturist Federation, as well as of the exhibition business LACMA (Los Angeles County Museum of Art). She is a fellow of the American Association for the Study of Modern Art (2013-16). She has taught at the University of California, San Diego, and Columbia University.BooksMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009.Svetlana Boym: The Politics of Emptiness: A Companion to Painting, Oxford University Press, New York (1977), p. 2124, cited in Susanne Kuntschmid: On Anarchism and Public Art, Blackwell, Oxford (1967).Mario Negri: Everyday Painting, Verso, New York (1976), p. 7, cited in Susanne Kuntschmid: On Anarchism and Public Art, Blackwell, Oxford (1967).Inhabitant: Stories from the Counterculture Generation, Picador, New York (1986), p. 34.Download this article as PDFMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of EmptinessMarijke Steedman: Painting and the Politics of Emptiness, Yale University Press, New Haven, 2009, pages 32-34, responds to Debord’s, and in some instances her own, formulation as to the type of fascism that characterises contemporary capitalism. Drawing on her years as an artist at the New Museum in</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common. The biennial format is the result of a historical tendency towards the confluence of resources, which has been accompanied by an increasing dependence on them. In the twentieth century, this tendency was seen as the direct consequence of the growth of the welfare state and the urban sprawl that accompanied it, and which today is seen as a cost of living increase. In the twenty-first century, it is also seen as a necessity in an increasingly urbanised world. In both historical and contemporary terms, the confluence of resources – which in contemporary capitalist societies is generally understood as a city-dwelling population – is a more or less unavoidable condition. But the tendency towards the confluence of resources has shifted the balance of culture production away from the city towards the rural and the coastal, and in this process has created what Richard Florida calls a ‘new urban terrain’. Florida is the John Lennon of the Bio-biennial generation: born in New York in 1957, Lennon became a multi</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common. These cultural resources are scarce, but they are culturally relevant and can act as a catalyst for change. In a biennial, the museum is a political office, a site of power and control, but also a place of liberatory possibilities and possibilities. It is the site of the artist’s most visible expression, and it wields considerable political and economic influence. The biennial is a political office because it is so easily manipulated into action, as evidenced by biennials across historical periods, from the late eighteenth century to the early twentieth century, that were led by men such as Francis Galton, John Graham Kerr and Noel Burch. Biennials in the twenty-first century are more easily styled as ‘curated for the people’, a term that is as opaque and misused within the field of contemporary art as it is in the museum. The impact of this misappropriation is felt in numerous places in the city, where artists are frequently employed by the</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common. The biennial format allows for the cultural resources of a city to be brought together in a common space in the form of resources – which is to say, cultural resources and their resources. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily the money, which is coming due; the real trouble is the ability to think imaginatively and creatively about its cultural resources. This may be seen as a challenge to the biennial format, but I believe that the museum must address this problem in order to achieve its current and future cultural resources. For example, the ability to bring together cultural resources in an accessible and useful way is closely tied to the capacity of museums to fund their activities, which is increasingly precarious in an era of austerity. The biennial format may be an effective counter to this crisis, if it is seen as a maintenance and repair mechanism rather than a potential growth engine.In sum, the current biennial format – which seeks to capture and distribute cultural assets and resources across a geographically broad geographic area</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common. The biennial is financially sustainable through its membership in a regular, predictable and growing lump sum. But the access to these resources – which are shared between the biennial and the city – is seen by many local residents and artists as something that is marginalised and not valued as highly as it is by other residents and artists. As a result, the biennial has tended to be exclusionary in its programming, excluding other forms of cultural activity and exhibitionary in its own way. But this is changing. The biennial will now have a curatorial team of artists dedicated to its development, and will actively participate in making the city what it really is: a city with a biennial on a regular basis. The biennial will have a social mission statement that draws on the values and histories of the city it is housed in, and adopts the language of the local. It will have a legislative framework around cultural resources, funding and law that draw on the local’s cultural practices and</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common. The biennial’s current financial projections are as follows:2018 – $165-185,000,000, with a focus on the arts and their connections to the city. 	[1] http://www.biennial.com/en/art/exhibitions/2018/exhibition-list/artists-in-charge/sign-up/?utm_medium=DownloadArticle&amp;utm_source=BIennial&amp;utm_campaign=160646afb58c9bcbcf4afbcf055afbcf7afbcf7afbcf72afbcf6c6db4c6db2efbcf6dbcf6dbcf6dbcc6dbcd6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6dbcc6</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common. The biennial structure is an odd hybrid: it can be seen as an investment in the local community but also as a way to channel cultural energies into artistic production. The annual budget of the museum is allocated through a complex formula that places a heavy emphasis on the museum’s assets, while simultaneously demanding that the museum preserve the city’s cultural character and ethos. The current budget of the biennial is set at US$8 million, with a target of US$12 million. The museum is in a unique position: its resources and assets are in constant demand by artists and curators wanting to make the city a museum, yet it has no institutional funding source. It relies entirely on member contributions, tax-deductible donations and membership fees. The biennial format has become so popular that it is now commonplace for the biennial to have a residency programme, whereby artists and curators move to the city from other institutions, often through a very short programme, and this brings</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common. If the museum is to maintain its current level of investment in the area, it is imperative that it is able to shift these cultural resources to where they can have a significant impact on the local communities. It is impossible for the museum to continuously fund itself through the sale of cultural resources or the purchase of art, because this would negate the historical value of the resources. The biennial format is the only viable long-term vision for the future of the museum, because it is both historically accurate and culturally responsive.In the 1970s and 1980s, cultural resources were seen as a way to bring about a revolution in urban planning and the social policies that would then be implemented in the area (corneria ad Luxima). The biennial format is a direct result of these previous curatorial interventions. It is a way to simultaneously celebrate the cultural resources of a city while also exploiting their economic potential through the production of cultural tourism. The key is to deliver a message to visitors that is both powerful</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common. Fundraising has been a problem for the biennial, due to the high cost of materials and staff, as well as the museum’s often pop-culture-laden programming. The new curatorial approach may solve this as well as any material difference. The new format may be more about the people – the people who now live there, and who will one day move away – than about the art, or art in this case, that is being produced in the area. It may be a biennial where the art is produced by a community of locally relevant artists, or it may be a community of artists producing work across multiple sites in a densely populated area. It may be a ‘home of artists’ within a larger cultural context’. In the former case, the arts producers would establish networks of artists through residencies, fellowships and other programmes, while the local communities would benefit from the arts being made visible across multiple media. The new curatorial approach to the</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common. The biennial’s current financial situation is mainly dependent on the number of visitors, who come to the museum as an increased customer base leads to ever-greater bookings and museum admission prices. If the visitor numbers stay the same, but the resources that are produced by the museum (its curatorial instincts, its historical resources, and its exhibitions) increase, the biennial will have to raise its game or be left behind. In the past, this has meant inventing more museums and acquiring wider geographic areas to explore. Today, it is much easier to access a museum (or a large collection of objects) via a commute than it is to get involved in a local community or attend a museum regularly, especially since museums charge a nominal admission. So the biennial has to find new ways of existing in an urban context. It also has to find ways to connect with the people who visit the museum. This last step can be problematic, since the museum is seen as a transient</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. It will focus on the city’s past, as imagined by and for the urbanist/biennial. It will be an extension of the Biennial project, though this time around the artist will be leading the curatorial team. The museum will play a central role, providing a long-term home for the art and encouraging a dialogue between art and the natural world that is at once respectful of the artist’s past work and present-taking.The biennial format has its roots in the 1960s and 1970s, when the museum was seen as a more authentic visual language of the city compared to the archaeological, archival and historical resources of other museums. This was seen as a way to ensure that the biennial would be responsive to the needs and interests of the local communities that would inhabit the area once the museum closed. The museum’s current financial situation is a consequence of this historical model of the museum holding cultural resources in common. If the museum is to maintain its current budget, it is necessary for the museum to grow in both size and diversity. This is why the biennial form, as an entity and as a curatorial strategy, is so crucial to the sustainability of the museum and its ability to engage with the needs of the local communities. If the biennial is to have any chance of remaining relevant in the city in the future, it will have to change or be replaced. This is why the biennial form has to be proven sustainable in the city. It is possible that the biennial could be part of a strategy to create a new kind of urban museum, one that openly engages with the needs and interests of the locality through a culture of the city. This would mean creating a new kind of museum that openly engages with the past, while offering historical and cultural resources in common. This would make the museum both bureaucratically sustainable and culturally relevant in the same way that the urban museum is today. But this</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He is Editor of the online journal Stages published by the New Press Syndicate. The photo above is a series of five images from the exhibition Stages I: The Second Stage. It catalogues the steps that a curator takes to activate a site, audience, or an idea. The images were taken in front of a live audience at the Liverpool Biennial 2018.PreviousNextMeehan CristMeehan Crist is an artist. Her work is the narrative of a book, published in 2015, The Residues of Empire: US and Cuba at War in the 20th Century, that looks at the legacy of the imperial fiction produced by the New York Times, Nation of Islam leader Louis Farrakhan, and other prominent figures in the twentieth century. She is the curator of the forthcoming 13th Annual of the Black Arts in Togetherness, New York, USA. Togetherness is the home of Togetherness International, an international network of arts and cultural institutions, founded in 2002.</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He has a particular interest in the role of the artist in the social and political life of nations. He has written on a range of topics, including the politics of art, empire, displacement, identity, and the politics of media. He has a book out now called The Post Empire Reader.His most recent project is called Erased Pages: Surveillance and Incarceration in the Digital Age. It is the result of a year-long residency in the United Kingdom and the United States. He is the author of the forthcoming book about surveillance, Incapacitating Surveillance: Surveillance and Democracy in a Social Media Age.Mike Stubbs is a writer and producer based in London. He has published more than twenty books over the last twenty years, including the four books about the civil rights movement, Signaling Spring, Signaling Summer, and The Signaling Spring. His latest work, Signaling Fall, explores the consequences of a social media revolution. He is the host of the weekly political podcast Sticks</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He is a co-editor of the online literary journal Stages published by the National Portrait Gallery. He has written for The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Times, The New Yorker, The New Yorker, The New Yorker, The Nation, The Nation, The New York Times, The Nation, The New York Times, The Nation, The Nation, The New York Times, The Nation, The New York Times, The New York Times, The Nation, The Nation, The New York Times, The Nation, The New York Times, The Nation, The New York Times, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The New York Times, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The Nation, The</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He is Editor of the online Journal of Aesthetics and Criticism, and was a finalist for the Pulitzer Prize. He has a particular interest in the role of visual arts education in the public sphere. He is also the co-editor of The Visual Arts Reader, forthcoming from Academic Press, and was a finalist for the John Urry Medal for Visual Journalism. His work has been funded by the New York Arts Council, the John Jay College of Arts and the John Muir College of Architecture. He is the host of the weekly podcast Remembering the Arts?, which was nominated for the Theodore W. White Prize and won. He is the recipient of the 2016 Turner Prize, the 2016 Guggenheim Fellow, and the 2016 Maxwell School Medal. His work has been published in the New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The Village Voice, the Village Voice Art Critic, the New York Times Best-Seller, the New York Times Best-Dressed Book</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He has written for Rolling Stone, The Village Voice, The Washington Post and The New Inquiry. In 2015, he co-founded the social practice group Improv Everywhere and served as the artistic director of ImprovBoston. He is currently the artistic director of Improv NYC.In her new book The Luminaries: The Art and Politics of Bitcoin (2016), Slavs and Tatars curator Elisa Atangana reflects on her years of observing and researching in Kyrgyzstan, where the emergence of Bitcoin as a form of electronic cash heralded a new age for cultural integration and political resistance. In Kyrgyzstan, Atangana reflects on the country’s early political economy and its transformation into a modern, post-capitalist economy based on renewable energy resources. In addition to artist-centered projects, Atangana speaks about the politics of media culture, in particular, the politics of Bitcoin. In her book, she takes listeners on a three-day ‘golden parachuting</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He has written for The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The Nation, and The New York Times. He has been a co-editor of the Journal of a Future Future Culture, an issue of which was published in January 2018, and has edited the Journal of a Future Urban Future. He is the editor of Next City, an issue of which was published in October 2017. He is also the editor of The Penninsula, a journal of the Penninsula Foundation, which he edited from 2009 to 2016. He has co-edited the Penninsula Review, a journal of the Penninsula Foundation, which was published in January 2018. He is the editor of the forthcoming book The Penninsula Review 2.0: Interdisciplinary Arts &amp; Social Planning, published by Pennalinista​ACS, London and forthcoming from ​Cambridge University Press, 2017.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and arts educator.</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He is the host of the weekly online series The Stubbs Brothers (www.thestubbsbrotherpodcast.com), which includes topics including the New Economy of Art, the Political Economy of Art, and the Discursive Arts. He has written for The New Inquiry, The New Republic, The Nation, The New York Times, The Nation, The Times of Israel, The Times of London, The Times of Berlin, and The Washington Post among others. He is a founding partner of Stubbs Media, a producer of public programmes including the PBS documentary series The Stubbs Brothers, which won an Emmy and an Oscar for Outstanding Public Programme Art Direction for the 2016 London Olympics, and was a curator at the Iowa Arts Festival Four Walls, which was part of the curator Jerome Kassouf’s group that curated the first Venice Biennale. He is the author of The Stubbs Brothers: The Rise and Fall of an Iconic Chicago Community Arts Movement and co-editor of the online literary</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He is the host of The Storky Show, a weekly arts and culture show on the arts-oriented KIRTLR radio network. He is a regular speaker at the Liverpool Biennial’s public events series and has written for the New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The Nation, The New York Times Magazine and The Washington Post. He is the recipient of a 2013 MacArthur Genius Grant and was a finalist for the Turner Prize in 2014. He is the editor of The Storky Book, published by New Harbinger Books, an imprint of Simon &amp; Schuster.He is a regular contributor to The Nation, a political and LGBT publication, and was the winner of the 2012 Simon &amp; Schuster Political Animals project, a collaboration with Radcliffe Press. His latest work for the New Republic, published October 2018, is The Dispossessed: Rebellion and Multicultural Survival in the Twenty-First Century, a treatment of the justice, political and social contexts</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He is the author of The Fragile Earth: Dispatches from the Fold (2017), published by Verso Books. His work is currently at work on the second instalment of his book series The Fragile Earth. He is currently completing a PhD at Lancaster University, entitled The Anarchist History of U.K. Education, which is the basis for his new book series The Fractured Earth. In collaboration with Lancaster University Archaeology and Museums Service, he is conducting a research project into the site of the annual event entitled The Fractured Earth: U.K. Education from Colonial Times to explore the roots of the present-day anger and frustration felt by the public at being displaced and denied any part in the process of making the site of the exhibitionary assemblage anew.The Fractured Earth: U.K. Education to Explore the Roots of the Present Distrust of the Public Understanding of the ArtsEmma ThompsonEmma Thompson is a writer, curator, educator and</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. The issues and stories that will be addressed at the show will be completely different from the ones that were reported in the media at the time, so it is important that the stories are told. If you are going to do a media-based project, you need to have a story. The media weren’t going to write stories about the same things over and over again, so the next best thing is a media-based project that is complete with retelling points of failure and successes. In a way, that is what Liverpool Biennial is: it is a repeated feedback loop. Every little bit helps.Download this article as PDFMike StubbsMike Stubbs is a writer, producer, and artist. His work has been featured in The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Digiday, The Nation, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He is Senior Editor of the Nation online and serves on the editorial boards of several other online publications. He is a co-author of the forthcoming nonfiction book The Architecture of Luxury (2014), which will be published by Verso in 2015. Stubbs is the host of the weekly political podcast Stages (now on Sirius XM Satellite Radio) and the New York Public Theater's Stages Live 8: Social Practice (2015-16), which documents the public practices of public-planning projects around the world. His writing has also appeared in publications including The Nation, The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Times Literature Review, The New Republic of Arts, and The New York Times Magazine. He is the editor-in-chief of the online magazine Stages.The Architecture of Luxury (2014) is a collaboration with The New York Public Theater.Iwo Jima Memorial Lecture 	In 2004, Iwo</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Theatre, Brooklyn Public Theatre, Brooklyn Public School, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn P.S.U., Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Public School, Brooklyn School of Arts, Brooklyn Public Theater, Brooklyn Theatre Workshop, Brooklyn Theatre Workshop, Brooklyn School of Arts, Brooklyn School of Arts, Brooklyn School of Architecture, and Brooklyn Digital Workshop. He has also curated the digital exhibition My Digital Self (2015) and the forthcoming documentary film My Digital Self (2016). He is the editor of the forthcoming online journal PLATEAU, and the published author of Systemics, or Art as Media (2015). He is currently editor and publisher of the online journal PCA Journal 3, and the forthcoming online memoir SPORTING ANGE.Alon Schwabe is the Curator for the forthcoming Venice Biennale, and the curator of the forthcoming Venice Architecture Biennale. He curated the</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library and Brooklyn Museum, amongst others. He has a particular interest in the social life and cultural practices of the Lower East Side, where he lived and worked for many years. He is an adjunct professor at Brooklyn College of Arts. He is the editor and co-founder of the online journal Stages, and the curator of the online archive StagesEast, where he curated over 200 objects in the library's collections. He is the author of several books including the New Curator and co-founder of the collective Stages, which publishes essays and commentaries on current art and emerging art.Alon Schwabe is the author of  	Future City: New York City, 1960–2008, New York Times, 9/16/16, and several other books. He is a co-founder of the collective Stages, which publishes essays and commentaries on contemporary art and emerging art. He is the editor and co-founder of the online journal Stages, where</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Transport, Indian Arts Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Poetry Project, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Serpent Workshop, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of History and Curating, Brooklyn Museum of Zoology, Brooklyn Museum of Archaeology, Brooklyn Museum of Zoology, Brooklyn Museum of Critique, Brooklyn Museum of Transport and Community Arts, Brooklyn Museum of International Relations, Brooklyn Museum of Communication, Brooklyn Museum of Urban Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Cooking, Brooklyn Museum of Architecture, Brooklyn Museum of Surgery and Early Modern Construction, Brooklyn Museum of International Relations, Brooklyn Museum of Zoology, Brooklyn Museum of Surgery, Early Modern and Victorian Embroidery, Brooklyn Museum of Anatomy, Brooklyn Museum of International Relations, Brooklyn Museum of Zoology, Brooklyn Museum of Surgery, Early Modern and Nineteenth-Century Embroidery, Brooklyn Museum of Embroidery</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Art, and Brooklyn Museum. He has written for the New York Times, The New Republic, The New York Public Library, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New York Public Theater, The New Yorker and The New York Public Theater.He is the editor and publisher of the online journal Stages, is the author of The Gallery as a Book (2013) and the forthcoming New York Times best-seller Stages. He is an adjunct professor at Brooklyn College of Arts.Schwabe is a pioneer in the field of critical art theory and has taught at Columbia, Cornell, UCLA and the City University of New York. He has edited the online journal Stages, edited the book The Gallery as a Book (2012) and is the recipient of the 2013 Arthur Danto Award for Critical Art from the Community Arts Network. He has a special interest in the social dimension of contemporary</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, and the Museum of Modern Art. He has also co-curated the 2013 Venice Biennale with Jonathan Safran Foer, The Artists’ Colony, and the 2012 London and New York Museums’ Museums of Modern Art, co-curated with Geoff Cox and Anita Kahana, The Vintage/Digitale Kunsthal, and co-curated the 2014 Seattle Biennale with Lois Hewlett, The Contemporary Condition. He is a member of the editorial advisory boards of the New York Times, the New Republic and the Guardian, and was a member of the Curator-General’s Council of Independent Curators. Jussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an architect, urbanist and member of the Board of Directors of the Brooklyn Museum. His work for the Brooklyn Museum has addressed a wide range of issues including homelessness, spatial forms of institutionalization, economic development, cultural displacement and his work in and</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, and the Museum of Modern Art. He is the curator of the forthcoming Institute of Contemporary Art, New York, USA, 8 June to 9 September 2014.His work has been published widely, including in The New Republic, The New York Times, The New York Public Library, The New York Public Theater, The New Yorker, The New York Public Theater: A Public Theater Project, The New York Public Theater, New York Public Theater, The New Yorker, The New York Public Theater, The New York Public Theater, and The New York Public Theater Review. He has been a curator for the collections of the Museum of Modern Art, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Theater, Brooklyn Public Access to History, Brooklyn Public Access to Theatre, and Brooklyn Public Access to the City.Schwabe is the Curator for the upcoming </text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, and the Public Theatre. He is curator of the forthcoming Future City: Art and the Politics of Virtuality with McGraw-Hill, New York, and co-curator of the upcoming Future City: Art and Politics with McGraw-Hill, New York. He is a member of the Board of the Advisory Board of the Zombie Task Force, which provides training and support to artists and organisations working in the public sector to oppose opiate abuse, and is a member of the Advisory Board of the Zombie Task Force, which opposes opiate abuse. He is the editor of the forthcoming online publication Art and Anarchy, and the co-author of the forthcoming book Strange Bedfellows: Two Worlds in Transition, due out in 2018.Alon Schwabe’s art often addresses the politics of technology (Google, Facebook, policing, the war on terror, etc.), and</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, and other local and regional art and cultural collectives. He has a particular interest in the work of artists whose artistic practices are informed by a deep understanding of the social and political contexts of their times. He has written for the Times, The New York Post, The New Republic, The Nation, The Progressive and The New York Times among other publications. He is a member of the Advisory Board of the Museum of Modern Art’s Centennial Programme. He is the editor and publisher of the contemporary and biennial publications Dispatches and Co-founder of the New York Public Library, where he has edited the books On Art and Culture and Art and Culture and edited the journal Stages. He has been a lecturer at Carnegie Mellon University and the University of California, Santa Cruz. He lives in Manhattan with his wife, Rosalind Franklin Schwabe.Interior of the Paris House, c.1917, via Wikimedia Commons.PreviousNextInterior</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Public Theatre, Brooklyn Public Theatre, BAM!, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn School of Art, Brooklyn Poetry Project, Brooklyn Museum of Ballet, Brooklyn Museum of Dance, Brooklyn Mum Brigade, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of History, Brooklyn Museum of Zoology, Brooklyn Museum of Dance, Brooklyn Museum of Dance, Brooklyn Museum of History, Brooklyn Museum of Dance, Brooklyn Museum of Geology, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of Art, Brooklyn Museum of</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that operates across platforms, using artificial intelligence and machine learning to detect malcontents, and to produce indices of good and bad behaviour, in-depth commentaries on current events, and art and non-art forms that function in a similar way. It is an innovative approach to a problem that is familiar to many people, but challenging in that it requires no prior knowledge beyond that person’s own background and knowledge. 	[i] New York Times, 7/25/17.Download this article as PDFConneling the Future of Public Art, Participatory Arts Centre,2013.Alon SchwabeAlon Schwabe is a writer, Curator at the New York Public Library, where for two years he worked on the commissioning and managing of the Museum of Modern Art (2000–03), which was founded in 1973. He has worked with the Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library, Brooklyn Museum, New Museum, New Museum, Brooklyn Museum, Brooklyn Public Library and others. Drawing directly on his experiences at the New Museum and Brooklyn Museum, Alon has written articles and essays on art and culture for the New York Times, the Atlantic Monthly, Art in America, Artforum, and numerous other publications. He has lectured at Columbia University and the New Museum about the origins and future of contemporary art. He is the author of numerous books and has written more than twenty-five books including the New Art Publishers' New Poets, the New Media Art Book and the newly published art-of-the-future: Art and Media after the End of the World. He is the host of the weekly public programme The Art of the Future and the new year’s special New Inquiry radio programme. Listen to the PodcastSvetlana Boym                              before or after the New Museum’s Open House. In the advertisement of the first edition, Svetlana Boym quoted from</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends in their own right. In this analysis, systems are at the root of what I call the ‘intersectionality’ that underpins ‘intersectionality’. 	[7] To some extent, I am referring to the folk assumption about humans, at least in part, a result of which is attributed to the Judeo-Christian model of the divinely constituted human ­human being. 	[8] For more on this, see Susanne Krehbiel-Weber, ‘The Image Explosion: Image Formation and Urban Future’,  	Geographical Research Letters 	Vol. 37, No.1, January, 2000, p.103.Download this article as PDFSusanne Krehbiel-WeberSusanne Krehbiel-Weber is a Ph.D. candidate in Geography and Theory at the University of Alberta, and holds a Bachelor of Arts in English Cultural Studies from the University</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends in themselves. Perhaps we can begin to see the value in the arts, in the promotion of culture, in the creation of new creative modes of being in and through the city. Perhaps we can begin to see the value in the craft of architecture, in the creation of shared resources, in the promotion of habitation and landscapes. Perhaps we can begin to see the value in the craft of everyday life, in the craft of domestic routines, in the promotion of ritual and repetition. Perhaps we can begin to see the value in the craft of activism, in the creation of ever larger, more encompassing systems of control. Perhaps we can begin to see the value in the craft of community.  	[7] The point of view of cultural production in the city, then, begins to diverge from that of the cultural production of the nation-state. The weight of this shift is being felt in areas of the city where, as the sociologist Peter Osborne notes, there</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends in themselves. In that case, the end result would be cities that are no longer able to function as they have up to now. We would begin to see cities as potential sites for some sort of emergent culture that operates outside the system that creates and produces them. New media would play a part in this, as it records the city’s growth and gives rise to new modes of cultural activity. New forms of art would emerge alongside new modes of economic activity, and perhaps, as a result of this, a part of the art form would be transferred from the artist’s gallery to the market place. New media would record social exchange as well as the actual exchange of these social commodities. And a part of the art form would find a place in the social. [top] Systems design becomes particularly interesting when considering the current state of the art in artificial intelligence and machine learning, which is viewed as a ‘game-changing technology’. One might anticipate that</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends, and as such, playthings in their own right. Such a mind-set will render the systems engineering that characterises contemporary infrastructure obsolete. Rather, we can envision non-linear systems that continually evolve and alter through interactions with the city, and that create and re-create new systems as they are needed. Such systems would be called ‘layerly’ systems, and they would permit layered architectures that are not confined to the confines of medieval urban environments. The emergence of such systems would render old questions like ‘urbanicity’ moot. 	[7] 	[8] 	This new infrastructural landscape will be produced not through innovative urban theories, but through infrastructural‐like developments that are driven by the new rich man, driven by the new technological revolution. Newer forms of capitalised infrastructure would emerge as a by-product of this metropolis, and would be used to support any future growth spurts. The infrastruct</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends in themselves. We might begin to see cities not just as sites of pollution and conflict but also as sites of potential solutions. We might begin to see the systems that comprise the city as a set of possible paths for change.  	[7] See, for example, Thierry Meyssan,  Infrastructures of the Imagined City: Renewable Energy, Urban Futures and the Pursuit of Knowledge  (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2016), p. 5.Download this article as PDFCooking University of Chicago Associate Professor of Geography and Co-Director of the Center for Advanced Urban Studies (CASAS) Jesse Singleton is the author of several books including the award-winning Beyond Off-World: Globalization and the Metainformation (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2011), co-editor of the forthcoming Stages blog (www.stagesjournal.org), and co-editor of the forthcoming Stages blog</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends in themselves. Such a perspective might lead us to reconsider the endgames of the metropolis. The megastructure of the metropolis might be reduced to a manageable scale, and the city might begin to enjoy a life of its own. 	[7] See Rob Manning and Christian Körner, eds.,  	Architecture of the Future City (Dordrecht: Deakin University Press, 2011), chapter 4. 	[8] Manning and Körner, ‘On the future of cities: a survey’, in  	Future City: Essays on the Future of Cities, pp. 33–47, 2007. 	[9] See Rob Manning and Christian Körner, eds.,  	Architecture of the Future City (Dordrecht: Deakin University Press, 2011), chapter 4. 	[10] Baucom, op. cit., p.</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends in themselves. Many urban problems can be traced back to the advent of planning, and the contemporary urban problem is no exception. 	[7] The problem with the city is not an inability to think beyond the city, but an endowment to think beyond the city: how to manage the finite resources of the city in the interests of humanity. Planning is a form of capitalism without end. Planning is often described as an ‘art’ in itself, but it has a social function too. 	[8] Planning has come a long way since Descartes formulated his problem in his Pensès, and modern planning processes incorporate elements of biology, geo-politics, economics and political science. Planning has come a long way since Karl Marx and Frederick Engels formulated in Capital, and today it is the object of a ‘commodity’ – a commodity – that is understood as a form of historical value. Planning has come a long way in the last</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends in their own right. As autonomous vehicles become more sophisticated and have human drivers on the road, we might begin to see cities not as collections of end points but rather as dynamically emergent playthings in a dynamic galactic system. This is the urban future, folks. It’s time to consider the consequences of such a future.Download this article as PDFSally TallantAs Assistant Professor of Art and Design at the University of Alberta, Sally works in and across art, design, architecture and construction, including the history and contemporary development of contemporary art. She is the author of The Complete Art of Building Materials (2006), Pattern Recognition in Automotive Production (2011), and the forthcoming Designing Urban Spaces: From Materials to Cities (2014). Inspired by the recent publication of Walking Towards Revolution: Building Societies and Crisis in an Uncertain Future, Sally is particularly interested in the ways in which design can contribute to the formation of new ways of living, working</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends in themselves. The end result will be that we can create, on an industrial or even an artistic level, environments in which systems can evolve and function in ways that are neither omniscient nor absolute. This is the kind of thinking that goes beyond the domain of engineering and involves cultural and social change. It starts from the assumption that there are other ends to be considered, and so the ability to consider the future, and thus the city, not only in relation to the past, but also in relation to other forms of social change. 	[7] The ability to consider the future is also one of the first places to identify one's own perceived limitations. If possible, the future should be possible because of the technology available today. But although the future should be attainable through technological means, it should be possible to notice the limitations and so mitigate them in ways other than through the use of technological means. For instance, the future should be explicable in terms of specific historical moments</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] is the sort of thing that a social-studies department might want to study. A system for tacitly constructing the social through its operations could give some insight into the mechanisms of bureaucratic interaction and power.  	[top] Systems design is a global industry, and ‘the new ­metropolitan’ is the product of systems thinking. The older, feudal forms of urban life are being radically reshaped through the adoption of information technologies, and cities are no longer confined to the confines of medieval or bourgeois cities. The adoption of new technologies has consequences that transcend the city. The adoption of self-driving cars, for example, has profound effects on urban environments, both large and small, and the possibility of ever increasing surveillance is all around us. 	[5] Such is the urban-messianic vision of the future city. 	[6] 	In planning for the city, we might begin to see systems as playthings rather than ends, and emergence as a mode of play is central to systems thinking. In play, systems engage with each other and create systems. We might begin to see the systems that emerge from the city as playful, unpredictable and subject to change. Play, in this sense, is part of the city’s character. 	[7] And it is this kind of thinking that underlies the emergence of new technologies and the metainterface. New media and apps can be seen as the new ‘trillian’, or ‘wild’, in the city, and they can be seen as the new infrastructure that supports that playful imagination. New media allow the individual to become anonymous, and create new modes of interaction between people. New apps empower citizens to take matters of the city for themselves, creating a citizen army. New online services empower citizens to trace and traceable, gathering and gathering information, gathering insights that can be used to alter urban development plans, and ultimately</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface is a common and unavoidable task, and many tasks can be done with fairly basic but powerful programming skills. So the interface fantasy today is a hindrance rather than a help. It is user-driven and user-friendly, but it is not a utopic nor perfect representation of the human condition. 	And this is why computer interfaces today are usually inhuman, chaotic and ambiguous. They are the opposite of utopic and perfect representations of human condition. They show the user the error of their ways, but they also show the user ways to escape the error. 	Thus, the interface today is both interactive and extremely constrained. It shows the user the error of their ways but it also provides a way out. 	An interface today is both transparent and incredibly constrained. It provides a way to do amazing things with data, but it also shows the user the error of their ways. This is why operating systems designed for tablets and smartphones today tend to be so obtrusive and corrupting</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface is part of a massive IT system that is part of the corporate giant, and part of the government. And although this sounds far-fetched and dystopian, it is also true that today’s users are multitransigent and can acquire almost anything they want on the web, just as the computer hacker in 1986 could. 	So what is the alternative? 	One possibility is that the user is indeed smart enough today to build his or her own interface, but not so smart that a computer would ever allow that to happen. This is the kind of interface that was in widespread use in the 1980s and 1990s, but is now rarefaction and restricted to a privileged few. 	The other possibility is that the user interface of today is too complex and impenetrable that a computer could ever build a functioning interface out of parts. This is the kind of interface that was in widespread use in the 1990s and early 2000s, but is now rarefaction and</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface is a reality all of its own.That is to say, the task of constructing such an interface today is an interface user’s job. It is not just the job of the architect to design an interface that all users can access, but also the user’s job to implement that interface and to carry it out. And this is precisely what the term interface designates: the task of the interface designer is something like that of a plumber or engineer: technically proficient, but also versed in the idiosyncrasies of user preferences, culture, and geography. The task of the plumber or engineer is to design and install pipes and wires, not to design and install switches or routers, or to engineer something much more sophisticated and that all users can access. But today's user is much more than a user of interfaces. She or he is actively engaged in cultural consumption, engaged with social networking, and engaged with ever larger digital screens everywhere one looks. And it is this active</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface is computer-programming genius done right. (As noted by Chris Wainwright, in  	User’s ‘Guide to Programming Languages’, Prentice Hall, 1981.)The interface today is a construct, and as such, its capabilities are unlimited. The problem with the interface is that it is constrained to suit a particular usage scenario – the paradigm of usage – and thus the user is constrained to conform to a prescribed pattern of behaviours. Such behaviours include habitual use, repetition, and so forth. Such behaviours are part of a larger trend towards ever greater inaccessibility of information and behaviour – which is to say, towards ever greater specialization and corporatism of everything. And this is to be embraced by those who would build new modes of interaction and distribution of culture. But such cultural orientations inevitably spread to other parts of the globe and require the labour of millions upon millions upon millions of people engaged in these new modes of interaction and culture consumption. 	As</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface is a mainframe computer – a computer that constantly learns and adapts to new challenges – a central processing unit (CPU) that is part of a supercomputer, and so on. 	As a result of this massive upgrade in processing power, the 1980s were hugely influential on how computer users think about the nature of interface design, and how such design might be approached in the future. 	As a result of this massive upgrade in processing power, the 1980s were hugely influential on how computer users think about the nature of interface design, and how such design might be approached in the future. 	Computer users today tend to see the interface as something that constantly evolves and is constantly influenced by external factors – cultural norms, political and economic influences, physical and mental – and as such user-pleasing media. But in its original form, the interface was designed to be constantly monitored and controlled. 	In 1984, John Nash and George Tudor Jones designed a free and open source</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface is a massively computationally intensive process that even the most powerful supercomputers struggle to carry out. And so, too, with augmented reality: today, the challenge is not to build a good user-interface, but to build a fully fledged, fully automated interface that everyone can use. 	Thus, the challenge today is not to create a good user-interface, but to build a fully fledged, fully automated interface that everyone can use. And this brings us to the second dimension of the term ‘user interface’: the one that describes something as ‘sensitive’ and ‘realistic’, and thus worthy of being called a interface. And the answer to this second dimension has recently come to characterize the iPhone, and the kind of interface that comes with it. Apple has come up with an ingenious way of naming what is apparently a quite common thing: the App Store is a user interface, and the websites that come with it are a platform.</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface is a highly specialized and resource-intensive process that requires access to the underlying networked databases, which are part of the operating system itself. Consequently, the level of abstraction and granularity required for such a task is vastly different today than it was in 1986. The ability to do amazing things with data today is a reality that computer users have to contend with, but the degree to which such capabilities are accessible and usable is a different question. Such capabilities exist in theory, but accessing them is a different game today than it was in 1986, and accessing those possibilities today is a different game from what its like to live under the rule of the state under Gorbachev.The fact that the question is hypothetical does not mean that it is not an important conceptual issue for theorizing today – indeed, much has been written about the possible futures of the interface and the networked society – but it is that the possibilities are different. The ability to do amazing things with data today is a reality that computer users</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface is computer programming; programming languages like Java, HTML, and XML allow the user to create beautiful interfaces out of seemingly ­random data. 	But back in 1986, the user interface was primarily a tool for user education and administrative tasks. The task of constructing such interfaces was computer programming. Nowadays, the task of constructing such interfaces is primarily done by administrators with specialized programming skills. And yet the kinds of programming done with text documents and images is essentially the same as that done with objects and structures – programming that is done entirely through programming languages. 	This distinction is important. Object oriented programming languages like Java and XML allow the creation of abstract data types, but at the same time they prescribe certain behaviours towards the underlying data – things like how data is dealt with, what is returned, and so forth. In programming, the underlying data structures are usually described in terms of operations such as ‘getters’ and ‘setters’ that prescribe how the data is accessed,</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface is a reasonably complex and technological problem, one that even the most primitive computers would have to tackle. So the implication of the 1984/boycott movement is that today, since there is no interface to speak of, we’d better design our own interfaces. This sounds daft and naïve and runs counter to everything we believe about how computers should be made. But this is the interface fantasy of a different kind – the interface designed by and for the elite. The interface today is a constructed object that can be accessed by a number of people at the same time, and thus the question is not whether there should be an interface but how. The challenge is to empower the people who make the interface with the knowledge and the capability to use it, and to a large extent, that is why computer users today are multi-taskers and not aware users. They are constantly accessing and adapting their INTERFACE programming to meet the needs of the businesses and users that comprise the site, and</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, the future or some sort of intelligent virtual assistant? Or might it be more relevant to consider that the future is now, and that there is some kind of intelligent interface that can tell you what to do?The second group are those who foresee an altogether different kind of interface, in which all users will be masters of their devices, and thus will be able to do incredible things with them: build bunkers, destroy enemy drones, repurpose natural resources, and so forth. These users would be nothing compared to the computer hackers of today, but they would possess unimaginable tools with which to tackle any challenge. And these users, like the computer hackers of today, would develop bizarre and sometimes brilliant programs to access whatever was available, whether that challenge was created by them or not. 	Such is the imagined interface today. But back in 1986, when the book came out, this was only the fantasy of a different kind of computer user. Today, the task of constructing such a user interface is a mainframe computer, and programming is an integral part of the computerisation process. And since the 1990s computerisation processes have accelerated at breakneck speeds, with applications becoming ever more powerful and data ever more stored on the device, not to mention the advent of cloud computing, which makes it ever easier to access and store huge amounts of data, there is every reason to think that the interface of the future will be something like the interface of the present – except that the users will be slaves to the data streams that exist outside their device.Interface criticism 	One might ask if the obsession with interface today is a symptom of the anxieties of postmodernity – a sign that the cultural logic of postmodernity has failed? One might even argue that the obsession with the interface today is a symptom of the anxieties of freedom, since the user interface today is both omnipresent and omnipotent. But there are signs that the real reason for the increase in screen real estate and the reduction</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation is a set of laws (national, state, and local), a collective body of powerful actors, many of whom interpret and enact those laws in ways that are not always transparent or public. For example, many corporations now establish governance bodies that are not transparent or public, employ legal strategists to shape the law (including those laws), and use tax havens and other tax-advantaged modes of financing to achieve aggressive corporate practices (including strategies to outsource operations, reduce corporate governance, and more). All of these strategies can be described as ethno-politicized, and are often implemented through elected representatives (including local and state governments) who later wield the legislation and implement its provisions. 	Conversely, the city is a site of cooperative and democratic acts (or perhaps utopic) – where individuals and non-profit organizations take part in deliberations, enterprising municipal officials take part in incentives that empower such initiatives, and civic groups take part in the formation of local and national governments.</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation has many faces, often maligned faces, yet collectively wielding vast and mysterious powers. 	In theory, the corporation could be broken into smaller parts and dispersed to avoid conflict and conflict over time. In practice, this is unlikely, as most corporations today are far too powerful and complex to be dispersed or dispersed, much less abolished. So what is the public really like? What is its primordial state, and how does that affect our conception of the public sphere, today? 	What does it mean to be ‘public’ in the modern sense of the word? How does the modern public sphere conceive of war and violence? How is the modern public engaged with and mobilized by such phenomena as mass media? 	What is the public sector, and how is it engaged with, today? Are there public forums for questioning, for creating, and for reacting to such phenomena as mass media? Are there publics that can be publicly elected and empowered through popular means? Are there public</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation is a transient concept, struggling to survive the social media revolutions of the sharing economy, and its predominant function is to meet the changing needs of the sharing economy companies. The corporation has no intrinsic value or purpose in the public sphere, but it does have a social purpose and a political purpose, which is in part defined by the public. 	So the next time you open up Instagram, or look at Facebook, or Twitter, or whatever social media platform you use, or subscribe to, consider how you are integrated into this social ecology. What are the social purposes of this social ecology? What are its social dimensions? 	Lastly, if you have any further comments or ideas, I would love to hear them. Drop me a line at  [email protected] 	References:  [1]  Gabrielle Royce Kaslowitz,  	The Gathering Storm: US and Israeli Military Intervention in the Palestinian Territories, Zed Books, 2015, p.11. [2]</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation has many desirable effects, but its primary task seems to be to meet corporate needs (albeit with controversy and discordant timetables). In this sense, the public realm becomes an arena in which conflicting needs and desires can be satisfied, a marketplace where competing visions and claims to fame can be debated and negotiated. 	But what is the public good, or what is its proper role, if not to take part in a marketplace that propitiates and engages in the public trough? The notion of public that emerges from these three paradigms of utility, common good, and public realm is that of a commodity, recognized as legal tender by all nations that make up the global commons. Though not a perfect conceptualization, the common good appears to me to be the prevailing ideal in a global marketplace of commodities, even though the public realm is subject to the whims of geopolitical struggles and natural disasters. Global systems tend to produce public goods, or at least public understandings of the public good. 	</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation has become a site of corporate social responsibility, where stakeholders—corporations, workers' unions, customers, citizens—are encouraged to adopt and apply the corporation's policies, laws, and norms. But this is not at all what has happened in the contemporary, postindustrial, urban environment. Instead, the corporation has become a site of corporate profit and loss, where stakeholders (employees, customers, shareholders) often benefit from the corporation’s success at various scales, and where the corporation is often accused of overstepping its bounds (blasting businesses, for instance, or polluting the environment, or both). The metropolitan region is a prime example of this kind of expansion. It is the size and shape of a country, but it is also the size and shape of a corporation: so-called ‘metro areas’ that span large distances and are thus bound to the centers of globalized capitalism. And yet, despite these recognitions, the metropolitan area remains a</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation has many specific, concrete effects, and so it is easy to identify the specific ones that are of relevance to the city. For example, the need for airports to report directly to governments; for banks to lend at interest; for stock exchanges to trade transparently; for transportation networks to post tolls; for pension funds to buy shares; for farmers to sell their land to urban markets; and for consumers to shop. Yet these are but a few of many ways in which the corporation can be defined and criticised. The city, by virtue of its size, population, and rich cultural heritage, is the obvious next step, and so we must ask ourselves, which of these many fronts are we operating in? How can the city be defined and dismantled through critical ecological, political, and urban-regenerative strategies? 	For more information, see  	Basel Committee on Climate Change, The Climate Crisis (2013), and  	The Climate Citadel (2011).  So what</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation has many functions, but one of its primary functions is to produce, to capture, to transform, to exploit, to exploit again and again. Thus the corporation – whether as an idea or a concrete bureaucratic reality – is a much less than complete conception of the public sphere. 	As an idea, the idea of the corporation as a public good is a powerful one. It conveys a clear conception of the public sphere, a common good, common property, and a set of obligations towards its stakeholders. But it is also a conceptually complex concept, and the complexity lies in its very structure. As such, the public sphere has many shapes and forms, but one of its primary functions is to deliver tangible benefits to a specific group of stakeholders – shareholders, customers, and shareholders – at a specified point in the trajectory of capital itself. Thus the public realm – the corporation – is both a conceptually complex concept, and a concrete thing that delivers tangible benefits to a specific group of stakeholders.</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation has become much more of a set of characteristics and attributes, a particular set of rights and responsibilities, than a living, evolving entity with particular characteristics and rights. Thus the nation and the corporation are often simultaneously thought of as constituting the living, evolving human species that is evolving into the new commonwealth: a hybrid species. 	However, while the corporation may be conceived of as a biological entity with particular characteristics and rights, it is also thought to be a social entity with a public sphere that is evolving. This social dynamic may be understood as the over-production, over-use and misappropriation of natural resources, the economic exploitation of workers, and the division and subjugation of newly emerging publics. And yet, despite this ongoing biological and ecological appropriation and creation, the social dynamic that results from the over-production, over-use and misappropriation of resources, the economic exploitation of workers, and the division and subjugation of newly emerging publics is thought to be generated</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation is a contractual entity, like any other legal form, and as such its very nature as public is contingent upon the public's compliance with its contractual obligations. As corporations have become more institutionalized, and as a result of the (largely unwitting) participation of citizens in expanding pension funds and other public funds, and as a result of for-profit and non-profit colleges becoming increasingly important actors in shaping civic life, and especially in the public sphere, we can see the corporation as having become, in some measure, a prop in our public life. 	There are of course other possible public forms of the corporation, including the non-profit, the municipal, the cooperative, the religious, and of course the student. All these other possible bodies of the corporation are possible exemplars of the public sphere, representative forms of social life that are capable of embodying the public's own sense of the collective. But the public sphere exemplars we have today tend to be agencies rather than viable alternatives</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system, where interaction is facilitated through data (and where social and cultural norms are activated through media). It could also identify emerging publics, such as mapping, action science, or quantification as a tool for monitoring and optimization. The notion of public may be a useful enabler for a social and cultural ecology that seeks to understand and perhaps even transform the world around it, in that the public is a necessary precondition for the success of such an ecology. 	But what is the public to begin with? Let me suggest three possible paradigms for the public sphere: the city, the nation, and the corporation. The nation is a convenient, powerful, mythologized template for a public that can be built upon. It is a general idea, a shared set of values, a set of laws, institutions, and norms. Thus the corporation seems to me to be the ideal public sphere, though I would question the necessity of the corporation in the public sphere today. The corporation and the nation form the backdrop for a number of different visions and different assumptions. 	Let me illustrate the idea of the corporation and the nation in terms of the city. The corporation is a globalized version of the nation state, with national production lines and distribution channels that link different parts of the world. Yet while the corporation clearly has certain primacy in terms of its global spread, it is also true that in the vast global systems of the corporation ‘mindset’, there is no such thing as the corporation. The corporation is an organizational form that has certain unique enfranchisement and primacy properties, and these are exercised through a set of specific legal and political frameworks. Yet the ways in which the corporation is constituted and its frameworks are varied, and its legal and political primacy in the context of the corporation is an idea that is constantly evolving, subject to the shifting and shifting sands of history and the dynamic range of capitalism. 	Let me illustrate this in</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation.
    <text>should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation. The City Council could have chosen to dedicate a significant portion of the Museum’s budget to a dedicated museum of its history, a museum that reflected the city’s extraordinary resilience and potential, or it could have chosen to dedicate a smaller portion of the Museum’s budget to a museum of its extraordinary powers. In either case, the Council would not have been able to choose between these two disparate priorities, since the Museum would have assumed control. This is the classic dynamic: the Museum seeking ever more esoteric and magical ways to understand its past in an attempt to institutionalise its own power and destiny.Such is the mythologised history of the Museum, and it is a mythologised history because the Museum is everywhere, fully embodied and present in every aspect of our urban landscape. We only have to know a few Arabic words in order to appreciate the Museum’s vast collection of objects, which is enriched beyond measure only by the presence of photographs, video and audio recordings.</text>
    <text>should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation. It is also the least likely reading, given the Council’s demonstrated hostility to art and culture, but also the Museum’s demonstrated hostility to the city. In an effort to placate the Council, the Museum sought to abolish the City Museum, the oldest and most institutionalised branch of the institution. This would give the Museum a new, more open-access, more dispersed exhibitionary programme, and the Council an opening onto the Museum’s vast collection of art and artefacts. The new Museum would be a place of its own, free and independent of government. The Council responded by proposing a city-wide, nationwide, but especially for the purposes of this proposal in Northern California, a move that was partially funded by a bond issue on the city’s debt, and in part (paywall) by the construction of a new, state of the art, multidisciplinary art museum. Art and artists’ groups lobbied hard to keep the Gallery of Miracles</text>
    <text>should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation. For the City Council, the museum was a resource for development – a means to an end, rather than an end in itself. It did not have the institutional power or the cultural capital to exert political control over the destiny of the Museum. In the end, the Museum was left to act as a site of discovery and reconciliation for the Council’s citizens and residents. It is this account of the power and the resourcefulness of the Museum that is often repeated by writers on the Council’s portfolio, but which is often contested by those who lack institutional power or cultural capital.1. The Gallery of Miracles, A Visual History of the City, by Ronald Kray, New York Times, 2014.Download this article as PDFNick Krulwich6 October 2014Updike House, Homebaked, 622 Fax Ave, Portland, OR, USAPortland, Oregon62212Updike House, Homebaked, 622 Fax Ave</text>
    <text>should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation. The Council might have chosen to create the new Museum on the site of the old, riven by violence and bureaucracy, where the Quezon Memorials are interred alongside the rest of the neglected city. That would have been a mistake, as the Spanish-American War soon showed. Instead, the Council chose to create a new Museum that would display the past in a manner never fully imagined possible in the city. The new Museum would be a museum of visual culture, but it would also be a museum of the past, exhibiting the present through the power of metaphor and symbol. It would stand for something, and be able to tell its story to an appreciative public. This seemed like a good idea at the time, until the Spanish-American War broke out in 1898. This is the story of how the Quezon Memorials came to be in the City of New York.Chapter 1: The City as Monument to Imperialism [00:00:00]  [Chapter Title] [</text>
    <text>should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation. The Council could have chosen to direct the Museum’s resources to the tasks already assigned to it by the Mayor’s Commission on Cultural Affairs, a dysfunctional bureaucratic unit that had been at odds with the city for decades. In its place, the Council could have chosen to redirect Museum resources to worthy causes, such as supporting local theatre, arts education or supporting community gardens. Council members might also have chosen to redirect some of the Museum’s resources to local causes. Yet such misallocations would have placed an enormous strain on the already limited resources of the Museum, whose collection was already constrained by the city’s social and curatorial priorities. The failure to address the needs of the local community, which had been slowly chipping away at its collection, would have placed enormous strains on the Museum’s already limited resources, and it is highly unlikely that the Museum would have survived without the support of at least some local residents and community organisers. It is also highly unlikely that</text>
    <text>should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation. In their zeal to slash funding and close a large number of museums, the policymakers who created the modern museum may have inadvertently endowed the Museum with a body of work that is both more representative and more persistent than its constituent parts. The Gallery of Miracles may be an artifact of the twentieth century, but it is a museum of the future.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the Department of Communication Studies and the History of Ideas at the College of Staten Island University, New York. Her work has addressed the cultural logic of the postindustrial society since the 1980s through the development of a new interdisciplinary interdisciplinary model of cultural production based on ideas from critical cultural theory and postcolonial/inter-hierarchical theory. She is the author of The Postindustrial Society: The Philosophy of Existing Societies and Material Culture (2015) and the forthcoming Culture and Society: Economy and Politics in the Age of Intangible Assets. In her research, she works</text>
    <text>should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation. One might even agree that the City Council could have chosen to honour the Museum’s earlier commitment to education, publishing a collection of its early writing on the walls of the building where it once hosted a theatre, and publishing a memoir of the council’s childhood in the pictures that it did not publish. But the obvious policy mistake that the City Council could not have foreseen or handled is what came to be known as the ‘Tenth Report’ – a document that became synonymous with the decline of the borough and the early urbanisation of the city.1 It appeared in January 1922, just weeks after the start of the First World War, and more than a year before the first of several false starts killed off the Boroughs. It read: ‘The War Department has been advised that an audacious scheme is being made by an eccentric London businessman – a name which, at the time, had not yet appeared in print – to take over the whole of</text>
    <text>should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation. The Council surely could and should have chosen a museum with a strong local following and culture portfolio, staffed by artists who could have a significant impact on a local context through their work in the galleries, as is the case with the Museum of Modern Art in New York and the Museum of Modern Art in London. The Council could also have chosen to support an arts organisation from the outset, provided a certain amount of autonomy, and provided an arts education alongside other subjects taught by an arts organisation. In the neoliberal era of globalised capital and postindustrial societies, this is exactly what the City Council and the Museum of Modern Art have done. In both venues, the Museum of Modern Art has become a de-imagining of the city in the service of profit, while the City of New York has become a de-imagining of the city in the service of profit. The Museum of Modern Art in New York has become a de-imagining of the city in the service of profit, while the City</text>
    <text>should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation. The gallery is a strange artifact of the global city, a relic of an older culture that is suddenly visible again and again, in thrall to the logic of globalisation. The museum as object is a relic of the past, is itself a strange artifact of the very logic of globalisation. The museum as object is a strange artifact of the past, and so is the museum as cultural practice. In this model, the temporal complexity and distance of the museum come to dominate the differentiating factors of the contemporary. The museum as cultural practice is a strange artifact of the contemporary, and so is the museum as an artistic medium. In this model, the museum as a cultural form is a strange artifact of the present, and so is the museum as an artistic medium. In this model, the museum as an artistic form is a strange artifact of the past, and so is the museum as an artistic medium. The beauty of this model is that it allows us to consider cultural practices from the point of</text>
    <text>should be curated and led by artists’ who had a say in the direction of the Museum’s collection. The Museum was founded in 1875 and was known as the ‘Magistrate of the Queens Bank and Trustees of the Queens Museum’. In the early twentieth century the Museum was known as the ‘M.I.T. Art Gallery’ and in the late nineteenth century as the ‘Queens Museum’. The Museum’s collection of more than six hundred paintings is thought to be the largest of its kind, and it is an important archive of the city’s colonial past. The collection was published in 1971 under the title The Gallery of Miracles: A Visual History of the City.It is the most natural and plausible reading of the Museum’s portfolio that the City Council could have chosen to honour the decision to create a new museum, an institution that at the time seemed particularly vulnerable to the forces of neoliberalism and globalisation. The gallery of miracles, with its scattered curatorial specimens, appears to have been a useful myth – a way to imagine the museum in the city, an entity that can be counted on to produce certain kinds of art and to keep other kinds of art out. But the reality is that the Gallery of Miracles never produced much art, except for a handful of artists who were absolutely bound by the circumstances. The real raison d'être of the Gallery of Miracles was its being a venue for a select few artists to come and sit for a number of years, while the rest of us went to bed. And while the gallery of miracles certainly has that convenient global aesthetic that artists crave, it also has to be said that the gallery of miracles is the only museum in the city that represents the city as a collection of individual achievements, achievements that are frequently rendered with impressive decorative effects. The rest of the city is represented through smaller structures called ‘museums’ and ‘</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3] See: https://www.wired.com/2016/7/two-levels-the-level-system/ [4] See: https://www.wired.com/archives/archive/2016/7/two-levels-the-level-system/ [5] See: https://www.wired.com/danger/archive/2016/7/two-levels-the-level-system/#sthash.7y9rYbTl.dpuf.98mT.98mR.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7y9rYbTl.dpuf.98mT.98mR.9xmJ.8.html[6] See: http://www.wired.com/archives/archive/2016/7/two-levels-the-level-system/[7] See: http://www.wired.com/archives/archive/2016/</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/uk-news-leeds/uk-news-leeds/uk-news-leeds-continuing-improvement-in-schools-performance-20170917-cta997943-3cfd-11e4-aa69-00144ba6bbcf7.html#sthash.6jTl90YmTl.dpuf.7zW.84mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.6jTl90YmTl.dpuf.7zW.84mN.9xmJ.8.html[4] See: http://www.queenslandline.org/cases/queenslandline/2014/regeneration-law-declaration-2013.html#sthash.9zdSY.600d.d</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3] See also https://www.engineeringinsights.com/articles/2769-improvement-in-social-emails-from-the-future.html?src=WP2LkMyE0NzMjE.WOWN.LF.4WYWYWYWYWYWYWYwMyL2IvMzE2NzM0OWY2MjE3NzM0OWMmE2NzM0OWY2NzM0OWY2NjE3NzM0OWY2NzMwY2MjE3NzM0OWY2NjE3NzMjE3NzMjE3NzMjE3NzMjE3NzMjE3NzMjE3NzMjE3NzMjE3NzMj</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3] See: https://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/21905.html?action=ReadinessReport. [4] See: https://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/21905.html?action=ReadinessReportComplete. [5] See: https://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/21998.html?action=ReadinessReportInfo. [6] See: https://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/21998.html?disabledSection=1. [7] See: https://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/21998.html?disabledSection=2. [8] See: https://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/21998.html?disabledSection=3. [9] See: https://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/21998.html</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3] Jamie McDonald, ‘On Violence in Multicultural Cities’,  	Sentencing Project,  	2011, http://www.sentencingproject.org/index.php/article/view/article/1097/violence-in-multicultural-cities, accessed November 2018. [4] See:  	http://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/2052347-leeds-studies-show-housing-affordability-controversy.html, accessed December 2018. [5] See:  	http://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/investigations-focus-on-housing-recovery-corner.html, accessed December 2018. [6] See:  	http://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/rise-and-falls-in-home-</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3] See: http://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-home-safety-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[4] See: http://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/home-safety/building-and-construction/home-improvement-1799671.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/home-safety/building-and-construction/high-rise-improvement-upgrades-needed-to-tackle-challenging-housing-in-the-north-east-1809638.html#sthash.kCiU6LyFqZ.dpuf.8jYXRiM.dpuf.98R.8.html#sthash.kCiU6LyFqZ.dpuf.8jYXRiM.dpuf.98R.8.html[4] See: https://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2017/11/12/heres-what-happened-in-uk-during-the-last-four-weeks-in-relation-all/[5] See: https://www.</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3] See: https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27521206_The_Crime_Writer_s_Guide_to_the_Warfare_Machine_in_the_City_Part_1_A_Index_2.html?PublicationType=openSuite&amp;PublicationIndex=true&amp;SubjectAlt=The_Crime_Writer_s_Guide_to_the_Warfare_Machine_in_the_City_Part_1_A_Index_2.html&amp;PublicationIndex=true&amp;PublicationType=openSuite&amp;PublicationIndex=true&amp;SubjectAlt=The_Crime_Writer_s_Guide_to_the_Warfare_Machine_in_the_City_Part_1_A_Index_2.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/home/kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[4] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/home/kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[5] See: https://www</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is due to open in 2019. 	[1] See: http://www.le.ac.uk/learn/en/index.html?lang=en. [2] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/crime/home-safety/building-and-construction/building-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[3] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/home-safety/building-and-construction/new-buildings/leeds-plan-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-crime-rate-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html#sthash.7m8PJlMl.dpuf.97mTs.94mN.9xmJ.8.html[4] See: https://www.leeds.co.uk/news/uk-news/home-safety/building-and-construction/leeds-study-reveals-massive-improvement-in-safety-in-kingston-1809639.html#sthash.7m8</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support of the museum, we visited the site again in early 1989, this time at the request of the East German government, who were keen to prove to the world that they still existed and were still taking part in the cold war. East German state symbols were removed, replaced with communist themed street decor, and portraits of former ‘heroes of the socialist state’ were pasted on the walls. The East German government was even keen to turn the Biennale into a vehicle for the ‘communist conversion of the whole city’. 	We noted that no East German art institution had ever commissioned an artist from the West, or even made an effort to produce an East German artist from the West. We wondered why. Perhaps the East Germans just didn’t want you to know what they were doing to you. 	We visited the site again in early 1990, and found that the biennale had become a vehicle for the ‘conversion of the whole</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support of the city government, we were able to find an alternative site for the Berlin Wall, which now adjoins the World Trade Center as a new urban landmark. We were even able to find an artist who could incorporate the symbolism of the Wall in her art. 	In the months that followed the blasts, we heard similar stories from different community members: that the Artistic Board for the Biennial had recently decided to relocate its community events from the Manhattan borough of the New York City borough of the same name to East Berlin, and that the new location for the Biennial would be in East Berlin. East Berlin is East Berlin, which means that East Berliners still live there and work there, although the East German national art museums have relocated to lower Manhattan in the US. The borough of Manhattan, which used to be the site of the American West Coast, now encompasses much of East Berlin. 	The decision to relocate the events from the boroughs to the city itself seemed arbitrary and</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support of the Biennial staff, we visited the site again in early 1990 and found that the same anti‐Chinese graffiti had been scrawled across the new set of archways: ‘Bild “Badung”, translated as “Big Ben Scared Shankly”. I painted  	a portrait of a Chinese artist named Fu Ying on the new set of archways in an attempt to blend in amongst the art community and the architecture admirers. At the time, I was still struggling to find my footing in the Biennial world and mainstream press. In my opinion, the Biennial staff and the architects had a field day with me – no punches were taken. I got a lot of press coverage that I am happy to say was manufactured by the Biennial in an attempt to discredit me. The Biennial staff and the architects had a field day with me too. The Biennial opening, with its power point and on‐site media circus, seemed like a</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support of the city government, we organised local street parties in the area where the Christmas tree would be installed (it was a great urban practice to have artists, street performers and other community artists construct public art spaces for the members of the art community, often with the support of the art board). These parties became very popular, and the board members became very frustrated, as they found themselves constantly outnumbered by the people organising the parties. They decided to have a ‘Restoration Party’ for the perceived betrayal of the Biennial by hosting the tree, which everyone in the biennial board wanted to attend. The city government also organised a number of events in and around the Biennial to mark the occasion. One of these was a three‐day folk festival entitled ‘Welsh Streets’ in response to the tree, which involved the ‘restoration’ of the shrub with sticks, hay bales, reindeer, tin can poles and twine. Folk‐artists</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support of the city government and the biennial, we visited the site and found the traditional story of the tree quite plausible: the tree had been in use for several years by local residents to repurpose after the destruction of their homes and businesses by the city. However, the board members apparently did not want the tree anymore and as a result, in 1967, they removed the poles and started work on a new tree, which was a hybridised version of the two we had grown up with. 	The tree that year was a hybrid, in that it shared many of the same chemical make-up but had its own set of flowers and fruits. These were very attractive to urban residents and created a new market for the newly invented urban tree, which rose up through the local landscape and was valued highly by the Biennial board. The board members apparently did not see the tree as a complement to their other buildings in the city and didn’t pay enough attention to the tree, which was</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support of the arts community, we managed to establish a coalition government with the support of the Social Democrats and Greens. After much pressure and perseverance, we managed to bring the Biennial to Birmingham, but the fact that it came as part of the Süddeutsche Zeitung and not as a ‘journalist club’ seemed an odd omission. Perhaps the biennial should be a member of the wider art community, but at the moment, its increasing independence seems unnecessary and even counter productive. At the same time, the fact that it came as part of the Süddeutsche Zeitung and not as a ‘journalist club’ seemed an odd omission. Perhaps the biennial should be a member of the wider art community, but at the moment, its increasing independence seems unnecessary and even counter productive. 	[1] See https://www.biennaleofcharlottes.com/. [2] See https://www.biennaleof</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support of the newly elected government, we were able to locate the new museum in Mitte, a predominantly Jewish neighbourhood in Mitte, a largely ‘Middle‐class’ neighbourhood in and around St Paul’s Cathedral. The cathedral is a traditional place for Baptists, Jews and Catholics to meet, pray and hold private meetings. It promoted an image of the cathedral as both prestigious and corrupting, allowing the museum staff to present a picture of the cathedral in a dominant position over the cityscape. 	In the days immediately following the explosions, people began to refer to ‘the cathedral’ as ‘the scene of the inferno’. 	Within a year, the museum was sold to a for‐profit developer, and the site turned into a residential neighbourhood. The new owners have repeatedly changed the facade artists had commissioned, and now use salvaged shipping containers as a billboard and promotional campaign image. 	The Biennale was moved to a new location</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support of the city government and the biennial, we visited the site and heard the residents tell their own version of events. While the locals clearly had a stake in the outcome, the visit also gave us a sense of the shifting narrative being pushed by the biennial staff, some of which we found distressing. In the ethnically diverse area, we met a few Buddhists and others who were more westernised and had come to study the history of meditation in the region. During the visit, we also met a few residents who said they had come out of the woodwork in order to help the city rebuild its post‐Second World War infrastructure. 	While our visit to the site did not produce any new policy changes, our experience in Berlin made the new biennials that we visited there – including the one that we visited in your ward – the occasion to launch into a detailed history of the area. While the locals certainly had a say in these events, the biennial staff certainly felt</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support of the mayor, we were able to find a new site for the tree in East Germany. There was no conflict of interest here, and the East German government was eager to move forward with the construction of a $2.5 billion ‘Centraal West Banki Centre’ – itself part of the DA ― a new ‘West Berlin headquarters for the AIB’s curatorial programme’ despite the fact that this would only hasten the demise of the branch, since the AIB was already planning to close the gallery space and start a new wave of art school openings in the area. Curators in East Germany were given a choice: either join the AIB or leave, and many did not want to go to East Germany. Instead, East German artists were asked to create new activities for the Biennial, while East German artists were asked to expand the activities of the East German exhibitionary tradition, which East German curators had started in East Germany in response to</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB and AIAD (Association for a Berlin-based Berlin-based Biennial) and an annual that documents the lives and works of the curators involved in the biennial. 	With the support of the foundation, we set out to find a location for the first part of the project in Berlin. The location turned out to be a surprise: the Artistic Board for the Biennial had already allocated a site for the ØBig Ben’s Christmas tree’ after the explosion of public and political reaction to the German federal government’s Brandenburg gate, which was soon replaced with a six-metre tall bronze Star of David. The board members apparently did not realise that this would spark a cultural revolution in Berlin and spark a national uprising, as the Chinese‐influenced East German governments had been – and still are – trying to prevent. Instead of trying to contain the uprising, the board members may have inadvertently helped create it. 	With the support of the foundations, we visited the site of the explosion and reported the findings to a local newspaper, who in turn reported the findings to the country’s top security police and to international aviation authorities. In addition to being banned from flying in South Korea, which is South Korea’s airspace, and which has a national anti‐terrorism law, we were also warned that our proposal would damage South Korea’s international reputation.  	When the South Korean government cracked down on our demonstration in December 1988, we applied for and were accepted into the Airports Security Administration (AS) 13 register, which registered and tracked all incoming and out‐of‐country aeroplanes. We were placed in touch with lawyers who argued that we were not breaking any laws by demonstrating at the Seoul airport. We were placed under surveillance and had our pictures taken with a security camera mounted on the wall. We were also asked to change our schedule several times a week and were asked</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social engineering, as well as the role of artists, curators, researchers and others in the context of creating and sustaining such cultures. She is the editor and publisher of the online journal AV Club, where she is a regular contributor. She has written for The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Stages and The Future of Art. She is the host of the online radio show Art in America and the forthcoming documentary film, A Providence Now. Walking Towards Revolution: Cécile Duval, Art and Architecture, 1995-2003 Jamaica University Press, New York, 2005, and she has written for the New York Times, The New Republic, Stages and The Times. She is the recipient of several awards and has received a host of mentions, including one from the New York Public Library for her work as an editor of Stages and The Times. She has lectured on art and social theory, and her writing has been published in a range</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social engineering, with a particular focus on the role of artists, curators, research institutions and others in the context of creating and regulating new virtual and augmented cultures. She is also the editor and co-founder of the journal Cyber Culture, which publishes emerging art and cultural studies. She is an adjunct faculty member of the Rutledge Library Research Centre and the Metropolitan Museum of Art, where she is also an adjunct professor. Her publications include the forthcoming book ‘Art as Mass Media: From Print to Virtuality’, from which this article is excerpted.Art as Mass Media: From Print to Virtuality&quot;Art as media is a term that has been used to describe a type of material that emerges frequently in the writings of theorist and critic Michael Hardt and in the works of many other artists, including artists and artistic administrators. It refers to media that are capable of engaging with and influencing their audiences, both those who produce the material and those who consume it. It is a modifier of notions</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social impacts of new media culture. In addition to her work in the art world, she is a co-editor of the forthcoming online digital art journal Stages, and co-author of several books including the award-winning work Animals for Colonists, published by Animal Liberation. Her work has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Washington Post, The New Republic Online, Art in America, The Art Publishers International and The Art Publishers International. She is a co-founder of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre and has a research chair in the department of Visual Cultures.Her research examines the role artists, curators, artists' unions and other cultural stakeholders play in creating and sustaining new media cultures. In addition to developing cutting-edge techniques for the interpretation of data, software and multimedia content, artists are also active in creating new media environments that enhance the capacity of existing media to function – enhancing the likelihood that a given artistic judgement will be taken on imparting value</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social engineering, as well as the role of data augmentation and infrastructure development in the construction of artificial social systems. In addition to her team's artwork and research, she leads collaborative activities within the department's art and digital media labs, including workshops and events for students, artists, and research teams. She is a founding partner of the online publication Digital Journal and has served on the board of directors of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre.She is a co-editor of the online publication Digital Journal and part of the advisory board of Digital Journal Digital Futures.[2] Digital Journal is an online publication that examines emerging media and infrastructure technologies through the lens of art and culture. It was founded in New York in 2014 and is published quarterly. Its mission is to report on developments in art &amp; culture, with particular attention being paid to emerging technological paradigms. The journal has been shortlisted for the Turner Prize, Guggenheim Museum, Carnegie Museum of Art, and FACT (Foundation</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social engineering, as well as the role of data analysis and interpretation in the development and validation of new art forms. In addition to her work in the art world, she is part of a research team developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research project involves the collaborative study of the Ubiquitous Media project and the related Ubiquitous Graphics project.Amongst the many advances in science and technology that have come about in the past twenty years, there are few developments that are as dramatic as the advent of the computer and internet. These advances come about as a result of the competition between nations and international organisations for a limited resource – a limited set of people – which enables massive scale and often unprecedented autonomy for these organisations. Here, international organisations attempt to address a perceived problem of depopulation – the growing gap between rich and poor nations – by directing people’s money and other resources towards projects that either eradicate poverty or create enormously powerful new ways of organising the world. The rise</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social impacts of new media culture. In addition to her work as a writer and activist, she is a co-founder of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre and serves on the advisory boards of numerous other virtual cultural institutions. She is a founding partner of the Media &amp; Culture Research Centre and the co-director of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre (2015-2020). She is a founding board member of the RAND Corporation and the Media &amp; Culture Research Centre[2] and was a director of the RAND Corporation from 2001-2007. She serves on the boards of several other non-profit media research organisations, including the Virtual Cultures Research Centre, the Media &amp; Culture Research Centre, the Indiana University Center for Virtual Cultures, and the University of Toronto Centre for Virtual and Augmented Cultures.[3] And she has served on the boards of the Asian Arts Initiative, the Asian Media Trail, and the AES, to name only a few.How might art and culture be contextualised? This is</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social consequences of such cultural practices. In addition to her research, she leads the VIDCultural Studies department and is a co-curator of the upcoming 15th Venice Biennale of Art and Architecture. Her writing has been published in publications including the online version of The Aesthetics of Art (2013) and the forthcoming online version of The Aesthetics of Architecture (2015). She is part of a team developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social consequences of such cultural practices.In addition to her research, she leads the VIDCultural Studies department and is a co-curator of the upcoming 15th Venice Biennale of Art and Architecture. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social consequences of such cultural practices.In 2014, the Biennale appointed Kari Weidman, an artist and activist, as a curator for the new wave of</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social engineering, as well as the cultural consequences of new media technologies. She is an Editor of the popular online art journal Stages and a co-editor of the popular art journal Stages &amp; Time, where she holds a joint appointment. Her publications include the award-winning article 'Art as a Medium' in the Journal of Digital Cultures and the volume of essays ‘Beyond Art’ in Digital Cultures: An anthology of essays on art and culture from across the social and cultural sciences. She is part of the curatorial team for the online art journal Stages, which is published by Princeton University Press.From CounterpartsTo understand how artists can be empowered and engage with their creative work, we must first understand what is meant by ‘counterpart’ and how the contemporary art market is constructed. The contemporary art market is deeply imbalanced and under-exploited. In the current economic climate of ever-expanding corporation and complex financial models, it is no surprise that</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social engineering, as well as the role of data augmentation and disruption in the creation of socially engaged art and culture. She is the author of Social Sculpture: Embodied Art and Virtual Cultures (MIT Press, 2017). The Virtual Cultures Research Centre is a collaborative research project between MIT and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT/MIT Advanced Study) that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. The project was co-founded by Professors Steven Levy and Amitav Ghosh and Professors Joseph Grima and Amitav Ghosh along with Professors Raj Chetty and Amitav Ghosh Rao. In addition to their roles as researchers, the three faculty members are artists, producers and act as advisors to the project. They are also the co-founders and co-directors of the renowned virtual cultures research organisation, the Virtual Cultures Institute (VCI) which is developing a new generation of interpretive technologies. Professors Levy, Ghosh and Rao</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system] that is both intuitive and predictive. The aim of our research is to develop tools and techniques to interpret data, both natural and artificially generated, to create systems that are not only intuitive, but also allow users to optimise their own experience. Our approach to aesthetic, aesthetic and environmental considerations is a consistent and long-term research project. Our next research project focuses on the ethical and aesthetic issues surrounding artificial intelligence and aims to bring together the experiences of artists, curators, researchers and others involved in the development of such systems.[1]Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is Associate Professor in the Department of Visual Cultures and a member of the Virtual Cultures Research Centre. Her research interests include the creation of virtual and augmented cultures, art and culture for industrial and social contexts, and media technologies and infrastructure. She is part of a team that is developing tools to interpret data using virtual and augmented cultures. Her research projects explore the ethical and political issues surrounding artistic decisions and social engineering, as well as the role of data curation and monitoring in the development of new media cultures. In addition to her research, she leads collaborative projects with artists and other institutions to explore how artists can influence the cultural practices of their communities through their artistic and social networks. In addition to contributing to the Centre for Art and Culture Research and its publications, she is an editor of the journal Artforum and is the editor of the upcoming online companion to the journal, called ‘The Artforum: A Journal of Radical Culture’. She is also a co-editor of the forthcoming book, Radical Urban Cultures: Contemporaneity and Its Putative Cultural Strategies.She is a member of the Advisory Board of the Mersey Ferry Literary Festival and has held other roles at the Mersey Ferry Literary Festival, where she was a festival manager, a curator, a writer and an administrator. She holds a Bachelor of Arts in English Cultural Studies from the New College of Art, City University</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice.
    <text>should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice. If a collective voice is being drowned out by the noise of development, then something has to be done.  So far, so normal in most of the world, but in places like Liverpool, where artists and landscape architects are organising and producing a new generation of artists who might one day lead the way in a new wave of biennials. And there is a collective responsibility to put these young artists off. I don’t think there is any contradiction in that. If there is a challenge ahead, it has to be met with enthusiasm and creativity and not with cynicism or lack of ambition.  So far, so normal, but what is happening in Syria could change all that. The challenge for us is to find new ways of working constructively with people, places and cultures who are moving through the landscape, in ways that are not driven by the interests of a corporation or the state. That is, of course, until we have to start facing the challenge of how to feed ourselves and</text>
    <text>should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice. How do we understand their role in the current project? We might start by thinking of how we use our own power as artists to create spaces that are different from the city. The projects we undertake as artists’propose a new way of looking at the world. We might alter how the city is planned, governed and made manifest. We might apply these ideas to the downtown core, where art is often a substitute for infrastructure or design. The city is a complex system that depends on a continuous flow of water, resources and industrial products, yet it is also home to countless species of life that require food, shelter, air and soil. In an effort to understand how we can all fit into it, we might need to create new curatorial approaches.ART AND ARTS FOUNDATION, 2013-Present 	The art and arts sector is a critical player in the city because it plays such a large role in supporting its growth. In 2014, the biennial market value of the UK</text>
    <text>should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice.The curatorial role in the production of ‘future art’ is a particular odd one. It seems that the only way that contemporary art can be made in the future is if there is a large influx of talented people from the outside world who join the art force. I don’t mean that art has to be produced by and for people; but if it is going to change, it has to be done by and for people. The role of the gallery becomes a site where people can come and be themselves, but also a site of social interaction with artists from all over the world. I find this a very exciting development, given the role of the gallery in the history of the art world. But I don’t think that the curatorial role is one that can be sustained. I don’t think that the curatorial role in a modern art museum is going to be the same as the role in a modern urban museum. The urban museum is a site of</text>
    <text>should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice. The art projects had a collective voice too: the young people at the airport, the urban explorers and landscape photographers, the street artists, landscape painters and photographers, the musicians, street lorries and furniture mongrels, the carnival workers, the school lorries and whippoorwills, the delivery men and tree men, the lorries and lorries themselves. The fact that these people all have their own voices, their own collective imaginations and histories makes the political, socially significant and politically charged things that we do together possible.But this collective voice also needs to be democratically empowered. And this requires political power. And sadly, for a number of reasons, both within and without the arts community, the political is often quite difficult to find. One of the reasons for this is that, although artists have political power, they have limited access to resources or to people who can exert that power in meaningful ways. So, although the arts community may have a</text>
    <text>should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice. How do we know what is and isn’t culturally significant? Because these are the people who created the exhibition that we were in: the museum, the gallery, the film, the radio, the newspapers, the schools, the community, visitors and volunteers, and of course the farmers. All of them had a say in how the art project would be presented, what it should be called and how it should be constructed. For example, the museum may decide that the project should be titled The Documentary and the building it sits in should bear the title The Pale Blue Dot. The BBC may decide that the film should be called The Blue Danube. The BBC could also decide not to do TV or not to publish a gardening magazine called The Garden that is distributed in 100,000 local schools. So the museum and the community have a voice and the ability to respond constructively to what is being planned for the space. This is an important innovation for a number of reasons. One is that</text>
    <text>should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice. Why don’t more artists have the opportunity to contribute to a body of work that is politically, socially or ecologically significant? Because the body of art projects in this country is small and dispersed. It’s much more practical for me to commission an art project from a locality because I have a network of artists who can be drawn into it. The body of the art project would grow and change with the artist’s individual tastes and sensitivities. But when a body of work is made by a small group of artists – say, a group of landscape architects – it is almost certain to be very specific and specific to that community: very specific, for example, about the site chosen, the people responsible for it and the work they want to produce. And that is precisely the case with the city, where the commissioning of art projects is happening at a local level. It is this level on which the artist’s skills are most applicable. The commissioning of a</text>
    <text>should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice. The curatorial role seems to have expanded in importance as the biennial has developed. There is now a role for the curator in every art project, regardless of how individualised or particularised the project may be. The role has become interlocutoral, or social, or political. It is incumbent on the organisers of a biennial to actively seek out artists with whom they can work with on projects beyond the local communities. This is not an easy thing to do, or to say, or do it on a regular basis. But the biennial should strive to do it, because the artists will appreciate what the Biennial can offer them. And the Biennial should work with the artist on that. The question becomes whether the organisers of the biennial have the resources to make that happen. The answer to that is simple: yes they do. But the resources will be different. The resources of the biennial will be different. And the artist will have to negotiate those differences, as well</text>
    <text>should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice. If a collection of photographs is not meaningful in and of itself, then a collective voice is even less so. The collection should ideally be a point of departure for further work, a place where the artist and the community can learn and exchange and challenge each other. However, this is often not the case. Collection after collection of photographs of the same places, taken in different ways, is news to neighbours who have to deal with it on a regular basis.New Media and the Presence of Art and Architecture in Postindustrial Areas  [1] Gareth White, ‘The Rise of the Creative Class: Art, Architecture, and the Geographies of Postindustrial Growth’,  pages 151–60, Verso, London, 2012.Download this article as PDFGareth WhiteGareth White is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, Royal Holloway University, London, where his research interests include the geography of architecture and urbanisation, of culture and creative</text>
    <text>should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice. The fact that these people happen to be artists also helps. Because they understand the politics of their place and time better than any of us do. It is their place and time, and we are making work for people to remember and use. But this collective voice also needs to be supported in order to progress. It is up to the community to create its own future, and the next generation can take part in that future through what is politically, socially or ecologically possible. In other words, what is politically, socially or ecologically possible depends on who is in power in the area. If the area is given over to commercial development, for example, the voice of the local people will become subordinate to that of the corporate developers. And if the area is given over to agriculture, then the voice of the local people will become the voice of the industrialists. This is why a biennale is so important: to create a sense of place and time that is not totally dependent on the whims</text>
    <text>should be curated by, or co-curated with, artists who are artists in their own right, or whose work is illustrative or poetic in nature. For example, a collection of photographs that captures the migratory habits of wild animals or plants might capture the imagination of a bird or animal lover but it is almost certain to anger a farmer. The collection might provoke a reaction from the farmer but it is almost certain to moulder the farmer further down the line when he finds out that in the past few years, a number of his neighbours have started collecting Dust-Off’s. How do we know that these collections aren’t just for show? Because these are the curators who appointed them: artists, landscape architects, landscape writers and landscape photographers. These people have a collective voice and can choose to take part in something that is politically, socially or ecologically significant. In other words, they are the future of the art project. And they have a collective responsibility to use that voice.When was the last time you visited a desolate corner of Belfast’s City Road? Or a neighbourhood abandoned by its own residents? Or a neighbourhood where violence sweeps through the neighbourhoods? Or a neighbourhood with a vacant shopping centre? Or a neighbourhood where drug addiction threatens the very fabric of the neighbourhood? Or a neighbourhood where mental illness is a major problem? It’s easy to forget now, but much of what’s happening in these neighbourhoods is reminiscent of the roots of the Troubles. And, although the biennial is a relatively new concept in this city, the memory of the conflicts it inspires lives on. When the Art Biennale was first proposed, the City of Belfast expressed its disappointment that the Biennale would have to choose between showcasing the city and engaging with the ongoing conflict between the city and itself. The Biennale was to take place in its current form between 2014 and 2020, but City Council have since 2015 removed the city from the proceedings. Instead,</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
