<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical,
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical, philosophical. The level of abstraction involved in the production of words, symbols and images is a social category distinct from that of abstract thought itself. In this scenario, the labourer is not just made redundant in the production of images and sounds, but is actively engaged in inventing his or her image through the mediation of language and cultural institutions. Language plays a key role in this production, creating what Ruiz refers to as ‘meaning-production via its various units of measurement’. Language bureaucracies, or language-systems, are bureaucratic apparatchiks that constantly intervene between worker and machine, intervening at various levels to shape what can and cannot be said in the workplace. They prescribe and control ‘how sounds can be said’, ‘what can be said (in the workplace), and (in principle), what is not said’. Language production thus becomes relevant not only to the capitalist mode of production, but also to the struggles of socially engaged individuals and grassroots</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical, subjective.  	Physical abstraction is the level of physical objects; language abstraction is the level of abstract thought. Physical and linguistic abstraction exist in opposition to each other. The physical is contemporary with the linguistic and the conceptual is historical. The Marxist takes up the question, however, and asks, how does the body imagine the social life of the modern society? 	[5] As Walter Benjamin famously stated, ‘When writing, “we” actually live in the society of the spectacle”. And this is perhaps what Marx meant by when he said ‘When writing,’ he was actually living in the society of the spectacle. 	[6] So, the social life of the modern society is found in contradiction to the objectifying logic of the machine. And as we saw, this contradiction is reproduced in the world through the mediation of language and convention. Yet despite its seeming contradiction, the social life of the modern society is in fact intrinsically</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical, conceptual and instrumental. Physical and locus of production are the main spaces of abstraction in modern society. Physical and locus of production are the main sites of articulation of ideas and concepts. In this writing, I mainly refer to the level of abstraction that characterises modern science and technology. There are many other levels of abstraction – those of language, aesthetics, religion, economics, political economy and social history – but these are the main. Infrastructures and their representations in media continue to occupy this second spatiality. Media that claim to represent the social life of modern man (just as much as the social life of the future) are the objects of surveillance, while the symbolic travels of everyday objects, from the factory to the web, contribute to the management of information and the dissemination of images. (VG)Symbolic travels 	The symbolic travels of everyday objects are the voyages of an artist or a small group of artists or writers seeking meaning or purpose in a world that</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical, conceptual and instrumental. The former is the level of the physical and the actuality of the things that are physically represented; the latter is the level of abstraction. Physical and conceptual abstraction are fundamentally distinct. Physical abstractions (like machines) are driven by the same underlying principles; they are not autonomous or self-sufficient. However, the thing that is represented – the thing that becomes embodied in a form – is itself subject to changes in its environment. The level of abstraction at which the computer programme is run is dependent on the underlying assumptions and politics of modelling. Ideas and images that are processed in the brainstem are not abstractions in the abstract space of things, but must nonetheless be negotiated between different layers of the social. As a consequence, the politics of abstraction that characterises modernity necessarily entails a politics of representation and representation alone.  	[5] This is one reason why Ruiz was drawn to the social logic of abstract labour – the labour that results from the exchange of</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical, conceptual, and historical. He distinguishes between the level of abstraction from the physical world, which reproduces itself like clockwork (no matter what the underlying mathematical and computational processes), and the level of abstraction from language, which allows different levels of abstraction to coexist. Language is to a large extent a construction, as all representations and discourses are, and so every system isomorphic to a particular level of abstraction. Language acts as a set of rules that prescribe certain actions, and so language is both ‘the summit of abstraction’ and ‘the level of negation’.1  The word ‘abstract’ has been historically used to describe levels of abstraction, and its place in this ‘nondening’ is taken by mistake. Abstractions are those abstractions whose true form is not that of rules, nor that of numbers, nor that of symbols, nor that of contracts, nor that of ethnologies, nor that of tribes, nor that</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical, philosophical. He defines abstraction as the level of abstraction experienced by the human being at that particular moment in time. Physical and conceptual aspects of abstraction are immediate and direct (contemporaneous), while empirical aspects are abstracted (detached and spatially distant). The physical and conceptual aspects of abstraction are immediate and sensitive to change, while the qualitative (life-like) and conceptual (figural) aspects of abstraction are abstracted (open and sensitive to change). 	[5] Russell, On Abstract Expression (1905), in Russell, Philosophical Essays (1894–1957), p. 551. [6] Russell, On Abstract Expression, p. 551. [7] Russell, On Abstract Expression, p. 551. [8] Russell, On Abstract Expression, p. 551. [9] Russell, On Abstract Expression, p. 551. [10] Russell, On Abstract Expression, p.</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical, philosophical.  	Within the logic of postmodernism, the physical and the symbolic are transformed into one another, becoming one with the rest of the conceptual world. Language is reduced to a set of symbols and deeds. The very notion of language is reduced to a set of actions. There is no concept of individuality or difference anymore. In fact, what is being said by the management of language is diametrically opposed to what William James had in mind when he wrote the essay ‘On Liberty’. 	[5] Like much of what was being produced in the name of postmodernism, the emancipatory project was itself produced on the backs of working-class communities. James was no naïve trimmer. He had anticipated the fact that labour would one day be taken for granted, and that corporations would one day run roughshod over working people’s rights. So he had already written a book about ‘Machiavellianism’ –</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical, philosophical. He begins by characterising the level of abstraction as that at the level of the living being – consciousness – which separates the conscious from the dead. The level of abstraction then diverges into that of metaphor, specifically, as opposed to that of physics. Level 2 is characterised by ‘the death of abstract thought’. This is to say that metaphors fail in their attempt to capture the essence of things. They fail because essence is outside the range of possible metaphors. For this reason, Ruiz argues, they rarely achieve ‘pleasure in their esthetics’.[5] As a result, they tend to obscure or denigrate the thing they seek to represent. They tend to render its nature ‘impure’ or ‘barbarous’ – something like the image of a corpse on a plinth. (AKI)Real-time 	Real-time refers to the responsiveness of information to changes in its context – what we might call</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical, conceptual and historical. 	[5] The level 1 of abstraction is the level of the observer. The level of abstraction recognises the fact that thought and perception are made possible by means of physical, linguistic, conceptual and historical means: means that are circumscribed, mediated and delimited in advance, and capable of being mobilized at any moment. The level of abstraction therefore anticipates and contributes to the rise of technological culture and capitalism.  [1] Secular Humanistic Publishing, Inc. v. 7, 2015 WL 57898 (E.D. Cal. 2016), http://www.academia.edu/2711387/Secular_Humanistic_Publishing_Inc_2015_WL_57898.html (accessed November 2018). [2] Rafico Ruiz, ‘The End of Postmodernism’, in  	The End of Postmodernism: On the Philosophy of Image, ed</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and were given a new order of operations. The question of labour entered into the equation, and the way in which it had been previously defined as a labour conflict. The adoption of new organisational structures and the demobilisation of opposition politics also entered the picture. The way in which the management of postmodernism attempted to reconcile the loss of mass appeal and politicised subjectivation through the rationalisation of labour – through the back room manoeuvres of bureaucratic niceties – was to some extent a response to the emancipatory politics of the postmodern period. In other words, the postindustrial society it produced was not the society of the spectacle, but rather the society of the labourer. 	[4] Rafico Ruiz, in his book The Society of the Spectacle (1974), the history of abstraction and its discontents, makes the distinction between two levels of abstraction. Level 1: Physical, linguistic, conceptual. Level 2: Empirical, conceptual. He points out that because of their constitutive links to one another, the abstract elements of the society of the spectacle are intimately coupled with its production of meaning – it is through this level of abstraction that the social totality is continually renewed. 	[5] The degree to which abstraction is socially productive, in turn, depends on a number of other features of the contemporary world. For example, according to the sociologist Max Horkheimer, capitalism produces a collective amnesia – the state of being unable to recall certain events or concepts – which results in a social stupor. (pp.12–13)Ruiz elaborates:  	Hence, too, the dynamic between the cultural critic, the economic historian, and the political scientist, the sociologist, and the ethnographer, and between the cultural critic and the material thinker, and between the critic and the biographer, and between the critic and the archaeologist. Each of these writers attributed new</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into
    <text>project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which social forms develop from the exchange of these theories. But more than that, it is an area within which competing theories are put into practice. The public square is an area within which actors from different worlds can come together and exchange. It is an arena within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an arena within which theories are put into practice and which social forms emerge from the exchange of these theories. Theory and practice are two sides of the same coin. In this coin, there are other kinds of theorizers and perhaps we could even agree that there are other kinds of ethnomusicologists as well. But the point I am trying to make is that the social sciences have a much greater role to play in understanding how we inhabit the public square than many realise. Theory and the extraordinary technologies of anthropology, geography, and ecology that have allowed certain kinds of knowledge to emerge naturally, or by default, are now playing a much larger role</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which social forms develop from the shedding of blood, sweat and tears. It is an area within which ideas are freely questioned and which social forms are open to possibility. It is an area within which individual artists have a voice and which social media can be a platform for expression. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which social media can abridge the voice of the ruled. It is an area within which individual artists have a voice and which social media can abridge the power of the powerful. It is an area within which theories and data are exchanged and which social media can play no part in determining that exchange. It is an area within which theories and data are not mutually exclusive but are instead a platform for negation.[9] 	[1] Capital &amp; Cultures, Paul De Bruyne, New York, 2000, p.40.Download this article as PDFCapital &amp; Cultures, New York, 2000.PreviousNextCapital &amp; Cultures,</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which social forms develop as a result of these experiments. But it is not just theories and social experiments within the public square. The experiments within the public square also need to be taken seriously, because if they are not, then there is not going to be a public square with democratic freedoms. In fact, this is the second reason why I believe that the social and political experiments in the public square are necessary, but they are not enough. The first reason is that an informed and engaged public takes part in the experiments, and if there is no public engagement, then there is no public square with democratic rights. 	I would like to suggest three experiments within the public square that I think are very promising, but which are not central to the discourse of the present moment and which can and should be developed into what might be called a ‘public sphere’. Three experiments within the public square are important, but they are not sufficient. I would like to suggest that there is a</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which can therefore be questioned. But it is also an area within which ideas are constantly reinterpreted and new theories can be developed. In short, it is an area with which people can engage with, challenge and develop their knowledge. It is an area within which new ideas can be put forward and challenged. It is an area within which debates are had and new understandings formed. But it is also an area within which capital and labour exchange. Capitalising on the spread of knowledge, it exploits the public for its own purposes, appropriating those very theories and processes that those with a particular set of skills and knowledge might possess. Knowledge-producing institutions, such as universities, academic centers, national museums, are valuable for the reason that they build and foster knowledge, providing access to knowledge and fostering criticality. But this is only possible because of the inaccessibility of certain areas and for the reasons that I have outlined above. As a result, the public square is an area within</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which social forms follow the theories which result. But it is also an area within which social functions and agency do not necessarily result. In other words, theories and the social square are not confined to the public square, nor are they confined to the worker’s and community’s square. Theory and social change are much more political, and much more reliant on participation, creativity and politics on the social level. In short, it is much more possible for a theory to become a practice than for a community to grow up independently of the social.  In short, theory and social change are much more political, and much more reliant on participation, creativity and politics on the social level. In short, theory and social change are much more political, and much more reliant on participation, creativity and politics on the social. In 2015, the Paris Climate Agreement was signed by over 180 nations, and the first concrete steps were taken towards reducing emissions. Even though the agreement came as a surprise</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which social forms develop from that process. But it is also an area within which social forms are always fragile and can only ever be constructed upon the backs of labour and struggle. And capital always seeks to exploit and bind labour together in order to further its own interests. This is why in the public square, as in other capitalist spheres, the arts are often the butt of oppressive social systems and why artists are often oppressed too. Why are artists often artists in oppressive systems? Because the social relationship between the artist and the viewer is fundamentally mediated through the medium of art. The social bond between artist and viewer is what Norman Brown called ‘the mutual aid of spectator and artist’.3 That is, the social function of the artist is to produce visual images that serve as a form of social resistance. But what kinds of images are capable of this? It is this question that underlies the nature of contemporary art today: why are artists obliged to engage audiences beyond their own communities? And</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which social forms evolve there. But this is only possible if the public square is democratized. Capital and labour cannot operate in this system as a single entity. Ideologies and social norms have to be continually (abstractly) renegotiated and upgraded in order to be applied across the board. Ideologies and norms have to be continually (abstractly) renegotiated in order to be applied across the board. Capital and labour have to collectively agree on how to move forward in order to affect change across the board. Otherwise, there is no chance of effecting change across the board. New ideas have to be cobbled together from disparate sources in order to effect change across the board. And this is what social transformation struggles against neoliberalism. I see two ways of articulating this phenomenon: (a) as capital itself, and (b) as labour embodied in labouring bodies politicized by labour. When looking at capital as a social relation, the public square is a space in</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which social forms are constantly in flux. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists and not just artists who fit the given form, and whom capitalism has selected for its future workforce. But it is also an area within which social forms are never static. Theory and ideology are much more powerful than that. They construct social forms and inspire creativity in people to act on those forms and to imagine new social forms. And capital often likes to combine the two. It produces what it calls ‘new economic models’ that predict how social life will be in the future, using existing data to support a future social form that is more like the past. These alternate histories are often based on the oppression of peoples of colour and low-income groups. I’m particularly interested in the ways in which technology is displacing workers and jobs, and how that is playing out in Canada and the US. But I’m also interested in the notion of how cultural</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which social forms subsequently develop out of it. But it is also an area within which social forms ultimately exist in response to the totality of social relations and global economic fluctuations. And this is precisely what I mean when I speak of the ‘ordinary’ people. I mean people who are born into capitalism or follow its tracks, people like yourself. You are not extraordinary. But the point is that capitalism endures because there are limits to how much can be produced at a time. There are social limits to what can be produced. And these social relations eventually have to come to terms with the contradiction between the growth of knowledge and the growth of social life. And this is what we are doing right now in many parts of the world, by exploring the possibility of what might be called ‘regeneration’. This is a concept that was employed by Marx and Engels in their concept of the ‘periodic cycle’. They defined it as follows: ‘the</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human knowledge is organized within what is sometimes referred to as the ‘public square’. In Humanities and Social Sciences Today (2008), Peter Osborne describes how the social sciences embrace and develop knowledge through what he describes as ‘the public square’.2 In my thinking, it can be said that the public square is an area within which theories are put into practice. It is an area within which theories are freely questioned and where ideas are put into disuse. It is an area within which ideas are circulate widely and not necessarily confined to a particular community. In other words, it is an area where capital and labour exchange. It is an area within which social forms are open to question and to possibility. It is an area within which ‘ordinary’ people become artists, and not just artists who fit the capitalistic mould. It is an area within which ideas circulate widely and are not necessarily confined to a community of artists. It is an area within which theories are put into practice and which social forms can be shaped through it. But what is meant by ‘the public square’? What is meant by the concept of the commons? How does the public square come to inhabit and be inhabited? These are questions that address potential power structures underpinning the social. The public square is thought as a site of exchange and possibilities. It is thought as a site of possibility where people come to define the terms and parameters of social life. It is thought as a site of domination and subjugation. It is thought as a site of domination by the powerful and successful at negotiating the terms of their social practices. The public square is thought as a site of domination and subjugation that is mediated and controlled by those with a vested interest in maintaining the status quo. It is thought as a site of domination and subjugation that depends on the prevailing order of things. The public square is thought as a site of possibility, and possibilities for those who lack access to the material goods of</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the
    <text>curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering at the New School, and Prof. Jeffrey Hawkins from the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the University of Southern California. Their expert reports and fascinating but brief but crucial question-and-answer session, entitled, ‘What is Machine Learning?’, is the impetus for much of what follows in this volume.  The audience for the next workshop was invited to come in early and explore the latest work in the area of reinforcement learning with reinforcement agents. This one-day, fully funded by the Ford Foundation, ISTE workshop was co-chaired by Prof. Jeffrey M. Hawkins (Principal Investigator on the AVArt project), Prof. Rob M. Malamund (Principal Investigator on the AVArt/DeepMind project), and Prof. Elizabeth H. Hudson (Head, Neural Information Systems, New York University).  The audience for the following three workshops was invited to participate in the next stage of the project, ‘Probe:</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Artificial Intelligence and Computer Science at the New School, who suggested to me while we were both in the audience that there were many ways to approach the topic of artificial intelligence and computer systems, and that this was a perfect time to bring up the work of the New York City-based Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory (C.S.A.L.), whose interest in computer systems and AI led them to me and to many others like myself). This workshop was also a turning point in my thinking about the kinds of systems that could and should be constructed, and the kinds of interactions between humans and such systems. Before this, I had been developing my own kind of AI, developing ways of understanding and interacting with the world through inference and machine learning. In many ways, this was pre-dating all of the things that came out of the Workshop and the various sessions that followed it, but it was still in the proto stage. Also, this was before the emergence of new media or computer</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Electrical Engineering and Computer Science at the New School, who organized the workshop, and to Prof. Jeffrey Cranor from Stanford, who organized the talks and labs in his lab.  To the students, I would like to thank for their valuable feedback during the workshop, which enabled us to expand the scope of the research project, and to develop a more sustainable version of the underlying research. I would also like to thank Jeffrey Cranor for his lab hours during the workshop, where many of the students discovered the fascinating world of artificial intelligence and computer programming. It was Jeff’s mix of theory and lab work, along with the participants’ playful banter and open-ended questions, that made the workshop such a great encounter. I look forward to seeing what these students undertake in the future.  A special thanks to the participants in the workshop who have made their own contributions to the research project, based on what they learned during the workshop, and on their own initiative. This will be</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering at the New School, and to Stan Van Veeler, the lead researcher from the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the University of Alberta, for their contributions to the topic of this workshop. The subject of this workshop was: (a) The Language of the Human Being (also known as Proto-Indo-European), (b) Human Language Scripts and (c) Neural Networks in the Impact of Histories, Cognitions and Migration. The audience for The Language of the Human Being was made up of leading figures in a wide range of areas of artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my dear friend Prof. Deepak Chopra, who led the team that produced and contributed to the 2014 version of The Language of the Human Being, and whose work we were fortunate to have in mind as our 2015 version of the script. The audience</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering at the New School, who organized the workshop and made it a project.  And a special shout-out to the late Prof. Aviv Klein, from Columbia University, whose research and teaching I greatly value and look up to. All the figures in the workshop had a major role in the social and political context of artificial intelligence and computerization; their research and teaching I incorporated into my own research and teaching.  And a special shout-out to the young people who came to the workshop, many of whom have a direct or indirect impact on the future trajectory of artificial intelligence and computerization. They are likely to be different from the people I have known who attend the workshop every year, but the insights they give are fundamental to understanding how we tackle the challenges of the contemporary society.  Aims and Objectives  Aims and Objectives is an evolving text that documents the trajectory of my research project, which is informed by the experiences of the people I work with</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering at the New School, who suggested to me that I should take the workshop as a research project rather than a teaching one; he was a leading artificial-intelligence researcher at that time.  The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure but potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering at the New School, who suggested to me that I should take the workshop as a research project rather than a teaching one; he was a leading artificial-intelligence researcher at that time.  The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure but potentially interesting ones. A special</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering at the New School, who organized the workshop, and to Prof. Rutledge from the Computer Science Department at the University of Bristol, who organised the exhibition, and to Prof. Graham Devlin, from the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the University of Southampton, who co-curated the exhibition, and who supervised the research project, and to Prof. Florian Sprenger from the Department of Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering at the New School in New York City, who supervised the lab and provided invaluable feedback on the exhibition)The topic of this workshop was: Relational Database Systems and Deep Learning  The topic of this workshop was: Embedded Deep Learning with Open Human Language  The audience for the workshop was made up of leading figures in computer science and artificial intelligence, who collectively had a clear understanding of the topic and its parameters. The contributions to date from these diverse areas of study have continued to grow, and it is with great pleasure to say that</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering:  ‘Rob, you are going to change the world!’ It was a first-hand account, based on years of supervised work with DeepMind, that I present in this brief essay. Even more importantly, the work is my own, from years of developing and delivering contextual content through my work as a writer, producer, researcher and curator. It’s a result of months of careful consideration, developed over two years in collaboration with the New School in New York City, led by Prof. Evelyn Forget, from the Department of Art, Gender &amp; Sexuality at Columbia University. The New School has a long tradition of producing thinkers who have been influential in the field of art and culture, and has been a home to several artists, including Paola Marrati, Damien Hirst, Guillermo Vitale and many many more. It’s an institution that I have great respect for and that has been a</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering at the New School, whose department I was part of before I went to graduate school: &quot;Computer programming is not just for nerds! It is a highly interpretable form of mathematics that can be used to unravel complex problems.&quot; and &quot;The art of programming is actually pretty beautiful.&quot; In addition to being brilliant computer programmers, Prof. Malamund and his co-workers at New School were also professors of Computer Science and the School of Architecture &amp; Urban Design, and co-curators of the New School Museum’s exhibition Computer Games and Art. Prof. Malamund is a prolific writer, speaker and curator. He has written more than twenty books on a wide range of topics. His most recent is called Things That Matter: Conversations on the Meaning of Life and Culture. He has been a presenter of the popular science-tv show The Amazing Race, which runs for four seasons on the BBC, and</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  judged to be friendly to humans. The programmatic interface is the point where the host and the ‘programmer’ meet, where the host and the ‘programmer’ come to terms over the differences between the two, and perhaps over what kind of programming language the host might write to execute the ‘programmer’’s ‘program'. In May 2016, I participated in Workshop: A Short Course in Artificial Intelligence at the New School in New York City. The topic of this workshop was: ‘Interfacing AI with Human Language’.  The topic of this workshop was:(a) Neural Networks and (b) Deep Learning’s Impact on Workflows and Politics of Art, Culture &amp; Migration.  The audience for the workshop was composed of leading figures in artificial intelligence and computer science, and many more obscure yet potentially interesting ones. A special shout-out to my enthusiastic undergraduate advisor, Prof. Rob Malamund, from the Department of Electrical &amp; Computer Engineering, and his class, ‘Introduction to Computerized Pattern Recognition’, which was a favorite of the proceedings.  The audience for this symposium was invited to suggest topics for the 2018 symposium, and to vote for their favorite. Topics ranged from conceptual foundations of artificial intelligence to practical applications of AI to the cultural production of language to questions of community and migration.  The voting class did not come to the symposium with clear defined roles or goals. Rather, their proposals were guided by a shared interest in advancing the understanding of how AI might change the world.  The audience for the symposium was able to come to understand that the AI that they were about to encounter was not an AI that they had created but rather a set of tools and systems that had been programmed with the goal of executing specific actions. This understanding generated excitement and new understanding around what AI might be able to accomplish, but it also raised questions around its ethical implications and the limits</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in her book The Urban Crisis (1987), the idea of the ‘global city’ first came to prominence in the mid-1970s with the publication of the book The Urban Crisis: Urban Problems in the USA. In that year, the New York Times ran an article by Leslie Staeheli titled ‘The End of Urban Life?’ In that article, she argued that the rapid growth of global cities was killing the ‘world’’’old’. She argued that the huge metropolises constituted a ‘monumental challenge to the prevailing logic of global growth’ and that ‘the cities’ constituted ‘the last stands of modern culture’. Rather than retreating into the metropolises, Sage argues, we need to encourage local alternatives through research supported by the ‘global city’.  [4] To be sure, the notion of ‘the city’ as a living organism</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in her research ‘Beyond Ground: Science, Architecture, Politics in an Expanded Form’, there are actually over 200 cities in the world with their own Wikipedia pages.  [4] See http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_metro_dock_communities, accessed 10 June 2016.  [5] See, for example, http://www.metro.com/en/about/default.asp?section=Environment&amp;lang=en, accessed 10 June 2016.  [6] The manuscript is structured as a series of interviews with key figures in the field, each conducted through text, images and audio documents. Interviews are arranged chronologically (starting with ‘Introduction’) followed by annotated question-and-answer sessions following that order. Interviews are conducted in English, French, Korean, Russian, Spanish and Chinese with the participants coming from a variety of disciplines, including urban studies, geography</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in her ethnographic study of New York, the city became a main stage in the emergence of modern bourgeois culture around 1870, when the US entry into the First World War broke out. She draws our attention to the role played by the arts and the performance in this process, noting how the city ‘became an object of international historical and maritime recorders’.[4]  [4] Sage and Beatrice Royce White, ‘The Second Wave of the Biennial Explosion’,  	Signal, 2004, p.20.Download this article as PDFEugenie SageEugenie Sage is a writer, curator and producer who, in addition to her work as an arts educator, is a co-founder and artistic director of The Resident. She is the recipient of several awards and has been named an ARC fellow, one of six artists to be part of the ART Sculpture Project, and one of the world’s most recognisable</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in her ethnographic study of the Mongol conquest of Australia, published in 1962, resistance to British colonialism came primarily from within the Mongoloid sub-species of the genus Mongrel. As a result, the name ‘Mongrel City’ derives from the fact that names in Australia and New Zealand were changed to reflect the fact that the Mongrels were the first Australians to arrive in Australia.  [4] See Kari Weil, Race, Authority, and Subversion: Race, Intimacy, and Law in Contemporary Democracies, Zed Books, New York, 2013, and Michael Ames, ed., Race and Class in Modern Democracies, Zed Books, New York, 2011, both of which examine this history.  [5] The Australian National University has kindly agreed to name a new postgraduate programme in Geographical Information Systems (GIS) and the Environment, Global Information Systems, after Alfred Nobel, who was a leading geologist and geographer of the</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in her ethnographic study of New York, The City that Never Sleeps: On Take-Off and Other Essays, 	p.129–42, New York: Zone Books, 1990: ‘Nearly all of the buildings on the top of Manhattan were built during the 1920s and 1930s by and for the Anglo-American multinational real-estate firm, Sullivan &amp; Cromwell. The dominant form of housing for the post-war boom lasted from 1945 to 1968, a period during which time large parts of the city were transformed into multimillion-dollar financial portfolios.’[13] This ‘domestication’ narrative is repeated time and again in the architectural canon. It gained currency in part because, during this period, architects were able to indulge their vanity by claiming a regional identity for the building stock and the neighbourhood. But ultimately, the justification for this kind of urban imperialism – which seeks to dominate and transform a city through the construction of ever larger and more</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in her analysis of globalisation and urbanisation in her book The Urban Crisis, 1989–1997, the concept of the ‘global city’ first came into being in 1967 in the United States. Prior to that, in 1967, in Paris, the entire city was segregated by a single, two-year-old structure, the Mallorca of Luxor. In both cases, the ‘city’ is seen as an expropriated mass of consumers and slaughterers of goods.[4] Sage points out that the megacities of the future – those with more than 10 million inhabitants – will consist mainly of software and data-intensive operations centres, with a scattering of smaller hotels and restaurants as ‘back-up’ structures. The city will be divided into zones with a budget set aside specifically for the use of specialised police forces and military agencies. The zones will be manned primarily by robots, with automated parking and surveillance systems that spy on residents and</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in her ethnography of New York, New Politics, she visited the city in the mid-1980s but was &quot;very shocked’ by how much she saw that her distance from the city had caused her to miss out on much of the action. She found the increased emphasis on cars and suburbs in the 1990s and 2000s to be a hindrance to envisioning the city in ‘the present’. By the time of her visit, however, the car was long since out of the picture.  [4] See, for example, Sage’s ethnography of New York, New Politics, p.28.  [5] For more on the Goffey–Semple Debate, see Sage’s, New Politics, pp.29–35.  [6] For more on Goffey–Semple Debate, see the article in Sociology of Arts &amp; Culture, Vol. 28, No. 1, October, 1991, p</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in her ethnography of the African diaspora, the rise of metropolises in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries was intertwined with the rise of fascism and genocide. Sage,  	Empire of the Metropolis, 2015. Image courtesy of the author.  [4] Meehan Crist, ‘Urbanization and Homemaking: An Introduction’, Journal of Feminist Cultures, Vol. 2, No. 3, Spring, 2015.  [5] William Julius Wilson, ‘The Dynamics of Community Development Corporations: Lessons from Miami’, in  	Urbanization: International Studies (New York, NY: Routledge, 1988), p. 38.  [6] Thomas Waugh, ‘Urban Studies: An Introduction’, in  	Urban Studies (New York, NY: Columbia University Press, 1991), p. 19.  [7] William Julius Wilson, ‘</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in her ethnographic study of the 1997 Amsterdam Biennale, the Biennale’s globalisation––the city in its transnational register––started long before then. In fact, the Biennale’s adoption of the city as a global register necessitates the city’s economic and spatial reconfiguration in order to work globally. In other words, the global city is not just a transnational register; it requires a spatialisation that goes beyond national borders.  [4] Excerpt from ‘The Global City: Urbanization as Spectacle’, the lecture delivered at the Art and Contemporaneity conference, as part of The Art Newspaper’s 'Speak Up' series, 2015, sponsored by the Australian National University and Curtin University.  [5] The Biennale’s 2015 edition is being presented as a ‘fortnight’ in a series of three-and-a-</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that, in theory, can monitor, control and analyse large amounts of data]is at the heart of a new paradigm of urban urban development, one that puts data at the core of urban development.  [1] The project was funded by the Australian National University (ANN) and Curtin University (formerly Curtin University of Technology) through the Australian Research Council (ARC). The ARC is a federal government ‘funder’’ of higher education, research and learning supported by the Australian National University and the Curtin University. The purpose of the ARC is to promote and facilitate a mutually exclusive ‘shared’ future for both the Australian and New Zealand ‘regions’.  [2] The idea of a ‘global city’ has gained currency in recent years primarily due to the proliferation of metropolises, particularly in Asia. However, it was not always thus.  [3] As noted by Eugenie Sage in her work Animals for the Market: Money, Capital and Capital Fog (2003), the market for animals in the nineteenth century was influenced by the work of French economist Thomas Malthus (1759–1817), who developed a mathematical formula that suggested a consistent rate of profit for economic calculations based on the rate of population growth. Malthus’ work lay at the basis of much of what we now think of as ‘capital’ – the substance that makes up buildings, farms, cities and the ‘aggregate products of which constitute the ‘stock’ of economic value – and so our calculation of ‘capital’ tends to follow his work.  [4] Morehshin Allahyari and Christiane Paulussen, ‘On the use of physical and mental capital in the process of urban renewal’, in,  	Urban-Agriculture/Conservationism: Capital in Crisis? Christiane Paulussen, Anne K</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with
    <text>curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with the changing needs and desires of the community, and to happen in response to that. Art’s real power comes from within, from the gifts that are given to it by the community. The art world needs to require artists to dedicate a fair amount of time to become committed to the profession, and to become part of a larger community that supports the profession. That is, artists’ commitments have to be long-term commitments. The commitment has to be meaningful and enduring. If the community is to have any real influence on the art that is produced, then the time has to grow long enough to permit that to happen. The time has to be organised, and art has to be produced in ways that are dependant on the community, and yet flexible enough to happen at a moment’s notice. That is, the community has to be able to choose when and where the art is produced, and the commitment has to be flexible enough to accommodate that.If the time and labour</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with the changing ­infrastructure of things, allowing the user to become fully involved in the work without forcing it to be something that he/she can ‘t‑get involved with. 	Art should be seen not as a fixed point in time, but rather an evolving canvas that allows us to perceive new possibilities and orient ourselves towards older histories. The tools that allow us to ‘see past the surface of things’ and engage with previously hidden patterns in the world should be made available to all artists. The introduction of new emoji should come as no surprise to people who use emojis and have been using them for some time. New emoji allow people to express more complex desires and multiple modes of ‘thinking beyond the surface’. New emoji allow people to ‘understand’ more complex phenomena. The ability to create innovative emoji that perfectly capture the nuance of a person’s voice and accentuate the point of origin of a word (even if that person isn</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with the changing ­infrastructure of things, not compelled to do so by an authority to which it is ­seriously committed.Art should evolve organically, rather than the other way around: programmed into the very fabric of the ­thing it ‘chairs’ and which it purports to ‘purify’. 	Art should be able to adapt itself to accommodate changes in its environment, rather than being constrained to conform to established paradigms and thus becoming stale and worn out. 	Art should have the potential to break free of its own implied meaning, whether that is by its own volition, historical accidents and creations, or other forces on the world around it. To some extent, art should also evolve through its own creative destruction. But this is much harder to pull off in the real world, because there is no guarantee that the world will always suit artists exactly. For instance, it would be absurd to attempt such a thing in the real world because it would</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with the technological necessities of the modern world. But art has to be creative in its own way. It has to work in the face of ­human-machine interface incompatibility, to the point where the artist’s role becomes one of actively ­enabling that compatibility by shaping the machinery of technology. This is art as an art form.Art should evolve with the times. But it cannot evolve in a vacuum. The role of the artist in the 21st century is one of creating means of experiencing art that are more ‘real’ than the art itself. The art should be interesting, the experience of art should be memorable, and the art should change according to what is happening in the world around us. The role of the artist is to create environments in which art can happen, and to let that happen through what is called ‘technologies of artistic perforations’. In other words, the role of the artist is to make the means of art perforations</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with the speed of change, and the artist should be encouraged to pursue new creative ways of exploring the world. It is this aspiration that runs contrary to the prevailing order of things, and few artists are willing to compromise their work for the sake of the future that is being promised for mankind by the machines. 	Art should not be confined to the narrow parameters of what is imagined to be possible with the latest computer or smartphone, and artists who compromise their craft for the sake of aesthetic gratification are often saddled with bleak and empty works of art. It is true that the Internet era of unlimited data and rapid innovation has rendered art’s role as curator and technologist redundant, but this is hardly an ideal for an artist to have to contend with in the 21st century, where the limits of what can be imagined and imagined are ever increasing. 	Art should be seen as a tool that helps us to imagine better, and to help us create better worlds. That is, it should</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with the changing ­challenges that man ­faces today. And as biennials become ever more institutionalised, and the arts patronised by national governments, the role of the artist will become ever more circumscribed. The biennial should offer its participants a range of possibilities, not a fixed look ahead.  	In the nineteenth‐century biennial form, the curatorial office sought to establish a shared common heritage between the different venues. Curators, participating in the biennial, were expected to produce works that would be shared between the different sites. Stages, each with its own character, was the formalised form of this shared sharing. Art’s public role in the twentieth‐century biennial was to offer a fixed image of the art to be exhibited, and to act as a surrogate for the artist’s self-consciously mediated image. Art’s plural image was put to much less use. During the nineteenth century, biennials became more and</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with the changing ­infrastructure of society. That is, society as it evolves. And to some extent, art should simply ­progress along with the changing face of things.  	But this is not always possible. And some artists will undoubtedly develop unhealthy ­relationships with the infrastructure of society (just as some ­humanists will inevitably develop unhealthy ­relationships with the machinery of production and distribution). And for some artists, the relationship between artists and the infrastructure of society might become adversarial.But this is also not always the case. And for some artists, the relationship between artists and the infrastructure of society might become symbiotic.And this is where the art of the machine comes in. The relationship between an organisation and an artist might become art of the machine.Artists and the artists who work for it might invest in the machinery of production and distribution because the organisation itself is an artist's machine. The relationship between the artist and the organisation might become art and vice versa.Art</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with the changing ­infrastructure of the global economy; its very character is a reflection of the decisions – along with the aims – pursued by capitalist modernity. But this is art, and art has to be careful what it orders. As the great poet Edmund Wilson famously said, ‘Where there is art, there is also a trapdoor’. And the line between artist and consumer is often slippery; the boundary between the artist and exploiter is often blurred. Artist-users have a particular responsibility to be vigilant, and it is up to them to scrutinise every aspect of their work in order to ensure that it is not artist-hindered by the capitalist logic of cultural consumption.Art should not be confused with artifice, and contemporary art is no exception. The word itself is  	discoverable, and when used in this way, denotes the state of mind of the contemporary artist-consumer; it is a ‘knowledgeable discovery’ that is crucially</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with the technological quotient. That is, art should be allowed to progress at a rate that is as ­potent as the capacities that it embodies. That is, the art should outlive the technologies that it is made to serve. This is the original mission of the Biennial and the reason why it is so ­truly contemporary. It is a reason why the art should be there to be discovered, to be shared, and to be enjoyed by future generations of visitors to the place where it was made. It is a reason why contemporary art should be made in areas where art has never been before, and by artists from the future. 	However, this is not to say that art should be made in a vacuum. Art should be made in relation to what is happening now, and in anticipation of what may happen in the future. We could also consider art as a prophylactic measure, a last resort measure, and a ­tool of last resort in the ­creation of</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  	and given the avatar of an 11-year-old girl, presumably the one most susceptible to the influence of machine learning, which is advancing at an incredible rate. 	Moreover, given the speed with which technological innovation is advancing, and given the ­ ­human capacity to analyse vast amounts of data in ways that could never be imagined, it cannot be denied that there will be times when the custodians of ­human history look back with regret on the decisions that were made during the development of technology. Machines will certainly play a part in shaping the things that happen now, but the role of the artist will be different. She or he will play a part in creating technological possibilities that are more ­potent and ­affective than those that were ­created by man. Machines will certainly do many things better than artists could ever hope to, and that is arguably what art is about.Art should be tools rather than engines of change. Art should be allowed to evolve apace with the changing needs of society, and the intrinsic richness of its possibilities should be celebrated in the fullest possible way. That is, society’s ambitions should be directed not towards the conquest of art as an object of consumption but towards the creation of creative possibilities for individuals and the social. Some of what is being created by artists today is even being created in response to the pressures of a capitalist circulation of images and images. The pressures of a capitalist circulation of images and images are immense. They involve large corporate media companies with huge website footprints and advertising budgets, as well as many other stakeholders, including artists, who are often left behind in the process of innovation. The result can be felt in curatorial decisions, which are often influenced by the images that are being taken. The importance of this in today’s media-rich world cannot be understated. Modern art today is often ranked amongst those images of the past that were most influenced by the technologies of the internet. The importance of art being</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based Economy: Trade, Resources and the Future of Cities’, in  	Global Platforms, Issue 2, 2000, p.28.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at McGill University, specializing in the social histories and infrastructure of medieval and Renaissance urbanisation in North Africa and the Middle East. Her current research focuses on the social and political contexts of transnational railroads and the links between infrastructure, migration and the postcolonial/hierarchical forms of production that emerged in the wake of the web. She is also the editor and co-founder of The ANNALS of the Near East and North Africa, a journal of art and architecture in the Arab World, and the co-editor of the N.W.A.R. Atlas: The World at a Glance – An Arab Atlas, a journal of art and architecture in North Africa and the Middle East,</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based Economy: Environmental Economics and the Micro-Industrial Revolution’, in  	The World Economy of Inert Materials (Oxford: Oxford University Press), 2001, p.6. 	[4] Gareth White,  	Post-Industrial Society (Cambridge, Massachusetts &amp; London: MIT Press), 1999, p.33. 	[5] William Burchell, ‘Technologies of Intangible Assets: Legal and Social Concerns of Digital Intangibles’,  	Environment and Politics 	, Vol. 25, No.1, Spring, 2000, p.1. 	[6] Rafico Ruiz, ‘Intangible Assets: The Plant and Its Poor Laws’,  	Environmental Ethics 	, Vol. 2, No.1, Summer, 2000, p.1. 	[7] Wilbur Ross,  	The Global Economy of In</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based Economy: Trade, Resources and the Metainterface’,  	Geographic Research Letters 	, Vol. 23, No.1, January, 2000, p.100. Available at: http://www.geocities.com/Appadurai1.html.[4] Hua et al.,  	Cities for Medium-Scale Economy, pp.1–4. Available at: http://www.wadsworth.org/architecture/2000/august/cyber.html?year=2000&amp;format=archival&amp;cache=1AAC8E4E0DF9C0AE0AE2048D0B3AE8A0B7469C9D0F994E7 [&amp;WBA]http://www.metainterface.com/en/download/1772/1/2/1/1/Terrain-generating-technologies-in-</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based Economy: Trade, Investment and Resource Segmentation in the Context of the Global South’,  	The Lancet, Vol. 354 (9), 2000, p. 903. 	[4] Thomas Waugh, ‘On the Nature of Global Warming’,  	Geographical Research Letters 	, Vol. 25, No.1, January, pp. 105–16. 	[5] Prafulla Lawrence, ‘The Politics of Eco-Capital: Climate Change, Capital and the Metainterface’,  	Geographical Research Letters 	, Vol. 25, No.1, January, pp. 1–23. 	[6] William Julius Wilson, ‘The Ecology of the Critic’,  	Geographical Research Letters 	, Vol. 25, No.2, January, p. 1. 	[7] Nad</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based Economy: Trade, Lifestyle, Resource Crises in the Nineteen Twentieth Century’,  	Global Environmental Change Review, Issue 8 (2000), p.335. 	[4] Arjun Appadurai,  	Global Environmental Change Review, Issue 8 (2000), p.335. 	[5] Eddy Cuellar,  	Environmental Reform: Lessons from an Ecological Society, Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore, 1988, p.37. 	[6] Eddy Cuellar,  	Environmental Reform: Lessons from an Ecological Society, Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore, 1988, p.40. 	[7] Eddy Cuellar,  	Environmental Reform: Lessons from an Ecological Society, Johns Hopkins University Press, Baltimore, 1988, p.40. 	[8] Steven Aftergood,  	Quantifying Social</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based Economy: Trade, Migration, and the New Media of Exchange’,  	Environmental Science &amp; Technology, Vol. 29, No. 2, September 2000, p.335. 	[4] Thomas W. Cooley, ‘The Kin-Layer’,  	The Chemical Biology of Moisture-Absorbing Bacteria and the Kin-Locking Collagen,  	Volume 2, Issue 2, March, 2000, p.339. 	[5] John A. Church and Neil J. White, ‘Comparative Biochemistry: Basic Chemical And Mathematical Principles’,  	Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, Vol. 90, No. 1, February, 1970, p.171. 	[6] John A. Church and Neil J. White, ‘Comparative Biochemistry: Basic Chemical And Mathematical Principles’,  	Proceedings</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based Economy: Trade Secrets in the Information Age’,  	Academic Emergency, Issue 10, 2001, p.183. 	[4] John H. McWhorter and Christian Körner, ‘Comparing San Francisco and Rapture: On the Possibility of Time’,  	Forecasting the Future 	, Vol. 3, No.1, Winter, 2000, p.1017. 	[5] John H. McWhorter and Christian Körner, ‘Comparing San Francisco and Rapture: On the Possibility of Intelligences’,  	Forecasting the Future 	, Vol. 3, No.2, Winter, 2000, p.1021. 	[6] Graham I.P. Vogel, ‘Possibilities for the Future in the Information Society’,  	The Future of Work 	, Vol. 4,</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based Economy: Trade of Livestock and Products, Part 2’,  Sustainable Development Research 	, Vol. 1 , Issue 2, 2000, p.109. 	[4] Raytheon Co., Inc. v. Singh, No. 97-cv-02407, 2000 U.S. Dist. LEXIS 10303. 	[5] The following example is taken from the book Sustainable Cities: Strategies for a Post-Industrial Future 	 by Donna Haraway, Chapter 8: Strategies for a Post-Industrial Future, Pearl, 1993, p.2. 	[6] The specification of ‘smart meters’ was part of a broader trend in the 1990s for integrated energy systems to be installed in buildings and for large scale renewable energy resources to be produced at the local level through the integration of existing energy infrastructure. For more information, see: http://www.energye.com/sustainable</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based Economy: Boston, Cambridge, and Mumbai’,  	Academic Press, New York, 1988, p. 60. 	[4] Asad Hashim, ‘The End of Oil: Will Our Petro-Capital Need a Revolutionshow?’,  	Oil, Issue 4, Spring, 2000, p. 45. 	[5] Richard Florida, ‘Oil and Plentiful Resources: A Survey of the Present and Future Possibilities of the Resource Class’,  	Cambridge, MA, 2002, p. 10. 	[6] William Schindler, ‘The End of Oil: An Economic Analysis’,  	Cambridge, MA, 2002, p. 12. 	[7] William Schindler, The Oil Crisis: Causes, Consequences, Strategies, New Perspectives, Princeton, NJ, USA, 1988, p. 39</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that obtains its properties from information collected on the ground.] 	[Possible applications for such technology include environmental monitoring, mapping and comprehensive hazard assessment services for construction, combined hazard and fire commissioning, residual hazard assessment and mitigation, mass transit design and propulsion.] 	[For more information, see: http://www.massonfire.org.] 	[Back to top] 	[2] Technologies for Remote Sensing and Manipulation of Material and Bio-Based Economies of Exchange and Need, a Workshop Held at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, September 2000. For a description of the origins of the concept, see: http://www.mideast.org/saas/files/docs/remote_sensing.pdf. 	[3] Arjun Appadurai, ‘The Rise of the Bio-Based Economy’,  	Academic Emergency, Issue 9 (2000), p. 485. Download this article as PDFJennifer Evans and Evan Calder WhiteBack to TopBack to Main Index of Infrastructures Homepage  1 MediaFire, Inc.Homepage: http://www.mediafire.com/downloads/media/0020749461656297722/MediaFire_Bio_Breadth... Homepage: http://www.mediafire.com/downloads/media/002074946167446927/MediaFire_Bio_Breadth... Homepage: http://www.mediafire.com/downloads/media/002074946168685744/MediaFire_Bio_Breadth... Homepage: http://www.mediafire.com/downloads/media/00207494617069922/MediaFire_Bio_Breadth... Homepage: http://www</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3 
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3  The snapshot includes a timeline that ‘continues to move’, a ‘snapshot’ of an empire that ‘continues to exist’.4  In part, this is a comment on Friedrich Hayek’s The Road to Serfdom, in which the late Nobel Prize winner develops his ideas about the welfare of labour and the welfare of labor-property in response to the welfare state collapsing around us.5  Lennon’s statement begins: ‘Stories matter; and more than that, they matter a great deal.’6  He later adds: ‘Such is the maxim of Max Brooks’s, the philosopher and novelist Max Brooks (1879–1971)’s reflections on the legacy of John Lennon and Paul McCartney:  “All those who have been cut off from the things that make them human, can learn to live without them.’7  Bro</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3  The snapshot includes a timeline ‘artifact showcasing some of the most significant events in [the] history of [the] world’, as well as a timeline ‘flipped’ that runs along the top of the image.4  The image is a 24-hour ‘live wallpaper’ display, ‘a new kind of cultural marker and monument’, ‘a living archive of cultural history’, that changes display format every day.5 The image is a live wallpaper displaying a timeline ‘stitching together the past, present and future’, which continues until ‘the next snapshot’.6 The image is a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline ‘stitching together the past, present and future’. 7 The image is a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline ‘stitching together the past, present and future’. 8 The image is</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3  The project’s tag line, ‘Workstations’, recalls Thomas Allsen’s better-known poem: ‘Times change, but life  stays the same’.4  Workstation is a nod to the administrative state, its traces entwined in the larger web of global corporate capitalism. Its adoption by the broader public comes as no surprise to John Lennon and Paul McCartney, whose collaboration on the tune was part of ‘The Beatles Anthology’. The Beatles were an iconic British rock band formed in 1964. Their song ‘Baby, Rava’, featuring John Lennon as Lennon, Paul McCartney as McCartney and Ringo Starr as Starr, topped the British charts on July 24, 1970, when ‘Rocko’ Rollo’ –––– sang the song in support of the UK’s participation in the first ever ‘Take Off’ military mission. The song became a worldwide hit,</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3  The early part of the project’s title refers to a ‘snapshot’ of a person’s or collection of people’s life ‘in one cohesive space’.4  The quote comes from Blake’s Moony Poppie, a poem that appeared in a poem entitled ‘The Wizard’ in the Sunday Chronicle &amp; Chronicle &amp; Tabloidopulphy in 1845.5  The project began as a ‘snapshot’ in Time &amp; Life in London, Britain, November 18, 1845.6  The poem is a re-telling of a poem by William Blake, ‘Time and again’, that appeared in the journal of Samuel Johnson Cash in reply to a question about the possible translation of Blake’s poem ‘Tippoo’ into the language of the English Empire, composed largely for the use of merchants and traders by Johnson Cash.7 </text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3  The project’s short story,  	The Ghost of Tom J.’s Corpse,3  includes a chilling account of a man named Tom J. (not his real name) who wraps his body in filth and despair as he watches his people ‘burn like chimneys’.4  The project’s interactive map suggests a way to map the area: ‘Start at the foot of the Golden Gate Bridge, which spans the Bay Bridge into San Francisco. Zoom in to find the intersection of Golden Gate Avenue and San Francisco Highway 5, which runs parallel to the Golden Gate Bridge. Double-click on the intersection to take you to the intersection of Golden Gate Avenue and North California Street. Zoom out to find the intersection of North California Street and Golden Gate Bridge. Double-click again to take you to North Bay Street.&quot;4  This description sounds eerily like the tale of Autumn Arbor, a ghost of a city</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3  The snapshot includes a timeline ‘stitched together’ by hand in the pages that follow Blake’s words – a statement of fact that runs counter to the dominant narrative of the age: facts of history, however stubborn and malleable they may be, are the last stand of the human enterprise. Blake’s remark is a cry of despair.4  To be sure, the snapshot is a lament for the state of historical fact as we inhabit it now – a lament that is at once widespread and particular. But the snapshot offers no comfort for the reader, only the bearer of a particular set of facts. The question raised by the project is this: what would you do with the information you uncover? Would you use it constructively? Or would you resort to oppressive control structures? In the age of the ubiquitous Internet and mobile devices, the answer to these questions is a clear and present possibility. The text presents the potential outcomes of such a project as a daily</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3  The initial premise of the project is that of a single event – flash flooding, tsunami, quakes, hurricanes, earthquakes – that collectively, through the historical and cultural parameters of the moment, emerge as the defining moment of our age. The event that gives form to the history of the twenty-first century is the mega-event that is the biennial, and while it is true that large cultural institutions are built on the biennial, the individual and collective archives that record the life and works of those long-lived and powerful institutions are often deliberately built so as to obscure the true sources of power and significance – i.e. the causes of the crises that precipitate them – so as to permit and facilitate the next event, and so forth.4  The logic of the project is that as the culture that is recalled and brought back to life through the exhibition is made evident in the museum, the biennial should record the culture as a whole, because, as the art historian</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3  The project’s tagline, ‘A Quickie’, is a play on words derived from a line in Blake’s famously weary and wistful poem: ‘Quotation marks are dead, and words are cheap now’.4  The project’s other statements of intent, such as its call for submissions in early 2018 and its intention to open for artist-led projects in summer 2019, are all based on assumptions about the future that may be more easily verified by the news of the project’s existence. In the intervening years, the project’s stated interest in the present as opposed to its desire to project its future inhabitants onto the present may have been motivated by a kind of nostalgia, or perhaps a familiarity with the ways in which the present is constituted. Whatever the motivations, the project has put its name behind what is essentially a historical document, or a snapshot of history as it happens to be unfolding in the present</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3  The project’s tagline reads: ‘Writeth the Future’.4  The project’s social media accounts frequently reference the events of September 11, and ‘911’ becomes a regular topic of conversation. In an effort to better understand how individuals would engage with such a proposal, I conducted a Skype interview with four individuals who identified themselves as being from ‘MIT Media’, ‘MIT Radical Research and Design, or ‘MIT VRD’, the organization behind the concept. Their voices were constructed using constructions from many different voices. These individuals described their sense of wonderment and elation when they first heard of the prospect of autonomous agency, but also their confusion and frustration over the futility of the human endeavor. Their position on the question of whether to expand the definition of life beyond the confines of the state crystallized in this statement: ‘We don’t know, and that’s the problem</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that answers, in part, the questions posed by the project’s title, ‘Autonomy Unbound’.  The project's website refers to itself as a response to the question: ‘What if instead of large corporations and state governments, we created self-governing, self-sufficient and charitable organizations? What would you do with such an organization?’ In part, this is a paraphrase of a quote by John Lennon, who famously said: ‘I want to be free, and then I want to be an agency’.1  Lennon’s statement echoes William Blake’s immortal line: ‘Man’, ‘tis but a flash of lightning to an empire that never sleeps’.2  The project's website refers to itself as a ‘snapshot’ of a timeline, ‘stitching together the past, present and future’.3  The snapshot is a timeline that appears at the beginning and the end of the project, as a way to document the way in which the historical and futuristic worlds interact. The image is an allegorically suggestive one – a snapshot of a timeline that existed before the invention of the computer – and its textual counterpart, the statement ‘Flash of Anus’, signals the gesture with which the user interfaces: the timeline is a passage of movement, an interruption, a signal that something has gone wrong. The image is intended to interrupt the flow of time, to interrupt the rhythm of motion, to signal a break from that motion.  The project’s Twitter feed announces that the timeline is a recording ‘of past times’.4   	The timeline is a recording of past times – in a temporal sequence – that exist outside the human race. It is a recording that can be accessed and altered through ‘key’ presses made in the operating system of the operating</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship, should give us some ideas. I will return to this in a moment.In the meantime, there are also questions surrounding the role of art institutions in the city, and specifically about the role of the artist-run institution, but first we need to distinguish between two kinds of institutionalisation: what we might call the ‘institutionalized imagination’ and what I call the ‘institutionalized reality’. The former is the imaginary world that is constantly re-imagined by artists and writers, through processes of institutional renewal and in-group/out-group selection; the latter is the reality of institutionalised choice. The former feeds the latter into existence, encourages the latter to act, and thus develops into what I call the ‘New Urban Frontier’. Here, I mean developments that are dependent on no one but for a specific set of circumstances – for example, the generosity of public funds – and thus emerge independently of any particular choice or intention on the part</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship, will allow them to create a unique and potentially game-changing experience in a city that’s still coming to terms with the impact of deindustrialisation. What I’m doing with Liverpool is a microcosm of what we’re hoping to do with the city, and I can say that this is something that Liverpool Biennial will inevitably aspire to. But I can also say that if we do it poorly, we’ll all get involved in making it better. That would be hubris. But I can also say that if we do it really well, we could even renovate a building and turn it into a gallery, or a synagogue, or a bakery, or a café, or a school, or a pub, or a dance hall, or a church, or a monument… People will ask me what I’ve actually done; I’m not sure if you’ve actually seen my work yet, but there are a few</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship, needs to be carefully considered. I do think that there are lessons for other biennials around the world that can learn from Liverpool, and beyond. For example, the relationship between biennials and cities-as-cities is a contentious one in Liverpool, with some people arguing that a biennial should be able to define its own form, and others arguing that a city cannot. In the end, the people of Liverpool will have to decide whether they want to become cogs in a machine, or become the very embodiment of a biennial’s ambitions.Join us for the second Liverpool Biennial Conference on October 7 and 8, 2016, organised by Liverpool Biennial and Cascadia Art Biennale. The conference will be held at Exhibition Research Lab, University of Liverpool.Tickets are still available. Find out more at www.eventbrite.com/e/2a167bcf0ba18763c7392739bcf8f05c</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship, will allow people like me to have a start in making sense of what that relationship entails.Download this article as PDFEmily Pringle-Hughes and Amber Dean-LawrenceSuburban Home Tour Emily Pringle-Hughes is the Curator for Liverpool Biennial 2016 and co-curator of Liverpool Biennial 2017. Her work centers on the intersections between cultural production, architecture, community and home, and explores the potential of new media and online technologies to create new kinds of urban environments. Her projects have been part of the following commissions: Architecture Biennale, Dolphin Arts Biennale, Future City, Drawing London and The Official Selection, to name only a few. She has been an advisor for the 2016 Olympic and Paralympic Games, the 2016 Commonwealth Games, the 2016 Leeds and 2016 Liverpool Biennales, and was a consultant for the 2016 Manchester Biennale.She has written for The Guardian, The Economist, The New York Times and</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship, will allow them to create something different and interesting. That relationship – between the artist and the city – is a unique one, and I look forward to seeing what they do with it.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is Professor in the School of Art, Design and Technology at the Royal College of Art, London, and holds the position of Chair of the ACSM Board of Governors. Recent books include The Age of Art (2015), Art and the Public (2016), Art and Public Sector (2017), Publics (2018) and most recently, Art and Public Space (2018). Recent publications include the book The Gallery as a Public Space (Routledge, 2015), the publication of the graphic novel and the podcast A Reconstruction of the Gallery (2016), as well as co-editing the book The Gallery as a Public Space: Issues, Strategies and Tools (Routledge, 2016). Recent projects include the projects funded by the British Council, the</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship, will allow for creative ways of approaching this. That’s for another day.For now, I want to tell you about another project that I’ve been developing for the Liverpool Biennial that’s set to open in December 2016: the project is called A Cinema At Home, and it’s a collaborative effort between the Biennial, the Architectural Association, and the Leanne and George Grantham Bain Architectural Group. It’s being led by Sally Tallant, the architect of the Grantham Bain home, and it takes the form of a multi-disciplinary exhibition, with design, interior and landscape articles, architecture lectures, landscape and interior design photography, and even a fashion and food blog. The aim is to show how the home can be a place of interaction, a space for contemplation, exchange, and a venue for creative work – all in one place. This exhibition will be a ‘homecoming’ for the area,</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship, will allow them to create what is perhaps a hybrid version of the present that is both sensitive to the city and able to survive its criticism. That is, perhaps, the future that Liverpool should be aiming for.Download this article as PDFLiorah RichterJade Eco Park, 2017Image courtesy of the artistPreviousNextJade Eco Park, 2017Image courtesy of the artistJade Eco Park is the largest private land and residential development project in Liverpool, and one of a number of projects commissioned by the Biennial through its Curatorial Impact Award. In 2011, the Biennial paid £18.5 million for the land and buildings to develop into 56 residential towers and nine small businesses. Since then, the Biennial has continued to pay for the development of the site through its own funds and building sales. The Biennial is the property of Biennial Liverpool, a company incorporated in 2002 and based in New York. The Biennial is an international arts organization with an annual budget of over</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship, can certainly be assessed. There are many ways of thinking about such relationships, and there are many ways of organising such relationships. It is critical that Liverpool Biennial be able to meet this challenge, and so I see this relationship as one that is sensitive to different kinds of relationships, and how that might shape the context and the characters of the stories told. There is a temptation, in curatorial work, to treat people as commodities, to treat them as interchangeable groups of people – to treat the audience as if it were people – but I don’t think that is the right way to go. To me, the audience is people – people who have chosen to come to this particular art event, people who have an opinion on the art by which the event is judged. People who have chosen to purchase a ticket, or to shop at a certain retailer. People who have put in a certain amount of effort to get a ticket. People who have made a commitment to come to the event</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship, will allow people to know that this is happening. The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a complex one, and one that, as we all know, no artist can or will ever resolve.But what has been happening in Liverpool lately, both in the media and in the building of new neighbourhoods, is that people are asking, What does it mean to ‘live’ in Liverpool? And although there are different ways of answering this question, there are also different definitions of ‘living’. We in the know, the urban professionals, have defined ‘living’ in ways that are arbitrary and capricious. The artists and designers who come out of the Biennial with their hands on the cutting edge of development, but don’t necessarily live there – that is living in ways that are arbitrary and capricious. The definition of ‘living’ as opposed to that of ‘living in’ is</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in 2016 and will see the city coming together as a whole, rather than as a collection of distinct neighbourhoods. This is a much more radical approach and one that our curators and artists have been developing. Will it be able to withstand the kind of critical scrutiny that the Biennial, and its curatorial team, will inevitably demand? I don’t think so. But it will certainly have the support of the city at large, and thanks to the work of volunteers – young and old – who will be helping to run it, and it will be able to stand up to the Biennial’s demand that it present a curated ‘picture of living and breathing’ of the city.The question of what constitutes a ‘picture of living and breathing’ is a tricky one, and while I don’t think that Liverpool Biennial can or will resolve this question, their relationship to the city, and the city’s role in this relationship, will allow artists and others to work together to create possibilities for dialogue, and by means of their work, imagination, and research. It will be a difficult partnership to negotiate, but one that will have rewards and losses to be reckoned with.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleIt is said that a picture is worth a thousand words; a phrase that encapsulates in one bound the disparate ideas and fragmentary fragments of what was once called ‘The Liverpool Biennial’. The phrase captures the essential notion of the ‘picture’, but it is also a pause, a way to speak the truth to power, to let loose a cloud, and a word that evokes memory but can also signal a change in context, a signal that can then be acted upon. In other words, words are not neutral or even just tools; they can also be powerful tools. There is a reason why the Biennial was founded on a platform of lies, and why it spread like</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive the old curatorial conceits of places and peoples. The images they produced were, in their attempt to be emulated, radically different from the images of the past curators. While the former responded to the aggressive curatorial gesture of the Biennale, the latter was concerned with the exploitative market forces of the museum and the collection. Although the biennale has evolved into a much more prominent form of its kind, its images continue to be a principal means of connecting with art, and documenting the past. The biennial – and this is a question that Liverpool Biennial 2018 will inevitably answer – is the last outcrop of a former colonialism that was then subsumed under the heading of modernity. Its discursivity and randomness of form are set against a background of institutionalised nostalgia. The museum is the locus of the imagination and the site of the museum, but it is also the site of the biennial. The biennial is the last remaining vestige of the</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive and redefine historical narratives.[10] The exhibition itself was a departure from the traditional curatorial format of chronicling the history of art – which typically focuses on a select few artists or a specific theme – in favour of an expansive survey of art and biennials in contemporary art in the global south and east. This is reflected in the name of the exhibition, which is a hybrid of two curatorial approaches: curatorial curatorial and museum-level. The aim of the museum-level approach is to detect the hidden meanings buried within artworks, while the aim of the curatorial curatorial approaches is to reveal those hidden meanings. The goal of the hybrid curatorial and museum-level curatorial approaches is to detect and reveal those deeper meanings, while the aim of the hybrid biennale is to catalyse a new wave of art-based cultural exchange between art and biennials in the cities where art is often seen as a foreign species. The hybrid biennale also proposes a</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive the past and the present in a manner that is treacherous to the historical narrative of the city in which they are embedded. The exhibition was also a test of the curators' willingness to consider controversial material on the curatorial and artistic side of the exhibition. This was particularly evident in the form of new media – YouTube videos, Instagram feeds and critical writing from the major online art and design sites – that were inserted seamlessly into the digitally enhanced museum sections of the museum. These inserted videos and essays, while critical in their own right, also provided the curators with an ideal vehicle to work in their art world by which to spread the word of the exhibition, its existence and practices, and to encourage a pilgrimage to the galleries and exhibition venues. In her introduction to the exhibition, Njabulo Olu Olu Olu for the catalogue entry, The Photograph that Miseducated John Lennon, the curator of photography at the Liverpool Biennial, remarks: ‘There is a sense that this</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive the past and narrate the future. This was not easy to achieve for a number of reasons, the biggest of which was the closure of the Old Bailey Courthouse and the associated loss of audience numbers. A second reason was the decline of the arts in the area: even when it recaptures the appearance of things, such as crowds at art exhibitions, art is now often equated with a large corporate exhibition. Thirdly, and most significantly, the biennial itself has become a tool by which art is produced and transmitted globally with minimal resistance. It is the largest museum in North America and the largest in the world, and its position as an icon of the art form is testament to this.  The triennale itself was a test of how art and the biennial could coexist in the same space, and in this sense, it met the biennial challenge. Art’s place in the city has become defined by its proximity to museums, and the proximity of biennials</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive the past and narrate the present.[8] The new works were presented in chronological order of appearance in the exhibition, beginning with works from the 2016 exhibition. The new media of travel and multimedia have also affected the art world in profound ways. As biennials become ever more media-savvy and media-obsessed, their aestheticisation and narrativity becomes ever more mediated and media-dependent. If the art world can be made aware of the extent to which art institutions and artistic-political/ideological/cultural orientations are fuelling this media, then perhaps the art world can too. That is, the art world could begin to organise itself around the notion of art and the voyages of art rather than in the form of a museum and gallery. This is the idea that was pursued by the European curators behind the 2016 Biennale, Francis Duhem and Christiane Paul, and the multi-disciplinary team led by Rubén Castro that toured the United States and Latin America</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive old modes of cultural organisation and make new forms of historical narratives. The new media allow the curatorial team to reveal the hidden agendas of interest to a more localized audience. The introduction of new media, they emphasised, is often a prelude to a more critical analysis and discourse. For the 2017 Biennale, that ‘potential for satire was further enhanced by the fact that the Trump administration was taking shape’. The curators saw a way to engage with the political situation without descending into hyperbolic character assassination. They invited twenty-one artists and creative professionals from across the globe to collaborate on a new generation of works that would be displayed in the main exhibition venue, the UN Headquarters in New York. The new collective ‘shared a common language and shared a commitment to exploring a range of ideas and constructing an ever-shifting tapestry of knowledge through their works.’ The artists selected from the first proposal were Sebastian Mehr, Elmgreen Walls,</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive the past and narrate the present.[1] The aim of this article is to examine in depth these two examples of the cultural ‘re-narrating’ that was promised when the museum was conceived. I have chosen to focus on the latter because it is the most accessible and representative of the three curatorial styles used in the Biennale, while the museum is the least accessible and representative of the curatorial styles used in the Liverpool Biennial. The reason is that the museum is a multi-use facility with multiple readings and uses. To meet the demand for both the 2018 and the most recent works, its programming includes numerous short lectures, videos and performances, many of which are designed to be performed at large festivals and other public events, and its exhibitions have a distinctive ‘big picture’ characterised by wide-ranging public performances and participating arts organisations. This article focuses on the ‘Main Entrance’ at the Museum of Modern Art, New York.</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive our notions of voyages and return to the shores of the ocean.  In the 2018 Biennale, the curators turned their attention to the impacts of climate change and the biennale as a historical entity. The first instalment in the ‘Tropical Wave’ series explored the historical origins of the concept, its use in contemporary art, and its possible evolution through the curatorial hand. More specifically, the first instalment in the ‘Al Gharib’a Cultural Centre’ series suggested a possible new trajectory for the concept through a possible combination of art and architecture. The latter part of the ‘Triangle of Life’ series suggested a possible new form of cultural organisation through a possible combination of social and economic means. The curatorial hand turned to the industry of art as a means of engaging an ever-expanding audience of visitors, while the form of the biennale expanded to include works produced in collaboration with other curators</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive and expand the notions of what is considered art and historic monuments.  The 2016 Biennale, on the other hand, sought to render the city into a museum, perhaps anticipating the curatorial approaches of the curators in the new biennial forms. Its aim was to show how the possibility of a museum building could be reproduced through the construction of ‘smart structures’ – structures that monitor, analyse and act as nodes in a ‘multinational database’ that captures and analyzes cultural activity in the city. At least one of the proposed smart structures was based on existing data-mining and monitoring projects.The popularity of biennials as an exhibitionary form has increased over the past decades, but despite these increasing numbers, their historical place in the city remains a point of contention. The early on-site biennials, such as Venice and San Francisco, relied on large numbers to sustain the vibrancy of the art being shown, while the more recent, but smaller</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial – which began in 2016 and will run for four years, from June 2018 to October 2019 – will be the final instalment in a planned biennial series. In 2017, the Biennale of Sydney launched in cooperation with the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, Sydney. In 2018, the Australian Museum and the Liverpool Biennial launched a collaboration to bring a permanent collection of Art and Artifacts to life through the production of new works and exhibitions. Liverpool Biennial 2018, curated by David Hogg, explores the city's past through the language of art.  In the 2017 Biennale, the curators behind the new works addressed issues of identity and migration and the voyages of discovery made by the advent of photography. They invoked the voyages of discovery of art and biennials in order to explore the contemporary condition through the tropes of the tourist, the tourist and the tourist trap. The aim of the exhibition was to test how photography and the new medium of the museum simultaneously reconceive heritage and attempt to reclaim lost identities. The exhibition was a response to the mass-circulation of glossy, art-negative, and often nostalgic contemporary art, which in the age of mass media is both ubiquitous (in terms of content and form) and enormously influential. The new exhibition pieces sought to address this in-rush of energy with art that is both powerful and enigmatic. They were made with archival and archival material, using works from the museum collections, and utilising the forms of both old and new to tell the story of the past, in the hope that their enigmatic nature will generate a sense of wonderment and enrapture in an anxious public. The exhibition was also made possible through a partnership between the Biennale and Liverpool’s Museum of Modern Art, which runs for two years from October 2018 to September 2019. Liverpool Biennial 2018 themes and topics were carefully considered and selected through a multi-year process that prioritised the interests of the city’</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between
    <text>curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between Liverpool Museums and the Birmingham Artists Placement Group.  The project was also supported by the Future City initiative funded by the European Commission, Cambridge Biennial, 2012, Cambridge, UK; MIT/Harvard/Meyer Foundation, Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Harvard/MIT/PSI, Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge, MA, USA; MIT/Cambridge</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between artist and publisher Apex (home of Cambridge and Cambridge Multimedia Design), and was presented in partnership with The Arts Catalyst (Cambridge, UK) and The Dolphin Arts Centre (Bangladesh) at 2015 Cambridge, UK.  The work is the result of a collaboration between Artists Pointer and Meehan Pope (the artist’s own words), through Apex and Pope’s publisher Simon and Schuster, who provided funding for the project. Artists Pointer's partnership with Meehan Pope was part of the 2016 Smith Commission, which saw six artists from the UK and around the world select six works from her studio for the exhibition at Liverpool Biennial. The artists were Andrew Curry, Angie Lefebvre, Satish Kanady and Sandeep Parmar. The commissioning phase saw the artists given individual worlds in</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences (the Academy being an independent storied British art institution founded in 1888), the New Media and Design Schule in London, and the Welsh Streets Arts collective in Cardiff. The project was made possible through the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences and the Welsh Streets Arts collective in London. The Welsh Streets Arts collective was established in 1980 and their collection of Welsh Streets houses is the largest remaining Welsh Streets legacy, with over 1,000 houses in total still in existence. 	In an effort to better understand the challenges faced by the Artificial Intelligence (AI) frontiers described in the Welsh Streets article, this multimedia project was developed in association with Computer Science and Humanities (Cascadia) University, with the Academy of Motion Picture Arts in New York. The project was designed to be integrated across all the major media platforms, and to be of value</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between Liverpool College of Art and Liverpool John Moores University Libraries, the latter providing access to approximately 1,000 audio and video recordings made during the 2016 Computer and Software Art Exhibition held at the LJMU Libraries. The project was presented at the Digital Art &amp; Design conference organised by Liverpool College of Art and Liverpool John Moores University Libraries.  The project was supported by the AHRC funded project  	Machine Image, part of the AHRC funded Programme in Animation Research. 	[i] Arjun Appadurai,  	Self-Organising Bulletin Boards, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1988, p.10.  [ii] John McCarthy,  	Information is Power, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1988, p.38.  [iii] Eddie Huang and Neil Johnson,  	The Shadow Economy: On the Uses and Risks of Digital Curating, John Benjamins, 2005</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Liverpool College of Art, Arts Intelligence, which runs alongside the school’s Centre for Art and Culture (CAC).  The project was conceived and directed by Nina Edge, a former art administrator at CAC who has a particular interest in the potential benefits of AI to art and culture. Nina Edge is the former Chair of the Computer Science and Engineering department at CAC who has a particular interest in the potential of AI/Artificial Intelligence to art and culture. She is the recipient of a 2015 Cynthia Tannen Prize for Art and a 2014 Rosslyn Medal for Art and Technology from the British Council. Nina Edge’s work often incorporates both theoretical and practical considerations in the context of technological and cultural evolution. Her work often operates between theoretical and practical considerations in humanistic terms. She is the recipient of several awards and has been a lecturer in computer and information science at Wesleyan University, Cornell University,</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between Ray Kurzweil, the founder of Google and Facebook, and philanthropist John Paul McCartney. The work is a multimedia installation that stands approximately 12 metres tall and includes a 12-metre high high high visual façade, a 12-metre long curved post that offers unobstructed views of the street, a 12-metre long curved post that connects the street with a series of circular streets, and an integrated circuit board that converts a computer system into a multimedia installation. The installation is intended to contrast the mundane with the artificial, while enabling the imagination to engage with the technological roots of urbanisation. 	[i] Macaulay, A History of the English Language, Pliny, 1621.  [ii] Macaulay, A History of the English Language, Pliny, 1787. Print.  [iii] Macaulay, A</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial, Merseytravel and Liverpool John Moores University, and the architecture practice Architecture of Tomorrow, an interdisciplinary research project funded by the Arts Council. The project was co-chaired by Peter McAlpine, Professor of Computer Science at Liverpool John Moores University, and Dr Vikram Seth, Professor and Chair of the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at Liverpool John Moores University. The project was also supported by an Early Career Research Grant from Merseytravel and a partnership agreement from the Arts Council. 	The new work addresses two different levels of cultural consumption – the consumer and the artist – while recognising the essential connection between the two. The video installation and its inverted / vertical format reflects the increasingly important role of the artist as an interpreter of media and platforms. The role of the artist is to create a context in which behaviour can be changed, but which remains constant; what the context is is is still the ultimate consumer need.</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial, Merseytravel, and Liverpool School of Art College. The project was also supported by a 2015 PhD from the Clinical Psychology Department at Liverpool School of Art Studentship, and a 2016 MA in Art History from the Johns Hopkins University Graduate School of Art Program in Architecture. Machine Image was presented as part of the exhibition at the Mersey Ferry Museum on 8 September 2015.  Machine Image was made possible by a grant from the Turner Prize Foundation.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is an artist. Her work in the public sphere tends to address the technological and contextual aspects of (human)-ness. She has exhibited internationally and has been a curator for the Museum of Modern Art, New York, where she has curated two exhibitions of contemporary art from around the globe. She has curated numerous exhibitions at the National Gallery of Ireland, London, and the U.</text>
    <text>curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial, Liverpool Biennial, the Oxford University, and the Institute of Art at Liverpool John Moores University. The project was curated by Peter Norvig and Peter Spender and premiered in Venice last October.  For more information please visit Machine Image.  Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is Artistic Director for the Biennial and holds a joint appointment as Curator for the Liverpool Sydney CA/Liverpool Biennial 2018. He has made exhibitionary work for the Liverpool Sydney CA/Liverpool Biennial since 2014 and is an associate curator at Welsh Streets Gallery, New York, USA. His work in the arts and social practice is increasingly focused on the relationship between art and social practice. His books include the “Art and Art practice: A Cultural Studies Reader” edited by Peter </text>
    <text>curated by an AI �Thy Art Will Tell Me’, was curated as a part of the New Media &amp; Design � symposium, �On Machines, Future Cultures, convened by Deena Chalabi and presented as part of the exhibition at Tate Britain, September 2014. The project was also part of the Tate Britain 2015 research project, ��Machine Image, part of the exhibition ��Machine Image, which was subsequently exhibited at the annual meeting of the Society of Illustrators in Liverpool. The exhibition was part of a series of exhibitions taking place across the UK and internationally themed around the cultural impact of AI/Artificial Intelligence (AI/A.I. is a branch of Machinery Systems founded by Ray Kurzweil and Peter Norvig). ��Machine Image” is the title of a new multimedia work that seeks to reconcile the technological and the cultural. It was made possible through the collaboration between Liverpool Scheme and MIT Computer Science and MIT Media Lab's Media Lab. The project is a collaboration between the Liverpool Medical Research Council, MIT Computer Science and Liverpool John Moores Medical Centre. The Medical Research Council is responsible for the design and development of medical interventions and gadgets, while MIT Media Lab is responsible for the implementation of innovative technology that is used in the healthcare system. The project was supported by the AHRC and Liverpool College of Art, Design and Environment (LJCDA). The LJCDA is a not-for-profit educational charity established in 1896 and founded by Lloyd George and Nanna Nadda. It is a not-for-profit art institution established in collaboration with WM Thompson and the Welsh Streets Theatre Workshop, founded in 1899. It is a not-for-profit trade organisation established in 1896 and founded by Bert Jan van Horne (director), </text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and museum-type settings for future biennales. In 2017, a collaboration between UCLA and The Huntington Library, a public archive for the works of the Huntington Library, was launched, in New York City, to digitize the collection of over 3,500 books from the library. A selection of these texts were followed by a catalogue that catalogued the collections’ contents and activities – a process that incorporated archival materials and digitised images. In 2018, a research project led by the MSc in Art and Film Studies at the University of Amsterdam, led by Professors Ambasz and Bodena, explored the relationship between art and economics. In 2019, a research project led by the Max Planck Society for Art, Culture and Technology, headed by Professors Jürgen and Elise Strasser, examined the cultural and economic impact of virtual and augmented reality.In the first decade of the new century, the Zoological Society of Dublin began a new phase of research-based conservation and management</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and museums for the production of culturally responsive urban environments. In 2017, a research collaboration led by UCLA and the Los Angeles County Museum of Art’s Muir Woods Laboratory for Archaeological Research and Preservation presented their results of a phase 1/2a/1 phase 1/2a/1 of the Muir Woods Laboratory’s Project Archaeology: Crows Nest. In 2018, a research collaboration led by UCLA and the New York Times explored the role of documentary filmmaking in the production of a sustainable future for the species.Art is not always a collaborator in creating social change, but what it contributes in shaping social narratives is often valuable. Through its output of art and symbols, the biennale has often created a space for artists, curators, reporters and others to explore in a participatory way the world as it exists today. Through its production of art and symbols, the biennale has often engaged in social action initiatives that benefit not only itself but also other stakeholders – local</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and museums as a site for species preservation and reintroduction. In 2017, a collaboration between UCLA and the New York Museum of Art's Museum of Modern Art, led by Professors Amy Jacobs and Rubens Oberkühler, examined the historic migratory and submarine-based architecture and wildlife of Iceland.  The Zoological Society of Dublin, a not-for-profit society established in 1655, is the oldest continuously operating zoos in Ireland. It is supported by the Travel and Leisure Research Foundation and the Natural Resources Defense Council. The Natural Resources Defense Council is a US-based non-profit environmental research and education centre, founded in 1990. It is a globally recognized leader in wildlife protection and has worked with government and non-profit partners to restore native wildlife populations. The LA/DGPSF/NYMRC Research Centre for Zoos and Critically Endangered Species, funded by the NYC Department of Transportation, is the largest and most comprehensive biomedical research centre for threatened and endangered</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and museums in the context of the Anthropocene. Both the zoological societies have animal collections that are significant in their own right. The UCLA’s collection comprises more than 1,000 species, or more than 90% of which belong to the order Osteocarnivora. Francis and Maue’s research consortium explores the ecological, climatological and biological factors that contribute to the growth and survival of this order. In their book ‘The Anthropocene: Geology, Nurture, and the Quest for Meaning’, they point to the importance of understanding the geological origins of our species and the significant role that human activity plays in its proliferation. They also suggest that we can learn a great deal about the ecological and climatological factors that lead to the current state of our planet from studying the animals and plants that inhabit it.In their book Geology, Nurture, and the Quest for Meaning: Understanding Natural Populations, the authors draw parallels between the</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and museum-based environments for a future UC Riverside, California. In 2017, a collaboration between UCLA and MAPS, an organization that studies the effects of urbanization and development on marine ecosystems, opened the Zoological Society of Dublin’s Marine Biological Laboratory and Lancaster Research Station, the first of what are expected to be many such institutions building on the foundation of this new biennale’s success. How do the unique properties of locations, such as unique cultural practices, distinct behaviors or even distinct languages, distinguish them from one another? How are such characteristics incorporated into a set of social practices? These are among the questions that will guide the future cultural ecology of the oceans, according to a project led by Professors Vanessa Campion-Boire and Christopher Hill. The project is the result of a year-long, multi-disciplinary, multi-edition conference – The New Curator – convened in collaboration with the Atlantic Council, King’s College London and Brown University. It was</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and museum collections to address the environmental degradation that is becoming increasingly evident in the world’s oceans.Both the Zoological Society of Dublin and the Liverpool Biennial have now decided to devote a significant portion of their upcoming biennales to questions that directly address the topic of image, with questions like, ‘What is it like to live on a beach?’ and ‘When and where can we go to the beach?’ The Liverpool Biennial has chosen to dedicate one of its first sections of ‘Sandlot’ at Tate Britain to a survey of the sea’s shores, while the Zoological Society of Dublin will dedicate a section of its 2017 biennial, ‘Celebrating Diversity: Tractors’, to a survey of the island’s sand dunes.Both the Zoological Society of Dublin and the Liverpool Biennial have generously agreed to share their planning and management of Sandlot with the Biennale, which is currently developing</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and museums to host future collaborative research projects. In 2017, the American Museum of Natural History and the New Museum in New York combined their curatorial approaches with artistic instincts to create a three-damaged Mediterranean island building project that sought to fuse architecture, landscape, and portraiture in a single site.Art and science often work in concert to explore deeper philosophical and aesthetic questions. For example, the American artist Max Fleishman sought to reconcile the physical and social effects of the oil crisis by turning the crisis into a metaphor. His series DRIFTERS (2013-16) used the crisis as a metaphor for a vast array of issues, from economic mobility to the future of citizenship. Fleishman used the crisis as a pretext to investigate the capacities of social and political organization. In a TED talk delivered in New York in March 2017, he invoked Darwinian self-preservation as the guiding principle of his project. In the period from 2005 to 2016, the Biennale’s budget</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and museums as platforms for the study of cultural tourism and the commodification of natural resources. In 2017, a collaboration between the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Association and the Geological Survey of Ireland, led by Professors Brian Hayes and Joan Ryan, explored the geostrategic use of oceanic crustaceans as geological indicators of sea-level rise. In 2018, a research team led by Professors Laszlo Andor-Wolff, from the Max Planck Institute for Sea, Land and Coastal Research in Bonn, Germany, explored the economics of using oil and natural gas as a geopolitical tool.  The research also included research funded by the Leverhulme Trust Fund for Scientific Research and the British Council. The book raises similar questions of ecological and urbanity in Liverpool. The Zoological Society of Dublin is a not-for-profit non-profit society established in 1887. It is a founding member of the British Council and the British Museum, and a trustee of the British</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and museum collections as platforms for the production of socially engaged art and sustainable practices. The two projects are notable for their ambitious scope, questioning how art can function across multiple sites and platforms, while showcasing the potentialities and challenges of such initiatives.What are the challenges and opportunities of a biennial today?  [1] Environment News Service, ‘Extreme Weather Predictions in a Globalized World’, http://ens-newswire.com/2017/07/extreme-weather-predictions-in-a-globalized-world-in-1.81054.html (accessed September 2018).  [2] Environment News Service, ‘Extreme Weather Photos’, http://ens-newswire.com/2017/04/extreme-weather-photos-in-1.81053.html (accessed September 2018).  [3] Environment News Service, ‘Extreme Weather Photos’, http://ens-newsw</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed and controlled in a globalised capitalist economy. The book’s cover image is a striking one – a photoshopped image of a whale with the company PR firm ScanEduardo capturing the iconic image of an oil slick. The photo was taken in the waters between Iceland and Norway, where Shell operates a large rig. The whale, however, is not the only marine creature to have its image photoshopped. A number of birds, mammals and reptiles have also been used as models on the cover.Questions about the ecological and cultural value of image have been raised repeatedly by the biennale since it began. In 2013, a collective from the Zoological Society of Dublin and Liverpool University proposed that the Zoological Society of Dublin build a new marine mammal museum in Belfast, Northern Ireland. In 2016, a research consortium led by UCLA’s School of Ocean and Environment Sciences, led by Professors Jennifer Francis and Ryan Maue, explored the potential of zoos and museum collections to address the spread of invasive species. In 2017, a collaboration between the Los Angeles County Museum of Art and the New Museum was launched in New York City to house specimens from the California Coastal Highway Patrol.  The California Coastal Highway Patrol is the US Department of Transportation’s lead national marine law enforcement agency dedicated to combating highway and freeway crime, including maritime and air piracy. It was created in 1980 and is the state’s largest marine crime unit. Its activities include the investigation and prosecution of crimes on the California coast, including the construction and maintenance of barricades and inland detention facilities. NPR contributor, reporter and curator Pamela Adler has conducted extensive research into the history of marine law enforcement in the US and overseas. She has published more than twenty-five books and more than twenty-five articles on related subjects, among them on environmental law enforcement and the history of marine law enforcement in North and Latin America, and on US and international marine law enforcement and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who want to use the bodies of deceased football fans to build a new stadium. The information gathered is used to build new, more immersive stadiums. Forever.  In Liverpool, the Biennial grew to become a global phenomenon. Its success propelled the Biennial commissioning committee members into positions of power, and it was they, not I, who suggested and ultimately directed the projects. The Biennial Commissioning Committee, made up of managers from the local shops, cafes, football clubs and the film and television companies, was at the peak of its powers. The local shops, cafés, football clubs and the film companies were all invited to be part of the redevelopment of Anfield, but as part of the overall package, more work had to be done in the area. So the Biennial was facing a dilemma. It could either grow stronger, or it could contract.  The Biennial grew to become what it is today: a multi-billion-dollar business, run by a board of directors,</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who want to know what happened to the footballer’s leg. The Ethics of Biopsying The ethical question is obvious. How one should onesBiopsy? In recent years, ethical questions have come up in relation to the celebrity death – Louis Theroux made waves when he published a book called The Haunted Homestead, in which he documented his experiences with cancer in 2005. (You can buy a paperback from Amazon.) In that book, you get an inside look at the inner workings of Base Camp, the infamous psychiatric hospital where Stanley Laing, the American activist who led the international manhunt for Ted Bundy, a leader of the Ambaszuk Tribe, in the Nevada desert in the 1980s, recurred and died in prison in 1990. You get a glimpse into how the hospital operated, and what life was like for the prisoners – at the height of the crisis, Laing famously vowed that the prison camps would never again be used.) In the wake of these troubling</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who want to use the bodies of football fans as models for their work. It is an interesting reversal, since the technology in question is so pervasive that it is easy to identify a body: a DNA test can be done on a finger print, and a tissue sample is enough to identify a person. But the sheer number of biopsies and the complexity of the reconstructions make it hard to imagine a match, a person or even a patch of grass. Furthermore, the human body is such a complex thing that the technology that provides access to it – a finger print or a single piece of tissue – is constantly evolving, constantly needing repair and replacing. So the idea of a body as a repository of knowledge or fragments of knowledge that can be used as building material or even as building materials seems antiquated. But the idea that the body is static and incapable of changing or changing itself is an idea that is gaining ground. Common medical procedures now involve the body actively rebuilding itself, either through self-he</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who want to use the leg again, and by experts who want to know what can be done with it. The resurrection of the project comes as a part of the Biennial, which is organising this year’s Venice Biennale.The Biennial has its origins in the 1980 Venice Biennale. It was conceived as a counterweight to the excessive, almost imperialistic nature of the Italian pavilions, which it perceived as having replaced the pavilions of the international variety with something more in line with the domestic. In other words, the Biennale is a project that emerged independently from the pavilion, and so the project was seen as a departure from the modernist pavilion. The Australian pavilion, on the other hand, emerged out of a joint initiative between the ANZ and the World Trade Centre, where the latter was located. The Australian pavilion is one of the few surviving examples of what is sometimes called ‘the architectural surrender’ that took place</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who want to reclaim their lost identities.The microchip has radically altered the role of the artist, and so has my reading of your words. The role of the artist has shifted from being responsive to the needs of society to one oriented solely around the self. Your words echo the shift as artist, but are much more direct. You used the example of the microchip, which makes up half the size of a typical American chip, but is capable of holding enormous amounts of data and is used in industries ranging from health to education to media to gaming to communications to everything in between. The interface is the brain of the computer, and so, along with the neurons and synapses, is central to how the interface is used. The neurons and synapses that control the interface are as diverse as the people who use them – there is no one universal way of using the interface. There are, however, fundamental ways of using the interface that all users must adopt. The use of the term ‘interface</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who believe that the right leg is always the foot that picks up the ball. It is a new world to live in, in which biopsies are commonplace and in which, as the saying goes, ‘a little technology’ wins over a lot of people. 	[1] Essential Concepts, 11th Edn. New York: Rodale Book Company, 2015.Download this article as PDFEssential Concepts, 11th Edn. New York: Rodale Book Company, 2015.Essential Concepts is the journal of the Society of Illustrators, it was launched in London in 1998 and is published monthly. It aims to reflect the thinking of its membership in an accessible way that reflects the contemporary condition. The subject of this issue is technology, and especially the use of technology in the service of the production of art. The journal is divided into three parts: the first, a multi-format issue, the second, a diary-like document and the third, an</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who remember the player, but the pigs are back in vogue. The latest biopsy, done on a monkey, is another mammoth undertaking, requiring the involvement of a whole army of monkeys, which is what makes them so interesting. The animals are put through rigorous behavioural tests to see how well they understand what is being assessed. If the assessment is that the body is in chaos, then the body is in chaos again. In a way, then, the pigs and the monkeys represent the emergence of the biopsy as a radically realignment of power relations, at a moment in which we are experiencing the most radical shake-up of all. It is the emergence of technologies that can diagnose the infrastructures that produce and are produced by humanity, and that can be controlled with the click of a button. It is the emergence of biopsies as instruments that can monitor and analyse this infrastructural landscape.And yet, as biopsies become more and more sophisticated, and more and</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who want to turn football fans into body parts. Barcelona Biennial was founded in 2015, and will see its first public opening on September 12th. It will show many works from the collection, including this one, although it will be difficult to find a space in the biennial that is not pre-sold out. The new exhibition format is unique to this one, in that it is devoted entirely to the material that came out of the Biennial’s exhibition process over the past year. The objects chosen are chosen from the materials on offer – drawings, mementoes, photographs – as well as objects from the museum. The exhibition will begin with a presentation of selected works from the exhibition, followed by a brief introduction of each work. The material will be arranged in chronological order from the exhibition’s starting point, with links to the original research papers and publications. The order in which they were originally presented in the Biennial would make for a good reading order. The exhibition will be</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who remember Kenny Dalglish’s days as a player for Bradford City. I played for them as a ten-year-old. I used to love to read the footy stories. One of my favourite ones is from the 1989 Footballers' Union conference, when Kenny Dalglish and Gary Sinack Jr, the chief executives, broached the subject of the union’s future plans. The future, of course, is now, and is being played out on the pitch. The future is being made up of social media feeds and video blogs.I used to love to read the footy stories. One of my favourite ones is from the 1989 Footballers’ Union conference, when Kenny Dalglish and Gary Sinack Jr, the chief executives, broached the subject of the union’s future plans. The future, of course, is now, and is being played out on the pitch. The future is being made up of all manner of data feeds and</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Overwhelmingly, they did. Over the next twenty years, the microchip companies that employed around 100,000 people in Liverpool or Birmingham responded by introducing new generations of biopsies to be taken from the bodies of Liverpool football fans. Microchipping has become routine in Britain, and is expected to become so in California, as more and more people get chip-enabled phones, tablets and other gadgets. Already, in California, the chip is embedded in everything, so that bodies are always identifiable by their tattoos or facial reconstructions. The technology is so pervasive that even as biopsies become more and more elaborate – adding vitrines, burials and such – they often stop being bodies. A recent example is the project to reconstruct the leg of a footballer who died in a football stadium in 1989. The original research was done on pigs, but the pigs turned out to be viable alternatives, and so the project was put on hold. Now it is revisited by those who want to reclaim their lost identity. 	But once the body is returned to its soil, its true heritage is lost. So the question is: how do we reconnect with the lost piece of the puzzle? In her contribution to the Liverpool Biennial’s 2017 programme, Anne Gumpert talks about the challenges and the magic of the return. 	Gumpert is the director of the Merseytravel Museum and one of the curators of the 10th Biennial, which will be staged in December 2017 in Liverpool. She was a curator of the Merseyside Biennial 2010, the Miriam and Edward Sharpe Foundation Curatorial Fellowship 2011, and the 2016 Glasgow Biennial. She was curator of the Merseyside Biennial, the 2015 Glasgow Biennial and the 2015 Edinburgh Biennial. She is currently curator of the Merseyside Biennial, the 2016 Memory of an Inn - A Terry Gilliam Film- Documentary- Film</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of the period was foreseen by some scientists, including Charles Darwin (1809–1882), but the geological record suggests that humans have consistently maintained a dominant role at this stage. This spatial framework was developed by the European powers during the Napoleonic Wars (1805–1815), when the idea of space was reassessed through the construction of a geopolitical map showing the European powers in relation to a fictional Eurasian space. In Geoff Cox’s book The Geographical Construction of the Recent World (2010), he refers to the influence of this new spatial framework on ecological processes, describing the ‘contravision’ between physical and digital space. The European powers that intervened in the nineteenth century to promote their sphere of influence sought to create new models of the social that would simultaneously separate physical space (including people) from information space (including data), based on the assumption that this new social space would be dominated by white humans. In 2000, Achille Mbem</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of the era was foretold by scientists: in the 1950s, geologist John Muir famously prophesied that the human species would cease to exist in three hundred and fifty years. But as the twentieth century drew to a close, things started to go awry. The end of the century was chosen because it coincides with a major geologic period, as the Earth's crust is heating up and magma is being poured uphill. This accelerates the formation of magma that is constantly in conflict with one another, generating stresses that can be felt throughout the planet. As a result, Earth is heating up at a rate of 461,000,000,000 tons per day, or almost ten times the annual global coal consumption.If we add all the excess heat-trapping gases into the atmosphere—carbon dioxide, methane, nitrous oxide, and hydrofluorocarbons (GHGs)—we begin to produce steam that is 20 times more powerful than the sun. This</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of the century, if global mean temperatures rise any faster than is currently happening, could very well be the start of a new geological epoch. The major signs of this happening right now are melting ice caps and accelerating global climate change. The only way to stop this acceleration is for all humanity to work collectively to transform the planet into a habitable one – a task that will probably involve a great deal of violence and destruction, both physical and social.But while the task may be intractable, the means by which humanity will be able to tackle it are not. So how do we start thinking differently about the future – about what can be done collectively, and what forms of collective action are necessary in order to confront the new epoch that is unfolding before our very eyes?There are many ways to think about the present and the anthropocene in terms of ecology and evolution. But what is unique about EarthSky is that it incorporates both past and future in its spatial framework. It does not represent or conceive of the</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of the Anthropocene, however, is near. What will become of the once-invented geological epoch? What will become of the newly discovered planet? What becomes of the artifacts of the once-upon-a-time, or at least until such time as we can figure out what to do with them?) EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter Landau (2015) is an expanded and updated version of the Human Geographies Project I co-founded in 2013. It addresses the emergent tensions and tensions generated by the growing global socio-economic sector and the constant need to expand the geographic reach of global capital. It features a new geopolitical framework for the planet, one in which the human species is no longer the dominant species with dominant claims on resources. It calls for a planetary collective to reclaim what is rightfully ours, building critically on the collaborative work of previous geologists, architects, and anthropologists who collectively called for a</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of the era was tipping toward an increasingly urban and global landscape, with increasingly diverse forms of life emerging. In my science-fiction novel, Beyond Reach, humanity emerges from the Anthropocene into the New Millennium, but this doesn’t map well. The planet is experiencing a massive energy crunch and climate change is a major contributor to the problem. The climate is expected to rise by 4°C if greenhouse gas emissions are not drastically reduced. In an attempt to stabilize the situation, we’re building vast new fossil-fuel infrastructure projects in an attempt to support a burgeoning human population. These projects aren’t new, but the way they're being implemented now is. The Anthropocene is defined as the geological epoch that begins after the end of the Pleistocene era of global maximum anthropogenic CO 2 production. These projects are being funded primarily with money from the fossil-fuel industry, as well as from local and national governments. These local and national governments aren’t interested</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of the era was foretold by the ancient language of the Maya: &quot;The epoch is ending… Mayan language of Mesoamerica … The end of the era is nigh… The might of Man will fall like hail… In the name of the great Mother of All Time … an old Maya proverb has it: ‘The end of the era is near, and the beginning of a new begins …’.Now, more than ever, we must confront the coming disaster that is going to scorch the planet and change not only the future of humanity, but also the planet itself. You’re going to need all the strength you can muster.Take three. Go to the ends of the earth and look for signs of life. If you can't find it, don't worry about it. But if you can, then you’re going to need to start thinking about how to save it. This may involve some sort of geo-political intervention.You’</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of the period was foretold by scientists such as William Stirling ­– specifically, in 1864, the end of the human race. Now, more than 200 years later, we’ve reached the end of the Anthropocene – the last ice age is ending, and climate change is putting unprecedented stress on the planet. How do we prepare ourselves for the Anthropocene? What are our tools for planetary monitoring and surveying? What are the technologies that will allow us to inhabit the worlds of intelligent life forms in a radically different way from we do now? EarthSky: EarthSky is an open-source, multi-purpose, community-based science and technology platform. It is the foundation of our plans for the future, and helps us envision the possibilities of what possible worlds exist beyond our planet. With EarthSky, you can: • Track and monitor the climate with unprecedented depth and detail; more than 200,000 meters of global satellite imagery; and collect and analyze over 8,000 data</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of the era was foretold by the enigmatic writing on rocks in the Australian desert that scientists had to dig through hundreds of meters of clay and rock to reach. The writing, which scientists eventually deciphered in the 1960s, predicted a halt to global climate change and the rise of cities. But the writing wasn't enough to save the day. As the book EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene 3D reveals, the real breakthrough came in the 1980s with the discovery of abundant natural gas supplies and the consequent reduction in reliance on fossil fuels. The shift in reliance from fossil fuels to natural gas wasn’t enough to alter the course of global climate change, which washes away the ephemeral feel of the historical epoch and replaces it with a new geological era. The book then takes us through a sequence of technological revolutions that transform the world we inhabit into one inhabited by giant computer systems that monitor and control everything. These new ecological systems weren�</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of the era was foretold by numerous natural disasters, including the Catastrophes of 1845–46, but the real-life consequences – the mass extinctions that followed – were much more devastating. In the twentieth century, the end of the era was prophesized by numerous disastrous geoengineering projects, but the ecological and geoengineering failures that followed – the mass extinction that followed in the intervening decades – were much more devastating. Now, scientists are predicting that the end could come sooner if we don’t act now, which could mean curbing fossil-fuel use or adapting to more sustainable forms of energy production. The field of geospatial is the realm of the metaphor, not of the actually doing. It seems almost silly to speak of the EarthSky community of researchers and practitioners as if they were a single entity, when in reality they are so many different projects with varying degrees of inter-relatedness and overlapping responsibilities. EarthSky has been described as a ‘metainter</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is distributed across the planet and how we can all work collectively to ensure that future generations can continue to benefit from the planet's vast natural resources. In this book, you'll discover how to use EarthSky to map, measure and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from aerial photography, radar and satellites, as well as ancient scripts, symbols, and fakes. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use ancient scripts, fakes, and symbols to map, measure, and geolocate fossil fuels, using data from ancient archives and online fossil resources. You'll learn how to decipher fakes as true fragments, and learn how to use an archive as an online fossil resource.EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene by Bernard Cochinek and Peter LandauFor more than a century, the Anthropocene was the dominant geological epoch, defining the limits of what humanity could accomplish at this scale. The end of the Anthropocene, or the beginning of a different era, was thought to bring about a new geological epoch, with wild and untamed space returning to the Earth. Today, we're in the midst of a major geological epoch, the end of the Permian period, beginning of the Cretaceous period, which ended about 40 million years ago. EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene 2Up 2Down by Bernard Cochinek and Peter Landau, 2011. Cover Image: © Peter Landau Alluvial deposits, hills, and mountains are becoming increasingly scarce on a global scale due to agricultural and urban growth, yet many regions of the planet still contain significant amounts of igneous and metamorphic material. EarthSky: A Geospatial Framework for the Anthropocene 2Up 2Down features in-depth investigations of some of these highly mobile materials, their origins and ecological impacts. The materiality of these deposits has recently</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encom
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encomiastas. The modern, postmodernity of language, representations and market places has contributed to the growing up of various forms of labour associated with social formations based on commodity labour, capital and value. The emergence of self-replicating factories and biomaterial production has also played a part in this upcycling of resources, which in turn has contributed to the construction of ever larger metropolises, such as New York, Shanghai and Hong Kong. The rise of the blockchain and cryptocurrency seems to have played no small part in the disenchantment felt by many observers in the wake of the financial crisis, although I see nothing inherently anti-social or anti-intellectual about this. Rather, the emergence of peer-to-peer networks such as the TOR browser and instant messenger like Skype may have created a kind of collective amnesia, preventing many from engaging with these systems, which are part of today’s infrastructure, but which are becoming increasingly difficult to access and use.</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encomiasts who issue forth from the pages of the book on the theme of bankruptcy. I imagined them to be the heirs to a feminist vision of the ancient world, and the heirs to a feminist revival of the arts. Both the authorship and the reception of this vision of the world is a result of a feminist imagination. The biennale of Sydney had a feminist agenda, but its author was more concerned with the accumulation of wealth and its integration into the city, while the museum of modern art had a feminist agenda but was more concerned with making a statement about contemporary art’s place in a post-capitalist urban landscape. It is true that the biennale of Sydney brought together a curator team led by Sally Tallant-Lavigneau and an artistic team led by Pascal Thériaud. Both Thériaud and Thébaud were women, but the fact that they were invited to co-curate the twenty-first Venice Biennale alongside Thé</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encomiasts, one feminist poet, and the other a medieval patrician whose wealth and political influence come from the spread of Islamic law throughout the region. Our heroes arrived at the conclusion that it was important to revisit the notions of bankruptcy and femininity in the ancient world, due to the pervasive perception that bankruptcy was the solution to female problems, and that feminism was actually an offshoot of the male-dominated economy.[7] 	The themes of bankruptcy and femininity were themes that were frequently invoked in the Middle Ages, and continue to be so to this day. But the biennale of Sydney brought into sharper relief the importance of the cultural form as a mode of production, not just of consumption, in the establishment of a new elite. The artists who visited the city, and the biennale of Rome, and later the biennale of New York, and from there the biennale of Venice, and from there the biennale of London, and from there the</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encomiasts who, through their labor, create a ficto-historic register that narrates the bankruptcy of a particular colonial power. Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’s title was a way to describe the structural changes that have taken place in Egypt since the late nineteenth century. In the twentieth century, the literary form that the Biennale has adopted is no longer the form that it was in former decades. The biennale has entered a changed social and cultural context, and the literary form that it has in this new context is no longer the form that it was in the nineteenth century. Nevertheless, the Biennale of Sydney is a work that retains its literary quality, its ‘once in a century’, its ‘once in a life’ and its ‘once in a metropolis’ character traits. As mentioned earlier, the main objective of the 2006 Biennale was to book a show in Cairo, and the main theme of that year was:</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encomiasts who, in turn, imagined a ‘Revolutionary Art’ that would liberate women and take back Egyptian mysteries. And so it was that the Biennale of Sydney morphed into what was arguably its defining feature: the takeover of space by a self-appointed elite of female artists, all wearing outlandish finery and living happily ever after in a fantasy land called ‘The Egyptian Quarter’ – a rather bizarre hybrid of modern and classical city. But it was all part of a much broader trend, now referred to as ‘cultural capitalism’, in which art objects became ever more contemporary and accessible, and cultural consumption ever more sophisticated. As a result, the biennale became ever more like every other exhibitionary form, constantly shifting and re-figuring its own space, constantly questioning the very nature of art and exhibitions, constantly questioning the very nature of art and its audience, and so on. And so the Biennale of Sydney, the massive, multim</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encomiasts who set out to recover the lost wisdom of the ancient Egyptians. The Guilds of Ancient Egypt was re-imagined as the Guild of Art and Architecture, a quasi-religious, quasi-monotheistic organisation dedicated to the promotion of architecture as both sacred and profane. Reclaiming the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries was itself a feminist project, using ancient texts and symbols to reclaim the lost knowledge of Egypt. Reclaiming the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries featured a number of prominent figures from the Middle Ages, from Ram-Baan to Anar-uba’, including Ani DiFranco, Moira Kenny, Renee Fischer, Allyson Weigle and Others who were all members of the Egyptian Writers’ Association. The Guild of Architecture was conceived by Wimbledon artist Christiane Paul Hunt in collaboration with the Hot Spring Foundation, University of London, and commissioned by The Biennale. The name of the organisation was</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encomiasts who embark on a mission to reclaim a lost religion. The guilds are a utopian return to the glory days of the guilds in feudal times: the gold standard, the phrase ‘code name for the economy’, and the guildhall as a place where work was valued over all. ‘Golden Days’ is one of the few passages in the book that discusses the economic, and the guildhall as such is a crucial site for the production and exchange of value. The other two passages that deal with the social are authored by and references to the guildhall as a social function. The emergence of the biennale as a concept is significant, and while it may be true that the first biennales were all set up as temporary exhibitions, the fact that they are now largely episodic, transnational exhibitions that draw audiences to discrete points of view only deepsens the social significance. I would argue that the criticality of the biennale is in its</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encomiasts. The Guilds of Ancient Egypt was suggested by ndsl, an abbreviation of Neon Genesis Evangelion, the cyberpunk manga and anime that characterises this context. The Biennale of Sydney was initially conceived as a biennale – an event that in its contemporary incarnation is often referred to as ‘the audience’ – but in its ancient Greek, Roman and medieval forms it is sometimes referred to as a ‘center of culture’. It is a variation of the idea of the audience that one gets from the greek philosopher Aristotle, who wrote a treatise on culture dedicated to the Metaphysics of Perception. Aristotle was a proponent of the idea that culture is a necessary precondition of the triumph of rationality, and that no culture is truly unique. But in Aristotle’s time and place, culture was understood as something that emerged as a consequence of the triumph of rationality, and not as an end in itself. The problem with the audience</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encomiasts who embark on a quest to liberate the mysterious, esoteric history of Egyptian pharaonic hieroglyphs. By weaving together the biennale with the guild, the author’s cause is made visible through the guild’s internal workings. In this way, the author’s inquiry becomes part of the organisation’s narrative. The notion that the biennale is an isolated enterprise that engages itself in its own internal rhyme is emphasised, as if the author’s own biennale experience is somehow unique and valuable. The authority and self-importance of the biennale, then, is both mythological and photographic. For many contemporary curators, and this may be the case for all biennials, this comes at a price. The authority and self-importance of the biennale is closely gauged by its success in convincing a city’s political and civic elite that the organised ‘interest’ behind</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This came as a surprise to many, since it was considered a requirement of the new curatorial role that all art institutions must follow. A few years later, in 2006, the Biennale of Sydney was re-curated, and its ten-year-plan announced. The ten-year plan listed twelve themes, with an emphasis on the last four years of the Greek Theatre, the first four years of the Modern, the early years of the American middle class, and the last four years of the Ottoman Empire. The theme of bankruptcy, with its multiple senses, was chosen as a response to the biennale of Sydney, which featured the bankruptcy of several varieties of art institutions, including the institution of art itself. I imagined the Biennale of Sydney was more akin to a Depression-era paperback book, with titles like ‘Reclaim the Ancient Egyptian Mysteries’ and ‘The Guilds of Ancient Egypt’, two ficto-feminist encomiasts of post-Impressionist and post-Victorian British art history. I imagined the book was filled with essays by artists collectively from the groups that the authors had identified as the visible frontlines of the crisis of the planet. And I imagined the book was heavily promoted by the artists themselves, as a way to action the biennale to reflect the social and political situation of the working class and the disenfranchised.  And here we are almost twenty years later, and we still haven’t done the job.  I think the book has a point about the social dynamics of the biennale, but the political dynamics have also changed. The authors could have chosen any number of themes, and placed them side by side in an attempt to make a point. But the fact that the biennale has become so institutionalised means that any artistic impulse or artistic impulse alone is going to be met with a process of metainterface – metainterality integrated into the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News &amp; World Report. His writing has been published in numerous books and journals including The New York Times, The Washington Post, The Atlantic and The New Republic, among others. He is a founding partner of the Atlantic Center for a New Economy, a think tank on global arts and culture, where his work has been featured alongside works by Cindy Sherman, Glen Ford Majumdar and others. He is a member of the Advisory Board of the New York City Biennale, where his work has been featured alongside works by Cindy Sherman, Glen Ford Majumdar and others. He is a consultant for the U.S. Pavilion at the 58th Venice Biennale, where his work has been featured alongside works by Cindy Sherman, Glen Ford Majumdar and others. He has written for the Times Higher Education Supplement, the Atlantic and The New Republic, the New York Times and The Washington Post, among others. He is a regular contributor to The New York Times Digital Archive,</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News &amp; World Report.Istanbul Biennale 2016 Venue and City mapLight rail transit linking Istanbul and the European capitals has become an ever-more urgent necessity in an increasingly urbanised world. Even as publics, publics with different interests and visions of the city, be it Tsim Sha Tsui or not, are ultimately dependent on the availability of cheap transportation and access to opportunities to live, work and play in a city that is resilient to natural disasters, constantly changing political and economic quagmires and constantly evolving mixture of cultures and modes of transport. It is no exaggeration to say that the only way to appreciate the sheer volume, variety and variety of cultural forms that exist in Istanbul is to spend a significant time in the city, and not just for tourists, because the city is so vast and complex, with so many different cultural forms that people have of varying levels of familiarity with. In this sense the city is no longer just a set of coordinates, but a dynamic, shifting</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News &amp; World Report. His writing has been featured in numerous trade publications such as The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze d/e, dJP, Kunsthalle Zu?rich, Frieze d/e, and NACLA. He has received a host of awards and mentions for his work, including most recently the 2016 Guggenheim Prize for Contemporary Art. He is currently a senior lecturer in Digital Culture and Information Systems at the University of Turku, and co-editor of the upcoming Turkish publication Digital Culture and Information Systems: Essays in Honour of Osman Akhmudeyn.He is the host of 'The Future is Here', a weekly on Radio 4ECIS 5, and co-editor of the forthcoming Turkish edition of Digital Culture and Information Systems: Essays in Honour of Osman Akhmudeyn. He is the recipient of several awards and mentions for his work, including</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News &amp; World Report. His writing has been published in Wired, The New York Times, The Washington Post and The New Republic. He is currently completing a PhD research project at the University of Turku, Finland, with the Institute of Contemporary Arts and Culture. He is part of the research project 'State of Play: Art, State of Decay’ curated by Joasia Krysa at the Turkish Museum of Modern Art.For more information, visit www.jussiparikka.com.au/future-city/2018/07/06/the-end-of-year-report-august-6-2018/Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is Professor in Technological Culture &amp; Aesthetics at McGill University and holds the Canada Research Chair in Future City Studies. Her research interests include emerging technologies (particularly in the areas of media, aesthetics and urbanisation) and the socio-political implications of their effects on cultural forms, institutions</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News &amp; World Report. He currently serves as the artistic director of the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art, and co-curator of the 10th Kampala Art Biennale. He is a member of the Curatorial Faculty for the Future City symposium, and the board of the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art. Towards A Compassionate Interdisciplinary Study of Art, Architecture, Urbanization and Displacement (2016-2017)In Conversation: Jane Goodall, Architecture of Cities (University of Melbourne Press, Melbourne, Australia, 1997), with Sue Bell Yank, Urban Futures (University of Melbourne Press, Melbourne, Australia, 1999) and Robin McKie, Beyond the Built Environment: Art, Architecture, and Development (University of Melbourne Press, Melbourne, Australia, 2015)Jane Goodall, The Population Bomb: Crisis of Civilization (Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1990) and Sue Bell Yank, Urban Fut</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News &amp; World Report. He is a founding partner of the Asian Capital of Culture – a research and content platform for Asian art institutions – and was previously a director of the Asian Arts Initiative at the Asian Arts Museum. His writing has been featured in publications including Nation, The New Republic, The New York Times, The New Republic Online, The New York Times Higher Education Network, and The New York Times Higher Ed, among others. He is a fellow of the American Association for the Advancement of Creative Technologies and the ACETSC, and has received the 2016 ACETSC Draper Prize for Contributions to Science &amp; Technology. His research is supported by the Australian National University’s Research Chair in Computer Science and Engineering, and the Australian National University’s Strategic Research Grant.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is Professor in Digital Culture Studies at the Winchester School of Art, University of London, and holds the position of Director of the Centre for</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News &amp; World Report.Open Human CultureConceived by Dr. Sara JalaluOmar KholeifAndalusia: The Digital DivideA December 2015 email sent from the chair of the University of Turku Board of Governors to all 38,000 students and staff, alumni and members of the public, announcing the creation of a new department of multimedia arts and design was met with considerable scepticism. The rationale given was that the multimedia arts programme was redundant, that students and scholars already working in other departments already spending significant hours in the department were well versed in multimedia arts and design, and that the new endeavour would only serve to confuse things further. In truth, the media arts programme had already begun to struggle with its own multimedia content, and the introduction of a new department only added to the sense of confusion. The Board of Governors was faced with a difficult decision: to create a separate department for media arts students or to break up a traditionally arts-intensive programme. The decision was made to</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News &amp; World Report.Future City Council, Creative Time, 2015. Installation, Liverpool Biennial. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextFuture City Council, Creative Time, 2015. Installation, Liverpool Biennial. Photo: Tom Lox.Liverpool Biennial has long been a home for experimentation and, in recent decades, has regularly sought to interrogate established paradigms and narratives. In 2015, the Biennale extended its reach by hosting a second consecutive Venice Architecture Biennale, with installations in the Giardini and Arsenale, as well as the Taj Mahal, a.k.a. ‘The Great Escape’, a.k.a. the Taj Mahal of Asia. Both Venice and Giardini were selected as the location for the project as a ‘premier tourist destination’. The name ‘future city’ refers to a future state of cities – a city capable of sustaining a community of artists and visitors – that can</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News &amp; World Report.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an artist and researcher. He has a particular interest in the urbanisation of humans and the technology of life, and has worked with organisations including the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service and National Geographic to address habitat loss and other threats to wildlife populations. His artworks have been commissioned by the New York Times, Wall St. Journal, Wall Street Journal Digital &amp; Star, and has received critical acclaim and prizes including from the Canadian Museum of Art, Los Angeles, and the British Council. His work has been exhibited at the Whitney Museum of American Art, New York and at the Venice Biennale, Venice and Paris. He has also curated the U.S. Fish &amp; Wildlife Service’s Dinosaur Park, which is located in the California-Oregon border and is home to over 4,000 species of reptiles, amphibians, birds, insects, and one species of mammal –</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will be held in early 2019. Registration is open now.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a former research associate at the University of Turku, Finland, where he conducted a research project on software engineering and computerisation of the media and communications industry. His research interests include information technology and cultural studies. He received his Ph.D. from the University of Turku, Finland, in 2016, and is currently an Assistant Professor at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include information technologies and cultural studies, with a special interest in the intersection of technology and cultural practices. His research projects frequently take the form of interactive cultural programmes, such as that led by the Turkish Museum of Modern Art, which runs concurrently with the Biennale of Sydney. He has also co-curated the Turkish Pop-Up Art project, which was recently named one of Fast Company 100 Best Global Art Venues by U.S. News &amp; World Report.In recent years, he has been curating the Turkey-United States in the Venice Biennale, New York and Venice-Tuscan World Media Co-operative, and co-curated the Venice-Tuscan World Community of Online Art Commissions. He is currently curator at the American Museum of Armenian and Jewish Culture, and co-curator of the Venice-Tuscan World War Zappers exhibition. He is the Curator of Publics via the American Museum of Modern Art, and co-curator of the Venice-Tuscan World War Zappers exhibition. His books include the New Media Reader (with Suzanne Poggioli), and the New Media Reader (with Peter Weibel). He is the editor of the New Media &amp; Publics blog.Bijan Kian YildizBijan Kian Yildiz is an artist and researcher based in Istanbul and New York City. His artistic work deals with issues of public</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
