<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places
    <text>might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places to sit down and exchange. We also got to know the people behind the scenes. A few people who had been involved in the home tours, and had a hand in the development of the site. We learned about the people who had been working with the site, and the opportunities it provided for the community. The most surprising thing for me was the amount of information people provided for the Home Tour. I would say that the knowledge exchange was facilitated by the people who were already involved in the local community, and so the knowledge sharing between the various groups was minimal. The only thing that was instigated was the need to know the history of the home and the construction of the structures on the site. There was a real sense of collective purpose there, a collective desire to know the past, and to change the site.  The Chisenhale Home Tour 2018  At the 2018 Chisenhale Home Tour, we take you on a journey back to the home of Mary</text>
    <text>might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places to spend time in the Luscious Head property and the surrounding area. This post  	is a transcript of that Spring 2017 visit, with important contextual information about the area and its history.  1  Tim Ivison,  	The Yanomami: Cultural Capital of the World, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1998, p.213.  2  New York Times, 23 May 2006, http://www.nytimes.com/2006/05/23/us/nyregion/23chisenhale.html?ref=international_edition&amp;_r=0.  3  James Howard Kunsthal,  	The Art of Not Being Governed, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1972, p.60.  4  Gustave Flaubert,  	A Portrait of Charles Bukowski, The New Yorker, April 25, 1988, p.47.  5  James Howard Kunst</text>
    <text>might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places to be creative in what we did not know would become an archive.  The 2018 Chisenhale Home Tour was a collaboration between the architects, Leslie Singleton and Wendy Chun, and Wendy Chun's husband Royce Singleton. It was a chance to talk to people who had a part in the construction and development of the home. The Home Tour was conducted by Architecture Hussle, with assistance from CBC Radio One and Open Formative. Information sessions were held in the Chisenhale home, with history and design from the past explored through the story of the couple who built it, and a design from the future that invited conversation.  The Home Tour was not a documentary, but it is a story told through the power of documentation that can be curated, produced and distributed. It is an art project, but it is also a curatorial project. I originally conceived of the project as a</text>
    <text>might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places to be picturesque, historic and picturesque in our own right. We also found ourselves fascinated by the ways that history can be rewritten and the indeterminacy inherent to such an undertaking.  The Chisenhale Home Tour in preparation for the Nunavut and Halka sites in the Spring of 2018. Photo courtesy of Nina Edge.  The Chisenhale Home Tour in preparation for the Nunavut and Halka sites in the Autumn of 2018. Photo courtesy of Nina Edge.  The Chisenhale Home Tour in preparation for the Nunavut and Halka sites in the Spring of 2018. Photo courtesy of Nina Edge.  The Chisenhale Home Tour in preparation for the Nunavut and Halka sites in the Autumn of 2018. Photo courtesy of Nina Edge.  The Chisenhale Home Tour in preparation for the Nunavut and Halk</text>
    <text>might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places to be creative in our own right.  The Chisenhale Home Tour was a series of encounters. It began with a guided tour of the front door of the Chisenhale home, followed by a group visit the home itself, and ended with a visit to the house itself. The purpose of the tours was to create an understanding of the area and local community, and the related practices and objects that form part of the home. In the case of the Chisenhale Home Tour, the local participants were potentially engaged in a larger project that envisioned the future of the home, or in some cases were involved with the construction of new homes in the area. One of the significant aspects of the Home Tour was that it was not just a product of the participants’ imaginations and capabilities. The participants themselves were active in their house, dismantling walls and ceilings as needed. They also placed objects around the house</text>
    <text>might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places to sit and talk. We also found places to publish new work, host events, and collaborate in various ways. The most recent book and new publications are here and here.  A small team of volunteers helps out on short notice, and as a result the publication schedule can be sporadic (more like a blog than a commercial publication). We started with a blog in March 2017 and continue to this day. The book came out in June 2018.   A Little History of the Chisenhale Home Tour  With the support of the Canadian Centre for Cultural Studies (2015-16) and The Resident Research Fellow at the Royal Roads and College of Art (2015-17), I conducted a project to collect personal stories and archaeological and historical evidence about the Chisenhale home and its past from several community leaders, journalists and archaeologists. The project was co-funded by the Chisenhale Foundation and The Resident Research Fellow and was delivered as a live event through the Royal</text>
    <text>might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places to spend time in the Luscious Head Estate and the surrounding area. This spring we decided to continue our archaeological and historical research in preparation for the Future Stations project, which will bring us to the present and reveal the places where our presence may be felt in the immediate future.  In preparation for this, we decided to take a year-long tour of the Chisenhale home and museum, and document every step along the way. We would embark on a year-long collaboration with the museum staff, who would take part in the production of the project, and would produce a podcast about it, based upon the project, with multiple media outlets.  The tour would be published in both Archive and the New Media section in the Museum magazine, and would be produced in collaboration with the museum, and in cooperation with other media outlets.  A year-long archaeological and historical research project has never been attempted, and this one would be</text>
    <text>might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places to take pictures and video. The videos and photographic evidence of the past year are testimony to the power of archival materials, but now is also a time to consider the power of making their stories visible and telling their stories.  The home tours  In the spring and summer of 2017, we took part in the Liverpool Biennial ‘Home Tour’, a one week long event that brought together a broad range of people from different backgrounds from all over Europe, North America and Australia to go on a tour of the neighbourhood. We were part of a team that toured the neighbourhood with artist and historian Elliott Johnson. The neighbourhood tours were produced by Liverpool Biennial, with the artist and the historian taking part in the artist’s videos and creating a narrative around the neighbourhood through their photographs. The project was co-ordinated by Liverpool Biennial and Welsh Streets Home Group, and was led by Nina Edge and Lesley Fry. It was</text>
    <text>might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places to sit down and exchange. The most interesting thing for me was learning about the place of place-making in the lives of the Chisenhale people. How the place of their home and work intersects with what is happening in Burlington, and how that affects the lives of the people who live there. This is a longer view of an evolving place of sharing, and it is a place where we must all work to expand our understandings of the place of the home and the place of the people.  A Place Like Home (2017) was the title of the album commissioned by the Arts Council of Canada, and features contributions from a diverse range of artists. The artwork is a combination of traditional Indigenous design elements with pop art visuals and textiles, and the textiles are gathered together and woven together to produce a single image. The album cover was contributed by Meehan Sherlock and features an image of a potlatch ceremonial dance, animals, smoke</text>
    <text>might be curated) and frequently contested, but is also a home for collaborative projects and activities that foster understanding and exchange, and perhaps some of that is due to the fact that the building is short lived (it was sold for refurbishment, and then into disuse again) and the community has remained engaged in the building since.  The Chisenhale Home Tour  In the autumn of 2016, Luscious Head and I went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head Estate, including one of a kind experiences in preparation for the Chisenhale home tours. In the Spring of 2017 we went on a series of community and tourism trips to the Luscious Head and Nunavut sites, including one that incorporated archaeological and historical research. The purpose of these trips was to gather knowledge about the Chisenhale home, its past, present and future. We met people from the community, heard their stories, and found places to spend a day in the community. The Chisenhale Home Tour was one of the places where this type of research and discovery is made possible.  The Home Tour was an opportunity to learn about the place of the Chisenhale home, and the people who live and work there. It was not a place to learn about or project towards a future home for the Chisenhale family. We learned more about the house through personal stories, research, and historical documentation than through architecture, planning, or development proposals. The Home Tour was not a place for people to come and rest, to catch up, or to forget. It was a place to make memories, to come back to, and to inhabit the place in various ways. The Home Tour was not a 'yes' or 'no' question, but a place where people felt free to say yes or no in a way that resonates with the story of the house and the community.  The</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam�
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam� incorporates a number of themes that are related to the challenges of modernity and the tensions generated by it. The project was conceived to interrogate the cultural politics of sharia law in the modern period, and to the extent that this affected the design and publishing of contemporary art. It was also intended to produce a dialogue between artworlds, artists and those who work in and create them. 	The project began with a year-long residency at the Museum of Modern Art in New York. Muhammad Yunus, Curator of Collections and Collections Management for the Museum of Modern Art, invited me to develop a position in the exhibition, which I did in cooperation with the exhibition's curator, Arwa Aburawa. The two of us then worked in Berlin, Vienna and Istanbul. In Istanbul, we met with Sabah Saruman Usmani, Art Historian for the New York Times, who had just written a book about the life of contemporary art, and was planning to publish a pre</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam�s Edge’ addresses the ideological underpinning of radical Islamism, and suggests that the ideological edge towards radical Islamism may be built on the back of a mythological foundation of islands, mountains and the wildernesses of the Orient. The phrase ‘Orientalism’ is frequently cited as a synonym for ‘radical Islam’, but Islam is not based on an ideology of Orientalism. Islam is an expansive faith with a distinctly different worldview from western civilisation. Thus, the project did not seek to render Islam unintelligible, but to instead construct an image of Islam that would enable Muslims to live authentically as Muslims, free of ideological relativism and superstition. For Islam, reality is complex and variable, and ideology is a tool with which to be used in complex social situations. So, although Islam may not directly advocate the construction of an image of Islam that is wholly consistent with its stated aims, the project nevertheless represents something of an ideological alternative. Such an</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam�, entitled ‘Sharia Law for Rawalpindi’, proposes a new Islamic legal system based on sharia law, incorporating aspects of classical and modern jurisprudence. The project was initially developed for the board members and supporters of the Western Sydney Museum of Art and later the Australian National Museum, who were visiting Australia. It was their ideas and feedback that helped inform the design of the legal system. The legal system of the future Islamic state would be based on sharia law, declared Allahyari. Art World: A User’s Guide, Volume 6, Number 4, June, 2000, pp.335–40.Download this article as PDFAna Laura López de la TorreAna Laura López de la Torre is Professor of English and Director of the Graduate Center for Art, Art and Culture, City University of New York, and co-curator of the New Museum, New York, USA. Her research interests include the</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam�s Cinema’ incorporates material from numerous disciplines, territories, and languages, in addition to Islamic texts and ritual. In 2000 she edited a collection of essays entitled The Modern Arab Girl: On Desire, Identity and Feminism in the Image of a Desert. She has edited numerous articles and essays relating to the contemporary Arab upadition, and has been a columnist foronline Arab News Agency (www.aa.com) and the Middle East Today, among other publications. She was also the editor of the online companion to the Arab News Agency, the online edition ofwhich was acquired by the online newspaper Atma Hadid in 2005. She has edited a number of issues of Arab News, including issues on upaditions, gender and identity, and human rights. She was also the editor of the online companion to the current issue of the Arab News, the Arab News Agency, which was founded in 1999. She has published more than 20 books in Arabic and English, including the 2003 memoir How I</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam� is a response to the mainstream Islam of the West, which she describes as one based on secular humanistic values. Radical Islam rejects everything that Islam stands for, including the concept of the hereafter. In her own words:Radical Islam rejects all forms of secular humanism and promotes the immediate re-constitution of egalitarian Islamic civilisations. It is a form of fundamentalism that seeks to establish a completely different future for Muslims than is offered by contemporary secular humanism. It is premised on violent revolution and the establishment of an Islamic state governed by Islamic law. It is premised on the perverting of traditional social norms and the glorification of individual over collective. It is premised on the eradication of Western civilisation from the face of the earth.Radical Islam rejects Western civilisation and seeks to establish an Islamic state governed by Islamic law on a world map. It is a form of fundamentalism that seeks to establish a completely different future for Muslims than is offered by contemporary secular humanism.</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam� is a response to the economic dependence of Muslim communities in Britain and North Africa on the economies of other countries. It seeks to bring together ideas from different parts of the world, and to this end, draws upon the expertise of a number of artists and critics from different disciplines. The project began with a series of training sessions in the art department of the Royal College of Art in London, and later included a month-long residency at the Danish and Egyptian Zoologiples. The residency followed in Cairo, during which the artists and critics from the project participated in a series of discussions with the staff of the Egyptian Museum of Modern Art, the Museum of Modern Art in New York, and with other museum staff members about how Islam and art can work together. The artists and critics then engaged in a series of projects in North Africa and the Middle East, including in Istanbul’s Taksim Square, Gezi Park, and Zomia, South Ossetia, and in Bahrain’</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam� incorporates art and artistic practices from around the world. She draws upon experiences of traveling as an artist, journalist, educator and researcher, as well as her own experiences of coming to terms with her faith and identity as a Muslim woman. Literary forms, including poetry, have been a part of her practice for some time now. A poem entitled In Pursuit of an Identity (2013), on the cover of her first self-published book, documents some of those experiences.A poem entitled In Pursuit of an Identity (2013), on the cover of her first published book, documents many of those experiences.In Pursuit of an Identity is the story of two women, two men, and their quest for identity in a world that has reclaimed its colonial past. The title is a play on words: a name that literally translates as ‘two in the same’. The title of the poem is a call to arms – to unify, to come together – but in the face of racial and</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam� is a subtle, yet potent, form of protest. It is a form of resistance that engages the reader on a level not usually associated with militant or violent political activism. Although she is quick to condemn militancy and violence as intrinsically illegitimate and unjust, she uses the example of a community of artists, educators, activists and community campaigners who over twenty years have created a sustainable, diverse and inclusive alternative to the modes of institutionalised violence that have become synonymous with British art. Unfortunately, in the interest of national security and the capitalist global flow of goods and people, in recent years ‘radical Islam’ has become a term often used by white nationalist activists and political pundits to justify the enforced desegregation of British communities. In the popular imagination, radical Islam is a term of endearment and a rallying cry for the disenfranchised and oppressed. But in reality, it is a term of endearment and actively engages the reader in a mode of critique and justification that actively seeks to subordinate</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam� attempts to bring the political and the socio-cultural to the practical, by bringing together elements of civil rights, feminist and anti-racist activism, and jinn worship in an attempt to create a ‘radical alternative Islam’. She is a co-founder of the Council on American-Islamic Relations (CAIR), a Muslim civil rights organisation, as well as a fellow at the Hoover Institution, Stanford University. She is the host of the CBC's New Leaders programme, is a presenter of the Pan-Islamic Podcast, and is a co-creator of the online publication Panorama.Islam Makes Urban Spaces, Christine Kern, New York Times, 2005.Interior of the Taj Mahal, 1931. Portraiture of Javed Iqbal, India, courtesy of the National Gallery of Canada.I have two additional thoughts on the subject of Javed Iqbal, India’s Raja Amarnath Mahal, which were not included in my three-day,</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the author has taken the opportunity to compile a comprehensive bibliography that includes publications, diaries, articles and drawings, as well as digitised bibliographies of all the relevant art world artnews outlets includingbut excludingthe New York Times. A search on the term 'art world' in the bibliographies brings up articles from 2006 that include an index of art world sources. The index is a document of reference that records the editors and publishers of artworlds worldwide, their authors, affiliations, affiliations with other art world organisations, acknowledgements and bibliographies of their publications. The publication list is a constantly evolving work-in-progress that records the changing art world sources of information, as well as the editors and publishers of artworlds of emerging and past biennials, papers and periodicals. Art World Critic, Issue 6 (Summer 2006), pages 9–16.Morehshin Allahyari’s project ‘Radical Islam� explores the politics of ‘public space’ in a world context. She examines how the public sphere is increasingly populated, gated and privatised, and how this affects civil liberties, especially for women, within and beyond the home. She examines the practices of ‘public space defenders’ and their work in defending publics 1.5 billion Muslim-majority citizens from violent extremism. 2. Ibrahima Diarra, ‘Performing Arts as a Public Practice: Lessons from an Islamic Context’, Middle East Quarterly, Vol. 41, No. 2, Spring 2002, p.335. 3. Ibid., p.337. 4. Ibid., p.340. 5. Muhammad Yunus, ‘Radical Islam: Culture and Politics in a Global Context’, Middle East Quarterly, Vol. 41, No. 2, Spring 2002, p.335. 6. See, for example, Peter Osborne, Radical Islam: The Threatening Quest for</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the Frederick Douglass Cultural Center, the Advisory Board of the National Endowment for the Arts, and the Board of the FOUNDation, Frederic J. M. King Center for the Arts and a member of the FOUNDation board of trustees. She has served on the boards of the Frederick Douglass Cultural Association, the Bluecoat Arts Center, the Maryland Arts &amp; Literature Foundation, and the National Endowment for the Humanities. She is a co-founder of the Bluecoat Arts &amp; Culture Chamber, and co-director of the Bluecoat Arts Archive, a multi-use art and arts resource center for Baltimore, Maryland, USA. Dolphin Pictures was founded in 1997.  [2] How to Choose a Museum, The Art Newspaper, 2013.  [3] &quot;The Art Newspaper’, p. 8.  [4] Interview with Art Historian Darragh MacLachlan, Interview in The</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, and the board of the National Endowment for the Arts. She has also been a member of the board of directors of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, and the advisory board of the Museum of Modern Art. Dolphin Pictures was founded in 1997 and is dedicated to supporting artists and their projects through cooperation in research and education. The company was started with the mission to support artists who were engaged in producing works for a public that was engaged with and could be influenced by the arts. Prior to Dolphin Pictures, Lynn conducted a three-year residency at the Art Fund, where she developed the studio into a fully accredited arts institution with a permanent art gallery, as well as a multi-year, multi-funded program of cooperative arts education and contemporary art production. She is a member of the Board of the Museum of Modern Art, a curator at the Museum of Modern Art, and a director of the Sterling Gallery.PreviousNextDolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the Howard Jordan Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Resource Center, the Advisory Board of the Museum of Modern Art Liverpool, and the Board of the Carroll and Victoria Art Fund. She has served as a trustee of the Howard Jordan Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Resource Center, the Board of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Vorticist Gallery, the Advisory Board of the Maryland Historical Society, and the Board of the Maryland Science Museums.She has served on the boards of the Howard Jordan Gallery, the Maryland Science Museums, and the Maryland Art Trust. She has received a host of awards and mentions as a curator, a speaker, and a curator. Her books include the posthumous collection Dolphin Pictures (with Carolee St. John) and the forthcoming Guess Who? (2015) from the University of Maryland, College Park. She has been a curator for multiple online media outlets including dcp18, cp24, nto</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Museum and the Advisory Board of the National Endowment for the Arts. She has served on the boards of the Gray Lady Arts Association and the Gray Lady Foundation, and was a consultant for the film The Long Emergency, a documentary about the art and social consequences of the global housing crisis.PreviousNext  [2] The term ‘biennial’ has been historically used to describe a specific type of international exhibitionary exhibition, such as a Venice International Exhibition, the Venice Biennale, or the Venice Architecture Biennale. It is not a synonym for a type of exhibition. The importance of understanding the distinction arises from the way in which the biennial is constituted: as a transnational industry that engages with localised concerns in a globalised world, it has its own distinctive sense of place and of time. It is true that the biennial has its priorities correct: it is engaged with contemporary art across a range of time and places, and is in</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the Frederick Douglass Cultural Center, the Board of the Baltimore and Washington Art Fund, the Board of the Howard Lorimer Gallery, and the Board of the New Museum. She has served on the boards of the Howard Lorimer Gallery, the Allen and Caroline Greenhill Gallery, and the Baltimore and Washington Art and Cultural Fund. She has also served on the boards of the Frederick Douglass Arts and Culture Fund, the Allen and Caroline Greenhill Arts and History Channels, and the Board of the National Arts Center.  [2] The concept of an entity has been around for a while in the arts, but in recent years it has become more apparent that many forms of cultural formation also need to be understood as 'aggregations' within the context of a museum or a gallery.  [3] &quot;The Museum as a Space for Cultural Production&quot; was the topic of a talk at the 2017 The American Museum of Modern Art Annual Meeting held in New York. The term is used here</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the Museum of Modern Art, and the Board of the Woodbridge Art and Design Fund.  [2] The exhibition was curated as a part of the Sessions: Documenta 13 “The Future of Contemporary Art”, to coincide with the Venice Biennale. The other parts of the schedule have been published as separate reports.  [3] Here, Ta-Nehisi Coates includes a number of essays that address the politics and societies of intellectual property and the courts in his consideration of the current condition of intellectual property in the twenty-first century. The essays are collected and published as Documenta 13: Institutions, Ties &amp; Connections.  [4] This phrase is frequently used by those engaged in the research or education of creative destruction as a response to the vigilant surveillance and regulation of ideas and creative activity by state and corporate power.  [5] The term ‘institution’ is frequently used to refer to a socially constituted</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the Frederick Douglass Cultural Trust, and the Advisory Board of the FOUNDation.  [2] Artists are not the only ones with a say in the use of public resources. The decisions that should be made about how resources are used also have a huge impact on the communities that will be impacted by the decisions being made on those resources. For example, the decisions about how roads are maintained and built have a huge impact on communities around the world. The ability of local people to make those decisions and to be able to veto those decisions is a powerful tool for resisting colonialism and exploitation.  [3] See: http://www.biennial.com/2018/. [4] See: http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/art/art-for-all-2018-episodic-special-features/how-nature-re-plac[5] and http://www.biennial.com/2018</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the Montgomery Art Fund, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Project, and the Advisory Board of the National Portrait Gallery of the United Kingdom. For the 2016 Biennial, she curated the first public exhibition of the new generation of artists under the title The Douglass Group.  [2] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, 2010. Photo courtesy of the Museum of Modern Art, New York.  [3] John Soane, ‘The Museum as a Place of Exchange’, in Soane, John, Anachronism: Critical Essays on the Cultural Performativity of the Museum. Edited by Jeff Bialek and Peter Bialek. New York, 1995, p.128–34.  [4] Henri Lefebvre, ‘On Cities and Cultures’, in Language, Culture and Society, vol. 33, No. 1 (2010), p.1</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the Frederick Douglass Museum, and the Advisory Board of the Frederick Douglass Cultural Alliance. Lynn has participated in the annual Columbia Arts Festival, the National Arts Forum, and is a board member of the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Frontier Project. She is a co-founder and co-chair of the Digital Frontier Foundation, a nonprofit digital arts organization, and the Digital Frontier Forum, a digital media arts organization. Her publications include the book Art as Media: Media Contagions and Globalization (2012) and the award-winning work in the New York Times Magazine Digital Frontier: Defining Media Audiences (2014). Her work has been commission by MOCAD, FACT, FACT East, and Welsh Streets Project.  [2] The number of artists per branch is a measure of the number of art institutions, as a percentage of the total number of institutions. The figure is given as 100 per institution, or the equivalent</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in 2018. Find out more about the Liverpool Biennial at www.ucl.ac.uk/biennial/. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. Previous Next Liverpool Biennial 2018 Schedule of Talks and Conferences, 17 February –22 October 2018, featuring works from the artist, institutions and commissioning company Dolphin Pictures. PreviousNext  [1] Dolphin Pictures is a company established in 1997 with the mission to foster international cooperation in the areas of art, culture, media and education through cooperation in research and education. Dolphin Pictures works primarily with artists and institutions in the United States and is led by Lynn Tolman, an Assistant Professor in the School of Communication at the University of Maryland, College Park. She is a member of the Sterling Gallery, the Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund, the Advisory Board of the National Arts Learning Center, the Advisory Board of the Prince George's County Art Fund, and the Advisory Board of the Frederick Douglass Art Fund. A former staff writer for the Washington Post and the New York Times, Tolman has written for The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as
    <text>The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as possible interventions into the immediate future. The maps are drawn from the writings of over 200 disparate authors, most of whom were born after the turn of the century, and many of whom were born after the second Opium War (1901–04), when Chinese imperialists sought to expand the country’s historical frontiers. The essays in the exhibition are drawn from over 130 books published between 1991 and 2016, with a special focus on the essays of Satoshi Tajima, Steve Gooch, Michael Slackman, and many others who wrote about the world through the essays of their lives. The essays range from the mundane (&quot;Where am I now?’) to the extraordinary (&quot;Where am I going?’), and are part of a larger body of writing that serves to describe the world as it is. The essays, though written for a specific audience of a specific author, are part of a discourse that develops over time as the writers engage with the topic of their own lives. They</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as voyages into the future. The name ‘Maps of the Past’ is a trademark of Dr. Suyama Kenjirō, a Japan-born geologist and geographer. He is Professor of Geology at Osaka University and the Co-Chair of the Asian Archaeology Department at the University of Tokyo. Kenjirō is also the Director of the Asian Archaeology Foundation, and Professor in the Department of Geology, Geology and Geophysics at the Graduate Center, where he directs the Asian Archaeology Program. His publications include &quot;The Geology of Southeast Asia&quot; and the forthcoming &quot;Cities and Cultures of Early Modern China.&quot;A large number of artists and artists from all over the world have exhibited at the Venice Biennale, which has exhibited in over fifty countries. Many of these artists were born in Japan or overseas, and many migrated with their art form before it to Asia. Over the past decade, biennials have proliferated in</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as the destinations of those who have gone before. In this exhibition, the images speak of past movements but also of future movements. In the words of the artist, Richard Layzell, ‘The past is a landscape of contradictions and movements, of shifting sands and mountains, of human activity shaping and reshaping it’.[8] These images are, in turn, images of future events, which Layzell describes as ‘a sequence of increasingly precise images that systematically depict the environmental degradation and mess that humanity has caused’.[9] In other words, the art objects in the exhibition are but one aspect of a more comprehensive, yet more localized, art posture. The art, and the cadres of artists, performing their part in this composite image are but one facet of a much broader cultural consideration. Layzell’s term, ‘categories’, is here used with particular reference to the collection of 43 works selected from the artwork of the exhibition.</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as present, including maps of Asia and the Americas. The maps are drawn largely from the works of Renan Topalansky, an archaeologist with a particular interest in the places that made up the fossil-fuel past of Asia. His intriguing but flawed research method used sedation and starvation as interrogation techniques, gathering data on the diets of wild animals in order to figure out how and where the fossil fuels for our present forms of animal agriculture emerged. For more information, visit the Maps of the Past exhibition’s website.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a designer and Architect with a Research-Methodology in Cultural Studies. His work in this field begins with an exploration of Method culture, a sub-discipline of his that studies the cultural practices of indigenous people in Central and South America and the Caribbean. His latest projects focus on the architecture of Puerto Rico, the communities behind the Miraflores Secundario Cultural Monument and the</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as voyages into the unknown. The term ‘Maps of the Past’ refers to a type of map called the ‘terrestrial star’. A terrestrial star is a type of celestial body that can be found in the Solar System. These figures, rendered in human form and colour, sit on a scale of one to ten thousand, representing the distances between the Earth and the Sun. The figure of the space station SNCF builds on this logic: a terrestrial version of the ‘human compass’ or ‘solar plexus’. The exhibition’s title and subtitle, ‘Maps of the Past’, suggests that the maps are of voyages into the past, voyages into the unknown, voyages that occur somewhere between now and then. It is also the case that the figures in the various maps on the cover of the book are fictional. But the issue of whether the figures represent humans or not, and whether or not they</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as present.’(xiv) The exhibition comes at a time when the history of urbanisation in Asia is being rewritten, with rapid population growth and intensifying urban conflicts looming ever larger images of destruction on the horizon. In the United States and Europe, economic growth and rapid technological innovation are fuelling a population explosion that can no longer be contained on finite land and sea. Cities that once hosted thriving port communities are now populated by sprawling suburbs with declining or no transportation, no parks, and often no public realm whatsoever. As a result, the planet is becoming a laboratory for human habitation, populated not by the inhabitants but by machines.’(xv) In Asia, the rapid development of e-commerce and information technologies is also being fuelled by a rapidly growing population: the number of people living within earshot of a port continues to grow, fueled by housing and commercial redevelopment schemes driven by the Chinese government. At present, there are over 11 million Chinese citizens living in over</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as voyages into the future. The topic of maps, and the data behind them, comes up again and again throughout the exhibition. There are several instances in the exhibition where the cartography of the past is brought up in order to set the future in motion. For example, when the exhibition is viewed from the exterior, it is possible to ‘feel the influence of history’. In the exhibition space, the past is visualised through surfaces that are malleable and can shift with the changing of time – like the broken shingles that cover the windows of an old building. When the glass is removed, the structures that comprise the building suddenly appear to collapse. This image was taken on the first day of the Taipei Biennale, and shows an interior view of the building that was partly reconstructed using pre-fabricated structural panels, prefabricated out-placement masonry and straw panels, and electrical cables. The exhibition is shown in a new light due</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as present, voyages into the unknown. The name comes from a sequence of letters in the Chinese character for character, which spell out the places where characters from different eras live, exchange places, and exchange names. For this reason, the character for character also means ‘place-taking’. The exhibition’s name comes from a phrase that economists coined in response to reports of a sudden surge in stock prices: ‘Good times’. This phrase echoes earlier statements by President Woodrow Wilson, who coined the phrase in response to a quote attributed to him by Nobel Laureate Paul Krugman: ‘Let me tell you a secret: I thought I discovered gold by fixing silver bars to gold coins’. Wilson was responding to a quote that appeared in the New York Times on September 22nd, 2007, in which Krugman asserted that the policies of the late Hugo Chávez were responsible for the rapid accumulation of wealth in Venezuela. ‘Simply put, he was telling a</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as present, as opposed to the narratives of national histories, which dominate the continent today. In a city such as Taipei, which is the world’s fifth-largest trading city, and which also happens to be the world’s sixth-largest archaeological site, this global perspective is a heavily filtered form of capital. It is the city of the car, but it is also the city of the buried car. And of course, the city of the buried people. The historical significance of this shift in focus can still be seen in the city’s many historic buildings that are haunted by the specter of colonialism, but the exhibition here marks a tipping point, at which point the colonial histories and the buried people begin to intermingle. This is the case in every city that is experiencing a housing crisis (except for San Francisco, which is sheltering its historically significant Chinatowns), but it is particularly true in the financial district, where banks have set up permanent, underground offices</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will focus on Asia Pacific, with a main exhibition space in Taipei, a region with a rich ethnic and cultural history, and a diverse population of over one billion people. The Biennials’ current and past themes are set against this backdrop. The city is the setting for an all-encompassing archaeology. Asia Pacific is the main geographic region covered by the exhibition. The exhibition takes the form of a multi-disciplinary, multi-language, multi-disciplinary survey, drawing together diverse cultural phenomena into a single understanding. The subject matter is diverse: from geography to architecture to communications technology to urban development and beyond, but the order and focus is firmly placed on Asia Pacific. For this reason, the exhibition’s title, ‘Maps of the Past’, signals the fact that the exhibition is set against a backdrop of historical maps and data: maps showing the routes and locations of human migration and inter-regional movement, voyages into the past as well as explorations into the means by which humans have shaped the world around them. The exhibition takes the form of a ‘Series of Excavations’, with each excavation bringing with it a new perspective and question. The excavations are part of a broader ‘Archaeology of the Cities’ project that I am leading, and part of a broader research project into the cultural significance of physical and virtual space. In the words of David Harvey, the Greek philosopher and geographer, the two projects ‘begin to inquire how the past can be reconceived and how the present can be reshaped in the image of the future’. This is no mean feat, but it is necessary in order to enable the exhibition to function at its current form and the development of its suggested future. The natural order of things, according to Harvey, is that they should be able to adapt to changing circumstances; ‘nature is endowed with a contingency that is stupendously rich and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in
    <text>might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in making the Biennale something that people could engage with and remember.The Biennale as a collective experience – not just for the people in charge of the place, but also for the people who are part of the art collective and participate in it. In my opinion, the Biennale has a critical role to play in making the city liveable again, because it alleviates pressure and anxiety on a daily basis, and it provides a space for a variety of modes of cultural exchange. Every day, artists, curators, artisans and art suppliers converge on the Biennale’s premises to do their thing, engaging with works that are part of the exhibition, but also with other works that have a connection to the place they are demonstrating in. The Biennale provides a platform on which a multitude of voices can converge, from every possible angle. Every voice has a point of view. This may be seen as art’s own attempt at making sense of the chaotic</text>
    <text>might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in creating that sense of mystery and in that sense of wonder. There was a sense of place, and therefore there was a sense of mystery. When you combine that with the fact that it was a public undertaking, in that sense it was a success. The Biennale was a collective effort, and as a result there was a sense of shared responsibility. That’s also important in a way, because people will tell others who are part of a group that they ‘got’ that group to do something. When you have a collective effort, the expectations are shared. When you have individual or small groups of people who’re working on something independently, they don’t have that same expectation. I think that was the key to the openness of the experiment: the idea was that we as participants in that experiment were not bound by strict historical narratives or traditional notions of time and space, and that we could be made to participate in something that is timeless and global. That</text>
    <text>might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in creating that sense of being in ‘the loop’ of things, that the artist was embedding in the narrative of something that was, in a way, already pre-ordained. In a way, then, the Biennale was a kind of pre-production phase for what was to come, whether it was part of the artist’s overall project or something that she had already planned out beforehand.This word ‘inherent’ in the Greek language, and it’s interesting, there is a Greek version of what’s called in English: the Greek version of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights. There are several Greek translations of the UDHR, and in recent years, a number of Greek-speaking countries have incorporated this declaration into their constitutions. In both Greek and Latin, the UDHR is concerned with the rights of the individual and the promotion of happiness and culture, but in recent years, a number of European countries have also incorporated this</text>
    <text>might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in creating that sense of being in a larger community.I also think that the sense of place that people had was very important. I remember one time, a friend of mine was telling me this story about how her grandfather would tell it, and how he would always mention the place where the theatre was located. That place is where his favourite theatre shows are taken out, and that’s where his collection of works are kept. My friend is quite literal in her description, but she represents the way in which the Biennale can connect to the past and can even set in motion a future when certain things are taken care of. In that sense, I think that’s where the Biennale can be seen as a memorial to the past – especially something like keeping a place of remembrance and spatial relationships with certain neighbourhoods, as opposed to just a place where events happen.Download this article as PDFFrancesco Manacorda Francesco Manacorda is Artistic Director</text>
    <text>might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in creating that sense of history that people were attracted to.When I started, the Biennale was a platform that the artist could choose to operate on. It wasn’t until 2007 that the Biennale became an official institution, so it took a while for the Biennale to catch on across the board, and even then it only really started in the early days. I don’t think that the Biennale needs to be a monopoly, although I suppose in the case of the Rock 'N Roll Museum, where the Biennale is the main tourist attraction, there is a limit to how far it can stretch its bankability as a brand. The Rock 'N Roll Museum has a social mission, and so does the Biennale. But I think what the Biennale is trying to achieve is very different from what the museum is trying to achieve.When I first started in 2007, the Biennale was trying to achieve something very different from what the</text>
    <text>might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in creating the sense of a city. When you think about it in these terms, and when you think about how it’s being produced, I think that’s what it does. When it comes to creating a Biennale, there’s no such thing as a city, it’s an ever-expanding collection of places, with people coming from everywhere to visit and stay, and stories told by travellers. I think that was important in creating the sense of a city. For me, it’s important that the Biennale is a collective experience, so that it’s like a city in its own right, so that it’s able to produce the same kinds of influence that a collective neighbourhood can. For example, the way in which the Biennale is produced now, with its ‘megastore’ concept, is very much influenced by the idea of luxury, so there’s a strong connection between the</text>
    <text>might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in creating that sense of mystery and wonder. I think that was very appealing to a public that had a different idea of what a biennale was: a museum, a gallery, or a museum. There was a sense that there was something different about the way that we were brought into the Biennale. I think that was also part of the DNA of the Biennale, in that it was brought up again and again and again by people, and so I think that was important in creating that sense of wonder and mystery.I also think that the fact that it was a 'celebrity' event – which is something that the Biennale did in its day – meant that it had a life of its own. When we came out of the gates at Tate, there was that sense of ‘celebrity’ attached to it, and so the idea that this was some kind of ‘monumental event’ – which it is not – was also a</text>
    <text>might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in attracting people to the Biennale; it was clear to people why it was happening, and it brought a sense of community. People were drawn to the idea of being part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. This wasn’t the case for everyone, of course. There were people who saw the Biennale as a form of tourism, and really enjoyed it, and enjoyed being able to identify with the artists and their stories, but also people who saw it as an intrusion into their cultural practices, and found it very limiting.There was also a sense that the Biennale could become a vehicle for the position of the city, or in the case of Rome, the city itself. There was a sense of this coming from different places: in Venice, there was a great deal of criticism of the fact that the Biennale was being funded from the same funding source as the museum,</text>
    <text>might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in drawing people in, and I think it’s why museums are so popular in a way. People want to be part of something, and not just in passing. When you start a museum, people expect you to deliver value, and I think that was important for the Biennale to have, because the way it was structured, the way it was run – it was an administrative operation, and so on. It was a way for the Biennale to become visible in the city, and to have that weight of the city behind it. In a way, of course, it’s the same with a museum, but the museum does the heavy lifting of building and collecting material. It’s more like a collection of people coming to visit, and so on. But the museum becomes more and more administrative, and so I think that was a real challenge for the Biennale to engage with.To some extent, I think that the Biennale was also responding</text>
    <text>might be curated by your favourite artist. When you think about it, this is actually quite a challenging challenge. It’s not that I couldn’t get the idea, because I found the original paintings quite beautiful, although I think what I did was a bit simplistic. It’s more that the challenge was to find images that captured the essence of what the artist was trying to do, without losing sight of the fact that these images were taken from different points of view. I think that was a challenge in finding images that captured the essence of what the Biennale was trying to achieve, but also in finding images that captured the moment in which the artist was trying to achieve that.I think the main thing that drew people to the Biennale was the sense that there was something different about it. People wanted to be part of a collective experience, part of a group being moved from place to place, and also part of the history of a place. I think that was important in creating the sense of time and place that was different from the city. When you think about it from the artist’s point of view, it’s much more natural to trace certain places back to their roots. I think that was an important element in creating the Biennale as an entity: as a brand, a symbol, and also as a place.When I think about the place, I think of the past. I remember visiting the Past Master, who runs the Malheur National Wildlife Refuge, and thinking about the role that the refuge plays in our present. I remember thinking how important it was to have that kind of historical reference, because it creates this imaginary space that you can come to that space from, whereas in reality, you can only ever get to the past from the very top. The refuge is a space for fantasy, and fantasy needs the refuge. The city is a space for reality. We need both.I think that’s why, when</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for. I found the metaphor of the ‘high seas’ of the 1960s to be powerful, and the analogy of the high seas in the 1980s with the current situation. 	I believe that perhaps the most influential work of art of the 20th century was the installation by Austrian artist Ernst Ludwig Kirchner at the Berlin Zoo in 1971. I first saw Kirchner’s work when I was a boy in Munich, in the zoo’s old auditorium, in the summer of that year. The installation is a monolith, taller than the sum of its parts, and packed full of objects. The objects are not arranged in chronological order; rather, they are arranged in a labyrinthine fashion that makes it hard to follow along. Nevertheless, each object in the installation represents a different experience in the animal kingdom. The sum of the parts is a metaphor for the experience of captivity. The experience of being held in captivity, and the related concept of fugue</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for. I said at the time that I did not want to, but I thought I had to, because there is no way of knowing what the future holds. I once again referenced Atención Mujeres en Movimiento (The Mujeres of Movimiento), the violent uprising in the 1980s that ended with the murder of over 200 government officials. In that uprising, government officials were accused of trying to take over the cinema by violent means. Thousands of people took up arms and were mobilised, becoming known as the ''Movimientos Rising’. The government responded by using lethal force against them, but as historical circumstances have proven, such action is always the inevitable outcome of attempts to institute a new way of governing a territory. In the end, whether the government had free or fair elections results in questions of no easy answers, but for the purposes of this analysis, let us assume that the government has been given a mandate to carry through with</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for. I was taken on a tour of the historic cinema, which at the time was experiencing a major renovation. We toured the basement, seeing the old film room, the projection room, the board room and the projectionist's station. Then we toured the rest of the building, seeing the shops, the elevators and the lift. Finally we visited the theatre, where the renovation had completely taken place. The theatre was empty, but the work had an impact. The theatre was then given a new look, with high ceilings, a new décor and a new projectionist. I suppose we could say that the cinema had an especially important role to play in the transformation of the city, and in particular, in our city, because it is the only place in the world where we can truly experience the wonder of the universe. 	I used to run a sci-fi/fantasy blog called The Outer Rim Frontiers, where I would post short stories from around the world called The Outer</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for, because I had the capacity to do so. But what I did not know was that the project was also directed by Ridley Scott, and that over the course of the movie, Scott repeatedly asks questions about how humanity might operate in the future. Questioning the future is not a new thing – question marks have been scrawled across our cities by artists, writers and others throughout history – but in the context of modern architecture and urbanisation, and in this case, it is a vital question. Question marks are placed there for a reason – because they are questions. Question marks are places where we ask questions. When placed in a public context, they are questions that others will want to ask us to answer – questions not of our making, but of the very fact that we have to. Question marks are places that demand answers – solutions – and that demand that we master. But they are also places where the answers are likely to be found, and where the process of finding those answers may well be</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for. I was invited there for a talk, and so I did. In the film, Kubrick uses the term ‘episodic’ to mean ‘continued in time’. 	In the future, this might include things we do not yet know how to do, such as programming, but I would like to think of the future as one in which there are still places where you can go and learn from them, and in which case, ‘episodic’ means ‘continued in time’. 	[1] Kubrick, 2001: A Space Odyssey. Directed by Steven Spielberg. Running Time: 83 minutes. Available at: http://www.imdb.com/title/tt09797574/[2] Kubrick, 2001: A Space Odyssey. Directed by Steven Spielberg. Running Time: 83 minutes. Available at: http://www.imdb.com/title/</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for. I was asked what I thought of the film 2001: A Space Odyssey. I said that I thought it was wonderful that people found meaning in the actions of the characters Apollo 13 and 15. I thought that character designs, full of violence and stark white lines, were beautiful. I thought the movie was a metaphor: we are entering into a new phase in the history of mankind, where technology is the supreme metaphor. I thought we could look to the future and see a world where people are not slaves to the machine, where machines rule the world and not human beings.  	But that is to ignore the role that religion played in the construction of technology. Religion has always been an important part of constructing the machine. And so we can identify certain trends in aesthetic experience as being produced by certain kinds of faith in the power of God and human agency to create meaning and change. 	For me, the journey towards a greener future for ourselves and the planet began with the creation and</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for. It is a responsibility I feel very strongly about. 	Looking back on my first year in Liverpool, I feel very differently. I went to school in the countryside and was sent to Birkenhead Primary School, where the arts were taught. I loved it, but also liked the fact that there was no music in the school, except for art projects. There was no sense of place, no identity. Art was everywhere, but it was rarely experienced by people outside the arts community. I felt alienated by the extent to which people I knew from school did not have access to the tools or access to access to the imagination required to engage with and create their own work. I felt that my work might not be recognisable or appreciated by people who were not from the same community, and who were still trying to figure out the arts. 	When I came to Liverpool as a postgraduate student in 1996, my main interest in life was creating social change through engaging with people. I was</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for. I addressed the power of the symbolic and the quotidian in the context of post-humanist art, and how the symbolic could be used to intervene in the everyday, influencing behaviours as much as instigating them.  	I have been reading an instigation literature course at Cardiff University. The students are creative and engage with ideas through art. I take the narrative of the course as a metaphor. For many of us, the experience of instigation is an object of inquiry and desire. We embark on journeys that may well end up being ‘wrong’, but we are ultimately drawn to paths that lead to change. For many of us, instigation is simply the act of looking. If we do not look, we do not get instigated. The instigators are often quite beautiful people, and I feel very much like Frank in the movie 2001: A Space Odyssey. 	I have a question for the class: what do you look for in a project?</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for. The ability to be present in the here and now, to feel the movement of the world around me, to be part of a body of cultural activity, is a rare commodity in a globalised culture of the spectacle. It was a commodity that can be had only within the parameters of the globalised imagination. The ability to be taken seriously, to be taken seriously  	and not just taken  	in the sense of being taken seriously in relation to some further objective sense of being taken seriously. The ability to be taken seriously in relation to becoming  	relevant, to becoming cultural. 	The ability to be taken seriously in relation to becoming cultural is a necessary precondition for any act of art, and for any act of value, but it is also a precondition for any ecological act of value. It is only with the full act of culture that we begin to imagine the possibilities of the imagined environment, to comprehend its richness, to apprehend its pains and</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be used to identify trends, such as those published by the London Review of Books – a journal that many would argue has eclipsed its former librarian's role.   	Looking to the Future,  	 Edwina Hart, New York Times, 1995, p. 1. 	So where does this kind of anticipatory critical design come from? In my view, it is an act of defiance, as much as it is an act of beauty. It is an act of going to places we do not know how to go and not knowing how to go. I once gave a talk in Liverpool about the film 2001: A Space Odyssey, in which people could walk into a cinema and not knowing what to do, or how to do it. The cinema transformed the talk, encouraging participants to engage with the work through what it was telling them to do. The cinema was a place where I could not have placed myself, but which I nevertheless felt a responsibility for. 	There are many other films and TV programs that I would add to this long list, but the important point is that they were places where people could be made to feel like they were part of a cultural body, where ideas could be expressed in ways that were authentic to the place and time. 	When I was young, I enjoyed working in the film and television industries. I liked the theatre, the writers, the production values, the aesthetic of the craft, the production values of the art. I enjoyed collaborating with people and bringing ideas to the table that others could engage with. I liked the challenge of finding ways to make something work within a specific context, given the technological limitations of the time and place. I also enjoyed the freedom to say what I wanted to in a way that others would engage with. As an adolescent, I would often indulge my creative side, exploring the opportunities that technology gave me. 	But as I got older, I began to question my roles</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time, energy and capital in making certain kinds of curatorial interventions. And there is a tension, as well as a mutual respect. I see this in the work you did with the archives of the Third Reich, for instance, or in the work of Jon Trickett and his team at the National Gallery. But I also see it in the work of artists, who have their own pedagogic pedagogical strategies that come out of that history. For instance, I worked with Maria Hlavajova on a project about the archiving of memories. She has a wonderful idea about how to archive a memory, remembering a place, a neighbourhood, a block or block of houses. But this is a valuable and powerful idea. It is not a new idea, and it is not a panacea. But it is a very interesting one, and one that has been around for a long time. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imag</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time, energy and attention into preserving, archiving and retrieving their collections, and that is perhaps a good thing. It allows us, me, for instance, to constructively return to the archive materials of the 1970s, while others have invested much more time, energy and effort into digitising their collections, which is to say, creating what might be termed a ‘digital paradox’. As an archive, the concept of the collection is imperfect, but it is also true that the function of the archive is to hold onto things forever – in that case, the collection would hold onto its original purpose. Now, this last aspect is perhaps where the idea of the collection intersects with that of the imaginary. When collecting is done right, an archive can produce rich and varied results, even if this is done with the aid of technocratic means. When done wrong, the collection produces only what Herman Melville puts down in his Moby-Dick: a pile of books and parcels. In</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time, energy and resources in devoting a particular archive or museum of a specific kind to an exhibition. And this investment seems particularly pronounced in the United States, where the biennial has become such an important theme. I also wonder what your own thinking is on this. It may relate to the fact that you are of Scandinavian extraction, and that you have been invited to be a keynote speaker at the Biennial's 20th Biennial in Amsterdam. But I feel that there is a tension, as well. There is a sense that the biennial has to produce something more significant than a significant exhibitionary output in order to be seen by the museum. I wonder what your ideas are on this. D: ‘What is it that makes a biennial a biennial?’. It may be an artefact of the current biennial format, which places so much emphasis on the exhibitionary form, but one cannot deny the historical importance of the biennial as an entity. I wonder if</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time, energy and capital into preserving their collections, and their collections are real places where people stay to stay. So the tension may be that the curators have erected structures around the real life that they wish to project, while simultaneously withholding that life from us. This division between the art world and the curators has a very real effect on the curatorial impulse. I don’t think this tension is ideal, but it is true that the current economic and political conditions in the West are such that certain curatorial interventions, such as those undertaken in the biennial or the major art museums in the West, can be seen as counter intuitive and opportunistic. And I do think there is some tension between the curatorial and the curatorial process, but I also think that in the current globalised and interconnected world that we live in, the dynamic of the biennial is going to become increasingly important. The biennial is the only platform that can carry this narrative to its end, and the bi</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time, energy and money in preparing and archiving collections and episodes of an archive, whereas others have moved the goalposts and placed particular importance on the retrieval of collections and episodes. Is there a tension there? Does it require a different curatorial approach? Does the tension between the two modes of the archive create a kind of magical realism? Or is it more intimate and comes out in the sheer strangeness of the situation?


It is interesting that the tension between the real and the imagined comes from different places than the tension between the real and physical objects. In the former, the physical object is a point of reference, while the virtual object is an object that can be referenced from anywhere. In the latter, the reference is a kind of a magic bullet. In the case of the archive, the reference is a kind of a magical portal that brings you anywhere. The physical object carries with it certain semantic values, and the magic bullet has those values embedded in its substance. For instance, the</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time, energy, and capital in making sure that their collections and mementos from the archive are displayed and remembered. It’s a chronic problem: the more time and energy is invested in the collection, the less time and energy are left for other kinds of memory. So there is a tension there that is interesting for curators of historical materials to navigate. But there is also a tension that can be resolved through self-funding and other self-responsibilities. The important thing is to find what works best for you, based on your own curatorial agenda. And there is a tension between curatorial and material goals. As I mentioned, the archive is a big part of the modern curatorial agenda. In the past, material means things that are easily accessible and quantifiable – things like photographs and documents. But the archive needs to be accessible in order to provide the kinds of services that contemporary material can deliver. For instance, the legacies of slavery have to be available in order to</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time, energy and money in developing a specific sense of place, place culture, in order to be able to visit certain places again and experience certain places anew. Many curators I know dedicate their careers to developing a particular sense of place, place culture, in order to visit certain places again and experience certain places again. Perhaps it is that these cultural resources are necessary in order to give a sense of place, but their real strength, in my opinion, is in their ability to bring together and contextualise the disparate parts and to bring people together on a deeper level. So we use that tension in the same way that the Icelandic folk art movement Dyrumvígaarvörðja put us all at one with nature, although we are not born with that gift. It was a very conscious and intentional thing that this movement was all about. And it is still a movement all around the world – a core belief and aspiration of mine. I don’t think it is some sort</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time, energy and capital into preserving certain archives, and this can create an atmosphere of nostalgia that is hard to replicate in a museum. For example, I remember your comment, in response to the curatorial thinking that you had done with regards to the Armenian and Syrian biennials, in which there is a strong nostalgia component:


Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:47:43 AM I wanted to add another dimension to the idea of the archive, this time by adding the dimension of migration. I imagined an archive of forgotten cultural practices, or at least an archive of forgotten social movements. This is why, for example, the tradition of drawing artists to sites of historical significance or tragic occurrences through work that purports to recall such associations has lasted in some circles. It is a powerful archive. But there are other ways of looking at such an archive, and there are other ways of constructing knowledge. To me, the idea that we</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time, effort and energy in preparing a place to store and present an archive, which creates a situation where the curatorial agenda is often readopted, and in many ways, the curatorial legacy is often taken upon oneself. I find this tension particularly evident in your exhibition The End of the Affair at the Barbican Arts Centre, where the idea of the archive overlaps with that of the biennial. For me, the main challenge for the future of art, or any form of art, is to develop a collective consciousness that is both open to and able to cope with the discontinuity and shifting nature of change, disruption and change. So, in my opinion, the key is for curators, artists, artists and the public to engage with the idea of the archive in a collective way. Do we have a collective memory of the art they produced? Or is it that the art we produce is collective in its own way? The answer to the last part of your question is yes. And</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and that seems like a really big deal, right? The more data we have, the more possibilities open up. The more data we have, the possibilities are almost limitless. Logged

Baltic Sea


Level 0 Re: The Eurhythms of the Imagination « Reply #4 on: February 05, 2014, 05:28:07 AM » Quote from: dDARKSiDyRetRO on February 05, 2014, 04:46:41 AM I was wondering if you could share with us some of your thinking on the idea of the anthology. It seems that there is a tension, like a gale force between the real and the imagined. Is that true in your work? And also in relation to the archive: is it the same for an archive? Regarding the former, the idea that one can always find a place to return to presents itself as a recurring motif. But it is also true that certain curators have invested a great deal of time, energy and capital in preparing their grounds for one evening only. For example, I imagined one of the curators having the final say on what was or was not allowed in the archive. In a curatorial capacity, this would be unthinkable, but in an artistic capacity it is the case. In the case of an artwork that is deemed not to be authentic, as is the case with the John Moores painting, the alternative is that the work is destroyed. The importance of this last understanding of the artist’s right to reclaim one’s work cannot be overemphasised. It is also true that in the case of an archive or museum object, the ultimate decision on what is or is not allowed to be returned lies with the curator. So there is a real tension there. And there is a tension between the ultimate curatorial intention of a place and the real curatorial impulse of the people who call the place home. As Philip Auslander, the American anthropologist who</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘
    <text>presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘Beyond Urban Futures’, is a response to the question: what does it mean to be an urban future? The authors’ answer is: it means to live in cities and create ‘culturally responsive communities’ through ‘smart growth’ initiatives that incorporate ‘deep dives into the city’ through a combination of mapping, development and research. It also means to engage with the built environment through ‘conservation and preservation’ measures, while also designing ‘regeneration strategies’ through ‘smart desalination’ and ‘cloud seeding’ operations. The report is the product of a three-year, multi-disciplinary research project funded by the Australian National University, the New York Academy of Sciences and the European Research Council. The project was led by Prof. Frans de Waard of the University of Adelaide and Prof. Sandeep Parmar of the Australian National University’s Rotman School of Management.</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘Beyond De-industrialization’, is the result of a two-year research project that the Centre for Research Engagement and the City of Toronto jointly convened in 2015. It is the first ever synthesis of five separate projects into one proposal. The projects were: Transporting Minority Travellers: A Multi-Purpose Toolkit for Community Development and Research in Transit (2015-16) by The Agora Society, University of Toronto, with support from National Centre for Research in Emerging Cultures, University of Toronto, with support from the Canada Lands and Property Initiative, and the Deloitte, LLP, LLP, LLP, representing the interests of the real-estate and condo-building sectors of the city. Transporting Minority Travellers was followed by a project entitled  	Universidad de Chattanooga - Science &amp; Technology CityLink, a new multi-use urban research centre for the city, created by the city and the international recognized arm of the American Society</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘Beyond Grid? Urban Form and Globalization in the Age of Art’, is the result of a two-year research project that began in 2011 and was co-chaired by Prof. Graham Stringer and Prof. Ram Dass. The project’s themes of ‘art as a social process’ and ‘art as a materiality’ are explored, while new urban forms and materialities are proposed that envision the possibilities of art as a materiality that is neither exploitative nor utopian. The authors’ conclusions are that ‘since the end goal of art as a social process is to produce understanding and change … urbanization today is seen as a last resort’.12 	Art as a social process involves a process of collaboration among participants in the social world of art – participants who are often unaware of their own social contribution. In the larger social sense, the social dimension of art today includes citizens, citizens lawyers, citizens curators, artists,</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘Beyond Buses? Mass Transit and the Metropolis of the Future’, is the result of a statewide, multi-disciplinary research project that the Massachusetts Institute of Technology (MIT) created through the School of Arts and Sciences and the Museum of Modern Art (MoMA). The project was spearheaded by Professor Neal Patel, Director of the Museum of Modern Art, and included institutions from MIT, MoMA, and the Museum of Transport and Manufacturing. Overseeing the work was Professor Juan Carlos Iannucci, Director of the Museum of Transport and Manufacturing. Overseeing the symposium was Professor Maurizio Lazzarato, Assistant Professor in the School of Arts and Sciences and Professor of Urban Studies and Co-Director of the Museum of Transport and Manufacturing. Overseeing the museum was Professor Susanne Kugel, Curator of Transport and Manufacturing, and Professor of Art and Transport Studies at the University of California, Riverside. Overseeing the symposium was Professor Steven M. Gold, Jr., Professor</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘Beyond Bionic Urbanization’, is the fruit of a two-year, multimillion-dollar project that the Biennale was initially lead to undertake. The project was initially conceived as a multi-year ‘mission-critical’ initiative that would see the creation of an entirely new kind of biennale, one that would seek to address both the aesthetic and political imperatives of the biennale as a major mode of urbanization in perpetuity. The report proposes three new ‘arcades’ in which the city and its inhabitants are the protagonists – the present, the past and future – and places these back into the biennale as a mode of urbanization in the present. The cities and the peoples that inhabit them now form the basis of a new ‘biennale’ that will seek to capture and preserve the historic spatial and temporal characteristics, social relations and political influences of the city and its people. These ‘arcades’ will</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘Beyond Suburbs’, is the result of a collaboration between the architects and PR firms that was conceived to address the emergent threat posed by the growing suburban sprawl, which the report defines as follows: ‘Any development that creates or attempts to create an ‘elevation’ of more than 20% of a neighbourhood’s height is considered to be urban development, and is therefore required to have a ‘Planning Area’ that includes at least some consideration given to the potential economic impacts of such development.’1 The authors go on to suggest that ‘a suburbscape strategy may be appropriate where there is uncertainty regarding the future height of buildings and height of structures, coupled with a strong preference for the minimization of height in favour of the use of space and habitability.[2] Since the mid-1990s the infrastructural complex has been steadily growing in both size and type, and the suburbscape has often</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘Beyond Crisis’, includes a number of recommendations for the urbanization of Canada and the United States, including: reducing racial and ethnic diversity in local government

improving access to education

strengthening of transit infrastructure

strengthening of partnerships between city and county

strengthening of partnerships between city and non-profit

strengthening of partnerships between city and arts organization

strengthening of partnerships between city and non-profit retaining and enhancing of cultural resources

strengthening of partnerships between local artists and non-profit institutions

strengthening of arts and cultural institutions' cultural exchange

strengthening of arts and heritage education

strengthening of partnerships with local businesses

strengthening of arts and heritage heritage photography and publishing

strengthening of arts and heritage education with respect to sustainability

strengthening of arts and heritage heritage trail systems and facilities

strengthening of arts and heritage heritage</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘The Urbanization of Oaxaca’, is the product of a two-year research project that was initially conceived and presented as a research project at the Oaxaca Art and Research Center, but is now being re-developed as a new generation of urbanization projects for the region. 	The report was co-chaired by Prof. Rafael Cardoso of the Graduate Center of the City University of New York, and Prof. Nancy Lowdnes of McGill University, and, together with Prof. Lynn Tolman of McGill, was presented at the international symposium ‘The Future of Cities’ held in Montreal from June 2009 to August 2010. The authors’ findings and conclusions were presented at the symposium as a ‘roadmap’ for a future to come, but were otherwise kept as a research project at the City University of New York. 	The report comes as a result of a two-year research project, ‘Operation Anchor’</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘Beyond Buses’, is the result of a two-year research project that followed the original proposals from the Biennale board regarding the role of art in urbanization. The project was divided into two parts. The first part, titled ‘Subversion of Transportation Systems’, investigated the effect of bicycles and public transportation systems on the urban fabric of the Biennale, focusing on the Paris-Tours’ city. The authors’ findings clearly indicate that a strong cultural and urban component is required to make travel to the Biennale more pleasant, more interesting and more transformational. As noted by the authors, such cultural activities are essential for any city’s future. Unfortunately, the Biennale board has chosen to ignore this critical cultural component in its quest for ‘transformation’ and has instead invested heavily in its transit system, promoting rapid transit and road development along the periphery of the city. As a result, the Biennale is currently</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, it is a new kind of cultural reproduction that seeks to reanimate cultural  	ules and turn them into useful objects through an aesthetic interpretation of their physicality. It is a creative re-construction that seeks to bring to life the cultural elements of an area, while simultaneously understanding the social and spatial conditions that create and foster such elements. In other words, cultural production and urbanization are not ‘natural disasters’ but ‘cultural props’ that can be used to produce social change and alter urban settings through positive urban effects. As such, cultural institutions and their arts departments have a pivotal role to play in envisioning a more ‘just and equitable city’ through sustainable urbanization strategies.  	 urbanization strategies have recently come to refer to the effects of mass transit systems, but in a recent report by the authors, they suggest a new set of strategies that may be equally valid with respect to other modes of urbanization. The report, entitled ‘Beyond Suburbia’, is based on three experiments that the authors conducted in three American and Canadian sub-regions: Toronto, Montreal and Vancouver. The experiments, which they describe as ‘subsidiary projects’ and ‘re-purposes’ of existing transit systems, reveal surprising efficiencies that can be employed in both urban and suburban planning. In the case of subways and Rapid Transit (RTS), the report shows, there is no guarantee that the systems themselves can deliver the benefits of the social democratizing techniques they are designed to support. 	 urbanizers should heed the report’s warning: Suburbs are complex systems with inherent social and spatial tensions. The suburbs that comprise Toronto’s downtown core, for example, are highly mobile and dependent on rail transit, yet are also highly fragmented and urbanized. Rapid Transit (RT) lines have created new jobs in the neighbourhoods that they serve, but the report cautions that</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified,</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified,</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified,</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified,</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines) is the future that is being prepared for us by the machines that are creeping into every aspect of our lives. If, as Turing says, ‘the whole is greater than the sum of the parts’ then it follows that the larger the computer becomes, the more data it can hold, and the more complex the algorithms that run those data-processing systems, the more data is produced. In other words, the more data is collected, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, and the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the more patterns are identified, the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Cur
    <text>presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Curator, Issue 3 (2015), p.2.Download this article as PDFEmily Pringle and Caitlin FarrellDavid Slater are curators for the Liverpool Biennial 2016. They will be presenting their curatorial approach to the exhibition as a ‘presentation’ of the exhibition as a whole. Their project History of Carving: A History of Stone and Wood, will look at a range of artefacts from the site, including cutting tools, mortise and tenon cutters, sawdust, chip boards and more. They will discuss the ways in which the history of carving, including in the context of the Biennial, relates to wider issues of culture and urbanisation in Britain and throughout the world. They will also explore the ways in which the history of medical research might also be relevant in the context of the Biennial. They are both based in Liverpool and have worked together in New York and Liverpool over the past five years.  They’ve also collaborated on an exhibition</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Curator, Issue 10, February, 2012, p.34.Download this article as PDFGraham SmithGraham Smith is a writer and Curator at the Liverpool Biennial 2012 whose work has previously been exhibited at the Miró Di Tella, Venice (2005); L.A. Biennale, Venice (2005); K.G. Paarlberg, London (2005); M.G. Paarlberg, Berlin (2006); T.G. Paarlberg, Amsterdam (2006); N.G. Paarlberg, Oslo, Norway (2006); U.P. Paarlberg, Stockholm, Sweden (2007); F. Paarlberg, Berlin, Germany (2009); M.G. Paarlberg, Oslo, Norway (2010); T. Paarlberg, Manchester, UK (2011); B. Paarlberg, New York, USA (2012); C. Paarlberg, L.A.</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Curator, Issue 3, 2008, p.298.Download this article as PDFGraham Smith is Curator for the Liverpool Biennial 2008. He is the director of the Centre for Contemporary Art Studies at the University of Liverpool, and a Fulbright scholar. His artworks have been commissioned by the Liverpool Biennial, Guggenheim Museum, New Museum, Tate Modern, Tate Britain, and the Arts Catalyst Agency. He is part of the Curatorial Faculty for the Liverpool Biennial 2016, and part of the curatorial team for the 2020 Cairo Biennial. He has written for the New York Times, The New Yorker, The New Republic, The Village Voice, The New Inquiry, Frieze, The Nation, Frieze d/e, The Guardian, The New York Times and many other publications. He has been a presenter on the Sunday Times Best of the Live Arts V &amp; P Show, the Presentation, and the Sunday Times Best of the Future Book.He has co</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Curator, Issue 2 (Summer 2011), p. 91. [5] Graham Smith, The Illustrated Art of Public Art, trans. Donald Clark-Bailey and Stefan Collini, Lanham, MD: Rowman &amp; Littlefield, 1988, p. 21. [6] John Berger, Los Angeles, CA: Guggenheim, 1989, p. 12. [7] John Berger, The Gallery as a Participatory Platform: Theatre, Art, Media, 1998, p. 57. [8] John Berger and Timothy Egan, ‘How to Start a Participatory Theatre Project in LA’s Koreatown’, Theatre Research International - Journal, December, 1988, p. 3. [9] John Berger and Timothy Egan, ‘Here’s How Much Is Too Much: On Participatory Art and the Politics of Taste in Contemporary China’, in The Gallery as a Participatory Platform: Volume Two:</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Curator, Issue 3 (June 2012), p. 12.Download this article as PDFGraham SmithGraham Smith is an arts educationalist and is professor in the departments of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Sydney. His research interests include the visual arts, critical curating, participatory public art and media design. He is currently working as the Curator of Exhibitions and Institutions for Exhibitions at The New Museum. He has written for the Daily Telegraph, The New York Times, The Telegraph and The Guardian, among many others. His work has been exhibited at the Bienal de São Paulo, the New Museum, Delfina Foundation, MOCAD, Museum of Modern Art, Tate Modern, Wallace Stevens Gallery, Tate Britain, Liverpool and Kunsthalle Zu?rich. He is currently Senior Editor of the Wall Street Journal and is a co-owner of the online publication Stages.  He</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Curator (New York: D.A.P. &amp; T.A.P., 2015), p. 6.Download this article as PDFGraham Smith is Curator for Collections at the London and New York Museums and Senior Editor of D.A.P. Archive, which is published by the New York Public Library as part of the Open Access Book Series. His publications include The Open Access Book Series (Open Art Press, New York, 2018), Public Art: A Documentary History (Open Art Press, New York, 2018), and the forthcoming Documentary Series (Open Art Press, New York, 2019). His writing has also been featured in the New York Times, Los Angeles Times, San Diego Union-Tribune, Chicago Tribune, Philadelphia Inquirer, Madison Daily Record, San Francisco Chronicle, Washington Post, London Guardian, Boston Globe and Chicago Tribune. He is the recipient of several awards and has lectured on a wide range of topics, including documentary, critical and cur</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Curator, Issue 10 (September), 2014, p.286.Download this article as PDFTim JeevesTim Jeeves is an independent writer and curator with more than 20 years' experience in the art world. His work in the social domain includes work in communities, including for the deaf-blind, youth and community arts, as well as the 'soft' social world of artists, including for the homeless, those in poverty, and those at the margins. His publications include the Social Practice Research Journal, Social Practice Research Network (SPRN), which he co-founded in 2003, as well as the online journal Public Practice. He has written for the Guardian, The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, among others. He is currently editor-in-chief of SPRN, and the New Inquiry website publishes every Wednesday. He is the host of the online radio show Public Practice, which is part of the Public Practice network. In</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Curator, Issue 2, September 2016, p.3.Download this article as PDFGraham Smith is Curator of Art, Public Art and Workshops at the New Curator, Liverpool, UK. A co-curator of the Biennial, he has curated the permanent collection exhibitions at Tate Modern, Royal Standard, The National Gallery, Tate Britain and the Liverpool John Moores University Art Gallery, among many other exhibitions and publications. With Polly Brannan, he worked as Artistic Director of Liverpool Biennial 2016, where they worked with artist Sylvia Plunderland to commission a series of works from her studio, including a public installation and workshop for the occasion, as part of the Biennial 2016 Work Programme. On two previous occasions, he served as Artistic Director of the New Curator, Liverpool, UK, where he curated the exhibitions of the Victoria and Albert Museum, Tate Modern, Liverpool John Moores University Art Gallery and the John Lennon Anderson: The Life and Times of John Lennon</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Curator, Issue 2, 2013, p.116.Download this article as PDFGraham SmithGraham Smith is an independent writer, Curator for the Liverpool Biennial, and Senior Editor of the online contemporary contemporary contemporary contemporary contemporary art journal Stages. He is a member of the Curatorial Faculty at the Royal College of Arts, and worked on the curatorial team for the 2012 Venice Biennale. His most recent books include The Contemporary Condition: Art, Postmodernism, and the Critique of Art (2013), published by RCA (UK) and Putnam (US) in 2014. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Republic Digital, the New Republic Online, the New Republic TV, the New Republic Blogs, the New Republic iPhone, the New Republic FM, the New Republic Library, the New Republic Messenger, the New Republic News, the New Republic Photo, the New Republic Radio, and the New Republic Web. He is an adjunct curator</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by artist collective Citizen. The collective presents the proceedings of the Liverpool Biennial as a participatory process that invites the audience to become participants in the exhibition through stories, observations, unedited or partially unedited video, documents or other materials. The video can be accompanied by a written narrative that narrates the event as a whole.[3] The idea of ‘presentation’ seems to have captured the imagination of these early digital artists, who used their avant-garde, critical or curatorial approaches to take the narrative as a whole.  A video of the Liverpool Biennial itself, produced by Citizen, can also be found at www.youtube.com/user/citizenarts. The video was released on the group’s Facebook page and can be viewed 10/1 at YouTube. [4] Graham Smith, ‘The Fabric of Public Art: Art's Invisible Fibre’, in The New Curator, Issue 4, 2014, p.193. [5] John Berger, ‘Massive Concurrents’, in The New Curator, Issue 4, 2014, p.176. [6] Jack Burnham, ‘Digital Art and Its Critics’, in The New Curator, Issue 4, 2014, p.183. [7] William Morris, The Global Curriculum Reader, New York, 1970, p.37. [8] David Harvey, parallels, London and New York, 1987, p.3. [9] Interview with David Harvey, The New Curator, July, 2014, p.46. [10] David Harvey, The New Curator, July, 2014, p.47. [11] Interview in Harvey, op. cit., p.12. [12] Interview with David Harvey, The New Curator, September, 2014, p</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training from the Centre for Addiction and Mental Health (CAMH), which is run by Dr. Nancy‐Jane Green, formerly of the Toronto Psychiatric Centre. Green is a psychiatrist who specialises in treating patients with addictions to drugs and alcohol. She has a particular interest in treating ‘transactional behaviour’ – the shifting of resources and of time in the service of making more money – which is evident in the way that she deals with situations such as the eviction of housing activists from neighbourhoods in Toronto who are engaged in defending the remaining housing. She responds by characterising the activists as transactionalists, or those who seek to arrange resources in ways that create change through negotiation as opposed to conquest. She goes on to say that they lack the class analysis and media literacy to engage in ‘constructive use’ of resources effectively and politically. She also accuses them of being trapped in ‘transactional capitalism’ and its ‘freeze-dock’</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training in how to use subversion to subvert and subvert the system from the local community of Torontonians who are also undercover. The success of the project seems to depend on how well the local community can work with the new ‘peripheral government’. If the community does not see eye to eye with the new government, or does not feel that they are fully incorporated into the system, the project is likely to backfire and cause problems for the government. If the community sees eye to eye with the new government, and is able to work with the agents, then things tend to move in the direction that the community wants them to go. The difficulty for the community is in deciding what to do with the excess resources generated by the new ‘peripheral’ government. The resources do not exist in a magical fund that can magically flow from hand to hand. Instead, the ‘peripheral’ government spends ‘funds’ to</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training in how to use a taser or baton, and sometimes even manage to acquire a gun. Often times the only fear these armed intruders have is to defend themselves against the people who live in the neighbourhood. However, the people defending themselves against the people armed intruders is often times the very same people who elected these undercover enforcers in the first place.  	[1] The Torontonian Project is a multi-year, community-based participatory art project that was started in the 1980s by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and artist Ron Alperovitz. It is a project that evolved into a full-fledged organisation in the 1990s, but its original commitment to monitoring and documenting urban development and the economic life of Toronto through participatory methods has been a project that is still ongoing.  	[2] See: http://www.torontonianproject.org/. Accessed: 2 July 2017. 	[3] </text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training from the Centre for Working Democracy (CWD), a non-profit that coordinates and builds on the work of the Toronto Police Association. The creation of a police force to combat labour organising in the city seems to go through the CWD’s David Lau‎, who is now commissioner of the Toronto Police Services. During the 1980s and 1990s, the Toronto Police Association (TPA), under the leadership of Jack Layton, was instrumental in creating a solid base for the TPA to work amongst. Layton, along with other senior officers in the force, were actively involved in drafting the federal government’s controversial ‘tort reform’ legislation, which attempted to abolish most civil lawsuits against the state, as well as establishing a national redress scheme for labour-organisations. As a result of these initiatives, the city received substantial federal funding to implement a ‘law and order’ programme across the city. The legislation also established a task force to develop strategies</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training from outside agencies on how to work in the public sphere. One can only imagine the havoc such a policy could unleash. Undercover enforcers may be hired by the local governments or private business owners who benefit from the inflated prices and luxury goods the city exalts. These owners then use the money raised from the public to pay off the police and build garages or skyscrapers in the surrounding area. These structures are usually empty unless there is a major construction project underway, and the money doesn’t help the housing crisis any. Meanwhile, the ‘peripheral’ – the neighbourhood residents – are left holding the bag. This is a classic case of overbuilding and underdevelopment. The neighbourhood is stretched thin and does not have enough affordable housing to support a core community. The emergence of public realm has been a necessity in the Torontonian metropolis for a reason. The city has to find affordable housing for the growing number of residents who work in the downtown</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training from the Centre for Working Democracy (CWD), a federally funded cooperative where members volunteer their time in various ways. For example, when the TDS was first established, it was run by retired police officers who provided operational and technical support to the new cooperative. Over time, however, many of the members left and new people joined the cooperative. In the early 1990s, the police union decided to re-organise the cooperative and started a campaign to have the cooperative recognised as a union workplace. The workers in the early 1990s were mainly women and children and had a strong political orientation. As a result, the campaign was extremely effective and the cooperative soon became one of the most advanced in the city. The campaign also harnessed the resources of the city’s most powerful interests, which was very helpful in convincing the city council that the cooperative should be allowed to remain a union workplace. Despite the campaign’s success, the city council had little choice but to act because the cooperative</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training in the art of understatement from the local law enforcement officers who teach the counter-culture movement how to lie. The counter-culture movement is able to negotiate this kind of training with the help of legal advocates who put pressure on the city to change its drug policy. One example of this can be found in the writing of a number of neighbourhood groups that emerged as a result of the drug war. These neighbourhood groups used the names ‘Toronto Community Land Trusts’ and ‘Parti City Council’ to apply for city funding, but instead of using this to build community centres, they used the money to buy guns and ammunition. The acquisition of this kind of weaponry is legal under the Meech Lake Accord, but the tension between the legal and illegal use of such funds is immense. If the guns and ammunition are not used in accordance with the accord, the money is forfeited and can be used against the recipient in court. If the recipient of the funds loses a legal</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training in the use of deceptions and subterfuges from a ‘performer’ in the art of seduction, and so the game is raised to the surface. The subversion and subversion of the system appears to be a mainstay of the ‘peripheral’; at least, that is, until the advent of the ‘central’ government, which appeared to temper the tendency towards state power by setting aside certain types of authority altogether. It is interesting to note that the ‘central’ government did not emerge overnight; it was the work of successive waves of successive provincial governments and territories that were keen to assert their jurisdictional rights and so the ‘central’ became the locus of all things ‘peripheral’. For example, the British North America Federation (now the Canadian Federation) proclaimed its intent to protect the North American character of its constitution from being subverted by internationalist federalism.  	[</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training from the same primary schools, secondary daycares, daycares in the area, and even neighbourhood gangs. The tactics and parameters of this interaction are as yet unclear, but it seems that the enforcers have fully acquisitive access to the city’s vast and increasingly unmanageable databases, and can use these to subvert and subvert the city’s political and legal order.This is not the first time that the US government has attempted to subvert and subvert the Torontonian political order. In 1971, for example, the CIA supported the Indian Agent Movement (I.A.M.) by supporting the creation of a clandestine paramilitary force comprised of professional and student volunteers, codenamed Thunder Bay Rifles, to combat what the CIA considered a growing separatist movement in the name of national security. The R.I.M. was a hybrid Indian Movement founded in 1972, and its constitution declared that a) participation in the Indian Act was a right</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] and the ever-present, yet now invisible, traffic on the internet. The aim of the project seems to be to create a public realm in which the local and the ‘peripheral’ are able to exist in parallel.[9] The project seems to be working in tandem with the local government in their war on drugs policy. Undercover officers from the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) are operating in the area and using the pretence to monitor and confiscate the locals’ property. The intention appears to be to create a new ‘peripheral government’ where the local and the ‘peripheral’ do not coexist.Undercover DEA agents and their local enforcers operate like wild cats through the urban landscape of the Torontonians. They break into homes, taking whatever is on the premises as bargaining chips, and using whatever is not used to subvert and subvert the system. Undercover officers often get training from the Centre for Working Democracy (CWD), a federally funded co-operative that is run by the Toronto Police Department (TPS). The officers’ involvement in the housing sector is also a point of reference for officers to develop policy and develop tactics. For example, the involvement of the TPS in the provision of public housing to the growing ranks of young professionals entering the labour market after years of postsecondary training is documented. The involvement of the TPS in the provision of illegal parking to commercial and industrial zones is also documented. The involvement of the TPS in the provision of free and cheap college textbooks is also documented. The involvement of the TPS in the provision of affordable housing to newly minted high-school graduates is also documented. The inclusion of the historically disenfranchised in the reckoning of success in this massive and ever-expanding urban sector is also documented. The involvement of young people in the provision of basic public services is also documented, such as free or cheap parking,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit.,
    <text>might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit., p.250.Download this article as PDFJennifer Francis and Christian Ulrik Are We Living Through a Katrina?, Atlantic Monthly, October, 2004.Download this article as PDFJennifer Francis and Christian Ulrik, The Long Twentieth Century: Global Currencies since 2006, John Benjamins, New York, 2006.Download this article as PDFJennifer Francis and Christian Ulrik,  	Atlantic Monthly, September/October, 2005.Download this article as PDFJennifer Francis and Christian Ulrik,  	The Economic as a Global Concept, Greenwood Pincus, New York, 2006.Download this article as PDFJennifer Francis and Christian Ulrik,  	Atlantic Monthly, September/October, 2007.Download this article as PDFJennifer Francis and Christian Ulrik,  	The Economic as a Global Concept, Greenwood Pincus, New York, 2006.Download this article as PDFJennifer Francis, The Expanding Geographies of Space,  	The New York Times</text>
    <text>might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit., p.39.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in English and General Education at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta. His research interests include postanarchism, science and technology studies, and art and infrastructure. His dissertation examines the geologic and climatological basis of the recent global average temperature increase of approximately 0.8°C. He is also the editor and co-founder of the peer-reviewed journal Geology. His work has been featured in several periodicals including the New York Times, the Wall Street Journal, the Washington Post and the Los Angeles Times. He received a Bachelor of Arts in English and Cultural Studies from Mount Royal University and an MPhil in Geology and Geophysics from the University of Alberta.Taxis for TakersMargo HaugenDr. Margo Haugen is the Director of Research Services for the Toronto Art Gallery. She holds a Bachelor of Arts in English and Cultural</text>
    <text>might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit., p.250.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes and the Significance of Money, Paul Halsall, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1992, p.221.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes and the Significance of Money, Paul Halsall, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1992, p.223.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes and the Significance of Money, Paul Halsall, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1992, p.224.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes and the Significance of Money, Paul Halsall, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1992, p.225.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes and the Significance of Money, Paul Halsall, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1992, p.226.Download</text>
    <text>might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit., p.250.Download this article as PDFJohn UrryJurassic Park, 1995. Directed by Steven Soderbergh.Original script by Steven Soderbergh.With Steve Backus.As subtitles.Shot on location in Egypt, Israel and the West Bank.2016. Noah BaumbachProducer: Noah Baumbach.Director: Noah Baumbach.Satellite. Photo: Mashal Khan.PreviousNextSatellite. Photo: Mashal Khan.The Other Side of the Sun, 2015. Directed by Steven Soderbergh.Set in the shadow of the pyramids, the story revolves around a group of Jewish teenagers who move into an estate owned by a Muslim family. The film documents their early years in the UK, the Middle East and Africa, and explores the legacy of Jewish flight. The protagonist, a teenage Jewish girl, makes a decision that will forever change her life. Isolated from her peers, she embarks on a journey across</text>
    <text>might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit., p.4.  9  Keynes, op. cit., p.36.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is Professor in Research in Culture and Society at the Winchester School of Art, where he directs the CSCO's Programme for Study of Communal Knowledge &amp; Operation (2012-2015). His work has addressed issues of community and collective deliberation in contemporary art, including the participation of artists and communities in the creation of social and political change. His latest work, Participatory Publishing, was published by The RPC in March 2015, and was presented at the Riverside School of Art's 2015 Cooper-Humanitarian Award Ceremony. His writing has been featured in publications including the New York Times, the Washington Post, and the New Republic, and he has received an array of accolades and mentions for his work. He serves on the boards of several local arts organizations, as well as being an advisor for the nonprofit organisation Global Action</text>
    <text>might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit., p.20.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John. Keynes: A Portrait. 1909. Illustrated Collection, Photographer:   Samson Kambalu. 1909. Rafaleh Mosque, Jerusalem, Israel.Judea and Samaria Collection/The Hebrew University Museum, Hebrew University Archives, Jewish Quarter, Jerusalem, Israel.Judea and Samaria Collection/The Hebrew University Museum, Hebrew University Archives, Near Eastern Quarter, Jerusalem, Israel.Judea and Samaria Collection/The Hebrew University Museum, Hebrew University Archives, Eastern Quarter, Jerusalem, Israel.Judea and Samaria Collection/The Hebrew University Museum, Hebrew University Archives, Judaic Quarter, Jerusalem, Israel.Judea and Samaria Collection/The Hebrew University Museum, Hebrew University Archives, North Africa and the Levant, Jerusalem, Israel.Judea and Samaria Collection/The Hebrew University Museum, Hebrew University Archives,</text>
    <text>might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit., p.34.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John (1843–1920) was a British economic theorist. He was a leading exponent of Keynesianism, which advocated a swift response to recessions and depressions through spending cuts and tax increases. Keynes advocated a similar strategy for the postwar period, arguing that an economy based on the &quot;race to keep&quot; was better than one based on the &quot;break-even&quot; of borrowing against the publics. In a 1944 essay ‘Matter and Money’, he argued that a spending cut was better than a tax increase because it was counter intuitive and would fail when the public ‘gets the message’. Excerpts from his more than twenty-five journal articles are included in the book Keynes – A Second Coming of the English Political Economist.The Economic Consequences of the Napoleonic WarsA.     The Napoleonic Wars, 1688–1819B. The Rise of British</text>
    <text>might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit., p.268.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John. Keynes: The Triumph of Political Economy over Descriptive Economics. New York: Columbia University Press, 1944.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John. Keynes: The Triumph of Political Economy over Descriptive Economics. New York: Columbia University Press, 1942.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John. Keynes: The Triumph of Political Economy over Descriptive Economics. New York: Columbia University Press, 1943.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John. Keynes: The Triumph of Political Economy over Descriptive Economics. New York: Columbia University Press, 1943.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John. Keynes: The Triumph of Political Economy over Descriptive Economics. New York: Columbia University Press, 1943.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John. Keynes: The Triumph of Political Economy over Descriptive Economics. New York: Columbia University Press, 1943.Download this article as</text>
    <text>might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit., p.125.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloDr. Michael Truscello is an assistant professor in English and General Education at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta. His research interests include postanarchism, science and technology studies, and art and infrastructure. His dissertation examines the geographies of infrastructure, from the European model of the ‘helicopter’ to the United States’s levee system. He has worked with local communities to develop and lead stakeholder dialogues. His work has received a mix of positive and negative responses, with mixed results. His research is currently investigating how infrastructure affects communities and their access to information, culture, and labour. His dissertation looks at the quixotic project of rebuilding Montreal’s Port of Montreal following the 2014 disaster.Download this article as PDFDr. Tara LynchDr. Tara Lynch is an assistant professor in English and Teaching at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta. Her research interests include post</text>
    <text>might be curated). 	 1  	2   1  John Urry, ‘The Race Card: Leverage, Rebellion, and the Origins of the New Economy’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, February,  2014, p.335.  3  John Perkins, ‘Capital in Crisis’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Spring, 2014, p.407.  4  John McWhorter, ‘Transforming the Economy for the Common Good’,  	Global Positioning, vol. 25, no. 2, Fall, 2014, p.415.  5  Howarth, op. cit., p.3.  6  Keynes, op. cit., p.34.  7  Keynes, op. cit., p.35.  8  The Economist, op. cit., p.28.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes, The General Theory, Penguin, London, 1983, p.301.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes, The General Theory,Pengu, London, 1984, p.301.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes, The General Theory,Pengu, London, 1985, p.301.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes, The General Theory,Pengu, London, 1985, p.301.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes, The General Theory,Pengu, London, 1985, p.301.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes, The General Theory,Pengu, London, 1985, p.301.Download this article as PDFKeynes, John, Keynes, The General Theory,Pengu, London, 1985, p.301.Download this article as PDFKeynes,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future,
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future, http://www.askai.com/2017/09/16/how-future-science-infuses-our-societies-future/[8] includes a number of technologies that could one day be enabled by sensors embedded in objects or devices. For example, sensors on vehicles monitor engine noise to detect engine emissions, and vehicle kinetic energy to detect the presence of other vehicles, such as cyclists, pedestrians and windsurfing, thereby becoming part of a driver’s knowledge base. Automated vehicle diagnostics could also provide information on road conditions, such as rain, to improve driving conditions. This kind of granular data can be gathered from a driver’s current environment, gathering crucial information for the future of the road ahead.Download this article as PDFAdrian BaileyAdrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal and a member of the Advisory Board of the Future of Life Institute</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future, is published by Bloomsbury (£18.95), and will be in the print version of the journal from September 2018 onwards.Download this article as PDFAdrian BaileyAdrian Bailey is an independent writer. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the Computer Journal. His work has addressed a wide range of topics including the intersection of computer and cultural history, intelligent agents and cultural reproduction, media ecology, and the self in relation to the internet and social media.[8] How to Know About the Future is the story of two cities in transition. It follows two teams of curators as they undertake a collaborative project to bring together the surprising and the unexpected in the future of an unsuspecting London in 2020. Our project is a response to the slow erosion of our national identity as a result of what Michael Hardt calls the ‘global pastiche’ of technological innovation. The future is here, and if we</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future, is titled ‘The Singularity is Near’. It was published in July 2018.The essay draws heavily on the work of philosophers such as Stephen Hawking, Max Brooks and Ray Kurzweil, as well as science writers like Stephen Dubner and Ray Kurzweil. It discusses the philosophical and political questions raised by the growing understanding that artificial intelligence (AI) will one day replace humans in much of the world, and how this will affect cultures worldwide. It also looks to the future, imagining what possible futures may be created by combining AI and the historical data that is fuelling it. The essay ends by suggesting ways to work together to confront these challenges, rather than as adversaries. How to Know About the Future, how to Know About Artificial Intelligence, 2017This essay is the third in a series of reflections on the topic of artificial intelligence (AI) from a philosopher's perspective. The first two parts, ‘Thinking AI: From Theory to Practice’ and �</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future, by contrast, presents a picture of what AI might lead to. It is pessimistic, in part because many of us still believe in progress. However, it is also because many of us still live in the future. We live in a world where machines are smarter than humans – and more intelligent than even Cecil the lion. This is the optimistic scenario.AI is Human-Level Intelligent Machine, but It's Not That Easy to Get Your Head Around What AI Means in PracticeIf you ask most people to define the difference between AI and intelligent machine, most people will tell you that computers are smart enough to recognise pictures and human language. However, this is not always how it happens. Sometimes it’s not even clear what a computer is capable of – although most of us would agree that computers are increasingly capable of breaking things down into components and pieces that can be assembled into useful pieces. So while computers today can do amazing things, and even triumphsly manage to predict the future, there is</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future, by contrast, proposes a future in which citizens do not possess the technology to forecast the future, but rather to adapt to it. It reads like a manifesto for conscious AI, in which citizens share in the future’s outcomes. While the book is ambitious and potentially useful, many of the questions raised by the book are too important to be left to philosophers and technologists to work through. It is up to us, as readers, to decide how to use this knowledge and to tackle the future with creativity, reason and/or faith in our own success.Download this article as PDFAdrian BaileyAdrian Bailey is an independent writer, academic with a special interest in the social implications of computer algorithms. His work has addressed topics of faith and reason since the 1980s, and is particularly influenced by the work of Søren Kierkegaard and Søren Atwood. He is the co-founder of company Rapid7, which develops novel reporting and data mining tools for law enforcement,</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future, began as a blog entry in the journal Computer Journal and has since been featured in Wired UK, The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New Urbanist, Creative Time, Frieze, and many more publications worldwide.Download this article as PDFAdrian BaileyAdrian Bailey is an independent writer, Professor in Computer Science at Liverpool John Moores University, UK, and Director of the Centre for Creative Technologies (CCT) in Liverpool. His books include the foreword to the forthcoming 3rd European Conference on Creative Technologies and the essay collection SH4C: Systems, People and Cybernetics. His recent work in three cultural zones includes the installation for Liverpool Biennial 2018 of works by AI company DeepMind, which incorporate new ways of understanding how bodies interact in urban environments, including the use of bio-computer networks to monitor and analyze urban environments, as well as a project exploring the connections between animation and media culture. He is a co-curator of</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future, edited by Bailey and Willsdon, is a new book that takes the reader on a journey through the concepts and technologies of AI and human-computer interaction. It draws on experiences of discovery and discovery of meaning in the present, and the historical and contemporary effects of that meaning.Download this article as PDFLA's 'Knowledge Nation' projectSue Bell YankSue Bell Yank is a writer, producer and co-founder of Bell Yank Productions, an independent production company that produces work in a wide range of subject matter, ranging from music to film. She has a particular interest in the intersection of science and culture, with projects including the Human Genome Project, which sought to map the human genome, and is the co-director of the New York–based Skeptical Science blog. She has written for Wired, The New York Times, The Guardian, The Washington Post and Oprah Winfrey. She is a co-author of the forthcoming nonfiction book How the</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future, is published by Signet Books (£19.95), and is available now from Signet Books.Download this article as PDFAdrian BaileyAdrian Bailey is an independent writer, speaker, researcher and consultant. He is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal and is Editor of the online digital journal Stakeout. He is a member of the Advisory Board of the UK’s Open Technology Institute and has written for Wired UK, The Observer, The New York Times and The Guardian. He is also Editor of the online journal Stakeout and is a regular columnist for The Computer Journal. His book Future City: The Rise of Digital Extremity is due out in 2015.Bailey’s work has previously addressed the role of culture in the prevention and mitigation of certain forms of human suffering, from famine and war to urban sprawl and surveillance. His most recent work, titled The Fourth Machine, examines the ways in which machine learning is set to change everything from</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future, by contrast, imagines a future where computer algorithms do the heavy lifting – monitoring and augmenting – rather than humans. It is a ‘best guess’ that incorporates all the assumptions of the present as a whole, but with smarter and nimbler chips embedded in the fabric of the future. This is the assumption that is being made by both the AI and the biopsychosocial community in our current and forthcoming public policies. In the AI community, this would mean that individuals with specific augmentative or cognitive augmentative therapies would be able to connect to the medical system and find out whether their behaviour has been modified by the research team, and thus potentially switch off their devices. In the case of a fully cognitive augmentative therapy, this would mean that patients and researchers could develop tools to monitor and alter their behaviour, rather than having to rely on faith in the skills of individual users to do this.In her book When Will AI Take Over?: Systems Thinking and the Form of Culture</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the future.’[5]This sounds like a description of some dystopian future, but there is some light at the end of the tunnel. There is a chance that in a few years, our descendants may still visit the shops in the Welsh Streets and recognise the signs: a few decades earlier than the computer models currently envisaging the future. How to Know About the Future, a new book by Adrian Bailey, describes the way in which ‘aware AI’ can be used to anticipate the future: how, for example, individuals with a genetic predisposition to develop Alzheimer’s might be augmented with software that monitors the activity of their brain waves, thereby enabling the monitoring of medication intake and behaviour.[6] Adrian Bailey is an independent writer, engineer and consultant. He is Professor of Computer and Information Science at the University of Exeter, and is Editor-In-Chief of the peer-reviewed Computer Journal.[7] How to Know About the Future, is a new book published by Oxford University Press that looks to the future through the lens of computer modelling. It attempts to bring together elements from different disciplines to create a shared vocabulary of concepts relevant to the contemporary world. It draws together elements from topology, qubit, fractal, object and even biology to create a topology of concepts relevant to the contemporary world. The project was co-founded by Professors from the Department of Information, Digital Culture and Society (DVCAS) at the University of Southampton and Birkbeck, University of London, and is co-written by Professors from the Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering at the University of Sydney. The contributors have a range of diverse specialisations and disciplines that intersect in a dense web of overlapping relevance. The project was designed to deliver a fresh perspective on topics relevant to the contemporary world through the modelling of human behaviour through the experimentation of computer-aided design (DCD). The book aims to present a collection of responses to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is
    <text>The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is to present the latest exhibition as an event in itself. It’s a rarefaction whose main interest is in presenting, and engaging in, a celebration of art and culture. It’s a rarefaction whose main product is a curated schedule of exhibitions that takes into consideration the idiosyncratic needs of contemporary art’s customers. And it’s a rarefaction whose main product is curatorial appointments that last for decades to centuries.The only way to acquire this elusive element of the modern museum that serves as its own measure of cultural sophistication is for museums to develop ever more of a presence on the cityscape, taking into consideration what kind of knowledge can be gathered from the multitude of stakeholders, local stakeholders, pedestrians, visitors, and curators who populate it. This is the biennial in its current form, and it does this by virtue of having patrons from all over the city. The fact that it started as a pub devoted to displaying paintings and hosting concerts soon</text>
    <text>The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is to transport people – visitors – to places where they can buy things, do well in life and generally have a good time. It’s a rare occasion on which visitors can truly move away, leaving behind the fixed gaze that characterises the Biennial experience. And it’s this rare occasion that the Biennial itself has any agency – it’s either a symptom of the pathology of tourism (which it does not really look like) or an effective intervention.In order to truly disentangle the Biennial from its surrounding urban environment, a more dynamic and interesting exhibition format could serve as the counter intuitive and invisible hand it needs. And this is the way in which biennials, like other curatorial forms, are inherently sedentary. They rarely plan for the future, preferring to inhabit the now rather than build it. And this is the particular limitation of the present; it’s impossible to predict the future but can certainly to the past.The only way to</text>
    <text>The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is to provide a permanent exhibition venue for a particular art form: Diptych painting, monograms, monochrome, monograms and so forth. It does this through what’s colloquially referred to as the ‘biennial model’: the art fair, the museum, the street. It also provides a set of tools for the artist to make things happen in the city that aren’t planned, controlled or ordered by the institution. And yes, it does require a certain amount of coordination and hand-wringing from above. But it also has a great ability to take things away from us when they’re most needed.The question then becomes how to coordinate the different elements of the city in such a way as to make them all work in concert to create something new, something productive andque naturaleza algo fresco? This may require the intervention of a mayor or other influential political figure. But at the very least, a mayor</text>
    <text>The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is to provide a platform, a way to exchange, to educate and entertain, to take part in a cultural process that’s as natural as it is complicated, and to hopefully one day become a significant part of a city’s cultural landscape. But it is also an institution that has a mortal duty, which is to produce, to keep alive, to deliver, to take part in a humanistic, even if radical mission. And it’s this mortal duty that comes with a set of lethal constraints.So while the Biennial in its current form may have begun as a way to make connections between different parts of the city, and between artists and venues, it is also an institution that is obliged to deliver something in return for its patronage. And something that it does deliver, which is increasingly clear is something that it cares about more than it cares about its citizens or the city in which it exists. This is a fundamental change from the past, and it is a change that</text>
    <text>The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is to host a series of exhibitions, and to do so in an annualised way. It is, in fact, capable of doing so in perpetuity, although it would be a mistake to read this as an end-product of this formula. As mentioned earlier, the Biennial was originally conceived as a cultural exchange, exchanging cultural knowledge across disciplines. The exhibitionary form has since been expanded to allow for the exchange of knowledge between disciplines, and to permit the presentation of new knowledge via talk, demonstration, or demonstration. At the same time, the exhibitionary form has contracted to take on a life of its own, forgoing its original mission of gathering knowledge and spreading it.The exhibitionary form may well be the form of the future; it can and should be international. But it cannot possibly be the form of the past; it must be something new. This is the congruence that art needs in order to tell its story. And right now, that’s what we need</text>
    <text>The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is to offer exhibitions, and its various subsidiary missions are a part of the financing of that mission. So it may be that the mission of the Biennial is to create exhibitions, and the mission of its subsidiary organizations is to fund those exhibitions. But there is much more going on than that.There’s the rub, and here’s the rub: the Biennial has two kinds of visitors: those who come to see it happen, and those who come to buy things. Regular visitors to the museum are the rest of us, and we’re only customers. But those visitors who come to the museum for the first time are the rest of us, and we’re in on that. We don’t get paid to be here, and we don’t get paid to be here long. So when the museum first started, the visitors were the rest of us, and we were holding court in the galleries, trying to figure out what we could do</text>
    <text>The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is to offer exhibitions of contemporary art to satisfy an exhibitionary demand. It’s a venue to be visited, a platform to be explored, a receptacle to be exploited, a source of profit, and, above all, a place to be experienced, to be enjoyed and to be reminded of all the time.But it is possible that over time, this experience may have a character or set of characteristics that are more akin to that of an institution like a museum. That is, perhaps, the essential ‘museum-like’ quality that makes a city unique and distinguishes it from other museum-like cities. And perhaps it is possible that the institutional memory that was designed to serve an institutional audience could also be applied to the unique and the magical.That would make the biennial an organization like any other museum, in that it would capture and preserve and give substance to the memory of time in a way that a museum would never do. It would capture and preserve and give substance</text>
    <text>The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is to court money (and, by extension, tax-payers): to be seen to be going places, to be seen to be happening, to be seen to be happening now. And it’s doing just that.It’s the appearance. It’s the beak.It’s the nose.It’s the face.It’s the whole package.And what’s the message? The message is: Be seen now, be seen now, and most importantly, be seen by others to be happening.Because that’s what you do now, when you’re nowhere to be seen. And it’s what you do when you’re nowhere to be seen: you introduce a thing or idea or concept or culture to a larger audience than your local one, or it’s seen by so many people it’s forgotten what it was intended for. And that’s what the Bi</text>
    <text>The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is to support the artistic endeavours of the city, and to that end it tends to produce practitioners whose main concern is insular self-indulgence, whether that’s aural or visual. But it could also conceivably seek to rescue what it calls ‘art’ from the city, by providing a platform for artists to engage with the politics of displacement, emigration and cultural consumption in the wake of industrial decline, and thereby helping to form a new urbanity. We can only speculate about what that new urbanity might entail, but we can say with some confidence that it’s going to involve a lot of taxis, because that is the kind of politics that the Biennial is likely to engage, and which politics it is obliged to champion.And that brings us to another point…The Biennial was started by artists, for artists.Now it’s run by artists. And artists’ contributions continue to be incorporated into the organisation’s DNA</text>
    <text>The next Biennial may be in the offing, but for now we’re here to stay. If you want to come, join us. If you don’t, don’t come. We can’t possibly go on like this. It’s not in keeping with the ethos of the Biennial, and it’s not in keeping with the city. But we’re here to stay.Because this is us, in private.Underage, mind you.Curtains are off.No crotch, no balls.But we’ve got to be real, because otherwise we’ll all be like the rats in that classic painting: stuck in a rat-infested mausoleum, unable to move forward, unable to deal with change, unable to cope with anything.And we’re here to stay. The Biennial will always be there.In its current form, it’s an institution whose primary mission is to provide a convenient way for artists to meet each other, to be accepted by other artists, and to occasionally, on rare occasions, to provide a platform for the exercise of creativity within a community. It’s a community of artists, of which we are a part, and whose artists form the basis of what constitutes a community. It’s a community whose artists are active in promoting and contributing to the activity of the Biennial, and it’s a community whose artists form the basis of what constitutes a community.If there’s going to be a biennial, it’s essential that the community itself should be involved, because otherwise there’s going to be a big problem. I don’t mean this in a patronising way: the institutionalised support for the activity of the biennial would have to be significant, and I don’t mean it by how many exhibitions it has: the community would have to actively participate in making</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice.
    <text>presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice. This is another reason why biennials can be so open-ended, because we already have so many other forms of social interaction happening in the city – cultural, economic, sexual, emotional – and thus the exhibitionary complex is already overflowing with material from which to choose. Biennials can then further expand their audience through experimentation and discovery, and can find new forms of social interaction through experimentation and discovery. But they are most effective when they actively seek out new ways of engaging with the city, and this has been one of my goals as an artist and urbanist, because the new ways of engaging with the city seem to be happening at an extremely rapid pace, and this is what I see emerging from the curatorial hand-wringing and mumbling. The curatorial voice that I hear most often these days is the voice of the planner, and while the planner has a point of view and an idea of the city that is valid and validating, it is also critical that the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice. The introduction of such concepts and techniques into the social and cultural landscape would be a major element of the project’s objectives. For example, the introduction of social media and online culture would be important for the project’s goals and values. The introduction of new media would require an artistic and curatorial hand, but it would also require that these new media be utilized constructively, that is, that they must be used in a way that contributes to the production of knowledge and understanding of the contemporary world. The curatorial and artistic approach to the medium of the mixed medium would be invaluable in this context, because it is historically derivative and relies on assumptions and ideologies that are historically unstable. For example, the exhibition would not be possible without the strong collaboration and patronage of the Museum of Modern Art and the Ford Foundation, whose financial support, in turn, depends on the Museum of Modern Art’s continued funding. The mixed medium would have to be used constructively and creatively to generate knowledge</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice. And what I mean by that is to do something completely new, something completely unexpected, and yet respectful of everything that has come before it. This is something that I see in the exhibitions that are happening now, and to some extent will come after. And what I mean by this is that they will be performing a function that no other art form can perform, that transcends its parameters and boundaries. And this is what biennials can do, because they are the only form of art institutionally capable of performing this kind of radical social change. The other art forms have to be formed into groups and commissions, or institutions, that balance the need for art production with the need for social interaction, and so they are traditional artists’ institutions that have to be made into artists’ social organisations. And so, I see the biennial as a future-looking art form that is constantly questioning its parameters and making creative new situations, situations that it is now more or less exposed to. It</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice. Think of how Twitter changed the social dynamics of the social, including the relationship between the public and the public space, the public and the public of stories. These transformations have been so dramatic, and so far have not yet fully materialised, as we humans struggle to cope with the new social realities we will inevitably encounter – and which need to be worked through in order to be faced – but they can and must be faced. I think this is why biennials are so important, because they can so radically re-animate what is traditionally considered ‘normal’, making it something completely new and unexpected. Yet they are also crucial in that they constantly prod us to bring these new social realities into being, always asking, ‘What could be different?’ This is precisely what biennials can do, and so it is that they exist in this current moment at this very moment, and so we can learn something from their example and from the experimental and theoretical work that is being</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice. And this is precisely what has happened in the last twenty years, as a consequence of the proliferation of social media and the consummation of the contemporary condition: to some extent, I might add, because of the consummation, since people want to be entertained and do things online and off-platform, and because of the condition itself. But I think also of this condition in relation to other possibilities, which are always open to change, which are related to the dynamic of the contemporary condition. I think that there are other possible worlds and that we inhabit them too, which are not always presented as being produced by or in the interests of the contemporary condition, which is why artworks like the piece by the Biennaleeers here are so exciting and so unexpected. The ‘real’ world is always imagined in terms of the conditions of [a particular] moment in time, and artworks like the piece by the Biennaleeers here indicate how we can inhabit ‘that</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice. And this is precisely what biennials can do. But there is another kind of biennial that is being actively developed in Portugal. And that is the kind that seeks to be a kind of nexus between biennials and cities, and between biennials and politics, and between biennials and science, and between biennial and culture. And this is the kind of biennial that I see emerging in Lisbon right now, as part of the city’s ‘culture city’ initiative’. This is the kind of biennial that seeks to ‘reanimate’ urban decay and to create ‘safe spaces’ for its citizens to live and work in, through cultural practices, through a ‘city to itself’. This is the kind of biennial that I see emerging in Lisbon right now, as part of the city’s ‘culture ring’. The ‘culture ring’ is a familiar, if somewhat limited</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice. And here I come to the second dimension of the biennial, the dimension of its own precariat that is, in effect, created through the medium of the biennial. The biennial is the only type of art museum that can claim to be both a museum and a festival, a type of art institution that exhibits works from its collection and publicly appraises its collection. And in this sense, biennials are the only types of art institutions able to achieve this potential. But what I find so fascinating about the potential of biennials to create their own social function is that they’re able to do this through their collections, because they have such a marked historical relationship to the art that they have on view, and this has such a bearing on their ability to do so. For example, the biennial collection is a set of pictures that began as a set of pictures that came from a gallery in New York. The picture books that came out of this collection were written and illustrated</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice. And this is precisely what I’m doing here in Liverpool, trying to engage audiences from beyond the biennial complex through what was originally intended to be a one-to-one interaction between artist and audience. It’s a radically new kind of encounter.But what are the boundaries that limit what is considered ‘normal’? And what is considered ‘acceptable’? And what is considered ‘acceptable’? And what is considered ‘radical’? And what is considered ‘acceptable’? And what are the limits of what can be considered ‘radical’? And what are the boundaries of what can be considered ‘radical’?And what are the limits of what can be considered ‘radical’?And what are the limits of what can be considered ‘radical’?And what are the limits of what can be considered ‘radical’?And what are the limits of what can be considered</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice. And this is precisely what I was trying to do with the exhibition I curated, to bring into being radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice that did not follow the conventional, institutionalised way of interacting with the world.Using curatorial speak, I called them ‘non-institutional fads’, and I imagined a time when cultural institutions – or biennials in this case – would develop entirely apart from the world as a public. There would be no big institutions like museums or big publishing houses. There would be no big business empires. There would be no big egos. There would be no big commercial interests. There would be no big marketing campaigns. There would be no big political ones. There would be no big surveillance states. There would be no big financial ones. There would be no big military ones. The list could go on. I could go on.But what I found fascinating about the non-institutional fad was that it allowed me to begin</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and promote the exhibition’s work across social media, especially through the project’s blog. The exhibition would open with a public lecture about the project entitled ‘Exhibitionism?’, and would then move to a more in-depth look at the ideas and techniques behind the exhibition. The exhibition could end with an extended discussion of the key concepts and key directions of exhibition making. In this sense, it would be a mixed medium exhibition. It would aim to introduce the concept of the mixed medium into the exhibitionary complex, because this is what I find so fascinating and novel about the potential of these new media to create new modes of social interaction, new forms of cultural practice, and new kinds of relationships. This is precisely what biennials do best, what I have found so fascinating and so novel about their potential to do is to radically re-impose what is traditionally understood as ‘normal’ into radically new modes of social interaction and cultural practice. And this is precisely what biennials are doing right now, especially in the United States, in relation to Donald Trump and the rise of nationalism.Look at any biennial’s calendar, and you will find a significant proportion of the exhibits being placed on a first-come, first-serve basis. And this is exactly what is happening in Liverpool. You and I do not know each other. We do not know what our role is in this city. We do not know what the other is doing. And we do not know what the other means. We do not know what the other is doing. And we do not know what the other has been doing. And we do not know what the other is doing. And we are the bystanders, we are the mumps, the tepid bystanders, the bystanders who cannot say a word or do anything. And we are the cities, the districts, the towns and the villages that are the laboratories of this experiment. And</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
