<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget of over $100 million and a staff of over one hundred people. But the market was becoming increasingly unpredictable and unpredictable places were opening up for the exchange of commodities and financial services were appearing in places such as Hong Kong and Dubai. And so Stratfor went back to its roots – it was becoming increasingly important for the firm to be able to monitor and control what was happening in the market, so that it could respond appropriately when it was told that something wasn’t quite right. And so the model that emerged was that of a corporation – it had a board of directors, MPs, and members of the royal family – but its real power came from the exchange of commodities on a global market. And so the role of the MPC was to monitor the market and so the city, and the market for intellectual property – not to mention its other functions, such as supporting the firm’s role in the event of a crisis – came to be seen as a very real and present threat.</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget of over $100 million and a staff of over 1,000 people. But then in the early 1990s, the Arab oil shocks and subsequent economic crises and the fall of Sa·mallameh, and the subsequent massacre of over 2000 people in Kuwait, and the ensuing civil war that broke out between the government and ‘Free Kuwait’ supporters, and that became known as the ‘Protocols of the Elders’ – the draconian and far-reaching edicts that became known as the ‘Takfiriya Declaration’ – and the rule of law was severely curtailed.So, the trajectory of Stratfor’s growth and eventual adoption by the Egyptian government is a very interesting one; it begins with the early 1990s oil shocks, and it ends with the oil crisis of 1991. During that time, the number of Egyptians trained as Egyptologists in the United States and Europe rapidly increased; by the early 2000s, the Egyptian National Museum</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget of over $100 million and a staff of around 1,000 people. Then the Arab oil crises in the mid 1990s and the US–Soviet embargo in 1994–95, and the ensuing economic crisis, and the implosion of the Burhanato [5] empire, and the subsequent rise of national economies based on oil, were huge. So the failure of the early privatisations and the Arab Spring in 2011 meant a radical rethinking of the logic of state building and capitalist socialisation in the region. Stratfor’s mission statement in the early 1990s was much more philosophical: it no longer identified itself as a set of ideas, but rather as a set of practices, a set of ‘rules of engagement’ that it was required to follow in order to ­become a recognised entity. And these ‘rules of engagement’ – which revolve around the concept of state – are fundamental to understanding why states collapse. State capitalism as a social system, and</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget of around $5 billion and a staff of over 1,000 people. But by the time of the Arab oil embargo in the early 1990s, and the financial crisis in the late 1990s, the business was in crisis. It shuttered its retail operations, and its office was mothballed. It couldn’t compete in the oil markets, and so it folded. It wasn’t until the early 2000s that the city really started to recover; a recovery that seemed especially urgent in the wake of the Arab uprisings, and which some have argued was even more urgent than the Arab revolutions. And while the uprisings that started in 2011 in all their forms – secular, militant and some violent – are clearly signs of a larger cultural shift that is fundamentally about systems, and much of what we mean by the uprisings today is more about individuals exercising power and asserting identity than it is about asserting identity and exerting power. So while I do see some similarities</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget of over $5 billion and employed over 11,000 people. But in the early 1990s, a lot of people lost their jobs, and a lot of them were replaced by machines; a lot of them were replaced by social media; a lot of them were replaced by analytics tools that captured and processed huge amounts of data; and a lot of them were replaced by drone aircraft. And while the city itself is getting increasingly automated, it’s not just the city that is affected. Manufacturing and the service sector is affected as well; things like warehouse management are affected by the rise of digital technologies, and so on. And so the monolith continues to have that weird alien look to it; it’s either the most beautiful building in town or it’s completely taken over by robots. But that weird alien look also has another kind of beauty – the kind of beauty that comes from within. Once upon a time, when people used to live in those old post-Commun</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget of over $10 billion and a staff of over one million. But then the Arab Spring and the end of the cold war in 1991 changed everything; it’s hard to define just how big a part that was. And now there’s a war raging in Syria between the government and ‘opposition’ forces; if you were to ask me, at the moment when the Syrian government started bombing ‘terror’ sites in April 2011, I would have said: ‘Oh yeah, that’s the job of the Stratfor guys. They’re the ones behind the shields and the bomb shelters and the ATGM sites and the medical facilities of the Syrian people. They’re the ones with the thermal imagers and the sniper teams and the AMRA […] And now the whole thing is going down in flames.’[5]A year after 9/11, Timothy Snyderman spoke about the legacy of the first plane crash. He</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget of over $100 million, which is huge in those days. But over the last decade, the company’s organisational skills have started to wear thin; there’s a growing competition for talent between the US and Europe, and the emergence of new technologies of economic monitoring that are more and more capable of monitoring activity in real time. So there’s a sense of this coming together, rather than a separate set of individuals doing something totally different. There’s a new economic order that emerged; firms no longer needed to be centrally planned. There’s a movement towards ever larger and better connected infrastructures. And of course, the internet has given us all unprecedented access to everything that’s happening in a radius around us. So the question becomes: what does it mean to be connected? And what does it mean to be connected in the current socio-political sense? ‘Art’, I think, speaks to the way in which</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget of over $30 million and was considered a premier research institution. But during the neoliberal period – the first half of the 2000s, and continuing even into the current decade – the institutions that provided Stratfor with its funding dried up, and its programming was slashed, leaving it to languish in the red. It still has a small but dedicated fan base, but now it has been taken on by the New York Stock Exchange, which wants to stock its index futures, which means it has to meet strict criteria that include holding a market value and being exchangeable. So it falls into the trap of becoming something that is both a replacement for what used to be called the ‘real thing’ – a thing that has a market – and also a replacement for what is essentially a non-market instrument that once was called the index.1  And so we find ourselves in the mess that is index futures.2  And so we see another contradiction in the spectacle of the index futures</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget of over $100 million and an annual budget of over $4 billion. But in the last decade of the century, things began to fall apart, and now the city is plagued by protests demanding an explanation from the Metropolitan Police Department and Mayor Boris Johnson. There’s a movement – Antifa – but at the moment it has no organisation; there’s no leadership. Antifa is the blunt end of the spear in this fight. And so there’s a vacuum – we don’t have a name for what’s happening in the city, and we don’t have a name for what’s happening elsewhere in the world. There’s a question of priorities and tactics and ideology. And so there’s a moment where we have to figure out what to do.Antifa has a project called De-imagining the City that’s an offshoot of the Stratfor project. It’s an attempt to</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the City Council and given over to a private equity firm. The project was given a name – Stratfor – and a business plan. Its logic was that it could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it, so that Stratfor could be both an extension of its name and the name of the firm that was buying it. So it ‘s like a monolith’. That’s what a monolith is: it’s both the name and the name of the company. And what a monolith it is: it’s both the name and the name of the city. It’s a monument to the logic of the market. Stratfor was born in New York in the 1970s, and its mission statement at the time was to track and analyse economic activity in North Africa and the Middle East. And from the 1970s until the early 1990s, it was very successful; it had a budget of roughly $7 million and a staff of roughly 200 people. But by the early 1990s, the budget for arts programming was firmly established, and the demand for arts funding was declining; the number of artists it could employ was much greater, and the demands for arts education were much more general. The demand for arts education became much more specific: young people in particular were much more interested in developing independent artistic skills than in acquiring formal arts education; they wanted to know what constituted an arts education, and how to access arts resources outside of the school itself. So the demand for an artist’s education shot up, and so did the budget; the school closed, and artists found themselves operating on a shoestring. The school housed only a few buildings, and the buildings sat fallow; there was no arts curriculum, no running arts centre, and no board of directors. There were a few scattered classes, and the classes that existed were run by volunteers; the classes that were funded</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic
    <text>should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ art form emerging in new and unexpected places and at new and unconventional times’.[4] The biennial format has its centre in the city, but it also exhibits its youth, its ‘influences’, and its activities in the ‘countryside’ and ‘tourist’ zones around it. It is an episodic office, conference, and even residency exhibition – exhibiting in galleries and museums around the world – and it takes place in venues including Basel, New York, Taipei, and Los Angeles. It is an exhibition that seeks to understand the cultural geography of a particular city, and it is an episodic but temporary exhibition, exhibiting work from all over the world. It is an episodic but temporary exhibition, and it is in no way a museum. It is a different kind of episodic and temporary, in that it is not exhibiting new art every day, but rather reproductions of old and recent art from different places</text>
    <text>should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ art form experiencing a proliferation of digital and social media’.[4] It encourages us to suspend our disbelief, but to act out what we have never experienced. It makes us dream, but makes us not dream. It inculcates a ‘kindred’ behaviour, but punishes those who disturb its balance. It facilitates a re-construal of time, but places a premium on preservation. It supports a critical ‘reading’ of contemporary art, but punishes those who neglect to reflect on contemporary art’.[5] The visceral, ‘muscular’ display of power and material wealth in the form of art objects, as exemplified by the biennial, is a powerful rhetorical device, capable of generating significant ideological distances. It mobilises cultural capital into contested territory, challenging prevailing narratives. It encourages us to ‘step back’ and ‘look at the bigger picture’, but leaves us with a question mark</text>
    <text>should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ urban form that is being resuscitated in the age of digital photography’.[4] It employs the term ‘avant garde’ to describe what it refers to as its own resorption. It is an avant garde that seeks to understand (through photographic means) what it calls ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more classic urban form that is being resuscitated’. It seeks to expose it as a retrofit for a new urban form that it does not identify, but which it is hoped will one day inhabit the planet. It is an avant garde that seeks to uncover what it calls ‘the odd but unique feature of an older and more classic urban form that is being resuscitated’.[5] It is a retrofit that seeks to inhabit the planet, not in terms of what it actually is, but in terms of what it will become. In that case, the space it takes up would have</text>
    <text>should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ city’, noting its resemblance to a mythical ‘sand dune’ or what Alfred Wegener called the ‘creeping dune’ of the Middle Ages.[4] It targets the modern urban centre, but especially its intellectual, commercial and institutional dereliction. It aims to render, in the words of Wegener, the spread of globalised capitalist society ‘impracticable’ through better infrastructure, education and transport ‘[w]ith or without] urbanisation’.[5] And it makes a case for what it calls ‘a new kind of ‘city-collision’, where the city is recapitulated through a multiplicity of replicas and recreations, each one distinct from the next, articulating qualities of its own kind, namely, its own kind. It is not a proposal of a utopian future urbanism, but a proposal of the present in order to envision a future where, unlike now</text>
    <text>should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ city’ – i.e. that characteristic lack of urbanity and culture that characterises contemporary North American cities – in this case, a metropolis that has incorporated a museum and urban registry (or, in Asia, a registry of street-architecture). It also exhibits the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ city coming to inhabit the digital future, i.e. the digital future. It is, in short, a museum that records and narrates the past, but also the odd but unique feature of an older and more classic urban future: it records but never really narrates it.  [1] See Bernard Stiegler, ed., Stiegler on Cities (2014). [2] See Stiegler, Stiegler on Cities, pp.24–27. [3] See Stiegler, Stiegler on Cities, p.28.Download this article as PDFBernard Stiegler</text>
    <text>should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ form of art contemporaneity, or contemporary art in a contemporary and globalised society, manifested in works from the ‘first half’ of the twentieth century, including works by major artists from the United Kingdom and abroad. It also features a ‘glimmer of promise’ in the form of ‘institutional memory’ and the ‘re-occurrence’ of artworks and artistic practices contemporaneous with those of the first half of the twentieth century.[4] It adopts the format of a museum, although it is not a museum as such, but a museum of a particular kind, namely, one that records, describes or documents the contemporaneous appearance, occurrence or development of a thing, place, practice or set of things, in whatever medium, shape or form it occurs.[5] And this is precisely what the biennial is, in its broadest sense. It records, describes or documents their occurrence, occurring or development.</text>
    <text>should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ art form experiencing a revival in some localities, but with less global circulation and especially in communities of colour’.[4]The advent of digital photography in the 1990s sparked a cultural revolution in many of the world’s largest cities, but it was not until the advent of social media that the vision of art as a social enterprise began to take root in many cities. Art today often serves as a counterweight to the weight of institutional culture, but it is often times more effective at undermining it. The rise of social media and urbanisation coincided with an increase in economic growth, which in turn stimulated artistic practices geared towards accumulation, not consumption. New urban development projects were put forth across the globe, including in predominantly urban centres where the emergence of digital photography and other modes of photography was also fuelling a creative perforation. Thus, the biennial became one of the primary places for artists to be invested in the future prospects of urban and rural life, especially in the</text>
    <text>should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ art form being revived and recommenced in an entirely new form.’[4] It exhibits what it calls ‘the odd but not unique feature of a biennial’, but which is in fact characteristic of cultural capitals throughout the world. As an institution, it exhibits what it regards as an ‘incomplete’ set of characteristics, or a lack of characteristics, which are common to all biennials. It is, in other words, an artefact of the contemporary condition: a curatorial artifact, a contemporary artifact, a ‘weltrihrer’ in the narrow sense of the word. It is also, in the strict sense of the word, a form of modern and contemporary art museum. It is the formal counterpart of a museum, although the former is understood as being in search of the latter. It is an artefact of the museum as an object of cultural consumption, and the consummation of a cultural exchange between cultures</text>
    <text>should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ style of art’ as a feature of a particular region or city.[4] It invites reflection on the notions of biennials in a cultural-political-ideological context through what it terms ‘the odd little ‘feature’ of the biennial’. It also invites critical reflection on the same by way of inquiry. Its proposal is that biennials become not only the objects of their fields, but that they become, as its title suggests, objects of reflection and interpretation. They should, as the saying goes, contain within them ‘the seeds of all that is most distinctive and distinctive[5] about the world we inhabit’. And they should do this in a way that invites further investigation and, in turn, what Jürgen Habermas would call ‘negative reflection’.That is, of course, reacting against the world as it is, not against what is supposedly unique or distinctive about it. Within contemporary art,</text>
    <text>should be curated together as a ‘weltrihrer’, i.e. an institution committed to reproducing, describing or documenting (in any medium) a particular event, performance, place, object, knowledge or practice. In this sense, the museum is contemporaneous with the city for the same reasons that the biennial is contemporaneous with the town or neighbourhood. It exhibits not only what it has witnessed, but also what it may have heard, seen or imagined on a particular day. It exhibits, for example, the huge audience that attended the Liverpool Biennial in 2013; or the fact that the Liverpool Biennial was the first art institution in Liverpool to offer free screening and public lecture programmes.[3] It exhibits what it conceives of as a ‘global’ condition, but which is in fact experienced primarily in the cultural capital of North America, Europe or Asia. It exhibits what it terms ‘the odd but not unique feature of an older and more ‘classic’ style of art’ in an interdisciplinary context, but it also exhibits what it calls ‘a less classic but deeper characteristic of contemporary art’, namely, of a more modern and ‘future-looking’ kind. It calls this feature modernism but it is really an attempt to conceive of a more traditional and ‘historic’ kind of art.[4] The need to intervene contemporaneously with the unfolding political and economic processes that it represents is an important constraint on artistic activity, but it is equally essential to intervene now, before the very social mechanisms that generate contemporary artifice are sufficiently developed to undermine the very fabric of contemporary art. This is what biennials do today: they insert themselves at various moments into the otherwise pre-existing political and economic narratives of a city or neighbourhood; they are, in short, art imitates that is needed to generate social and political change but that is neither contemporary nor classicist in its own right. This kind of</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF25 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova24 January 2015Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsSan Francisco, California24 January 2015Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have an ongoing collaborative project with Sally designed to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF25 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova30 June 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany30 June 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF25 November 2014To Rango Silva27 January 2015Rango SilvaMexico City, MexicoMexico City, Mexico27 January 2015Dear RangoWhat was your perspective on the idea of ‘homecoming’ in the city of my youth, Torreon? I remember Torreon very clearly: it’s the intersection of two intersecting but distinct worlds, with its shifting histories, cultures and political orientations. You were born and raised there, and as a child you always felt like you belonged somewhere. Did you ever feel like you couldn’t find what you were looking for? I imagine that for you, and perhaps for your generation, that was a difficult childhood. The sense of city multiplicity, of the multiple forms of travel and globalisation that it entails, is different from the sense of homecoming that I had growing up.Maybe your perspective is similar to mine: different generations of Brazilians are looking to different planets, and the</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF25 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova30 June 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany30 June 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and their places of exhibition. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to a series of sessions titled: The Resident. Sally has been</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF25 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova29 November 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany29 November 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and their local artworlds. That is, between the Biennial as a biennial and its local artworld, or between a biennial and its location. I agree that in a city like San Francisco, where art is abundant, this relationship is particularly important. But I also think that it’s a synchronic kind of relationship — it starts in the city and carries on all the way down to</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF25 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova32 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany32 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool — we know a lot of people in the city still identify with the Biennial there — but I wanted to make sure I heard you correctly. The Biennial there has a longstanding partnership with the city council to bring exhibitions and cultural activities, and through a per diem system</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF25 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova19 October 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsWashington, US19 October 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and their cities. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool — we have in mind a similar proposal to host the Liverpool Biennial — but there are several differences between the two proposals.1. Biennial means more than just a collection of art or a collection of works: it has to be places where art is exhibited, books or materials brought together, activities taking place in galleries, museums or any type of</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF25 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova29 November 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany29 November 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF25 November 2014To Rob Davies29 November 2014Rob,I wrote to ask about the new exhibition format planned for the Liverpool Biennial, Creative Time: Performance, Time, and Art — Spain, USA. Your idea of ‘performance, time, and art’ seems very pertinent in a world of constant digital media consumption. Could you explain how the new form of art time is framed within this new media paradigm? Also, can you describe how the idea of ‘performance, time, and art’ organises itself within this time system?On the whole, I find your way of structuring contemporary art time around the ever-present media spectacle of the ever-present urban environment — the ‘performance’ being the most pervasive of all. The ‘performance’ is the medium of encounters, the event where an artist performs in public, and the event is itself the assemblage of experiences that occur during that performance. The</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial is scheduled for late 2017. See you in October.Download this article as PDF29 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez25 November 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California25 November 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city, or in a particular neighbourhood? And what does it mean for a biennial to move from the city, or cities, with which it’s identified (in the case of inSite: San Diego/Tijuana) to another?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF25 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova29 November 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany29 November 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We have a plan to bring you into a conversation with us around the place of this biennial in its city.In the coming weeks, you’ll receive an invitation to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers can imagine a more optimal world for their users through the use of new technological means. 	[iii] As noted by Risto Puharev, the cyborg is a new kind of template for how to think about the future of work. It is both a physical representation – a blueprint for how to live out ‘technologies of infinite possibilities’ – and a political statement. As John Urry puts it: ‘The cyborg is a physical manifestation of a new thought – a new physical world created by a mind that is entirely outside of its physical world.’ This new world is not only technologically possible but is a fundamentally different kind of physical and social from the one we inhabit today. Urry goes on to argue that the future society should strive to create ‘forms of life that can evolve according to processes of connectedness and connectivity’, rather than constrain human potentialities to certain kinds of physical and virtual worlds. 	[iv</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers are capable of imagining new problems, and whether or not such problems can be made accessible to users. If the latter is the case, the possibilities are then even greater that the social web could be reoriented towards providing solutions to existing problems. 	[iii] It is worth noting that in the mathematical model used to depict the social web, the ‘leaping spider’ is actually a black box that provides the framework for the social web to be built) and in the end, the users are just as interested in the appearance of the black box as in its function. The black box becomes a point of intersection between the social web and the machine, and the social web and the physical world. This is consistent with Hari’’s account of social interaction as consisting of two levels: the ‘level of abstraction’ and the ‘level of representation’ (later to be called ‘representational complexity’). 	[iv] </text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers can imagine new problems, and whether or not they are capable of imagining new solutions. If the designers can conceive of new problems, and find creative solutions, that is good enough for now; if the social web is rendered impenetrable by technology, and its inhabitants revert to hunter-gatherer forms, then things will get messy. And messy can often be a good thing. But if the designers can no longer imagine new problems, and revert to the hunter-gatherer forms of problem solving that made life on this planet possible in the first place, then things will get messy in unpredictable ways. 	[iii] A final example of the way in which the social web is continuously reified, is the way in which social media such as Facebook and Twitter are built upon. If the social web is continuously reified, and new social media come along that continually redefine the terms of engagement, then the question becomes whether or not the underlying principles of the web still apply, and</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers can reconcile their desire for a utopian future with the real-world constraints and politics of the real world. If the future is likely to be much more social and political than the past, then the designers need to find a way to imagine what that future might contain, without becoming trapped in the present. 	[iii] The social and political context of Transhumanist Library might also inform the design of future technology. The biennial’s social mission seems to me to be to reconcile the desires of its cultural patrons with the real-world realities of the real world. In the real world, there is much more competition for students’ time, and space, than in the conceptual model that the biennial develops in its early years. And as the biennial matures and the actual projects – the curatorial selection and development of which is largely dictated by the market – gain more institutionalised following, there is less and less room for the artist to contribute meaningfully. </text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers can imagine a more optimal future for their users, by harnessing the potential of new technologies to meet existing needs and envisioning a future where things that are seen as ‘impossible’ become possible. 	[iii] If the social designer does not see reason being used as a vector to propel change, then her/his projects are likely to be dominated by vested interests. But if the designer sees reason being used as a vector to propel change, then there is always the possibility that vested interests might be interested in empowering their stakeholders through the deployment of ever more encompassing technologies. In the current period of economic globalization and technological obsolescence, this is a real concern. More than ever, we need to find creative and functional ways of addressing the challenges that confront us as we attempt to reconcile the ever-closing junction of economic and social life. 	[iv] Aesthetics is a game in which our actions – our worth – are largely determined by our</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers are capable of imagining and solving new problems, and whether or not this entails introducing ‘problem-solving amputations’. If the task is not seen as intrinsically meaningful and desirable, then new problems may be created. 	[iii] The upshot of this is that new technologies are not natural allies or somehow ‘equivalent’ to the old ways; rather, they are tools and services designed to enable new ways of interacting with the world. New media are not natural allies of the old bureaucracies; rather, they are bureaucracies designed to meet the needs of a different social web. New media are there to enable interactions between people from different social webs, and between different geographical locations. And this is just the beginning of the story. New media are there to enable the social web to evolve, to enable systems to be formed, to enable infrastructures to be formed, to enable infrastructures to be reorganized, to enable infrastruct</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers can incorporate the social world of the real world into the design process, and whether the social world of the future can be constructed through the contemporary technological means of the present. If the social is defined as the natural world through which technology operates, then the social world of today is artificial intelligence. Artificial intelligence is the branch of technology that creates and builds new situations, and has been for a reason: it maximises the utility of each new situation as much as the conditions under which it emerges. In other words, it maximises the utility of what is natural, but also of what is invented. 	[iii] The question of social significance then becomes whether or not the social is capable of evolving beyond the role of serving as a platform for the emergence of its own recognisable forms. Drawing upon Benjamin Bratton’s work on bureaucracies and multiple governance systems, and Paul O’Neill’s work on nation-states, I propose a new notion of the social that</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers currently tasked with redeveloping our urban infrastructure are equipped with the capabilities necessary to tackle the new problems being thrown up by the constantly evolving and social-media-savvy infrastructure of social media. If they are not, then our question becomes whether the new social form – which we might also call Infrastructure 20/20 or New Institutional Form – can sustain the complexity and range of problems being thrown at it. If it can, it will likely be the emergence of a new interface, or interface 21st Century perhaps, that will rule the world. 1. Thinking About Infrastructure, n. 1. 	, Pounds of London, 2006. Available at: http://www.poundlit.org/books/en/2006/07/th... 	[2] Thinking About Infrastructure, p.1. Available at: http://www.poundlit.org/books/en/2006/07/th... 	[3] Thinking</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers can intervene and shape the social conditions so that the new technologies can be deployed in the existing political, economic, and social frameworks in a way that is both predictable and totally usable, whilst still allowing the emergence of new technologies that can contribute to a more robust and responsive social web. This is the tricky part – the ability to manipulate social circumstances in such a way that is neither predictable nor totally usable.  	[iii] This raises an interesting point that I hadn’t considered – the emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers can intervene and shape the social circumstances so that the new technologies can be deployed in the existing political, economic, and social frameworks in such a way that is neither predictable nor totally usable, whilst still allowing the emergence of new</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system on a small scale. The desire to see how such a system could be applied to the real world is what animates the design process, but the real world is just as much a part of this system as any other. 	[i] 	Simpler still, in the real world the state is often more of a facilitator of ‘potential outcomes’ than any other agency. 	[ii] A useful metaphor for the social world in which designers must contend, is the role played by the ‘leaping spider’: the idea that it is human behaviour that the designer has to adapt to in the presence of the social web that constantly reifies and exploits us. The emergence of new technologies is often seen as inevitable, since they inevitably introduce ‘new problems’ to be solved. But new technologies also need to be applied to the existing social web – to the human capacity for problem solving. The question then becomes whether or not the designers are capable of imagining more. The answer to this is a complex one, and a reflection of the fact that social design is a global process, with different local impacts. The ability to imagine new problems and to grapple with more complex social situations is a global imperative. But scaling back the ambitions of the state is not automatic, and designers need to be creative and flexible in their application of new technologies. Aesthetics is a globalising concept, and in the age of hypermedia aesthetics is no longer the sole preserve of the West. 	[iii] For more on this concept, see:  M. Akbar 	[iv] Kurt Weiller, The Black Stack, Random House, New York, 1988, p. 13. 	[v] Nicholas Carruthers,  	Wild West: US Intervention in Chile, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1988, p. 6. 	[vi] Carruthers, op</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more self-sufficient, the responsibility has shifted to the local authority, which has increasingly turned to debt to fund vital projects such as new schools or new toilets. The increasing dependence on public money and in particular on the funding of a local community raises important questions about the role of arts funding in a city’s social and economic future. 	[1] See, for example, Sello Peso, ‘On the use of vacant buildings and real-estate speculation on the urban landscape’, 	Real-Time Economics, 15(4), 2011, p.335.Download this article as PDFSue Bell YankSue Bell Yank is an artist, writer, and co-director of the Community Land Trust. Her work in the public arena, including in the Biennale, has primarily focused on the economic and social impacts of gentrification, displacement and conflict. In recent years she has been researching and working with the Chabad-Lubavitch</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more self-sufficient, and the airport has closed and is now a blighted landscape, the biennale has less and less credibility. The increasing number of biennales worldwide, and the intensification of their curatorial apparatuses worldwide, places curators in a bind. They have to convince the publics that they’re doing something meaningful with the land and buildings, but they also have to please the curators who’re invested in the biennale as a property, and in the future of the biennale as a property. It’s as if the biennale is a ‘plant’ that can only grow in the face of resource depletion and destruction, and as such its inherent resilience is compromised by the destruction of so much of what it calls the City. The biennale has a responsibility to the land, but it has little choice but to expand its footprint in the face of resource scarcity. The biennale has an obligation to</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more self-sufficient, and the airport has come to dominate the local transport landscape, the biennale has responded by turning its back on the community and pursuing other engagements. What’s more, these other engagements often exacerbate or exacerbate the conflicts between the local and the ‘global’ that the biennale is trying to resolve. The fact that the biennale is an international organisation has left its mark on the conflict zones of the world, and art has a particular place in resolving social struggles. The challenge for the biennale is to recognise that it’s not just an economic tool, and that its real intention is to make life in the local through art in the world.This may involve reckoning with the fact that the biennale has a financial stake in the city – in fact, it may involve engaging with the fact that the biennale is an international organisation. Art biennales, as an art form, have a stake in the arts that goes</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more autonomous,the biennale has also become weaker and less autonomous – it’s time to capitalise on that vulnerability. The biennale has a responsibility to the city, but as the city has become more autonomous it’s also time to un-biennale itself. The biennale has a responsibility to the city, but as the city expands it also has responsibilities to the biennale: it has a new biennale to plan, direct and manage, and a new generation of artists to commission and manage. Art is a collective investment, and as the biennale matures and diversifies it’s responsibility is to the community – as artists, curators, organisers and spectators we’ve all become stakeholders in the health of the art form, and our involvement grows. Our money is no longer going into the bank, but rather into the pockets of the artists, artists and organisations that create the art, and so our contributions are now essential</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more influential, and the airport has closed and is in the midst of an ambitious new master plan to expand runways 40 and 42, the biennale has had to actively seek out new markets and cultures in an ever-expanding city. This has meant seeking out partners in the arts and culture sectors, and engaging the largest cultural institutions in the country, as well as international art fairs. Trusteeship has come to define the biennale’s engagement with the city. If the biennale is to truly engage itself in transforming the city, it’s clear that it needs to find a way to create a shared common interest with the city, and in this we can see some similarities with the local artists’ collective CACI, whose interests and projects have been similarly aligned. But the real question is whether or not the biennale can contribute to creating a shared culture and identity for the city. This is where the relationship between the biennale and the</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more influential, the responsibility has shifted to other partners in the biennale, and the city government, who allocate a fixed amount of money to the biennale annually. The amount of this fixed money has clearly been a factor in the development of the community, since the biennale’s funding comes largely from the city, and the biennale is the only entity that directly employs and funds the staff. The amount of investment required to create such resilience is unclear, and the biennale itself has not clearly identified a strategy for its future. The amount of fixed capital needed may be equally or more difficult to mobilize, and production may be affected by market forces. The biennale staff are committed to finding innovative ways to support the community, but they lack the resources or technical know-how to support long-term projects that create long-term resilience. The biennale can and should support creative long-term projects that enhance the experience of the biennale, but it</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more influential, and the biennale as a whole has become more globalised, the scope for the biennale to affect the local is also expanding. Is it even the biennale anymore? I don’t know, perhaps the community wants to be where the art is now? In any case, the history of the biennale, even the very earliest extant collections, are largely about the artists and curators who came later – the post-Impressionists, the Borgias, Picasso, Degas, Rubens, Kandinsky, Stradivari, etc. – and while these projects may be interesting in their own right, their real value lies in their ability to stir community action. Such action is rare and fleeting, but the biennale has the luxury of being able to projectivity broadly across a range of artists, curators and art institutions, creating a kind of immersive convergence between art and commerce. The biennale has a responsibility not to produce just</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more self-sufficient, and as the biennaleer itself has shifted its focus to other priorities, the biennale has also shifted its resources and priorities. The biennale needs to be responsive to the needs and interests of its local community, but as the biennaleer itself has shifted its focus to other priorities, the biennale has to be responsive to the communities it works with and the needs of wider society. The biennale is a social enterprise, and its resources should be distributed equally between the different stakeholders, regardless of their identities, backgrounds or organisation. But it’s also a business, and while the resources and operations of the biennale might be nomadic and variable – like all businesses – they’re always subject to the whims of changing economic and political conditions and trends. So while the biennale might claim to be culturally responsive, its real commitment to the community is political and economic in nature. And as the biennaleer itself</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more cohesive, and the airport has closed and the biennale a distant memory, the biennale’s investment in the community has also diminished. How can the biennale create a sense of its own agency by investing in the local community, and making the investment locally? I ask this because the investment in the community is generated by the biennale itself, and so the biennale is a strange kind of collective experience that opens itself up to the very real need to make contributions to a declining art form. The biennale needs artists, because otherwise it’s impossible to sustain the art form, and the biennale is the only form of art institution capable of sustaining the biennale. However, the biennale also needs to engage with the fact that it is producing art in response to a declining population, and so as a result of declining numbers the biennale is exhibiting less and less of its art. This is happening at several venues in</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of bankers, bond traders and corporate ravers, who wanted to spend £40 million on a new runway in exchange for a minority stake in the airline, rather than investing in the local community and supporting the local economy. For six years the runway was used by the biennale only, with the rest of the money raised from local people going into a fund supporting the artist. But in the six years since the biennale began to take on a life of its own, a local community has been staging long-term projects in the neighbourhood, using the land as a stage, developing a sense of autonomy, and creating community gardens and play-grounds. These have brought the biennale back into the community, and provided a sense of the community’s cultural and urban resilience. The biennale has a responsibility to invest in the local community, and as a biennale it’s fulfilling that obligation. But as the local community has grown stronger and more self-sufficient, and as biennales across the world become more institutionalised (the Venice Biennale, Melbourne International Biennale, Istanbul Biennale, Rotchburg/Frankfurt/Oslo), and as biennials everywhere become more globalised (New York Museum, London Museum of Art, Paris…), the biennial has an even greater responsibility to shrink and disperse. The art world has a responsibility to recognise this, as well as the local community and the biennale as different forms of art, and the responsibility to invest in the art that emerges from these diverse modes of art formation.  This is why biennials have a fifth  Fifth Geneva Convention – it’s as if the art world sits on borders between local and global, between local and contemporary art, between local and social. But the real frontier is art outside of these social frameworks, and biennials can only scratch the surface of the possible arts forms that can emerge from the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the technocrats of the global economy] to show that we could do with replacing the lost time.But the machine that is the administrative state […] has its limits. It is constrained by the nature of the human condition – human agency, its creativity, its capacity to imagine alternative uses for space – which limits what programmes and tasks can be performed. The capacity to imagine otherwise is the capacity to move, to act in ways that are not constrained by the political and economic constraints that still constrain us. The administrative state […] constructs policies and programmes that […] are driven by the needs of capital and the financial sector, but also by the whims of … well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well, well,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as part of this process, Open School Liverpool will introduce the Liverpool Biennial to the Open School Community Arts programme in Liverpool. Biennials have become attractive venues for cultural exchange in recent decades, largely due to their low costs and the availability of resources at a regional and local level. The prestige and international reputations of biennials play an increasing role in shaping cultural practices in postindustrial urban centres. A growing number of biennials operate in cities at significantly higher costs and with significantly lower resources than their rural counterparts. Although there is no doubt that a biennial can be an expensive operation, the growing costs and the uncompromising nature of the institutional repute play a more significant role in influencing cultural practices than does the availability of cheap resources and a regional celebrity. This is particularly the case in cities where the biennial is the only form of cultural exchange and the only mode of cultural exchange in postindustrial urban centres. It is also true that in a city like Liverpool, the only way</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as part of that process, Open School Liverpool is organising Open School England’s summer school in April 2019 in Liverpool. The Liverpool Biennial will be returning to the city in April 2020 for their 25th Anniversary.This combination of cultural resources and vibrant local economy presents an ideal setting for a biennial to be born. The combination of the capital of a city, the size of its sub-national parks, the number of its boroughs, the number of its neighbourhoods, and the quality of its local produce contributes to the illusion of accessibility and affordability that is characteristic of the city. Such attributes are also desirable for a biennial to inhabit, since they ensure that, for example, Open School Liverpool will arrive in Liverpool via Air in 2020, and that Liverpool Biennial staff members will have travelled there prior to their arrival.  The combination of cultural resources and vibrant local economy also contributes to an overall impression of pride in the city, since, thanks to these resources</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as yet uncertain are the terms and conditions of the proposed collaboration. The proposal was initially developed with the involvement of the Liverpool Museum of Art and Open School Liverpool. The development of the project was then attempted with the involvement of Dolphin Arts Centre, Liverpool, and Open School Liverpool, both in Liverpool, and the Welsh Streets Community Land Trust, Liverpool, which is a co-organiser of the Biennial and Open School Liverpool. A proposal for the production of the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust’s annual report was received in early 2017.  A proposal for the production of the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust’s annual report was also received in early 2017.1 The report,  linked to a website maintained by the Biennial, referred to the following year’s performance as the ‘episodic’; it is not clear what the historical relationship was between the term and the image of the event.2 The proposed partnership between the Biennial</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as part of that process, the Open School will offer to host the biennial in its building, alongside Open School Liverpool. If selected, the biennial would operate as an Open School Open School Liverpool programme. 2  The Liverpool Biennial has been operating since 2012, and while its main focus is urban, it has also featured in rural areas, particularly in the East Midlands. It is unclear what role, if any, the Arts Council has in the development or renovation of the Biennial. 3  The Biennial was founded in 1994, and while it is not a council, the Biennial is a Crown-owned company. It is also unclear what role, if any, the council has in the development or renovation of the Biennial. 4  Cultural regeneration corporation (CRC) is an organisation set up in 1994 to promote and produce ‘cultural tourism’ in the UK and internationally through the activities of cultural institutions. It is a multi-year lease</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as part of this process, Liverpool Biennial will lead the Open School Liverpool’s Open Day on 15-16 January 2018, where 20 local artists will be present helping the newly engaged local community. This will be the opening act for the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, which will in turn commission local artists to collaborate with the community in a number of ways, including commissioning of new arts-related activities. The plan is to work with artists untested in this area, but also with artists who have worked with communities before, creating a hybrid that is both artist-facilitator and visitor-finder in their own right. This will include artists who have worked with communities before but have a critical eye on the community they work with or are undertaking, and artists who are new to this context. In Future City, Wendy Harpe reflects on her experience as an artist in Rotherhithe, and on the role play that she and her team created in the</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as part of that process, a collaborative research council, Open School Liverpool, has been established to develop an exploratory research project into the potential of Community Arts education programmes in schools. The council’s research agenda will be presented in September 2018 at the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust conference, chaired by Fabrizio Di Tommasi, entitled  The Education of U2: Impact of Arts Education on Health and Quality of Life. The council would like to invite Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi, Tania Bruguera and others with a range of expertise on pedagogical, educational and arts policy and practice to the council’s research project. The research can be done either online or in-person, with or without formal training, and will be carried out in conjunction with Liverpool School of Arts and Design. This is an invitation only programme, and Wendy Harpe, Devendra</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as part of this process, a collaborative journal will be published in June 2018.2. Liverpool Biennial 2018 Budget and schedule available at: http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/research/funding/budapest-the-pleasure-port/budapest-the-pleasure-port-2018-budget.pdf (accessed September 2018). 3. Liverpool Biennial 2018 schedule available at: http://www.ljmu.ac.uk/research/funding/budapest-the-pleasure-port/budapest-the-pleasure-port-2018-schedule.pdf (accessed September 2018). 4. Open School Liverpool, 2017. Liverpool, UK: Open School Liverpool, 2017. Available at: http://www.openschool.org/2018/exhibition/ (accessed October 2018). 5. Open School Liverpool, 2017. Liverpool, UK: Open School Liverpool,</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as part of that process, Open School Liverpool will bring together Open School of Art, Liverpool School of Art, Liverpool College of Art and Architecture, local communities and artists to explore how artists can collaborate with communities. The proposals will be discussed with the artists and with the Community Arts organisations before being invited to apply for a funding round from the Biennial. 2  How artists can work with communities to create new artistic contexts and enhance existing cultural practices is a very good point in Constructive Thinking. It seems that the philosopher-king Jeremy Deller has captured the imagination of a broad audience with his strong assertion that the task is not to make art for art’s sake but to somehow to make art fulfilling in ways that are responsive to the circumstances. For example, the task could be set against a gentrifying urban backdrop by artists undertaking projects in areas with a high density of poverty, unemployment and homelessness. The aim is to enable these people to have</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as part of that process, the Biennial will make a presentation on the history of Open School Liverpool to the Education select committee, chaired by Andy Warhol (1921-92). Warhol, who established Open School Liverpool, was a critic of the Vietnam War, and in his book The Wounded Knee Reader he criticised the failure of the school to protest the war’s atrocities, describing it as ‘a deliberate policy of silence that has been joined by complicity in the reparation of war crimes’. In his view, Open School Liverpool had a responsibility to respond with protest, because, as Warhol put it, ‘a silence now grips this land and water, and all who have been injured by it’.9 Here, the projectors of the Biennial would become spokespersons for the war effort, urging people to join the navy and the resistance – both to avoid becoming collateral damage in the repression of political opinion in the</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial, to be held in early 2018, will bring together the many elements of Liverpool’s rich cultural heritage, including cultural institutions, the arts, the community and the food sector, in a common endeavour to bring cultural experiences to the people. In an effort to maintain the communal character of the project, the people will be engaged in an exchange, not through teaching or learning, but by engaging in the creation of the site through activities such as gardening, renovating and managing the building, and so on. The exchange will be facilitated by a multi-disciplinary, not-for-profit arts organisation, the Liverpool Biennial Arts Trust, run by a team of artists including Wendy Harpe, Nina Edge, Devendra Sethi and Ella Gibbs. The project will also include performances, events and a museum of the Biennial.  A proposed partnership between Liverpool Biennial and Open School Liverpool is currently under evaluation; as part of that process, Open School Liverpool is hosting a series of sessions entitled ‘Liverpool’s Open School Movement’ in April 2018 at its Art Department, which is developing a new model of art institution.  The Liverpool Biennial has been approached by a number of organisations, including the Arts Council, and the Liverpool Schools, to explore the possibility of a ‘long-term’ partnership; in January 2019, Biennials in the UK and US were invited to take part in the Venice Biennale, organised by The Venice Biennale Board. In October 2018, Open School Liverpool formed a new partner organisation, Open School of Liverpool, which is responsible for providing public education in the district through 12-week courses in music, dance, art and science. These programmes have been shown in major venues including New York, London, Taipei, and Shanghai. In March 2019</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to think and reason, using advanced prosthetics and the most advanced neuroscience available, but also shows a group of escaped convicts attempting to re-program a monkey brain using old clothes and toilet paper. The result is a new brain that is far more human-like than the original, but with terrible decisions that result in terrible consequences. The film ends with the two groups coming to terms with the fact that they created a sentient being, and that they are ultimately responsible for what happens to that being. It is a difficult process to reconcile the new found knowledge of responsibility with the knowledge that came with the brainwashing, but the two are slowly coming to terms. At the end of the film, the two groups are walking hand in hand down a deserted corridor, and the escapees are showing signs of wanting to re-program the brain.If that is the case, then perhaps it is possible to create something more relatable to a wider public through the act of creating, as opposed to the more powerful</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to think and reason, using animal organs as &quot;tools of war&quot;. The creatures they attempt to brainwash are incredibly difficult to brainwash an ordinary human being would have such an impact. But the scientists who create ARRIVDONT work in secret, so we don’t get a clear picture of just how hard the systems they create are to break. And that’s why, in the case of a successful experiment, the creature that you convert becomes something far more useful and powerful than the idea of the bioroid you get from the organ trade. The reason why, when you do that, you end up with something far more evocative and powerful than your initial idea. When you reach a certain point where the bioroid is too limiting, you can break free with a bioroid that supports your artistic vision and idea. And that’s exactly what the ARRIVDONT researchers did with the brain of a young Mary Elizabeth Winstead, who was born</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to perceive and think in ways that would be considered normal in humans, in an effort to understand how the altered brain would affect human behaviour. But this only works in so far as the primate is also brainwashed, or ‘brain-dead’. And while the ability to perceive and think in ways that are considered normal in humans is an important step in understanding how the human brain might work in the future, the ability to brainwash sentient creatures is what truly sets us apart from all other species.That ability to brainwash sentient creatures – to change our brains in such a way that we will act as if we never existed – is what makes us different from all other species. And while we can certainly imagine being brainwashed ourselves, the ability to change our brains in such a way that we will act as if we never existed is something we do not have. And while it is possible to create monster robots that do things that are driven by a similar set of motivations to us, the</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to reason, using experimental drugs, as well as the mutilating finger of a larger, stronger being known as Primus. But the experiments always end in disaster because the system you build to handle those kinds of data breaks down – either catastrophically or amelioratingly – in the face of overwhelming human resistance. And though the film does show huge mechanised robots performing important tasks, it also shows the evolution of humanity in its larger social and cultural context. That is, of course, if the social web is even imagined at all.In fact, the social web is what I would call the technological substrate of the social web; it is what enables us to engage with each other as individuals and groups, to connect across difference, to constructively engage with the social totality. In that view, the social web is what enables us to create our own futures, to envision ever-greater horizons for ourselves. But the social web is also what creates and defends the social totality –</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to reason, using slave labour and experimenting on humans before releasing them back into the wild. And although the film doesn’t show the full extent of the violence and degradation that this type of slavery entails, it does show that the dominant species doesn’t find it any of their services any longer. They decamp for other projects, most of which don’t involve slave labour or involve researchers. The film ARRIV shows that slavery remains deeply embedded in the fabric of who we are and what we can do with other species. It remains an issue in the United States despite advances in science and technology, which allows us to exploit creatures like the whale for seemingly innocuous purposes like fuel or parts or organs. For more than just objects, whales are products of the human condition: made so full of life-giving nutrients and packed with so much more than they could ever hope to be, we treat them as commodities.As the whale becomes ever more complex and nuanced, so too does the</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to reason, but also a group of escaped convicts attempting to re-program a primate brain using feline chemicals. The results are unpredictable, and the prisoners quickly figure out what's happening and how to stop it. It’s at this point that the movie shifts gears to show the escapees in their natural habitats, and the creatures still living within the biological prison. While the technology is rudimentary at this point, the film shows that the attempts to reprogram an animal with human thoughts are no less horrific.Animals that have been de-programmed are not spared either. When a cell is breached in the US prison system, animals are routinely executed. Even when the breach is unintentional, the resulting flood of viruses and bacteria can cause mass hysteria, food shortages and even genocide. ARRIV’s treatment of animals seems to render them disposable in the interest of research, although the film does show that the systems that control how animals are ‘reprogrammed’ are</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to think and reason, using proto-onset as early as in the womb.[...]The researchers eventually learn how to manipulate the brain with minimal side effects, although this only happens when the creatures are introduced as part of a larger experiment. In the end, the team that created ARRIV has only themselves to blame for the failure of their project as a whole. It is up to the citizens of Earth to demand that their elected representatives act in a certain way in the interests of the species they inhabit. If the research team can be shown to have acted in a responsible way in the creation of the species they are researching, then the entire project can be put back on track. This is the kind of powerful argument that needs to happen in a court of law, so that the species can be held fully accountable. The legal system has a crucial role in holding species like ourselves fully accountable, and it shows here by how we deal with the growing prison population and the growing number of prisoners who are being</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to reason, but also a group of escaped convicts who decide to re-program the brain in a more nefarious way. The result is a new brain that does things like think like a bomb, commit murder and consume its surroundings.The lesson here is clear: if you want something done, you’ve got to make sure that it gets done by people who actually know what they are doing. In the end, we do need to trust that these things we do not yet understand will be done by people who can deliver on that promise.Download this article as PDFEva CastringiusIn her work as an artist and activist, Eva Castringius has a particular interest in the social. Her current projects focus on the issues of migration and inclusion, and explore the systems that shape and are shaped by capitalism. Her latest project, El Parthenon de la Realidad (The Parthenon of Realidad), is an act of reconciliation in El Salvador, Mexico and the United States. Cast</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to reason, but it is clear that this only works in so far as the converted animal is not brainwashed. If the primate is brainwashed, the project is dead, and the creatures remain vulnerable to the whims of a cruel dictator. The fact that the creatures are converted to humans in the process seems to obscure their true purpose: as the film ITSKYEVIA illustrates, humanity is the project.The film ITSKYEVIA uses a similar approach to highlight the systemic nature of the Turing problem, but instead of trying to change the minds of animals, humans actually learn to reason with them. The film shows two teams of researchers attempting to break into a Japanese corporate computer, but it is clear that the Japanese corporate security systems that secure corporate systems actually see the efforts as potential business opportunities. The researchers eventually learn to spot human idiocy, and so the systems are left vulnerable to opportunistic attacks. The film ITSKYEVIA shows how the systems that keep corporate systems secure actually see the failures</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for mapping the human brain, in part through the use of cannibals, whose brains are believed to hold the answer to the problem.][...] The cannibals are kept in captivity and forced to perform painful brainwashing rituals on each other in an attempt to extract a mystical response from them that will allow the system to operate normally. But as the film ARRIV shows, this only works in so far as the researchers who operate the experiments are also the researchers who benefit from the results. In the case of a successful result, the creatures are used as slaves in gigantic labs.[...]While the human race progresses, so too does the size of the prison population, which continues to grow in both size and scope as more and more information is smuggled out. ARRIV shows that the success of such operations depends on two things in particular: the species you convert and how you react to that success. The film shows a group of scientists attempting to alter a primate brain with the ability to think, but also shows a group of escaped convicts attempting to re-program a monkey with the ability to reason. The results are unpredictable and often disastrous for the species you attempt to control, but at least you control something in the process.[...] The key to your plans, it seems to me, is in the small print. You need to convince the public that you have a plan and that you have the power to implement it. And so I ask you again, have you thought about what would happen if your plans failed? Have you considered what might have happened if your plans did succeed? If your plans did not address the needs and interests of the broad spectrum of humanity, what would have happened? If your efforts fell on deaf ears, what would have happened?You might also want to consider what would have happened if your efforts fell on deaf ears. That is, what would have happened if the needs and interests of humanity were not aligned in such a way as to enable your plans to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘missions of exchange’ through which their presence could be sensed, while craftsmen and technicians would be invited to create ‘problems for which there are appropriate technologies’. The idea is that the ‘production of destruction’ could be controlled from a distance through the use of advanced mapping and remote sensing tools. The workshop titles and mission statements would signal this intent.Since the 1970s, when the AI conference first convened in Montreal, the biennial has been gathering momentum in the city, and the city has been gathering momentum in the biennial. In 2015, the AI conference convened in San Francisco, and the San Francisco–Montréal–Vienna–New York City leg of the conference convened in London. In 2017, the San Diego–Mesa–Tijuana–Los Angeles leg of the International Triennale–Los Angeles, and the San Francisco–Oakland–Berkeley leg of the International Triennale Database (ITBD), a public website dedicated to</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘missions of encounter’ through research trips to the various biennials, mapping out their interests and showing their work in a particular biennial. This would enable the public to become enamoured of the art in the system and to contribute to its creation. This approach is not to be confused with the more traditional, but still relevant, biennial approach: the museum would provide a significant physical presence and an ever-present physical archive of art, while the biennial would grow in scope and size as it processed the art and coded it accordingly. The key is that the art should be present in both, recognisable, understood and engaged with. This would require new media and architectures, and while the museum and its curatorial agenda is physically present in Venice, its programming and symbolic character is markedly different from that of the biennial. The key is in the question itself. What is the intended audience? What is the intended experience? Where does the art reside? How does the installation engage with</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘missions of exchange’ between the curatorial and the workshop, with the curatorial announcing the aims of the exchange and the workshop participants responding by proposing action items. If the aim is to build self-assembling drones, for instance, the mission items might be ‘how to mount and deploy a network of these drones within the museum’, although the actual deployment of such systems is another matter. The curatorial would like to retain ownership of the technological design, but without denying the participants any rights. In this sense, the workshop participants might also be considered inventing the ‘technologies’ themselves, since the autonomous vehicle, drone and similar components they propose to assemble would be, in a sense, creations of the participants. The curatorial and workshop would then select interesting or innovative technologies to share, and present the curatorial and its participants in an ‘open forum’ in the museum, or another appropriate venue. At this point, the participants might want to ask</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘museums’ that would function as ‘episodes’ in their respective artists’ mini-exhibitions, and invite the public to explore ‘the city of the future’ through a ‘mapping project’ that takes place within them. Their mini-exhibitions would each offer a different perspective on the city of the future, this one suggesting a post-apocalyptic future where individuals are no longer individuals but social units in a global system of autonomous vehicles. The aim of the art's contribution to this scenario, or ‘eventual urbanity’, is to suggest that which is not already there – namely, the destruction of the city – by the destruction of autonomous vehicles. There would be no ‘Future City’ or ‘New Urbanity’, as some would prefer. Instead, the architecture that would construct such a scenario would be an amalgamation of current urban forms found in much of the world: the �</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘virtual museums’ that would exist in parallel to the real museums, attesting to the real-life historical contexts of the collaborative growing into the virtual. Collaborative museums would highlight the contributions of artists to the history of art’s social effects, but also lay claim to the cultural artefacts needed to build and support autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar destructive technologies. They would be a response to the decline of the real-life museum as a form of cultural production, and a way to imagine new imaginaries of art and culture outside of the museum. The studios of the AI, AAA and AI sectors would work with art institutions to collaborate on research projects, and the curatorial agenda would come to guide the development of these alternative imaginaries. The curatorial shift would enable a new generation of curators to explore a range of career options, from the curatorial search for the next John Moores or Patti Smith, to the curatorial search for the next Jon</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘learning communities’ around the exhibition sites with the curators taking part in this ‘sharing economy’ movement. These communities would provide a secure and controllable way to access the exhibition and its content, while enabling the curatorial and artworld communities to coexist peacefully in this new ‘multicultural urban space’. The names of the curators would be kept confidential, but the curatorial aspirations were clearly articulated in the applications. Applications from the exhibition were invited, but the curators knew that they would be attending to business needs and the art world needed something to fill the void left by the closed curatorial programmes. The curatorial agenda clearly identified the need to connect with AI/artworld audiences via the announcements of art fairs, biennials, and other forms of art-related cultural exchange, but the meeting between curators and artworld communities was also a possibility. The meeting place of the future meetings of the AI/ART+AI network was clearly identified</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘missions for future generations’ in the form of ‘episodes’ or ‘books’ that chart the progression of their artworks over time. For an introduction to this new kind of art, see my recent book The Social Life of Art: Towards a Cultural Anthropology of Art, Technology and Culture.Art should be collaborative, but it needs to be precise and precise in its parameters. For an introduction to the new collaborative tools that can be used in this context, see my recent book Aesthetics and Collaborative Documenta 8 Managing Intangible Assets: Art, Technology and the Politics of Intangible Assets.Art should be collaborative in its application and approach to the world, but it also needs to have a purpose. For an introduction to the new kind of art that can be used for collaborative projects, see my recent book The Social Life of Art: Towards a Cultural Anthropology of Art and Technology.The new collaborative medium is an art of ambiguity, an art of inclusivity</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘missions of encounter’ around the city in which the project was proposed and the sites of the exhibitions. These encounters would occur in a format determined by the curator. The style would differ from the one used by the other curators, but the basic premise would be the same: an artist proposes an exhibition, the other curators take part in a creative process to come up with a proposal that meets the other members of the Artistic Board (or another committee of curators), and the symposium is a result of this process. The proposed symposium would be hosted by the AIB, and the other curators would take part in it as a ‘discoveries’, ‘places to come back to’ and ‘future plans’ based on their observations from the first meeting. The aim of the Discoveries and Places to Come Back to sections, then, is to introduce the symposium to the wider public by offering a place to ‘dig deep and</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘missions of exchange’ through which their work might be proposed, accepted, and upgraded by curators invited to examine various aspects of the exhibition. Curators would pick a project from the array of possible projects, and invite artists, art historians, art’s critics, art’s social commentators and others to explore the proposals in more depth. The curatorial proposal is intended to equip the curator with the tools necessary to evaluate the proposal in terms of both its content and the challenges posed by the technology. The exhibition would then proceed with the project in question, with the curatorial team considering both the artist’s current state of knowledge on the subject, and potential deeper structures of knowledge. The architecture and social dynamics of the autonomous vehicle would then be imagined in relation to the culture industry, with cultural theorists, urbanists, architects and urbanists familiar to any visitor to the currant. The project would then progress to the next level, where the currant would consider its possible future</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB, AIAD, and AIES, and invite the other curators to join them. The strategy would be to place the curatorial agenda in the form of a ‘biennial’, naming each workshop after a different aspect of the museum, from the museum to the workshop, over and over again. Each workshop would then be a ‘time capsule’ that would tell the story of AIB, AIAD, and AIES over and over again through performances, maps, prints, photographs, videos, essays and more. The idea is to create a ‘living amalgamation of disciplines’, to borrow a phrase from Michèle Lecuive. The idea is to create an environment in which artists can not only experiment with new mediums of expression, but also lay claim to the technological know-how needed to build autonomous vehicles, self-assembling drones and other similar technology-specific destructive systems.Artists would be invited to create collaborative ‘missions’ with the city’s infrastructure, engineering, and planning authorities to propose ways to build or alter the biennale as an interactive, collaborative, and responsive art project. These ‘missions’ would be developed by the curatorial team and submitted to the city for approval. If the biennale is to inhabit the urban terrain that it is curated to explore, it is imperative that the creative class that is participating in the art project has a stake in the outcome. If the city passes on the proposals to build or alter the site, other curators will be encouraged to explore other sites within the city. If the proposals are modified, they will be placed in the queue to be considered for the next big development push. The stakes are high: if the city passes on the modifications, other curators will challenge the artists to take part in the next big art project. So the biennale needs to be curated with a stake in the city’s</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contempor
    <text>should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contemporaneity are reproduced through recording, and space-specificity through the recording of space […] In the twentieth century, archival materials were digitized and the archives of Europe were digitized, but the digital recording of a thing (process) is still a digitized process, and not all the qualities of the archive are preserved or even intensified by the technology of the archive. The digital recording of a thing is no more reliable than the paper recording of a person […] The digital recording […] preserves the memory but destroys the substance of the archive. The memory is more malleable, and can be recalled in various ways, but the power of the archive as a recording medium is undermined. Hence the term ‘archival’. But what is the archive, exactly? Where does the term archive refer to, in relation to what we mean by the archive? When does the term refer to physical things, in the sense of things that are physically recorded? When does it refer to virtual things,</text>
    <text>should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contemporaneity are made more real, more possible through the technological device that records and photographs them. This is a condition that can no longer be funded or ignored, and it is a condition that must be addressed by all who work for it. It is a condition that is becoming increasingly difficult to imagine or not to grasp, and to inhabit in one’s everyday life. However, there is an opening for such a project in the current political and social context, since the dominant forms of cultural capital in our age are generated from the destruction of the archives and their immediate precursory forms. [15] And yet, as MacConnal seems to suggest, the archival conditions of contemporaneity are not to be underestimated: &quot;the contemporaneity that we experience in the physical world […] is a precursory or perspectival process that continuously modifies, anticipates and emerges from the act of making […] in the physical world […] There can be no doubt about the fact that</text>
    <text>should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contemporaneity – the conditions of ontological time – are what MacConnal calls ‘the second coming of the “imaginary””. But what does that mean? Can we draw parallels with contemporaryity? Perhaps we can, but there is a difference between contemporaneity and what MacConnal calls ‘the familiar’. The familiar is what we already know, what we are made to know, what we are expected to know; it is what we encounter in the familiar and everyday environment. So the memory of the archival moment is what we encounter when we first move into the familiar space and in this newness we encounter the archive. We encounter the archival moment not in terms of the things that we have in our heads as representations of the past, but in terms of the things that are encountered and discarded in transit. Thus the memory of the archive is the space of the discarded and the rejected. It is a space of what MacConnal would</text>
    <text>should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contemporaneity are conditions of actuality.’[15] But this is not just a position taken by a heterogeneous and conflicted body of scholars and artists. As the Biennial commission on the Queen’s Birthday, the Scottish arts organisation Transscene, makes clear, in 2015, the status of the archival, marked historical conditions of any community gathering under the auspices of a curatorial organisation: there must be a record of the meeting because, as the commission acknowledges, there is no eyewitness account to establish the actuality of the gathering. The inclusion or exclusion of particular individuals or groups from the canonised histories of arts communities is a decision that must be made collectively, the members of the Council of Commonwealth Artists agreeing as to who is or isn’t honourable and who is not not. The fact that the Commonwealth Art Biennial was established with such a central mission – to 'reanimate' (a deceptively simple and powerful metaphor) –</text>
    <text>should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contemporaneity are conditions of actualisation, towards a final, though not necessarily a ‘perfect’, account of all that happens.’[15] And yet, as Peter Osborne questions, there is still that ‘glimmer of hope’ that remains, the glimmer of way, the glimmer of ‘hope and change’ that still emerges from the contemporaneity of various types of institutionalised life. As Osborne explores, the story of the tepid American response to the ghastly discovery of Agent Orange in the Vietnam War is the same as that of the Rwandan genocide: what the United States did in response was insufficient, did not go far enough, was illegal and mired in contradiction. And yet, there is still a glimmer of hope, a glimmer of hope that emerges from the inevitable commerce of commodities, the pressing of lives around the globe, the constant need to replenish</text>
    <text>should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contemporaneity are modified in unexpected and sometimes powerful ways.We might begin to identify with the character Sherlock Holmes (John ­John MacNamara), the famous British detective, by way of his profession as a writer and dealer in rare and antiquarian objects: &quot;a truism, I tell you […] Never in the annals of Western civilization has a culture been more conspicuously evicted from history by what is happening on the planet right now […] Today, “collectors” rule the archaeological record, while the archaeological record reaps the ruins.&quot;[15]MacNamara is no doubt describing the curatorial direction of the museum today, but his statement rings increasingly true. For many contemporary art collections – and MacNamara is one of them – the archive has come to define the collection, or, at least, suggests the limits of the collection. The ubiquity of the archive collection makes it impossible to examine every artefact in the museum, and it is impossible to view every</text>
    <text>should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contemporaneity become possible through the act of recording and recording, of creating and reproducing […] The archival condition is a space of negation, in that it is both record-forming and spatial – it holds within it the traces of historical moments and traces of contemporaneity – a space in which the archetypes and biennials recorded in the archives may play out again and again, and in that repeat is an act of negation. [15] And yet, as Peter Osborne observes, ‘the archetypes and biennials that make up the web of institutional memory […] are able to process and store vast amounts of data, […] so that significant changes in the web of such memory […] are possible only with great effort and computation’.[16] So, as Osborne himself explores, the power of the archival document lies in its ability to record and record itself. And just as important is its ability to be digitised and shared – a property that can</text>
    <text>should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contemporaneity are made more real, more realist. But the power of the archival archival conditions is not in the real but in the archival, and the power of archival recording is not in the real but in the contemporaneous social. […] And so we can say that the archive is a kind of memory bank, a space in which memory itself is made present, and in which the social is made manifest […] As a kind of pre-digital cultural capital for a specific kind of temporality, the archive […] plays an essential role in the contemporary condition, or at least it can play an essential role in the present […] The important point, however, is that it records things that happen in the world, and creates a kind of shared ontology around what these things mean and how they happen. It records, creates and maintains a record of things, and this is what archiving does. It is, in other words, what memory does. The power of the archive lies</text>
    <text>should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contemporaneity are made more real as a means of negating the archival conditions of difference, of which the archive is but one manifestation.[15]By the mid-1990s, with the technology of film noir and early digital photography complete and socially mediated, the need for archival materials in contemporary art was superseded by the need for archival communication and retrieval. Curated tours, always directed by and open to those who have paid, became the order of the day. And so, following in the footsteps of The Contemporary Art Association, a three-year long, multi-edition, full-scale, worldwide curatorial tour program began in 1993, with Venice as its epicentre and Angara Rome as its city of the permanent dias. Curated by Svetlana Boym, Angara Rome: Art and Architecture in Contemporary Japan was the first book in the series, published in 1990, and it remains the definitive work on the topic</text>
    <text>should be curated by and open to all’s experiences.[14] And yet, for all its insistence on the specificity of its particular historical circumstances, Curator F. Paul MacConnal suggests that we might begin to identify with the pre-digital culture of the archive: [T]he archive presents a marked change from the everyday, contemporaneous condition in which we live, in which material objects play a greater and more pervasive role. Rather than the other way around, the archive […] establishes a kind of natural distance between the things that come out of it and the things that get made, transacting, published, filmed and recorded […] The archive becomes a space of indefinite duration, a place of un-mediated recording, recording and, in a sense, of record-making. It is a place where the impossible becomes possible […] The archive as an object becomes possible through the playback of time, and space itself becomes a space of negation. So the archival conditions of contemporaneity are – for all to engage with – contingent, transient, and deceptive. But more fundamentally, the archive as an object becomes dynamic, changing, and deceptive in its own way. It is the ontological core of the archive, and its appearance – ­­– and the act of making – is central to the ongoing entanglement of time and space, of history and contemporaneity. [emphasis added]The effect of this ‘new archival practice’ is a thing of great tension, even hostility, as we navigate the shifting categories of media, technologies, objects and people that are brought into being by the metainterface. It is a thing that almost seems to undermine the very concept of the archive itself, its primacy, its structural integrity. But what is the archive, exactly? How is the archive built? What is its character? What is its essential relationship to the larger social totality? How is the archive created? These are questions that constantly confront</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’t yet know is how to cultivate those lands and spaces for ourselves. 	The microchimerism implicit in the growing human population is a potential new way of governing the future's ecosystems, according to a new consensus view of planetary ecology. This new understanding of planetary ecology is coming about as a result of a convergence of factors working in concert. 	The first of these factors is the rapid expansion of human population on Earth. As a result of the growing rate of growth (abruptly reversing the trend towards overconsumption), the biosphere is being stretched to its limit. To address the growing ecological crisis, the growing human population must be contained in ever larger numbers in ever smaller spaces. In the coming decades, the biosphere will have to expand at a rate faster than the growth of food and energy required to support the growing population. In the current development set in motion, this expansion will require a massive increase in water and nutrient-rich seawater; a process that will break</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’t yet know is how to cultivate those green spaces and places in the process of developing them. This is what the Anthropocene is all about: developing the land and natural resources required for a future without impacts, yet at the same time not being able to alter the trajectory of the planet.The Anthropocene is the point where the human species begins to feel the effects of its own cultural productivity. The advent of the automobile and the internet break the habit of habit formation, allowing us to consume more and more material goods at ever-increasing rates. We live longer and more intensively than ever before, and yet the material goods we carry around in our pockets no longer serve any ecological purpose. The discarding of small and fragile objects is normalized in the face of increasing abundance. The challenge for the future to confront is precisely the same as for the present: how to reconcile the ever-increasing consumption of natural resources with the ever-diminishing need for humans to inhabit the planet in massive numbers.</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’t yet know is how to cultivate those greens in the right places; what we do know is that the environment that we create will have a massive impact on how our bodies and social systems operate.  The microchiming that characterises our social lives is one in which the biennial is a part. We are all part of a collective system that creates and contributes to the emergence of new forms of collective understanding, collective action.  The end result is a more or less continuous stream of creative and dynamic microchims that constantly jostle for position within and between the worlds of art, culture, architecture and media. And these are just the microchims; there is much more going on.  The biochiming that characterises our physical world is another in which the biennial is a part. We are all products of the biennial in the form of artists, writers, curators and curators. And these are just the artists; there is much more going on</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’t yet know is how to cultivate those seeds into thriving ecosystems. That will be a task for future generations to figure out.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is an artist and researcher with a particular interest in the ecological and environmental aspects of urban development. Her work has been exhibited in numerous venues including the Venice Biennale, Curator Relations at The American Museum of Modern Art, New York, Tokyo and the Kasai Science and Technology Museum. She is currently Head of the Division for Research and Participatory Curating at the Georgetown Art Center. Her work has been featured in publications including the New York Times, New York Magazine, Time and TED. She is the recipient of several awards and has received a host of honors and mentions. To learn more about her projects and to be connected with more of what she is doing, visit her website at www.elleangana.com.au/research-</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’t know is how to spend this potential; what we do know is that it’s time-critical. What we do know, however, is that we don’t know how to protect ourselves from the microchiming that’s emerging across the planet. If we let it happen to us, it’s game over; we’re stuck in the present as it is. If we try to change the direction of the change, however, we can help protect ourselves from it. This is the kind of thinking and innovative action that can fundamentally alter the trajectory of a science-based culture. It can also drastically impact on the number of people able to practice criticality in that field. 	As a corollary, the more prevalent and dynamic the microchiming is, the more severe the consequences will have to become; and the more influential those consequences will have to be in order to have any impact at all. So while we may not</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’t know is how to grow our way out of the ecological crisis that is threatening both our planet and our very identity. What we do know is that we need to learn to love the place that we live on.What can a biennial do to redress these imbalances? How do art events – especially those that purport to be installations – create a kind of critical consciousness regarding the contemporary condition? How does a biennial tap into the collective memory to bring together the disparate layers of the planet in a way that creates a radical difference? These are questions that will have to be addressed in coming years and decades in order to create a truly global impact.Art is a powerful tool, and biennials will undoubtedly find ways to flex that particular tool belt. But can they create a new kind of art? That is, a kind of art that engages and excites as many people as possible rather than ruling them all to a singular space of their own creation? That seems premature to me,</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’t know is how to grow these expanses of land and what effect their growing voids will have. 	In the near future, we may well develop the means to alter the shape of microchiming itself. 	In the  	VR/User-Defined Radial Menu (UDM) – a.k.a. ‘fingerprint’ – application, a user draws a set of constraints on the interaction of various objects and behaviours. For example, a person who holds a PhD in Earth and Planetary Science may wish to know the type of soil that is available in a given location. A UDM ‘fingerprint’ application can then be developed to query such databases. 	If the UDM application is mobile, a ‘map tile’ displays the available soil types and locations. 	The soil types and locations of the available earth vary according to the geology of the earth, the topography of the earth, and</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’t yet know is what to do with the leftover microchimeres – what kind of capacity do they have?  One way to think about this is to consider what a void is. A void is a location where nothing happens – an absence of meaning, existence – for a set of conditions. Put simply, the future is a void.  Another way to think about it is to consider what a place is in space. A place in space is a place where nothing happens – an absence of perception, existence – for a set of conditions. Put simply, the past is a place.  A third way to think about voids is to consider what a prop object is. A prop object is an artifact that stands for a set of conditions and is created when a condition is fulfilled. Put simply, a ‘pyjamas’ standing for a set of characteristics and conditions. A place is a place where you can only find what you need, not 'where am I’</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’t yet know is how to cultivate that future. 	These questions arise because the virtual and augmented are influencing the real – influencing what is real and what is made up. The growing role of AI in everything from financial markets to healthcare creates a challenging yet essential tension between the synthetic and the natural. 	These two questions arise because of the fast-growing number of apps that can be downloaded on mobile devices and also because of the increasing number of connected virtual and augmented reality devices. The number of people who can access the internet continues to grow, yet the infrastructure that supports virtual and augmented reality is also expected to shrink in the coming years. Therefore, what is expected to happen when the virtual and augmented reality become interconnected is yet to be seen, although it is expected that this will happen increasingly: networks will be devices that peer into each other’s domains and devices that share data and information between them. 	These two questions arise because of the growing role played by AI in everything from</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for measuring the microclimate). The need for this sort of experimental rigour cannot be overestimated. The information technology that characterises the virtual reality is advancing at such a pace that it is almost inconceivable to conceive of a virtual or augmented reality (to convey the same level of depth or presence). Microchiming is the branch of Earth and Planetary Science that deals with the physical. The physical is increasingly mediated through matter, and its reduction in size and shape is the result of a rapid expansion of population. As the number of people on the planet continues to grow, so does the planet's population, swelling the Earth’s growing void in the form of voids, each with its own unique physical and virtual properties. Microchiming becomes even more critical as the human population explosion continues to consume more of the Earth’s finite earth. The future looks bright indeed with the potential to be a land of abundant resources, green spaces and beautiful places. What we don’t yet know is how to cultivate that future. The future may well be populated with monsters, but we do not yet know what that might entail.In the present, we are living through a micro-temporal equivalent of what the Anthropocene was in the past – a &quot;Great Acceleration&quot;, if you like – a time when the human species is undergoing a process of constant expansion and contraction, of which the word ‘emergence’ is often used synonymously. As the Anthropocene is being made, the number of species on the planet is increasing at an exponential rate, with nearly all of them becoming extinctions on a regular basis. As the number of species on the planet doubles, the number of species that are endangered will likewise double. If the number of species on the planet doubles again in the future, then the number of species that are endangered will quintuple. Thus, the exponential growth of the species that are becoming extinct at an exponential rate is the unfolding story</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the book's title to the chapter 'Politics of Art' in his forthcoming book (with Tiziana Terranova and Laura Lamb) Shadow of Myth: Culture and Postmodernism, from Byzantium to the Present (2015).He is the host of The Current Time’s Mainstage and has written for the public radio programme Current Time with Alex Hirsch, as well as the website of the popular talk show, Stages, hosted by Juan Carlos Pascual.Sam Harris is Co-Editor of the upcoming international digital journal, Stages, covering postmodernism and contemporary art. His book Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media was published in 1984. He is a co-founder of the popular art book site, MAPS, which has published essays by artists, including Teju Cole, Carol Becker, Carol Tavris and Rob Thomas, among many others. He has also written for the magazine of the European Arts Association, The ARTIST.2 </text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the U.S.-based website PC World, where he was a finalist for the 2004 John Lennon Poet Laureate, to publications including the New York Times, where he was a columnist in the Journal of Popular Culture Theory. He is the author of The Digital Short Story: On Writing and Unwriting Media Art (with Matthew Joy) and co-editor of the online journal Popular Culture: A User’s Guide (2015).He was also a finalist for the 2009 James Beard Foundation Award for Newcomers to the Arts, and has written on the arts for the New York Times, The New Republic, The New Yorker and The Washington Post. He is the recipient of five Tony Benn Awards (2002, 'For Service to Art' in The New Republic, 'Best New Artist' in The New Yorker, 'Best Painting' in The New Yorker and 'Best Documentary' in The Washington Post) and has been a finalist for the 2011 Guggenheim Museum Prize</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the issues of culture and identity in the wake of neoliberalism to the contemporary predicament of the urban minority in postindustrial society, from the former ghettos of the cataclysm to the present moment. His latest work for the New York Times Magazine, published in January 2018, is a two-part investigation of the history of urban minority in postindustrial society.In this podcast, the curator and producer discusses the role of the artist in the creation of new cultural forms, and how that relates to the contemporary condition. Free View in iTunes

Interview with Alison Bechdel, Curator for the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, and Senior Editor of the LA Musume Robert Bechdel, Curator of the Los Angeles County Museum of Art (Los Angeles, California), respectively, discuss the curatorial role of art, its relationship to the city, and the museum as a whole. Alison Bechdel is Professor of Art History and Theory at the University of California, Santa Barbara, where she</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the pages of National Review to The New York Times, from the pages of The New Republic to The New Inquiry. He has also edited a number of anthologies, including the Journal of Aesthetics and Criticism, published by Verso Books, New York, 2004, and was a co-editor of the forthcoming online journal of the American Association for the Study of Art and Architecture. His most recent book is The End of Postmodernism: Modernity or Deleuze and Guénon? (2017).Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is Professor in Cultural Studies at McGill University and Director of the Centre for the Study of Art and Culture, McGill University, Montreal. His research interests include postmodernism, the arts, and culture in general. His books include the popular polemic Handbook for Cultural Critic (with Peter Brook and Stephen Leacock), published by McGraw-Hill, New York, (1991); Culture and Criticism: Essays on Postmodernism</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the US and UK, and from the Middle East. His latest work for MUAC, a multimedia arts and design studio based in New York, addresses the topic of identity.1. Meehan Crist, ‘The Art of Not Being Governed: Contemporaneous Power Relationships in an Anarchist Perspective’, in Contemporaneous Power (edited by Crist,Perez, &amp; Tenness), New York, 1998, pp.1–37.2. M. Adalah, ‘Towards a Theory of Contemporary Popular Culture’, in Essays in Critical Inquiry, Vol. 2, No. 4 (Fall, Issue), pp.1–23.3. Stuart Moulthroup, ‘What is the Contemporary Cultural Monograph?', in Essays in Critical Inquiry, Vol. 2, No. 4 (Fall, Issue), p.1–24.4. Thoreau, Writing in</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the pages of National Review to Modern Language Quarterly. His most recent work is published in the September 2018 issue of the New Left Review, titled Postmodernism, or, What Postmoderns Really Are.Harris, S. (2015). On the role of culture in the social reproduction of infrastructure. In S. Harris and P. C. Stine-Bisset, eds., Culture and Anarchy (2015). Routledge, London &amp; New York. pp.231–47.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer and producer. His work has addressed a broad range of topics, including the social, economic, political, and legal structures of contemporary society, and the nexus of power and control. His work has also been commissioned by the United Kingdom’s National Theatre, the U.S. State Department, and the Museum of Modern Art, New York. His latest work, Culture and Anarchy: State and Capital in Transition, was presented at the 14</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the pages of the New York Times in 2011 to the pages of the New York Review of Books in 2013. His most recent book, Postmodernism: The End of Postmodernism (2017), is the most recent in a trilogy of posthumous novels that came out in 2014. He is the recipient of three Booker Prizes and has been shortlisted for the Nobel Prize. To hear him read more, visit Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is Professor of English and Creative Writing at the University of Alberta, where he directs the English Department and is co-editor of the popular scholarly journal STYLUS. His latest books include Culture and Anarchy: Social Existentialism and the Foundations of Capitalism (with Jacob Lund, Verso, 2015) and Culture and Anarchy: From Accommodation to Decommodation (with Amanda J. Stewart, Routledge, 2015). He is the host of the CBC radio</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the pages of Being and Nothing (2015, being called the Reader in Postmodernism) to his new book Things Fall Apart: On Being and Nothing (2017, The End of Postmodernism).In this book, he focuses on the art and craft of not being governed, in the sense that is familiar to many people after having read Bezdev Tylor’s Culture and Politics of Not Being Governed, published in 1948. In the 1940s and 1950s, he talks with Nick Hornby and Tom Vandeputte about the ‘crisis of governance’ in postindustrial areas of the UK. In the 1960s and 1970s, he talks with Richard Florida, John Urry and others about ‘the crisis of culture’ in Chicago. In the 1980s and 1990s, he talks with John L. Scott, Gene Epstein and Peter Carr about ‘the crisis of language’ in Los Angeles. In the 2000s, he talks with</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the US, Canada and the United Kingdom, for publications such as Neoliberalism and Rolling Stone, among others. He has also written widely on the environment for publications such as The Washington Post, The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, among others. His most recent work was published as part of the Nature Publishing Group, Beyond Zero: Essays on the State of Being in the New Economy (2016).He is Professor in the Department of Communication Studies and Co-Director of the Centre for Research Architecture and a Senior Fellow at the Fraser Institute. His writing has previously appeared in The New Inquiry, Rolling Stone, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Inquiry, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New York Times, The New Inquiry, Rolling Stone, The New Republic, The New York Times, The New Inquiry, Rolling Stone, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New York Times, The New Republic, The</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI, but with artists and curators from all over the world?  [1] The Art of Not Being Governed, translated by Sam Harris and published in the UK and US by Verso Books, New York, 1991, p.82.Download this article as PDFSam HarrisSam Harris is an independent writer, broadcaster, and Producer. He is Professor of English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and is the author of the popular book Slow Bullets: Violence, Politics, and the U.S. Experience in Art and Culture (1984). His most recent book is The Fourth Turning: The End of Postmodernism, 1900–1970, published by Verso Books, New York, 2015.In 2014, he participated in the Liverpool Biennial, where he delivered a series of lectures, from which the following book, Slow Bullets: Politics, Art and the Meaning of Media (2015), was commissioned. He has written extensively on postmodernism, from the US and UK, for publications including New Statesman, The Nation (1994), Art and Politics, edited by Norman Mailer and Norman Brown, with contributions in The Times Literary Supplement, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, Culture and Postmodernism, with contributions in Nation, ibid., pp.103–12; Culture and Postmodernism, edited by Norman Mailer and Norman Brown, with contributions in The New Inquiry, pp.19–30; and The Fifth Turning: On Secular Education, 2000–2006, edited by Norman Brown and Sally Tallant, Routledge, London, 2007, p.100. [2] Sigmund Freud, ‘Freud’s Interpretation of the Symbolic, or Why We Fall in Love’, in Psychological Inquiry, Vol. 35, No. 1, Spring, 1988, p.141.Download this article as PDFSam Harris’s fascination with the ancient unconscious, captured in the single line</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new bi
    <text>should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new biennial.  The idea was to create a unique and dynamic curatorial way to explore a ‘contemporary urban environment’ through archival materials and archival methods, while also incorporating contemporary artworks and contemporary art practices in the same form and manner. This was done in part by incorporating the curatorial approach to the site in the curatorial process, as well as the curatorial approach to the community. These curatorial approaches would be informed by a multi-year, multi-site curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another fifty years in the future, in large part to address the wishes of the local residents and artists who wanted to preserve and expand on the site and its traditions. The plan called for the continued exploration of the site through a series of series of small-scale, community-based projects, as well as a new generation of artists and artists to come</text>
    <text>should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new biennial. These two approaches would introduce a different curatorial model that would allow the cities of the future to inhabit one another’s cities, while simultaneously asking artists to explore a geographical area of the world through different curatorial approaches. For the first approach, the curatorial language would be comprised of biennials, while for the third approach it would be comprised of a city-specific, and even international, curatorial structure. The curatorial questions would be situated in ‘different cities with sharply contrasting social, economic, and cultural contexts’. This multi-tiered curatorial proposal was not a new one, and was actually one of the main themes of the 1992 Venice Biennale, and it continues to be one of the main arguments of the biennale as a whole.  At the time, the ‘biennial model’ was being actively reconsidered by curatorial departments across the world, and the ‘biennial model’ was finding new expressions</text>
    <text>should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new biennial. In the present curatorial paradigm, the Museum of Modern Art is the sole representative of a curatorial team that includes MoMA curators, while the Architecture of Tomorrow is the sole representative of a larger curatorial team that is responsible for a specified set of exhibitions. The Museum of Modern Art has a long-term vision for the city that is generally shared between the other two curatorial teams, while the Architecture of Tomorrow is a uniquely positioned team with a particular set of interests. Neither the Biennale website, nor any subsequent media reports of the event clearly stated which team was in charge of the exhibitionary structure. In the MoMA curatorial plan, the team in charge of the building were given broad discretionary powers to build the structure however they pleased, and to hire any artists they wanted to work with. While this seems like a positive development for artists in the United States and around the world, it raises serious questions about the level of autonomy and responsibility that</text>
    <text>should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new biennial.  One was a ‘city in the museum’s image, in which work done in the city would be recalled and reproduced in the museum, while a ‘town or neighbourhood’ image would emphasize individual and small‑scale achievement.  The other was a ‘city in the museum’s image, but with urban structures and neighbourhoods instead of individual artists’ work.  The fact that both the ‘city in the museum’ and ‘city in the neighbourhood’ frame the biennial’s curatorial mission meant that it could also address a specific and powerful interest of the area: a ‘needle in a haystack’.  The museum would host the ‘art space of the future’, where artists could anchor their artistic practices, while the neighbourhood would house the local art fair, art fairs, and ‘community centres of the future’.   A needle in a haystack is</text>
    <text>should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new biennial. In the older approach, the form of the biennial was modified – its  	occurrence was no longer conditioned by the development of the city’s infrastructure, but rather was a function of the city’s culture. In the new curatorial approach, the biennial would be expected to manifest its cultural assets at regular intervals throughout the year, and would no longer be restricted to the development of the city’s infrastructure. These curatorial approaches were developed in response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department’s Art and Culture initiative, which was launched in response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art and Architecture series, and which entailed the production of new curatorial approaches through the production of art and architecture that could be exhibited in a museum setting.These new curatorial approaches incorporated an artist’s ‘base64 domain mapping file’ and URL mapping software program that mapped</text>
    <text>should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new biennial.  Such a curatorial approach implied a relationship between artworks and the socio-politically connected, connecting to the site-specificity of artworks and the socio-cultural dynamics of the area. It was a way to experiment with the idea of a ‘biennial per se’, a term that had been used by MoMA to describe the curatorial approach to the institution. In the case of a biennial, the term ‘biennial’ referred to the total number of exhibitions, while ‘series’ referred to the individual works in the exhibition. In the case of a ‘series’, the term ‘edition’ referred to the number of pieces selected for a particular exhibition. Within the biennial, ‘edition’ referred to the physical, photographic and electronic media of the exhibition, while ‘series’ referred to the online texts and images of the exhibition. Within the new curatorial approach to the journal,</text>
    <text>should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new biennial that would address a new generation of artists and the city’s urban future.  The museum was to develop a new curatorial model that incorporated a multi-tiered exhibitionary structure that would offer a ‘snapshot’ of the city’s cultural landscape, while the smaller exhibitionary format would offer a snapshot of a particular city in a particular ‘snapshot-like’ temporal framework. The idea was to create a space that simultaneously captured the spatial characteristics of the city that the museum was attempting to describe while also mapping the city’s cultural trajectory. In other words, the curatorial language of the museum and the spatial grammar of the city were to be replaced by the more pedestrian-friendly and accessible methods of archiving and documentation that would permit a more detailed and continuous mapping of the city.  A spatial mapping of the city was to be accomplished by a ‘period’ that would occur roughly every 60 days (with or without a new</text>
    <text>should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new biennial. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another two more years in the future, and then it would be replaced with a new ‘fourth approach’ that would repeat the same exhibition structure, but would also introduce a few curatorial innovations. These ‘fourth approaches’ would be commissioned by, and open to a MoMA curatorial team led by, Dame Janet Smith.These new art historical interventions would be published in a new collection of archival materials and archival methods called ‘The Contemporary Condition’, and would be co-commissioned by, and open to a select group of curators led by Dame Janet Smith. These curatorial approaches would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would repeat for another two more years in the future, and then it would be replaced with a new ‘fifth approach’ that would</text>
    <text>should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new biennial. I proposed that the original curatorial approach to the city, which had been based on a capitalist logic of quantity over quality, should be restructured to take into account the needs of the local communities that were being served by the Biennale. The proposal was made in the context of the local crisis of spatiality, which was manifested most visibly in the reduced number of museums and large art collections. The city’s burgeoning urban culture scene was being fed by the Biennale, and the curatorial shift to a more ‘local’ focus would mean that many of the museum collections would be placed in the hands of the local governments, arts organisations and local art collectors. Such a situation would mean that the art collections would have to be conserved and distributed throughout the city, which meant that the cultural exchange between the city and the countryside would have to happen on a smaller scale. This was also part of the rationale for the fact that, during the 1960s and 1970</text>
    <text>should be curated by the city’s museums and large collections agencies that were part of the city’s Development Force, and were responsible for acquiring and managing the city’s cultural assets. The idea was to create a unique way to explore the city that would be open to a local artist exploring the city through archival materials and archival methods. This was in part a response to the Museum of Modern Art’s (MoMA) Art Department, which was currently developing a new curatorial approach that would better integrate art, architecture, and social practice. The curatorial approach would be informed by a multi-year curatorial plan that would include a biennial, a smaller number of smaller-scale, shorter-term exhibitions. The exhibitionary format would be repeated for another consecutive biennial in the future. The plan called for two parallel approaches to the same site: a ‘second approach’ to a much older, and a ‘third approach’ to a new biennial. The idea was to simultaneously present both the old and the new approaches to the same cultural resource at the same time. This new curatorial approach would combine the curatorial thinking of a museum with the curatorial skills of an architect. The term ‘architecture of the future’ seemed to capture this new perspective on the city. While the architects had a particular focus on transport and logistics in the 1980s, their research and planning for the cities that would one day be run by the museums came to fruition in many aspects of the project. The museum was seen as an essential building block of this new ‘future city’.For many decades, the museum was the site of one of two opposing approaches to urbanisation. The city was perceived as an island of extraordinary beauty, where the architecture of today was considered beautiful and the city was regarded as nothing more than an image of poverty and deprivation. As a result, the museum’s mission was to represent the city</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza Area: Design bureau | Photo: Ronen Rotem 	In 2015, the Board of Visitors established an area in East Jerusalem known as ‘Temple Mount’ – Jerusalem’s Al-Aqsa Mosque – as the site for the future site of the Palestinian national mosque. After the establishment of the mosque, the Board of Visitors plans to rebuild the Nakba, or historical displacement, settlement – a name given to the historical loss of Arab land and sovereignty – and commence building a new historical Temple. The Nakba is a geopolitical and urban-design concept that seeks to encompass all of Jerusalem, while the Temples are individual buildings that embody specific pieces of the puzzle. The purpose of the new structures is to house both Jewish and Muslim prayer sites, a museum dedicated to the Palestinian religion, and a public plaza space that is themselves discrete religious sites. The aim of this process is to create a city that neither celebrates nor resents the Nakba. If the new Jerusalem is</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.AI’s Board of Visitors, 2016. Photo courtesy of AIB.The AIB was founded in 1886 by Max Nordau, an American anthropologist and the father of AI, who was born in Berlin. Max Nordau is considered one of the founding fathers of Artificial Intelligence (AI), and his ideas about the relationship between humans and machines are foundational to the field. Nordau believed that the potentialities of AI meant that new social forms could be created, and that the possibilities for conflict were to be eliminated. He suggested that the potential social impacts of AI should be used to create new social forms, not used for the sake of it.In his book The Structure of Society, Nordau develops this argument in relation to working-class culture. He argues that the technological determinants of culture – technological determinants, or &quot;laws of causality&quot;) – determined what ideas and images could be produced, and that this ‘constituted</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2015. Photo courtesy of AIB.Download this article as PDFAna Laura Lopéz de la TorreAna Laura Lopéz de la Torre is an artist, writer, educator and researcher in the Occupied Palestinian Territory (oPt.). She is a co-founder of the Centre for Studies and Documentation in the Palestinian Territory (CSPRT), an organisation with a particular focus on the Palestinian narrative, that she established in 2003 in Ramallah, and whose board of trustees includes prominent figures from the PLO, including Saeb Erekat, the PLO Executive Board, former members of Fatah Central Committee, and others. She is also the executive director of the Centre for Documentation and Research in the Occupied Palestinian Territory (CDRO), an organisation that provides a platform for the production of knowledge and knowledge-producing capacity through research projects, public programs, and events. She is a founding board member of the Centre for Documentation and Research in the West</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2015. Photo courtesy of AIB.Download this article as PDFAna Laura López de la TorreAna Laura López de la Torre is a journalist and writer. She joined the AIB in 1997 and worked there from 1999 to 2007. She has written for El Universal, El Pais, Televisa, and TeleSUR, among other publications.She is also the curator of the El Pais Store and Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition series El Pais del Mundo Unidos. She is a member of El Pais Society for Computer and Network Engineers, El Triennalee de Mexico, El Arboretum, and El Pais Foundation.She has co-authored with Noel Burch The Gallery as a Problem Space?: The Impact of a Cultural Centre on a Local Economy and was a consultant to the New York-based architect Norman Wilkinson on the project for which he was awarded a Knight’s Medal. She</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza City, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.  	The Board of Visitors convenes several times a year. The 2014 visit was its usual, but the AIB decided to convene another visit in December 2015, due to the events in Ukraine and Syria. Its purpose is to monitor developments in the Middle East and North Africa, and to encourage and promote dialogue between different stakeholders, in order to maximise the impact of its activities. It also provides an incentive for other biennials to do the same.In 2014, the Board of Visitors convened its second annual congress, in New York. There, it was very evident that the activities of the organisation in the United States and internationally were much more pronounced. There were demonstrations in New York and Washington, and in London, and the AIB decided to create a branch office in Istanbul. The decision was made to establish an autonomous hub in Istanbul, and to establish a presence there solely to carry out its mission. This was seen by many</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza: visit with Palestinian students’ at Hebrew University in Jerusalem, November 2013. AIB Board of Visitors, historic West Bank and Gaza, photo courtesy of the AIB. Visit with Palestinian students’ in Bethlehem, October 2013. AIB Board of Visitors, historic West Bank and Gaza, photo courtesy of the AIB. Visit with Palestinian artists’ in East Jerusalem, November 2013. AIB Board of Visitors, historic West Bank and Gaza, photo courtesy of the AIB. Visit with Palestinian artists’ in Bethlehem, October 2013. AIB Board of Visitors, historic West Bank and Gaza, photo courtesy of the AIB. Visit with Ma’an family members and friends in Silwan, October 2013. AIB Board of Visitors, historic West Bank and Gaza, photo courtesy of the AIB. Visit with Ma’an family members and friends in Silwan, October 2013. AIB Board of Visitors, historic West Bank and Gaza, photo courtesy of the AIB</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2016. Photo courtesy of AIB. 	One of the challenges of the work we’re doing in the Gaza Strip right now is the migration of the population. We started a facebook page ‘For Gaza’ with the official ‘Facebook page’ of AIB in Gaza. We also started a twitter feed ‘For Gaza’ with the official ‘Twitter feed’ of AIB in Gaza. We’ve created a blog ‘For Gaza’ with the official ‘Blog page’ of AIB in Gaza. We’ve also started a series of podcasts ‘For Gaza’ which follow the social dynamics of the conflict. We’ve also started a youtube channel ‘For Gaza’ which follows the cultural dynamics of the conflict. In parallel, we have created an online magazine called ‘The Gaza Quartet’ which follows cultural dynamics in the Gaza Strip. It’s published by the</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.PreviousNextAIB Board of Visitors activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.

The Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.

The Board of Visitors activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.

The Board of Visitors activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.

The Board of Visitors activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.

The Board of Visitors activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.

The Board of Visitors activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.

The Board of Visitors activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB.

The Board of Visitors activities in the West Bank and</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza, 2014. Photo courtesy of AIB. 	[1] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Abandoned Property (1879), in Reflections on the Abandoned Cultures of Modern Art, edited by Søren Kierkegaard and Anders Upperland, Princeton Architectural Press, Princeton, 1921, p.34.Download this article as PDFAna Laura López de la TorreAna Laura López de la Torre is an architect and principal in charge of the architecture practice at the AIB. She is also the author of Reflections on the Abandoned Cultures of Modern Art (2014), which documents the experiences of the community of artists, textile workers, historians and artists who formed the Center for Research on Art and Culture (CRAC) in 2014. Her work has received numerous awards and has been featured in numerous publications and journals worldwide. She was recently appointed as the Director of the Lanham Art Center, Maryland, USA,</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIB’s interests and the purposes of the organisation's activities.AIB is a registered charity incorporated in 1985. Since its inception, it has worked to promote a ‘culture of peace and love’ in the Palestinian territories through educational, cultural and direct action. It is based in New York, and its board of directors is comprised of representatives from the United States, Canada and the Palestinian territories. As of 2014, it was investigating plans to establish an AIB-like organisation in the West Bank and Gaza, with a mandate to oversee cultural activities there and to develop actionable strategies to achieve ‘a just and lasting settlement of the conflict’.The AIB has undertaken many projects in the West Bank and Gaza, as well as in East Jerusalem, Bethlehem, and the Gaza Strip. The activities of the organisation’s Board of Visitors, which it maintains on a regular basis, is as follows: AIB Board of Visitors’ activities in the West Bank and Gaza: visiting schools, kindergartens, orphanages, homes for the handicapped, construction sites and the like; contributing to community events such as ‘Soccer Days’ and ‘Futura Days’ in Bethlehem; and designing and building facilities for community use such as cafeterias, kindergartens, childcare facilities, and so forth. More generally, the Board of Visitors promotes human rights and contributes to the promotion of democratic institutions throughout the world through its publications, seminars and so forth. Since 2014 the Board has been investigating plans to create a biennial based in East Jerusalem. The plans have been forwarded to the Israeli government for authorization.Should the plans become law, they would create a new division between East Jerusalem and the West Bank, one that would separate the city’s urban fabric from its desert landscape; assigning a specific number of restrictions to each district – East Jerusalem, West Jerusalem, and the Gaza Strip – and establishing a national museum for each district. This</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to collectors enabled them to pick up on trends in art-historical and ethnographic interest. As biennials expanded south, in the form of long-term membership in a professional organisation, they became entwined with the collections of regional art collectors and travelled there to pick up on local trends. In doing so, they provided valuable data on trends in art’s social, economic and political contexts. And they did so in the service of the collection they were entrusted with preserving.This symbiosis of large-scale institutional collections with evolving and dispersed community collections highlights the important role of data, gathering and archiving in the contemporary biennial format. And yet the scale, density and intricacy of the archive today makes it seem as if the biennial could be anything but a collection of artefacts. Rapid advances in scientific, technological and organisational knowledge, coupled with the dispersed and mobile lifestyles of our urban populations, necessitate a different form of archiving. And the biennial form is</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to collectors enabled collections to be gathered and distributed across networks of sharing and exchange. The collection that we know today as the art market was created largely through the collection of biennials and large institutional art collectors. The biennial character is further developed through the collection and exchange of other collections and large institutional collections. It is possible that the biennial form would have begun with a set of selected artists and collectors, gathering information from artists and documenting their activities. This is not how it is perceived by collectors and art collectors, who see a collection as a complex collection of diverse assets. The collection as a collection of diverse assets is the prevailing paradigm in art valuation, and the dominant paradigm in valuing cultural assets. The collection as a collection of diverse assets is the prevailing paradigm in valuing socially and politically. It is the prevailing paradigm because it is financially sustainable, culturally inert and, above all, socially malleable.The biennial format is politically contextualised within the broader concept of the permanent public gallery</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to collectors and art professionals enabled collections of several hundred paintings and a great variety of works of art to be gathered in one location. As collections became more extensive and diverse, and the biennial’s resources diversified, the biennial’s form became increasingly elastic, allowing it to adopt new media and formats of collection-building, including the collection of its local elected board of directors. In doing so, it fulfilled a range of functions beyond the museum: it established a shared vocabulary, common practices and expectations, and facilitated the exchange of ideas and experiences. It also fostered a certain amount of paranoia about the other, more institutionalised forms of cultural production, particularly in the developing world, which it perceived to be posing a threat to the biennial. As Frank Baum, the archivist and curator of the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, put it: ‘We are acutely aware that our biennial format is deeply dependent on the exchange between global art collectors and their populations</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to collectors allowed collections there to adopt a common language, a shared vocabulary and a shared interpretation of the same cultural practices and beliefs (which were understood by all three audiences). The biennial format has persisted in parts of the world where the biennial is a regular (but often transient) event, and in parts where it is a rarefaction with collectors from diverse areas and interests. It is important to distinguish between the different biennials. The main set of biennials in North America, for example, is Museum of Modern Art (MMA), followed by the Museum of Modern Art, which features works from all three biennials. The main biennial organisers in Europe and the Middle East are Qatar Foundation and Al Ain University, which together host around 30 events a year. In Asia, we have the Asian Philharmonic Association, which is the largest in North America and organises over 100 events a year. And in the Pacific, we have the Asian Foundation, which organises events</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to collectors enabled collections from all over the world to converge on a single location. The collection-shifting nature of the biennial – a collection of biennials meeting together to address a local audience – has continued to generate new forms of cultural production. In many cities, a biennial can be found in the same city for several years in a row, while in other cities it has been found in different cities for several years in succession. This observation was made by the art critic Frederic Jameson (1869–1971), who observed that the biennial form entered its thirty-first year of existence in New York and London, in June and July respectively. Collection-shifting and Precursor CuresBy the late nineteenth century, the biennial was showing increasing signs of declining cultural value. Art transactions with a social purpose were being carried out at an increasing pace, and the concerns of the art buyer were being migrated to sites of exchange rather than isolated individual collectors. Art buyers were starting to</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to collectors enabled collections from all over the world to be collected and used within a biennial context.[1] The early twentieth century saw the emergence of a biennial phenomenon in all its many forms, with collectors from all over the globe finding common cause with collectors from different parts of the world. It was at this juncture that biennials began to find their way into art museums, and later into art collections. In the twenty-first century, biennials are increasingly common in art institutions, particularly in those areas of the world where art is fiction to a large extent, but where the social significance of fiction is under intense assault. With the exception of a few rare exceptions, such as Venice, the major biennials of the twenty-first century are located in cities, particularly in the West. The biennial format is of course no panacea. It is true that the value of a biennial in terms of its own right is questionable. The biennial is an episodic production</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to collectors enabled them to pick up on trends in art distribution and consumption. Consequently, the first biennials quickly established a globally visible presence and established a direct line of communication with collectors and artworld managers. By the 1920s, this direct connection was proving to be vital, as a biennial had become the preferred exhibition format for the then nascent art world. The biennial form then spread to other regions, becoming increasingly regionalised and complex, and today it is found in a number of countries, but especially in Africa, the Middle East and Asia. It was at this time that the term ‘biennial’ was coined and understood its extended sense of ‘nation’.Today, ‘the biennial format is a convention that is used to categorise a set of objects or collections into discrete exhibitions, usually arranged according to a national or urban festival’. In this sense, exhibitions in and about museums and other large institutional contexts are classified as biennials.</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to collectors allowed them to pick up on trends in art supply and demand, and thus act as a filter for art’s activities. The biennial format began to be adopted in other parts of the world, and its appearance in Liverpool dates back to at least the eighteenth century. The term comes from Arabic, and is derived from the Latin bimonthractatus, &quot;a few selected items … [and] articles … delivered to the emperor … at the end of each reign … to be given up in exchange for articles of state goods&quot;]. The biennial format gained currency in the late nineteenth century in response to the financial crisis, and continues to be a feature of the global biennial market today. The total biennial market today stands at over US$4 billion, with over 100 biennials operating in over 100 countries.4. Large-scale international art fairs and the biennial as exhibition format. In recent years, art fairs have become increasingly important as exhibition formats for</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to collectors enabled collections from all over the world to be gathered into one place. Since the nineteenth century, biennials have gathered material directly from artists and art collectors, often publishing these collections in biennials, and have a history of collaboration that goes back to the nineteenth century.Biennials have also co-opted traditional forms of cultural production, from the museum or the gallery to the workshop or the workshop (or even classroom) with which artists and art professionals traditionally worked, and have used this toolkit to produce cultural outcomes that are informed by the collector’s particular interests and agendas. These include, for instance, the ‘Triennial hypothesis’ (a.k.a. the ‘four hundred and fifty-one’ edition of the Venice Biennale being the most recent example), the current globalisation of art and cultural exchange, and the use of online cultural resources. In a general sense, biennials are the repositories and platforms of what have become</text>
    <text>The next Liverpool Biennial will take place in 2019 and will be the largest and most international of its kind. It will be the largest art institution in the world, showcasing a wide range of artists from all over the world, as well as emerging and established biennials, curatorial approaches and curatorial approaches to art in emerging and old age. It will be the most radical and most autonomous institution of its kind, able to offer a range of activities and cultural exchanges that are not confined to the artist’s studio or institution, but that also take place in other contexts.The biennial format is a form of cultural production that emerged in large measure through a collaboration between biennials and large institutional art collectors. It emerged in Europe and North America in the nineteenth century, the latter partly due to a financial surplus arising from the sale of artworks by museums, mainly in the form of institutional collections. Biennials began to collect and disseminate artworks across a geographical area, and their close working relationship to collectors enabled them to pick up on trends in art and art culture, and thus to observe and respond to art’s temporal condition and geographical heterogeneity.[1] The biennial format has spread to other parts of the world, is still widespread in Israel and the Palestinian territories, and is now an increasingly important exhibitionary form in China and the Middle East. It was crucial for the Palestinian biennial to establish a strong presence in China before the end of its curatorial mandate in 2020, at the latest, because the first two exhibitions would be held in stages during the year 2020. The biennial format has been shown in Venice, Baie-Juniper Hall, Shanghai, Dhaka, and Istanbul. It was also shown in New York, Liverpool, and London. Liverpool Biennial 2018 will be exhibited in the Tate Modern Turbine Hall of the Arts, London (November 2018), and in the Tate Modern Turbine Hall of the Arts, Liverpool (January 2019).On another level</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
