<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet
    <text>future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet and social media, the aesthetic, and in particular, the curated aesthetic, is also affected by changes in the socio-political situation. Modern aesthetics, and the curatorial work that results, is constantly open to the changes that socio-political circumstances may bring, and to the possibility that these circumstances may not only bring about some things that artists produce, but may also produce new forms of artistic expression. The contemporary curatorial gesture is a contemporary artefact of the postcolonial and racialised condition, and its curatorial value is a function of the conditions on which it is erected. This is true both of the places where the art is actually located, and of course also of course of course in all art forms – but the particularity of this identification with the museum and museum-world is that there is only so much that can be contained within the museum-world, and that there is only so much that can be conveyed through the art-world medium. In other words, the real creativity and</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet and social media, it is easy to identify the contemporary artist who is working in the new media era, but these are fragile assets, and the media revolution that followed them wiped out the old art forms that were ephemeral, transient and subject to the whims of market forces. The aesthetic is ephemeral, and its images are ephemeral. The aestheticisation of the present is a global enterprise, and the aestheticisation of beauty as a commodity is an aestheticising enterprise. To some, this may seem absurd, to others it may be deeply problematic. But the fundamental premise of the aesthetic is that we live among those who look back at a past that was never really there, and who consequently lack any recollection of the past. Modern aestheticisms of the aestheticised aestheticised present are always anti-recurrent, and so they always demand a certain amount of consciousness of the future. For many people, however, this present – the aestheticised present – is something that they perceive, and</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet and social media, the artist has almost entirely ceded the art-historical role to social media, which has transformed what counts as art into something that can be shared. This is why contemporary artists are often accused of being apolitical, or apolitical but not beautiful, because they do not put a face to the shared media images they create. They do not put a face to the images they create because they are so acutely aware of the images they are creating, and their audiences are aware of them. This is a quality that the modern artist shares with our contemporary consumer, but unlike artists of yesteryear, today’s artists do not have a studio audience or gallery audience, because there is no gallery hierarchy in the United States or Europe. In both the United States and Europe, galleries are places where art is appreciated in equal measure, and are places where contemporary art is experienced most fully. The contemporary artist must therefore find other venues in which to explore these contemporary art-histories</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet and social media, the artist has become more present, but this does not necessarily make the work better. The emphasis today is on image-based media such as video and images, and the artist is often seen utilising her position to further commercial ends. Consequently, it is easy to see why, in the age of the Internet and social media, the role of the artist is often seen as one of many ways to profit from the work. I have often thought that the contemporary art market is more interested in images than images, and the role of the artist is often seen as a way to position the work in an image. For example, Nina Edge, whose work I featured in the Tate Modern Bulletin, took part in the crowdfunding campaign to commission the installation of a Roman statue in Liverpool, and was patron of the exhibition The One Show. She also commissioned the installation of a David Bowie cover in the Welsh Streets, and used the money raised to commission a series of paintings by artists including Paul McCarthy</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet and social media, the artist’s role is to produce images that are immediately recognisable and can be shared – on a global or regional basis. The problem with the contemporary aesthetic is that it produces images that are not immediately recognisable, and this is why contemporary art has to grow older in order to find a place in the cultural mix. The beauty of the contemporary artist’s contemporary work is that it contains a temporal dimension, and this is what the artist does with the images that are produced. The images that are produced are always undergoing change, and so the artist has to be able to predict what the future might bring, and how that might affect images that are made. The artist cannot produce images that are immediately recognisable, but images that are recognisable nevertheless have to be flexible and can be modified and changed through experimentation. The modern artist’s contemporary work is therefore often criticised for being too static, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being static at all.</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet and social media, the artist is no longer the sole user of an artistic body, but everyone is a user of the body. Thus, the contemporary curatorial role is to a large extent an image-producing one, and the contemporary aesthetic is characterised by an excess of visual media that sees the value of appearances in an ever more pervasive way.The aestheticising of appearance therefore has political and social connotations, and it is this excess that is thought to underlie contemporary art’s increasing political importance. In the age of the Internet and social media, political participation is encouraged not only by the media itself, but also by the material features of artworks that circulate online, including images. Thus, contemporary art is often depicted as being at odds with traditional forms of participation, and this is often seen as a good thing. In the age of the biennial and museum visit, the presence of artworks in places such as schools and community centres is constantly in motion, enabling people to come</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet and social media, it is not enough for art to be aesthetically accessible; it is even necessary for art to be aesthetically unique. In the age of the biennial and the museum, it is enough for art to be present in museum collections, but this is no longer the case. It is becoming increasingly difficult for artists to communicate their visions of the world, and this affects the value of their art as a whole. When the biennial and the museum are absent from a city, or when they move into a neighbourhood, or even when they are no longer based in a city, the value of the art as a whole diminishes. Artworks from the Twentieth Century are an ExceptionTo the modern aesthetic, beauty is understood as something that can be quantified and captured and transmitted, and beauty is both understood as being maximally transformatory and inherently contradictory. The theory of Cultural Capital attributes the enormous increase in social value that has occurred in the social sphere in the last fifty years</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet and social media, the artist is everywhere, and especially accessible. But this is no longer the case. The consumption of culture-related goods is the dominant form of aestheticisation in the contemporary world, and the market is no exception. The contemporary aesthetic is marked by a commercial imperative to be bought, and therefore any artistic or curatorial gesture that challenges this commercial imperative is likely to generate self-serving commercial benefits for the artist. In this context, the contemporary contemporary aesthetic can be seen as offering solutions to the problems of a rapidly urbanising world – solving the appearance conundrum by creating an image that is both universal and iconic – via the presentation of a diverse range of cultural products that can be attributed to the artist. As the market dictates, this image must be digestible by consumers, and yet it is seen as desirable in that it creates the appearance of things that are not what the artist intended. This is the dynamic at work in the contemporary market, and it is no exaggeration to say that</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet and social media, we can see the impact of this in the way in which art is performed today: the aesthetic quality that is expected of art performance is realised in a way that is disconnected from the actuality of art performance. Beauty is often performed at an early stage in the development of a work, before the artist has even completed developing her/his body of ideas. This is why artists tend to develop their works much earlier, and perform them much more widely, than in the past. It is also why beauty is an aesthetic quality that is constantly in flux. It is difficult to define what art is, or can be, and this is one of the reasons why, despite the various attempts at categorisation, we are constantly seeking a way to fold in and incorporate the art form into our own artistic practice. For instance, in the tradition of the biennial, the first Venice Biennale, the Biennale board decided in 1993 that there would be a 30th anniversary edition in</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which seek to reconcile the artist’s end of the bargain, with the curatorial meaning of the art’s end of the bargain. It is an art form that endorses its own forms of beauty, in the guise of a curatorial form, and in the guise of an aesthetic form, and celebrates its own aesthetic form as a way of thinking about beauty and beauty in contemporary art.Beauty as a Form of BeautyThe modern aesthetic is characterised by an inordinate focus on appearance, and is particularly attuned to the individual needs of today’s population. The contemporary aesthetic demands an excessive amount of material, and uses this material to create an image of things that are not what they used to be, or, at the very least, an image that is not of things that are different. This is why modern art is often criticised for being too present, and contemporary art is often criticised for not being present at the right time. In the era of the Internet and social media, the artist’s role is to produce visual artefacts that are shared, can be shared, and disappear at the right time. The aesthetic need is to be present at the right time, and at the right place. The contemporary artist therefore becomes both a traveller, and a settler. He or she must be present at the right time, and at the right place. This is why, in the modern age, it is so important for an artist to have a global reach, and why it is so important for artists to have a global reach, and to be able to touch, and engage, and enliven, and mingle across cultures. It is part of the contemporary artist’s job to be able to engage, and to be able to mingle across cultures. But this is no easy thing to do, or to achieve. It takes massive organisation and discipline, and this is why the contemporary artist’s career, and the art form</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material, since at the time, electronic material was the language of the infrastructural form. She showed me an archive that she had found an old postcard from. It was a black and white photo collage, collage-like in its arrangement, but with bold lettering and images, almost like a magazine spread. It was an image collage, in that the images were arranged chronologically – from the earliest historical examples to the most modern and contemporary examples of the form. In this way, it reflected the temporal order in which the interview was arranged.[xiv] One of the questions we asked her was whether there were any images of the essay that had not been published yet. She said that there were several essays published already in 2014 – Judith Butler’s work was recently shortlisted for the Oxford American Book of 2014. But she also said that her project had to be selective, since it was about celebrating the work of artists, not about offering a definitive</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material, because it came from images, documents or hard copies of the actual exhibition. Bartholdy has a particular interest in the role that art institutions had in the history of the twentieth century, and she helped me research the role that the museums had in the twentieth century. She also pointed me to a new generation of biennials that are increasingly independent, quantitative and urban, and which I would add are often not aware of this independence and quantitativeity within their curatorial portfolios.  Her interest is in curatorial perforations, in that they occur when there is a chance for spontaneity and emergence. In that sense, they are almost like new intellectual movements.  She also pointed me to a new generation of biennials that are increasingly urban and quantitative, and which I would add are often not aware of this urbanity and quantitativeity within their curatorial portfolios. I have to say that these new levels of urbanisation and urban perforation are radically opposed to the medieval levels</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material, since it came from a private collection. I would say that the amount of visual anthropology that was done on the project was extensive, and that material from the Biennale was a variant of that. When you combine visual anthropology with material from the real world, you get a completely different kind of understanding of the world. Transnational curators and artists’ many fans are quick to point out that none of this material ever existed in the form that biennials have nowadays. This is true in principle, but in practice this isn’t always possible, and in the case of the Biennale it often isn’t ever going to be possible, to recreate the sort of radical reconfiguration of the world that we would advocate if we could – for example, reviving the forgotten civil rights movements. The materiality of the commission and its appearance – in the 1980s and 1990s it was a prominent feature of the art world, now it is a largely unreal</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material – over 10,000 documents – in the form of maps, annotated with annotations by me, covering almost a third of the city. She also did some of the archival research for the book, which was based on documents from the N.S.A. She said that, although the documents that emerged after the N.S.A.'s programs ended were &quot;not exactly the way that things had been planned&quot;, the relationship between the art department and the military intelligence agency had been marked by an understanding that, at the end of the war, the N.S.A. would provide critical information for the planning of future conflicts. She said that, while there were many risks involved in such a venture, the agency’s work in this context was clearly seen as having significant value. She stressed the agency’s role was one of many, and that its value should be evaluated in the context of the larger society. Bartholdy believes that the relationship between the N</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material, because it was made up of photographs and video recordings. It took several hours of painstakingly piecing together a reconstructed programme in the art department library, each item by its own name, with fragmentary descriptions. The result is a very long and somewhat unsatisfying list: some of the curators were upset by the length of the process, others by the lack of interest shown by the public in the material, still others by the fact that the material was still relevant in 2015, and still others by the fact that the curators themselves had stopped reading contemporary art magazines. As an undergraduate, I found much of what I know of the contemporary art world fascinating, and I find much of what I know of archival curating distressing. But I also know that I can and should research and analyse my own work, and that is a cornerstone of a curatorial purpose. I also know that when I do research, it should be based on facts, and not on what others might</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material – about 4,000 volumes – which was transmitted to the public domain in 1990. Although there is a digital version of this material, its primary purpose is to support the structural work of a museum. It is a museum that was built on the back of the archival material it collects, in much the same way that an archive collects its material. It is a museum that is built on the back of the ephemeral media that it finds itself immersed in. It collects, exhibits and assembles this material in volumes and formats that are as variable and unpredictable as life itself. It collects it in the form of a database –   The Biennial Reader – so that it may be able to be counted among the exhibits of a museum, a collection of objects or a set of related related things. In the case of a biennial, the collection would be a ‘big data dump’, gathering information on a large scale about the institution’s activities, motivations and materials in</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material, because the sculpture and painting was installed in the church pews. In the event, this material became a monument, although it was mostly concerned with the worldly – the concrete, strings, ropes, metal, wires, tape, nuts, screws and other building parts that comprise the Biennale. The material it incorporated was of course of a different kind, made of plastic, rubber and iron. It was much more like water – a substance – and could therefore be broken down into its constituent parts and processed in a similar way to our own bodies. Bartholdy and her team managed to acquire all the materials they needed, but it still remained a long distance from its first application.  So what had started as a single application of these new technological aids as a way to imagine archival material at a broader scale in contemporary art production ended up constituting a much stronger statement about the technological capacities of artists and their bodies (as well as the society as a whole) than the original thinking allowed</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material, since the committee that curated the Venice Biennale was made up of art historians, archivists, journalists and others with a range of expertise in art and visual culture. Bartholdy and I collaborated extensively on the project, publishing a book together called The Biennale Chronicles. In the book, we reviewed the curatorial approaches of the past ten biennales and the subsequent development of contemporary curatorial approaches in the context of Venice. One of the things that stood out in the book was the marked changes in the relationship between biennales and the city that were experienced by both the biennale and the city in the years immediately following the venues' establishment. In the early twentieth century, biennales were primarily urban phenomena; in the second half of the twentieth century, global and regionalization combined to create new urban crises. But as urban problems became globalized, the biennale experienced a change throughout its form – it became something that happened in cities, and especially</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material, because, as you might imagine, a major exhibition of art was planned for those days. As you might imagine, this material was extremely time-consuming to process, and the curators felt that it was important to let the art speak its own story, in its own terms. So Bartholdy and her team created a series of video and photographic essays that functioned as a kind of paradoxical history of visual culture in the 21st century. These came out of a creative perforation between art and biennials, between visual culture and the social. Their form of archival material, which seems stylised and trivialised on the surface but has many rich layers underneath, is a clever evasion that avoids the problem of what to do with it when it is no longer a visual culture asset. It is, rather, a way to work through the paradoxes of modern art production and consumption.It was an exchange of art and biennials, then, that created and defined</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by, for example, the Museum of Modern Art, since the latter has a documentary-style format.) But even if this were so, the fact that we do have films and videos in our digital possession would still mean almost nothing to us, except perhaps as evidence that exists on a website that can be indexed. A small collection of vintage photographs and a few drawings, texts or photographs would suffice. An archive search in Google Books would yield many thousands of items, many of which would be of interest to biographers and researchers interested in the history of visual art. However, the question remains whether such materials exist in the abstract at all. As an undergraduate, I did my research in the art department of the University of Oslo, where I eventually met Merete Bartholdy. She was one of the curators of the Venice Biennale, and we worked with her and her team on a project that lasted almost two years. It was a significant amount of archival material – over 10,000 documents – which was housed mainly in boxes, in a building that was effectively a storage locker. Quoting texts from the curatorial statement from 1993, Bartholdy said that the exhibition ‘stayed out of the public domain’ and that it was only later, when the biennale was moved to a new location, that the artworks began to be ‘reclaimed’ by the biennale as a whole.  References to the ‘public domain’ are not limited to works in the public domain; they can also refer to private property, which is often misconstrued as being public. For example, the fairground that became the home to the Biennale in 1989 is now owned by the Norwegian government, and the Biennale website claims that the Biennale is ‘a global phenomenon, with a global impact’.[8] If the Biennale is viewed as a global phenomenon, then the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2Mj
    <text>future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjAy&amp;shill=1556959078.9792624177.435229958.101483928,6.988888888897.9888888881.869167044.869167046.9888888881.769167049.756916707.769167049.869167051.869167053.869167057.869167061.869167063.869167066.869167067.869167069.869167071.869167072.869167074.869167075.869167079.869167082.869167085.869167086.869167087.869167088.869167091.869167094.</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjYw&quot;}],&quot;renders&quot;:{&quot;act&quot;:&quot;article&quot;,&quot;actId&quot;:&quot;437&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;Drawing Blood: Trespassing on Private Property in Australia and New Zealand via Biennial&quot;,&quot;subtitle&quot;:&quot;Trespassing on Private Property in Australia and New Zealand via Biennial&quot;,&quot;body&quot;:&quot;[subtitle text here] In Australia, private property includes residential property, including both public and private lots. The term encompasses virtually all types of property, including lots such as residential property, but especially lots such as agricultural property, pastoral property, forestry property, mining property, commercial property and [...] more]&quot;,&quot;isReference&quot;:true,&quot;status&quot;:&quot;publishable&quot;,&quot;moreInfoCityID&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;moreInfoStateID&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;moreInfoCountryID&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;public&quot;:&quot;online&quot;,&quot;supportUserID&quot;:true,&quot;source&quot;:&quot;802b12939c979dbff48831cfbcf03afbcf4afbcf&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;Trespassing on Private Property in Australia and New Zealand via Biennial&quot;,&quot;publisher&quot;:&quot;Higher</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjAwMjAwMjAwNmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NjAyNmE2NzE2NzE2Nhc2NjAwNmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjAxNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAy5YmE2YmE2YmE2YmE2YmE2YmE2</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjAwMw&quot;}],&quot;thumbnail&quot;:&quot;https://static.biennialofsydney.com/2018/09/biennial-of-sydney-2018-exhibition-art-exhibition-2018-exhibition-wall-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.jpg?v=15056955169292921&quot;,&quot;title&quot;:&quot;From Processional to Biennial: 15 Years of the Biennial Frank Gehry Gallery, Sydney, Australia, 2017, © Frank Gehry. All rights reserved. Photo © Ewan Kinter/U’mista Art Foundation. All images courtesy of U’mista Art Foundation.&quot;,&quot;subtitle&quot;:&quot;Frank Gehry’s two year long collaboration with U’mista Art Foundation Gallery Sydney (2017-early) marks the first time that a U.S. artist has exhibited in a globally-renowned art gallery in Sydney</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjAlMmNlMjAyYkY2MjAyYkY2E2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzlMjAyYkY2MjAyYkY2E2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzaG5hZ2VzMjAyNmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0NmE0N</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjAlNkJhYyYmNkYzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2N</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjA3YmE2NzE2NzE2NjE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NjE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2Nz</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjYw&quot;}],&quot;renders&quot;:{&quot;default&quot;:{&quot;href&quot;:&quot;/schedule/7290/art-exhibitions-2018-2019.html&quot;,&quot;s&quot;:&quot;7290 6dschedule&quot;,&quot;class&quot;:&quot;event-time&quot;,&quot;type&quot;:&quot;BETA&quot;,&quot;international&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;image&quot;:&quot;https://isc.loc.gov/exhibits/7290/art-exhibitions-2018-2019.jpg?w=1080&amp;h=600&amp;q=7580&quot;,&quot;small2x&quot;:&quot;Sculpture Show, Alain Johannes &amp; Co.&quot;,&quot;medium2x&quot;:&quot;Sculpture Show, Alain Johannes &amp; Co.&quot;,&quot;large&quot;:&quot;Dazzle Bugle, Alain Johannes &amp; Co.&quot;,&quot;small3x&quot;:&quot;Sculpture Show, Alain Johannes &amp; Co.&quot;,&quot;medium3x&quot;:&quot;Sculpture Show, Alain Johannes &amp; Co.&quot;,&quot;large&quot;:&quot;Dazzle Bugle, Alain Johannes &amp; Co.&quot;,&quot;showMore&quot;:{&quot;showMore&quot;:&quot;&quot;,&quot;set&quot;:&quot;/schedule/7290/art</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjIlMjIwMmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NjAyNmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, where the public is invited to take part in the production of a (potential) work in progress. For more information, please see: https://www.biennialofsydney.com/2018/exhibition/art-exhibitions/art-exhibitions-whats-new/art-exhibitions-whats-new-20160921-hughes-beau-art-et-il-dessous-il-dessous.html#sthash.5bRiyJlMaaYkTuOdHNlJlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlMlHNlMjIlMjIlMjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2YmE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2MjIlMjFiY2E2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2YmE2NjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNWU4MGFlNzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NjEyNjEyNjEyNjEyNjEyNjEyNjEyNjEyNWU4MGFlNzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNjAyNWU4MGFlNzE2NzE2NzE2NzE2NjEyNjEyNjEyNjEy</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucr
    <text>a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy: On Human Bureaucracy (1926), in Science Fiction and Other essays, vol. 28, No. 1, January, p.287; William Burroughs, ‘Systems Instances: A Brief Pre-History of the Present’, in Systemics, or Human Bureaucracy: Toward a History of Ideas and Stories (1965), p.115. [5] Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media (1926), in Science Fiction and Other essays, vol. 28, No. 1, January, pp.289–405. [6] Systems or Information Science, the discipline that had given birth to Brave New World, was revived by the 1950s and 1960s with the emergence of Computer Science and Information Processing (CSE). By the early 1970s</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy: On the Nature and Consequences of Scientific and Mathematical Research, 1936, in Selected Essays on the Nature of Things,  2009, and my essay in Dialogue, Issues and Ideas, part of the Proceedings, of the Symposium: Systems, Universals and Futures published by the Symposium: Systems, Universals and Futures, No. 2, 2005, pp.79–97. [5] See the second part of this essay, ‘The Problem of Narrative Quality’, in Ralph Miliband &amp; Sarah Friedland, eds., Selected Essays on the Nature of Things,  2009, and part two of that same essay, ‘And Then There Were None…’, in The New Yorker, 29 November 2009, p.19–26. [6] See Lisa Parks, ‘Narrative of the Life of Frederick Douglass, Author of Animal Courier’, </text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy? Plato, Republic, or Bureaucracy?, Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1983; Thomas Allsen, From Bureaucracy to Network Culture, MacMillan, New York, 1986; Peter Brook, Aeneas Atamantorum: A Political Novel or a Physics Fictional?, MIT/Harvard UP, MA, 1989; Satish Kanady, On Sanity and the Material Culture of the Informal Workshop, Kluwer Academic Publishers, Boston, 1991; Peter Brook, The Rise of the Shadow Economy, London, 1988, and Peter Brook, Media and Society  (New York, 1989), pp.125–39. [5] See Bruce Baum, ed., The Contemporary Condition: Toward a Socially Responsible Encyclopedia of Art and Cultural Organisations, McGraw-Hill, New York, 1985. [6] William Burchell, ed.,  The New Media Reader</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy: New Media, Primitive Knowledge, and Modernity, Greenwood Press, New York, 2012. [5] See Tom Vandeputte, Systems, Fractals, and Interactive Calendars, Thunder Bay, Canada, Blackwell, Oxford, 1994. [6] Ray Bradbury, The Martian Chronicles, Simon and Schuster, New York, 1978. [7] David Harvey, The City in the Dreams of Its People, Viking, Oxford, 1975. [8] Hugo Lamb, The Fall of Gomorrah, McFarland/Prentice Hall, New York, 1976. [9] Ray Bradbury, The Martian Chronicles, Simon and Schuster, New York, 1978. [10] Evangelineal Ward, The Long Emergency, Viking, Oxford, 1972. [11] Ray Bradbury, The Martian Chronicles, Simon and Schuster, New York, 1978. [12] Ray Bradbury, The</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy: On the Nature of Computerization (1936), chapter in The New Science (1937), p. 3. [5] John Syvret, ‘On the Nature and Essence of Computer Programs’, in Proc. Roy. Soc. Lond. A, A. Asimov, London, 1867, pp. 710–42. [6] Wendy Chun, ‘Origins of Computer Programs’, in Proc. Roy. Soc. Lond. A, A. Asimov, London, 1867, pp. 710–25. [7] William H. Campbell, ‘The Structure of Computer Programs’, in Proc. Roy. Soc. Lond. A, A. Asimov, London, 1867, p. 710. [8] J. Robert Oppenheimer, ‘On the Nature of Computer Programs’, in Proc. Roy.</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy: The Cultural Logic of Space and Technology, Grove, 1999, pp.181–205; Thomas Michener, Media and Society: Essays on the Illusion of Media, Routledge, 1995, pp.183–206; Wendy Chun, ed., Media, Culture and Politics: The Politics of Art and Communications, Routledge, 2003, p.91. [5] Isaac Asimov,  	Science or Bureaucracy, p.261. [6] Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy, p.267. [7] Arthur C. Clarke, ‘The Art of Not Knowing: On Not Knowing and Being Things’, in  	Science &amp; Culture Vol. 22, No. 2, 1988, p.379. [8] Patrick Moore, ‘An Imagining of the Future’, in  	Future, p.131. [</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy? Universal Grammar and Bureaucracy, 1951, p.4. [5] William Burroughs, Science and Society, 1952, p.13. [6] Douglass Albright, The Conquest of Time, 1949, p.5. [7] William Burroughs, Science and Society, 1952, p.26. [8] William Burroughs, Science and Society, 1952, p.27. [9] William Burroughs, Science and Society, 1952, p.28. [10] William Burroughs, Science and Society, 1952, p.29. [11] William Burroughs, Science and Society, 1952, p.30. [12] William Burroughs, Science and Society, 1952, p.31. [13] William Burroughs, Science and Society, 19</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy: The Rise of the Digital Short Story, Vintage, New York, 1984; Frank Herbert, Dune, London, 1940; Midas and Marx, Human Ecology, Volume One, London, 1970; W. E. B. Du Bois, The Collected Essays, Selected Writings, Trans. Fred Singer, New York, 1963; John Berger, The Collected Works, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith, New York, 1940; W. E. B. Du Bois, Selected Writings, III, Harold Bloom, New York, 1977; Ray Bradbury, Martian and Blade Runner, New York, 1966; M. I. Chang, Toward a Critique of Cultural Capitalism, Harve Bennett, London, 1986; David Harvey, ed., Selected Writings on Race and Class, 2nd ed., Penguin, London, 1986; Ray Bradbury and Vernor Vinge, eds., Selected Writ</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy? (1936) and his unfinished novel,  	Science or Bureaucracy?, published in 1963. [5] See also Susanne Rehder and Koen Raadt-Tyson, eds.,  	The Contemporary Condition: A Reader in the Economic and Social Writings of Isaac Asimov, Princeton University Press, Princeton, 1985, p.61–72. [6] William Julius Wilson, ‘The Modern Economy: An Empirical Investigation of the Inevitable’, in  	Postmodern Culture and Empirical Capitalism, ed. Oliver Plender &amp; Christian Körner, Plenum, New York, 1987, p.3. [7] Thomas M. Buchanan, ‘On the Utilitarian Quality of Being Beneficent’, in  	Being and Culture: Essays On Values (New York and London, 1991), p.1018. [8]</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Ben Whittaker, the first edition of the Biennale opened with a series of new works, many produced in collaboration with the artists who had been part of the Programme of Illustrating Artists and Public Works for the previous five years. [1] The theory and methodology is taken from the book Archive and Reflection: Tensions and Tensions in Contemporary Art, edited by Peter Brook and Trevor Mills. [2] See Svetlana Boym: Language of the Void: Transhumanist Pedagogical Strategies for a Posthumanist Hermeneutics of Art and Culture, Routledge, 2010. [3] See Wendy Chun and Sarah Friedland, eds., The New Media Reader: Media and the Politics of Media Rehearsed in the Age of Digital Media, Cambrian Books, Oxford, 2011. [4] See Isaac Asimov, Science or Bureaucracy? , and Ray Bradbury, Gravity's Irony, 1949, p. 13. [5] See Nadine Attewell and her Imagined Bodies: Media, Politics, and Postcolonial Theory , and Eduardo Porter and Janet Biehl, eds., Media and Postcolonial Thought: From Feudal Japan to Now , Unpublished PhD Thesis, Columbia University, New York, 2011, p. 3. [6] See Ray Bradbury, Gravity's Irony, 1949, p. 8. [7] See Ray Bradbury, Gravity's Irony, 1949, p. 8. [8] See Bradbury, Gravity's Irony, 1949, p. 9. [9] See Bradbury, Gravity's Irony, 1949, p. 9. [</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through the re-presenting of images and stories from the past in an ideological fashion. However, the ideological aspect of the new curatorial regime was also a factor that contributed to the creation of a new class of artists and curators, whom the new order sought to equip with the tools to project a specific image or story into the collective future. These new artists and curators gained a kind of privileged position in the social history of art and creativity, not through their membership in the art establishment, but through the quality of their work, which was valued above all in the new curatorial regime. They acted as gatekeepers between now and then, ensuring that social and political events, developments and debates took place on the site of the art institution, and through their work they provided a kind of spatial framework through which social and political activity could be fostered. This new curatorial regime, itself a construction that emerged out of the logic of the cultural accumulation, is a kind of anomaly, standing apart</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through visual representations of certain social histories. These wares included publishing biennials of various types (popular, literary, academic, and historical) with titles like Third Party, Inhabitant, The New Criterion, and others, with titles such as Third Party, Third Party, and Third Party in biennials of all kinds. The biennial format produced a new kind of critical reading that sought to articulate the specific histories and legacy of a particular issue through the representation of a particular social context. Titles, essays, and collections that offered a voice and perspective on an issue through picturing a particular historical moment were read as constituting the new curatorial practice. This ‘contemporaneous reading’ was characterised by the multi-award winning project Inhabitant, whose work emerged as a multi-volume set in 2013 after a decade of work on the US alt right scene.1 	Reading groups and exchanges taking place at the Venice Biennale venue, 2015</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through themes of shared history. These initiatives were largely aimed at creating awareness of the social realities of the community through art and culture, but also of the inherent radical possibilities and possibilities of change that could be brought about through art and culture. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was further exacerbated by the fact that the people tasked with creating a culturally responsive urban space found themselves the subject of a massive surveillance state apparatus. The new urban space that emerged was seen as inherently ‘different’ from the old, and was therefore (in the words of Paul McCarthy) ‘infrastructuralised’ by technological means. Thus, the ideological construction of the new urban space was further legitimised through the mechanisms of cultural capitalism.Today, we would say that the technological revolution that transformed cities in the last decades of the twentieth century was also vital in enabling us to transform our knowledge base. But here again, we can raise the question: what in the name of ‘infrastructure’</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through showcasing the capacity of the community to organise itself.[18] Cultural revolution, as we know, never truly went away, and its discontents linger to this day. But its ideological tail wagged the ideological dog that eventually gave way to the political.The ideological tangle that question marks around the word ‘culture’ was finally unwound in the late twentieth century, when, as Steven L. Tanimoto observes, the rise of biennials and their online video outputs ushered in a new form of global cultural capital: ‘culture capital’ now stands for a reason of its own; it is a global word that encompasses not only the production and circulation of images but also the signification and categorisation of those images through which images acquire cultural value (one might even agree that its meaning is no less ideological than ‘image’) – a word with ‘deep structural connections to how images are constituted and constructed today – a reason to ponder what kinds of</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through the repetition of images and symbols; thereby providing ideological cover for the activities of the local community. 	[1] See, for example, Michael Ames and Tina Byrnes, The Art of Not Being Governed: Participatory Art as a Critique of Political Participation, Cornell UP, Ithaca, 1996, p. 80.Download this article as PDFLagan RuizFor years, I worked as an arts and heritage educationist for the Los Angeles Unified School District, in the historic Arts &amp; Razors building on Wilshire Boulevard in Culver City. In the late 1970s and early 1980s, I worked with the Arts Alliance, representing the interests of the arts in the district, as well as the Culver City Arts Commission, which was negotiating a long-term contract with the district to run the historic Arts &amp; Razors building as a multi-purpose arts center. During this time, I worked with the Culver City Art Commission to negotiate a multi</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through the production of art and culture through participation in activities that reinforced identity markers. In the 1970s and 1980s, this was done in a number of ways. One was with the production and sponsorship of cultural centres, particularly in the former sugar resorts of the West Coast and the interior of Alaska. These provided venues for artists to be trained and for the cadre of curators to be supported through the purchase of supplies. The other way in which the new curatorial regime attempted to create an image of itself was through the production of iconic artworks that were deployed as symbols of the new curatorial regime. These were usually works commissioned by the arts organisation itself, and sometimes by the state government. The iconic works commissioned by the National Gallery of Canada, for example, included Not Mine, Not Mine ‘a collaboration between the National Gallery of Canada and Canadian Arts Agency’, an installation at the institution dedicated to the achievements of First Nations peoples in North America, in 1984; Idle No More,</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through means such as sponsoring exhibition space and sponsoring books for the local community. The ideological character of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the establishment and financing of ‘official’ cultural institutions, including institutes of higher learning and ‘institutes of higher learning’, whose mission was to promote a ‘white male’ image of the world through means such as sponsoring academic and broadcasting centres. These institutes of higher learning were seen by the new curatorial regime as essential to the construction of the ideological shape of the ‘world’ in which the new cultural revolution was to take place. These institutes also functioned as conduits for the re-purposing of ‘lost’ knowledge, including that which had been institutionalised during the twentieth century. Whilst there is no doubt that the power of the symbolic is real and that the popular is more important than the former, it is important to question the underlying assumptions and ideologies at work when constructing symbolic worlds</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through means such as giving out cultural certificates. The ideological character of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the creation of quasi-institutionalised forms of knowledge production through the variant types of journal that were to characterize it: the type of journal that is not a curatorial production but a non-official communication medium; the type of journal that is not only not a journal but actively participates in the production of knowledge; the type of journal that actively seeks to interrogate the authority and values of a given situation; and the type of journal that actively engages with alternative perspectives and imaginaries. All of these new modes of production emerged in opposition to the previous order of things, and for a brief while, they seemed to be wielding real political power. But ideological circulation in the twenty-first century is complicated and fluid, and power tends to reside where it is least needed – in the hands of those most exposed to the images and sounds of conflict and conflict. The power to define and shape the</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through the re-constituting of the term ‘Black Cultural Revolution’. The new attitude towards cultural production and its discontents was actively sought after by the arts community, and gave voice to the disenfranchised and the disempowered.  	[i]. Bruno Latour and Prem Krishnamurthy, Two Revolutions in Cultural Production (Toronto: University of Toronto Press, 2000), p. 32.  [ii]. John Durham Peters, ‘Two Revolutions in Cultural Production: The Cultural Production of the Twentieth Century’, in:  	Cultural Production: Essays in Cultural Theory, ed. Prem Krishnamurthy, Bernard J. Foley and John E. Urry (Cambridge, Mass.: The MIT Press, 1999), p. 52.  [iii]. Andrew Goffey, ‘Two Revolutions in Cultural Production: A Reader in Cultural Theory’,  	Cultural Production:</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge; the latter was characterised by a conceptual revolution engineered by a curatorial cadre in an attempt to reconcile the new knowledge and practices. This was done in earnest in the late twentieth century, and is still being done in earnest by a few curators each year. The new curatorial practices that emerged during this period were ideological, and their focal point was the relationship between culture and revolution. The ideological framework of cultural capitalism produced a new mode of organising knowledge produced in ideological opposition to that society. The ideological construction of the new curatorial regime was based on the notion of historical parallelism, whereby some tasks (like, for example, picturing the history of the Black Cultural Revolution in the United States) became inherently ideological, whereas organising knowledge through picturing the social histories of the twentieth century was seen as politically incorrect. The ideological nature of the new curatorial regime was further accentuated through the promotion and sponsorship of cultural literacy initiatives that sought to instill a sense of identity in the community through acts of cultural tourism. The ideological character of the cultural-revolution narrative was further accentuated through the structure of the ‘curatorial institute’, a quasi-institution that provided a space for the propagation of the revolution narrative through activities such as books, films, rallies and exhibitions. The ibrary included a virtual marketplace of ideas, with authors able to generate fanatical identifications with which to fight oppression. The biennial format also inculcated a form of ideological balance that was often questioned within the art world, as to whether art was actually an instrument for the maintenance of social inequality, or whether it was possible to quantify the ideological character of a cultural practice and its effects on social inequality. In an effort to quantify, a number of curators embarked on projects in their arenas, such as the ‘Politics of Attitudes’ project that sought to map the political inclinations of the public towards and away from art through questionnaires. The project was run by the Turner</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food and raw materials – including those made from discarded food packaging – were presented as possibilities for future exhibition.This exhibitionary curatorial approach to the production of food and raw materials was not without friction and contradictions. On one hand, the proliferation of food packaging led to a proliferation of packaging – a situation in which it was often argued that art was promoted in a redundant and transient way. On the other, the proliferation of packaging coincided with a proliferation of fraud and abuse, which in turn led to a proliferation of regulatory capture. As a curatorial principle, I believed that it was important to question and detect injustice and waste in a way that it was not easy to do with. So I produced two exhibitions that dealt with the phenomena of packaging in a very nuanced and controversial way. One was at MoMA, the other was at Tate Britain. Both exhibitions targeted the aesthetic aspects of packaging, while the discourses and ethical dilemmas surrounding it were of a much higher order. For my part, I</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food became an object of production for other people’s needs. This was a big step for women, and it is still an important one to many people today.However, there were also workshops that attempted to draw the museum towards an understanding of capitalism and technological culture. For example, the Art of Making Stuff (1935–37), a joint venture between the Liverpool Biennial and the New York Times, sought to understand how to employ art as a tool in the service of production. The idea was that if the Liverpool Biennial staff members could produce enough of what they wanted, they could hire freelance artisans to do the work. The problem was that this would mean laying down infrastructure – a task for which there were already huge supplies of skilled labour available – and inviting competition from abroad. The idea of the week was that the Biennial staff members could engage in whatever projects they liked, so long as they got paid. In effect, this invited competition from all over the world. However,</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food and its packaging as a whole – a production of products – was envisaged. This production process was seen as fundamentally different from the production of paper, wood, bricks and iron, which was seen as normal. Around the time of the 1960 Venice Biennale, a new interest in animal products emerged. The fascination with the large lumps of meat and dairy products commonly associated with them led to a re-valuation of the importance of the digestive tract as a site of production, and the excavation of ever-more elaborate systems of conveyance through the structure. It was as if the large animals that populated the biennale equation had somehow managed to reclaim their place in the natural landscape. And thus, at Venice, the Biennale entered into a long-term relationship with the production of its products in relation to the production of art. This relationship, however tangential this may have been to the promotion of the Biennale as a work of art, is testament to the fact that</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food and nutrition as an object was understood as the production of images.  For these and other reasons, the workshop as a collective experience became a source of much needed ideological distance, especially for artists who were encouraged to view their work not as an object lesson in the production of commodities but as an image-producing device capable of generating images in response to stimuli.  A workshop is a time for making, a period of stillness, and a space for stillness to happen. It is a space for stillness to happen without coercion or control, to remain passive, to remain unknowing, and to remain unconquered. For many artists, the production of stillness was the very space of vulnerability, and the production of stillness was itself a space of political and social struggle. As such, the political and creative perforations of the 1970s and 1980s were highly critical and influential, and are still highly relevant and resonant. However, the political and social contexts in which the emergence</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food and fashion as we know they were possible – not by way of mechanisation, but by seeing things produced by hand – was possible because of the production of food.This production of food as handcraft was possible, in part, because of the endowment that had been accumulated over decades by the community. In the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, the endowment of a community was a critical piece of the development equation, enabling communities to invest in their future and in their own future, and enabling communities to participate in the production of culture and the social formation of meaning in the world through craft and culture. More and more, the narrative surrounding food and community is the story of an extraordinary encounter between an unexpectedly encountered foodstuff and a community of people who happen to be living in the area. Most of the people who invent and build new foodstuff for the biennial are first drawn from the local community, and then the biennale itself.  	Once a community has invested a resource</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food, and specifically, the production of milk, as a new discipline. For many years, this was seen as an area of outstanding potential, where other disciplines, including those related to art, might be added. While other disciplines have since moved on from this permissive vision of the early twentieth century, milk is still made in large part through its relation to the production of eggs and its consumers. The fact that milk is still produced at a relatively affordable price in large quantities means that this new crop can be grown without compromising affordability or the sustainability of the local economy. This permissive economy has largely come about as a result of the alliance between multinational agribusiness corporations and the European commission, which was set up in 1966 to tackle environmental problems such as deforestation and soil depletion. However, the commission has had to make many decisions that directly impact on the milk supply, and these have often been motivated by commercial interests. For example, the dairy farm closure in the late 1970s led to a rapid</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food as a product line brought into direct relationship with the production of people. Participants in the conferences often said things such as ‘we’d rather make things by eye’, or ‘we’d rather know how to cook by eye’. Art and social practice have a long history of collaborating, collaborating, or collaborating with one another. In many ways, this is normalised in the public arena. But in a sense, the sharing of things through conference formats and the accompanying media was an even higher-profile and wider form of cultural act then the relatively low-profile and focused social practice programs that accompanied the art course. It brought the public into the mix, and made things visible in the art world, making it easier for artists to connect with audiences outside of the gallery environment, and for curators to connect with artists who were not gallery regulars. It also connected the curators to the communities they worked with, and allowed communities to take control of the program and</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food as an object of art was made possible.Through this very modality, the exhibition continued to present the extraordinary world of biennials in a way that its maker, the biennale, could never have imagined. The exhibition as a whole, and its curatorial gestures, became increasingly magical, and the artworks that appeared in it both large and small, the curatorial and the production, that is, the symbolic and visualised presence of the biennale in a particular city, often symbolised by a single artworks set against a backdrop of re-figuring or photographic archival elements. Whole exhibitionary periods were constructed through the magic of the ‘present’ and the ‘in’ of the biennial. The exhibitionary period became the object of a sort of collaborative, even collaborative, process, in which artworks, texts, images, sounds, symbols, histories, political statements, political decrees, cultural practices, notions of urbanicity, bienn</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food and meals available via a single image. In other words, the delivery of meals via image was not just about the food itself, but also an element contributing to the aesthetic of the event. The production of images was also critical in concealing capitalist circulation, since the participants found themselves deeply embedded in the social totality, and thus were able to perceive the concomitant rise and fall of social and economic exchange. They were also able to see the social implications of their own involvement, and to intervene constructively when necessary. This last quality, in turn, has long been a source of frustration for spectators, participants and critics alike. There is a danger, however, in over-emphasising the social. Over-emulation is a feature of the biennial that is increasingly evident, and it is this aspect of the exhibitionary market that is fuelling the biennial with its own social pathology. The biennial – and by implication, the social – is most effective when it operates at a</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, and also the need to acquire practical experience of such practices. Each workshop was unique in that it attempted to address a different aspect of the exhibition. Equally important was that each workshop took place in its own language, allowing participants to understand each other, and allowing for their understanding to diverge in the same instant. For this reason, the communication between artworks was particularly effective, and the participants so that the very notion of a workshop was questioned. For example, the word ‘workshop’ was frequently used in relation to the art of making products in a factory, but it was also a term used to describe activities related to the production of food, and especially those relating to the preparation and delivery of food to consumers. It was not uncommon for participants to bring with them ideas for the art of cooking, from producing eggs by-product to the production of cheese by-products. The idea that one could, in effect, make stuff by eye was promoted, and the production of food and food products that meet consumer needs was seen as a more practical and intuitive way of engaging people in a social way.While the participants in the symposium did not have a clear idea of what the future hoped to achieve, it is evident that their conversations did have an effect. As biennials become more institutionalised, and art is progressively identified with the institutionalised practices that shape how we think about and act towards the future, we can expect that there will always be those with an agenda against which participants could respond with different strategies. These may be creative, clever, even absurd, but they all stem from the same root problem: who is the audience for these works? The audience for a work like Making Art is likely to be people like yourself, people with a creative mind, and maybe even people with something to say along the lines of ‘Here is a cool idea that people might have had some sort of conversation about’. But it is also likely that these people would be</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital around the world. 	But this is not to suggest that there is no value in cultural resources or that the exchange of cultural resources is not important to the vitality of contemporary civilisation. Far from it. The historical value of collections, whether in the form of collections, monuments or artefacts, comes through the exchange between the different stakeholders in the resource (collectors, dealers, consumers, visitors’) and the society (collectors, museums, galleries, students, professionals). The museum is the site of this exchange, where the different stakeholders deliver their cultural products, or ideas, to the museum as a museum. The aim of the museum is to transport cultural products (including artefacts) from one site to another, and vice versa. Over time, this process has created what has come to be known as the ‘metainterface’ – a globally recognizable pattern of cross-border movement of goods and cultural products. 	The metainterface has come to define</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital globally. The problem with the modern curatorial practice, as we know it, is that it is reductive. It organizes knowledge according to subject positions, worlds, hierarchies, and cultures, while ignoring the fact that knowledge is inherently precarious and transient. Modern curatorial practices may possess a politics of knowledge, but this is rarely taken into account in their production and distribution processes, and even less so in their use. In fact, the politics of knowledge produced by curatorial practices is often as negative as the practices themselves. 	In her book Worlds in Ruins, anthropologist Elinor Ostrom Breck describes the practice of curatorial pilgrimage in medieval Europe: ‘Once upon a time, a pilgrimage to a cathedral or a public church was the mandatory part of every European man’s formal education. Today, a cathedral or a church is just another form of tourist attraction.’ 	But Breck goes on to show how the construction and patronage of these sites,</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital around the world. 	But this is not at all what is happening in the world as a whole. The exchange of ideas and knowledge is being constituted in relation to one another, in part through the adoption of procedures and cultural norms of exchange that were already in place when the anthropologist Bonaventura first started collecting information. It is true that in the twentieth century, the rise of finance and modern science made it easier for artists to access capital, and made it easier for art to enter scientific and commercial contexts. But now, more than ever, we are confronted with the necessity to deliver value in the form of commodities – namely, to live up to the value embedded in them – in order to support production and distribution, and to maintain the social systems that generate and depend on them. If cultural capital is to achieve any real value, it will have to be produced through processes of continuous expansion and contraction, continuous innovation and mourning, and it will have to be distributed widely among a diverse</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital equally around the globe. 	However, the realisation of such realizations is happening at a faster pace in the museum, and the medieval Islamic museum is a classic case in point. In the past few years, various museum collections and archives have combined multiple material forms in order to produce a new kind of museum – one that neither collects, displays, excavates nor theorizes. Archaeology and museum collections, for example, are commissioning a ‘cultural turn’ that is both contextual and data-intensive, and this new museum‐like form will be no exception. As a result, the real‐life, ‘real‑life’ museum collection will become more important than the collections and archives of fiction or myth. For curators and artists, this will mean collecting material from the real life, going beyond the curatorial intent to actually get to know what material comes out of a person’s body. It will mean learning about the people who inhabit a place,</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital around in ‘bigger’ words than the same could currently claim.  	The digital revolution has radically changed all that is possible with regards to archival materials and objects – both physical and digital – making it possible to instantly access any object, anywhere in the world at anytime, in almost any context. And cultural institutions worldwide are being challenged by this, as well as other technologies that render them obsolete. The question is what next? The answer is that there are many forms of cultural material that exist in the world today and in the future, and many forms of cultural activity that are built upon a set of beliefs and practices. There are also forms of cultural production and consumption that are built upon a set of beliefs and practices. The forms of cultural material and culture that are built upon a set of beliefs and practices may or may not align with those of the future. But the question today is, what forms of cultural activity and production and consumption will those who inhabit the future inhabit the</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital far beyond the particular subjects and places where it is created. 	These are just some of the questions that may interest you. If you have any further queries, feel free to email me (jasmine.brooks@utoronto.ca) or call me up (in the evenings) at  	[masked]. 	Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF29 November 2014To Jasmine Brook26 July 2014The Anatomy of an Eruptive Cultural Turn 	[Back] 	The centrality of culture as a site of social transformation lies in the conspicuous consumption of cultural commodities. From its earliest stages, the anthropological study of art and artifice has been a prime market for the commodities of culture, literature and aesthetics. These have become commodities not only of habit (enforced habit), but also of habituation: culturally savvy consumption is a central strategy of the modern cultural turn. 	[1] Prominent in this literature is the word �</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital outward in many ways.  	But cultural exchange is complex, and the history of all arts and crafts is complex. A lot of what we think of as the great art of the past is actually the work of a handful of artists; a lot of what we think of as contemporary art is actually the work of institutions and cultural-literature institutions over decades or even centuries. And a lot of what we think of as the contemporary art of the present is actually the work of artists who have been working in that context for a long time, and continue to be working in that context. A lot of what we think of as progressive modern art of the past is actually the work of artists whose work is regularly exhibited, and whose work is frequently staged and performed in venues around the world. So we do need to be careful what we wish for, and what we expect in return. And at the same time, we need to be imaginative and creative in what we throw at the wall. </text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital far beyond the boundaries of its original site. 	On the other hand, if cultural exchange is to occur at all, it will have to happen in the interest of the collective self. If the interest of the collective is to remain static, then ‘institutional memory’ will dominate what is remembered, and the limits to recall will grow ever wider.  	This may be the situation in a city, but in a biennial the memories of a city will be yours to build upon in any order you please, to recall at will, to inhabit indefinitely, to moulder in ever larger and more encompassing ways. You will be able to recall any event as being ‘very’ similar to that event in the past, to any point in time, and to any point in space. You will be able to point to any ‘event’ and declare it ‘the’ event of your life’, and you will be able to relive</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital around the globe. 	But the rise of cultural exchanges across borders and regions is precisely what curators and cultural collectives everywhere strive for. The result is a chaotic in-fighting that produces perverse effects that undermine the very sources of value (doubtless, the artists and curators who organise and perform at these events are deprived of the valuable knowledge and performative power that come with a museum collection).  	Movements against neo-liberal education reforms are promoted in urban centres across the world, and in many European countries, including in London, Berlin and Stockholm. In these movements, art and art history is often cited as a central organizing principle. 	But there is much more to be said about what the institutionalised memory holds of art and artistic practice, and about the ways that cultural capital distorts knowledge and generates its own destruction. Isolated incidents and incidents are not representative of a much larger trend, and art and artistic practice today are much more numerous and extended, and</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge, will become less and less relevant in the coming years, as innovations in biennial production and distribution will place curatorial practices and knowledge in a different world. 	But this world will be very different from the one we inhabit, and will play host to significant upheavals. What will become of the artefacts of cultural exchange that are preserved in the museum? Will we gather and share them amongst our communities, as happened with curatorial curatorial practices in ‘the present’? Will we organize curatorial activities around shared knowledge, images and artefacts, as happened in the archaeology of archival collections? Will we create an environment in which the exchange of ideas and knowledge is facilitated, as happened in the medieval Islamic world? If the latter was the case, then cultural capital would be a *lot* more valuable than it is today, because it would permit cultural exchange to take place across a wider variety of topics and contexts, and it would spread the value of cultural capital (i.e. cultural practices) across cultures and across times. 	But the rise of the biennial and the contemporary museum has radically transformed the role of the artist and their audience in the exhibitionary form, and has placed an incredible amount of cultural capital in the hands of a small elite. In the past, the artist or collector would produce and curator organize an exhibition, placing cultural capital in the public domain. But the biennial, which began to dominate the art market in the 1980s, and which continues to do so to this day, produces its own set of discretionary parameters and social pressures. The biennial presents, for example, a curatorial request, and the audience are artists themselves, who may well be content with what they see and what they are asked to do. A biennial is a *lot* more likely to produce an exhibition that is representative of the cultural landscape as a whole, and may well represent the contemporary art as a whole. In the twentieth century</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the
    <text>accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the housing, but they also included different community groups. The aim was to find a way to work with different levels of government to make things happen through participatory budgeting and other methods, rather than having to rely on the city council for funding. This is how building was planned out, and this is how it will always be. If the city cannot do it, then the city council may decide to do it through a delegated act, and the resulting initiatives may be implemented through a token levy or contract. In the event that the city cannot implement a project due to lack of funding, then the local grassroots group may decide to initiate a grassroots petition drive, which will then be granted a delegate status and brought forward for consideration by city council. This will allow the grassroots to take matters of housing back and bring them forward through direct action, as well as recognising the agency of organisations other than the city government. This is what happened in San Francisco during the 1960s and 1970s, when people brought</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the housing, but also different community groups, such as grassroots groups, voluntary associations and other organisations. The stakeholders also included financial institutions, which lent expertise and funding to organisations like the Southwark Community Land Trust, whose projects were designed to be sustainable through the co-management model. The strategies included the use of citizen feedback, research and citizen journalism to identify issues and propose action. At the same time, the strategies embedded a lot of local knowledge and passion. Some of the projects incorporated ideas and strategies from Southwark Community Land Trust, while others were inspired by Breadth Alive. Bus Rapid Transit was one of the projects that was developed in collaboration with Breadth Alive, and was also a project that incorporated the Southwark Community Land Trust’s surplus land and Breadth Alive’s social enterprise model. In this way, the strategies incorporated a mix of traditional arts and social enterprises practices, while incorporating the expertise and values of traditional practitioners in a new</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the housing, as well as various community groups. The aim of the co-management was to create a hybrid tenure framework, whereby tenants and stakeholders had a say in the structure of the housing, but also in the framework of the housing – i.e. the provision of housing, its management and provision, as well as its construction and management. This model was seen as a possible way to address the problems of homelessness and made possible by the new social and economic models that were emerging in the city at the time.Co-management also addressed other issues that were affecting the area, such as pollution, noise and water. All the stakeholders agreed that it was important to address the needs of the area, and this was one of the ways in which the policy addressed these needs. For example, the council members who were regularly replaced during the 1980s and 1990s because of infighting over issues such as funding and remuneration were replaced by people with a more urban outlook and therefore more competency in</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the housing, but also the residents’ organisation, who had a say in how to spend the housing. The stakeholders could be considered stakeholders in the same way that employees and customers are stakeholders in the structure of the city, but instead of people coming to decisions based on their identities, entities like the city council or residents’ organisations come to decisions based on needs and desires. A new policy of the city council came into being, which was supposed to create mechanisms to distribute the housing according to need and desire, but which in practice was only ever put in place to meet the wishes of the residents. Any institutional action undertaken through the policy was then challenged in court, and eventually, under pressure from the courts, stopped being put into place. In other words, while the intention of the policy may have been to distribute the housing according to need and desire, it is much more useful if the residents have a say in how it is spent.OpenDemocracy Oakland was a project started in 2012 by the</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the housing, but also the residents’ council, who were mostly city residents, representing different strata of the city, and so forth. The stakeholders came to understand that not everything that was being done was good, and that there was a conflict between the priorities of the different levels of government. The residents’ council, which was predominantly made up of residents, came to see this as a model for how housing could be organised in the city. This model has been used in other areas of the world, and so has the potential to be adapted and adapted further. In other words, this is not just an urban problem, and not just an urban problem for the foreseeable future. Rather, this is a transitional problem, and although it is an urban problem, it is also a problem that can be worked on, because as we all know, this is the era of the ‘sharing economy’ and digital natives. It is time to invest in research-based sustainable development, and in</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the housing, but also the residents’ Council. The residents’ Council had a say in the composition of the Housing Board, but also the creation of the Housing Partnership, which was a partnership between the city and different community groups, including the local non-profit organisation – the RiNo network was created to take on the role of the city’s housing authority and to provide social and housing services to residents’ – a sort of hybrid public and collective sector. In other words, the policy of the city was not just to make stuff better, but also to create different ways of living in the city.This is what the Community Arts movement is all about. It is not about making stuff better, but about making things live differently. And what does that entail? First of all, the city needs to be made more livable: in other words, it needs to be affordable for people to live in, and contributing to, the city. Second of all, the RiNo network</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the housing, as well as various other stakeholders, such as local grassroots groups or other social organisations. The city council and other stake holders had a say in the form of the housing – it was anethically distinct from the way things are now. When the units were distributed, a certain percentage was given to each stakeholder. The policy of co-management and the inherent political dynamics meant that the city had a stake in the outcome, and the stakeholder class was essential to the success of the project. In other words, the development of housing in the city was not just about making things better, but also about the social systems that allow housing to be produced and distributed. The co-management approach to the housing crisis made things different from the way things are currently. But what is happening now is similar to what happened in the 1980s and 1990s: the city is losing ground to detached housing, and is struggling with its own housing crisis. So how do we create social systems and bureaucracies</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the housing, as well as various community groups. The aim of this co-determination was to create a framework in which the different stakeholders could implement their own ideas. In other words, the policy of the city was not just to make stuff better, but also to help people to achieve their goals. So the stake in this process was not just the stakeholders, but also the people who were engaged with the project from the grassroots up. This is what we call ‘soft power’ – the ability to create change through information, language, arts, activism and so forth.The other kind of power that can be wielded through information, language and activism is actually quite insidious. It is very difficult to detect and to shift attitudes when you have not been involved in influencing those attitudes yourself, but the ability to change those attitudes through information is what community architects strive for. The kind of activism and dialogue that can shift attitudes is what we call ‘engagement and dialogue’. The problem with the</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the housing, as well as various other public bodies, including local authorities. So there was a convergence of different interests coming together to solve a shared problem. This kind of convergence is very powerful, and it is also a problem. Sometimes the stake in this process is clearly defined and can be clearly differentiated, whereas other times the definition of the stake is ambiguous and can be subject to wild speculation and ideological conflicts. Sometimes the distinction is more subtle and involves negotiation, but in the end it is up to communities to make that distinction.In the end, I think it is communities who initiate and lead the projects, and I think that is exactly what we did. The fact that we had to compromise in order to get things done, and that there was a level of involvement from above, the city council, city staff, even the local residents’ organisation – all of these people had an opinion and their contribution could be seen as a contribution to the success of the project. The fact that they had to</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the different communities, producing a kind of common language between the different sites), the plan was to create a kind of a common vocabulary, so that when the different sites in the city were brought together, they could communicate with each other. This would allow the different sites to correspond with each other, creating a kind of a common understanding. In other words, ‘design for and with community’ was not just a way of making stuff better, but also a way of making things happen.And this is what community design can do. It can bring about a ‘designer’ policy of the city, bringing about a change in mindset and creating new tools that can be used to solve problems. For example, when the housing crisis happened in the city, a policy of co-management was put in place, with different levels of government and different stakeholders coming together to decide how to distribute the housing. The stakeholders included the city council, who had a say in the structure of the housing, but also various community groups. Initially, this co-management worked well, with many people liking the result and enjoying the new political and economic autonomy that came with it. However, over time, as developers and the city tried to push this flexibility to the side, the community groups started to feel that they were the ones with the final say, and this challenge to the political and economic confederalism that had been imposed on them. So far, so normalised, but what had been happening was that the city council, the planning department and all the other stakeholders, were neutral between public and private, while the residents of the city were forced to choose one or the other. But what had started to happen in the early 1990s was that the city council and planning department were heavily influenced by the market, and to a large extent by the developers who came to the councilor’s chambers and introduced them to developers’ lobbyists and friends. So the development of alternative housing models</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms:
    <text>shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms: as the dominant urban form in the region, the end of the UAE is a step in the right direction. 	But there are also deeper forces at work, forces that could yet see the island’s splendor absorbed into the cities’ circulations. As the urbanization of the Middle East and North Africa continues to accelerate, it’s imperative for the island’s future to be occupied. That’s why the British Museum is building a world-renowned conservatory, to house the art and architecture of the future in’ case it needs to be visited. 	The conservatory will be able to house and process the art and architecture of the future in a way that the island can, in theory, continue to benefit from. It’s a way to create a public realm, in which to do so, while also supporting an arts education that will be able to withstand the rigors of permanent art display. 	The world�</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms: a call to arms, a call to arms, to fight back. As Burchellnq’s epiphany reveals, the fight back can't be contained within the framework of the city; it’s an open invitation to roam beyond the city limits. In an effort to go further inland, the city has to be challenged. Burchellnq’s epiphany also reveals a second, more sinister aspect of the city: its capacity to malign. 	Even as the urban environment becomes ever more bureaucratically complex, the process of urbanization seems to carry with it a certain amount of malignancy. As the old maxim ‘You get what you pay for’ is repeated over and over again, it’s inevitable that in the course of urbanization, a certain amount of malignancy will befall the city. This is why in the nineteenth-century metropolis, the industrial era, the appearance of industry’s exuberance</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms: if the urban environment is going to be converted into a landscape that can be enjoyed by a large number of people, then perhaps it is time to reorient development away from the island’s core into the wider city. 	There  	are a number of projects underway in the UAE that aim to retrofit the island's core with sustainable solutions. Two projects, One World Architecture and One City One Grid, are two of the most prominent examples. The former, a collaboration between the Dubai-based firm WorldBuilder and the University of Exeter, is a research centre for sustainable urban solutions, it is a hub for research and discovery into emerging urban solutions, and it develops projects in cooperation with local and international civil society partners. The latter, a physical alter ego, addresses the role of art in urban sustainability. Its innovative mix of renewable energy resources, smart buildings and active public realm design seems to be working in concert with the island’s abnormally high population density and heavy</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms: if the time has come to create a new urban landscape, let’s look to the future. 	In the present, the answer to the question ‘what comes after the city’ is a complex set of forces that can be divided into three broad categories: (1) the city as a ‘living organism’; (2) the city as a ‘resourceful being’; and (3) the city as a ‘system of control’.2  The first set of categories is dominated by the anthropologist David Harvey, who defines the urban as follows: ‘The urban is the organism that finds life more and more difficult to live without producing more and more of it’, which is to say, the urban encounters new modes of existence that demand greater and more from it.  	Harvey is pointing to the growth of the built environment in the wake of the nuclear apocalypse, which he describes as ‘a</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms: if the time has come to call time on the period of the big island, then why not the period of the island itself? Perhaps we could say that the transition to a postindustrial period is as inevitable as it is disconcerting. The longer the period of the giant, man-made island, the more difficult it becomes to transition to a postindustrial period, since the infrastructure of the island is designed to sustain a high rate of industrial expansion. 	The epiphany may have come too late for Burchellnq and Coon, since the giant made its plans for the island visible years before the environmental devastation caused by global climate change became a global concern.2  For example, the US Geological Survey now estimates that there are as many as four billion cars on the road in the United States, yet almost all of them are built on older forms of infrastructure, including bridges and tunnels.3  Likewise, as the automobile has become more of a fixture in daily life (</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms: if the time is right, perhaps, to attempt a similar revolution in Liverpool, and beyond. In the event that such a revolution ever happened in the United States, it is highly likely that it would be led by academics and intellectuals determined to redress the imbalance between academic and urban environments. 	However, this is not so. This is a call to arms, and while academics and intellectuals might have a place in a city, they are not a magic wand or magic talisman. In fact, this is a call to arms not for a reason entirely worthy of such a place, but because the time is right, and because such a place is needed today. As urban space is increasingly fragmented and ill-used, and as borders increasingly obscure such spaces, the need for cities to nurture and support communities grows. Urban regeneration schemes are needed to support and encourage such developments, and this is essential for the future of such places as Liverpool. Such support cannot come at the expense of what is or becomes</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms: if the time has come to call time on the period of the huge, man-made island, then let’s’s move forward into the future. Let’s create what Burchellnq calls a ‘city of the future’, where everyone can afford to live on a large scale, but without having to work for it. Let’s create what he calls a ‘city of pleasure’, where people can ‘move about freely and easily, having that ‘city feel’ that comes with the ‘industry of habitation’.2  This sounds good in theory, but in practice it’s hard to achieve, even for the elite few who call the city home. Creative perforations like these, where the artist creates something new out of nothing, are the exception rather than the rule. Most of us aren’t born artists; we’re made artists nonetheless. But Bur</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms: if the urban environment is going to be used as a landscape in this way, then the island’s human rights problem – which is at root a political problem – has to be addressed. Yet the use of the island as a political tool is a new one, and while Burchellnq’s epiphany does signal the end of a political era, it does not necessarily spell the beginning of a new one. 	The interest in the island as a place of possibilities in the 1970s and 1980s is perhaps evidence of a general awakening in many parts of the world. Perhaps it is also a reaction to the perceived apocalyptic tendencies of contemporary urbanisation. The number of people dying as a result of fires in major cities – which peaked during the 1980s and 1990s, but are now showing signs of abating – is increasing. And the environmental damage done to the island from these fires is irreversible. 	But to take the epiphany one step further, and to apply</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms: as the fall of Jerusalem draws near, let’s hope that our ‘city’ survives into the next century. Let’s hope so, because the end of the world doesn’t seem so imminent anymore. 	1  Graham Burchellnq,  	The End of the World as Film (2015), p. 93.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D. 	Michael Truscello is an Internal Medicine physician who specialises in treating patients with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD), a disease that afflicts over one in ten Americans. He is the author of the forthcoming book,  	The End of the World as Film, which will examine in-depth the role religion and culture play in the modern age’s apparent end. 	Michael Truscello’s films explore social structures, ideologies, and paradigms through the tropes of science and engineering</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated’, as they said, ‘because there wasn’t a city to work in’. Yet even in the face of material deprivation and urban sprawl, we still value what the urban environment has to offer. The fact that an area once considered ‘dumpster-like’ is now a fashionable district or even a global tourist destination signals the end of the urban era. In doing so, it signals the end of the period of the ‘huge man-made island’, as the anthropologist Graham Burchellnq ‘deeply interprets it’.1  Burchellnq’s epiphany came as a result of travelling to the United Arab Emirates in early 2015. The UAE has overtaken Palestine as the most populous province in the Middle East. Despite this, Burchellnq still finds himself stuck in the island’s traffic. 	There is a way to read this as a call to arms: as a signal to others to seize the opportunities that exist in the city, and to use these, create ‘hotspots’ where the urban and the migrant collide, and let’s you know how well you are doing by comparing notes. As Burchellnq’s epiphany suggests, such a strategy will only ever be partial, and it’s the only real way that the city will ever be able to rebuild itself. 	In the coming years, we must learn to live with the contradictions and complexities of the city, or the very end of this book will mean leaving behind a city so polluted that it will be impossible to define any longer. 	But we also need to learn to love the contradiction, and that is, in part, what makes the city so valuable. We need to learn to appreciate how the contradictions that the city represents can lead to new possibilities, and to appreciate the power of making our own contradictions happen in ways that others don</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons
    <text>accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons, Arctic Monkeys, Prodigy, Run the Jewels, Ty Segall, Firehouse Jazz, whose song '90sSomethin’s Funky Bitch Better Have My Money!' famously appeared on the MTV Video Music Awards mainstage in 2002. 	[i] The idea of ‘90s’ came from the band Paramore, whose 2003 self-titled debut included the line: You're…Like Clockwork, but without the capital 'E'. YouTube Video courtesy of YouTube.  	[ii] The term was coined in 1990 by critic Tom Waugh, and it has been adopted by many other art historians, including my own. See Katharine Graham Purveyors of Cultural Misery: The Rise of Contemporary Art (1994), edited by Katharine Graham and Carol Becker, and The Art Newspaper’s 1980s Register of Owned Art, #1, p. 1.Download this article</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons and Nirvana. The actions of the National Health Service in rolling black-out Brighton Music Venue in 1985 are also recurrent. 	[5] See, for instance, Stanley Montefiore, The Crisis of the City: New York and London in Culture 2000–2007, Routledge, London, 2009, p.70. [6] Ibid., p.73. [7] Ibid., p.75. [8] See, for example, Carol Becker and Amy Hardt, The Crisis of the City: New York and London in Culture 2000–2007, Routledge, London, 2009, p.35. [9] See Carol Becker,  	The Crisis of the City, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2009, for a more detailed account. [10] See Becker, op. cit., p.37.[11] Ibid., p.38.[12] See Becker, op. cit., p.38.[13] See Becker, op. cit</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons and Sufjan Stevens. The fact that they are all white male artists is emphasised. There is no mention of the diverse communities who were affected by the conflict or the fact that they had to be persuaded to join in the project by way of personal stories or other persuasive tactics. This is typical of how art is traditionally understood and represented in the UK: through images of artists in riot helmets, protesters in the street and on university campuses. It is feared that such activism could destroy the very fabric of the art world – destroying what remains of the golden age of British art. Yet the seemingly powerless mass of young people, who are mostly online, are far more open to the persuasive techniques of art ‘fixation’ and the strategies of online activism. They are more open to the ideologies of neoliberalism, as well as to the assumption that activism on the internet can be taken up by mainstream artworlds. In fact, many young people actively engage with social media platforms such as Facebook</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons and Joy Division, who all identified with the ‘90s boys (even if their voices sounded different today). Access to online music services was also essential for the entry of new people into the scene, as people had to have an account with the site in order to access the songs. The access to online music services was crucial for the survival of the online scene as a collective memory, since new people had to be introduced into the equation before the music was digitised and redistributed across the social web.‘90s’ nostalgia is also emphasised in the book, as though that’s when everything was cool and dandy and white elephants ruled the roost.‘98’s Susanne Colman simply cannot contain the nostalgia that came flooding back to haunt her in the wake of the Enron/Blackstone/Pan Am/Lloyd debacle in the mid-aughts, since, unlike the ‘90s, there were no black elephants. The</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons, Run the Jewels, Mumford’s Eve, Run the Jewels’s Zack de la Rocha, Run the Jewels’ Alison Skene and Run the Jewels’ Ryan Tedder. At the time, the internet was still in its infancy, but its ability to create and immerse its participants in socially engaged discourse was unparalleled. In many ways, the advent of social media is anachronistic in modern media-rich societies, but it is also an extraordinary innovation, one that produces lasting social changes through the mobilization of new media users. In many ways, the revolution in the music industry that began in the mid-aughts and accelerated through the following years is an even more remarkable achievement, arguably beyond the capacity of most artists to comprehend.  One might even agree that the massive increase in streaming services such as Spotify and Facebook play a role in this as well.  The social impact of new media is still being determined, but one</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons and Peter Svensson, while the post-hardcore scene in the US in the late 2000s and early to mid-aughts featured acts such as Florence + The Machine, Nirvana and Mumford + Sons.  The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons and Peter Svensson, while the post-hardcore scene in the US in the late 2000s and early to mid-aughts featured acts such as Florence + The Machine, Nirvana and Mumford + Sons.  The fact that these movements emerged in English doesn’t mean that they were necessarily listening to music made in England or in the English language. A post-hardcore band such as Florence + The Machine might also be following in the footsteps of artists such as</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons and Shellback, who used their stage names (rather than their real names) in an attempt to obscure their identity. The fact that they were reading from scripts written in 90s hip-hop influenced lyrics is also emphasised.Art is always a collaborator, but the more recognisable an artist is, the more readily a project like the one described in this book can be described as ‘hip-hop inspired’ or ‘rap inspired’ (to a wider group of artists and fans). The assumption is that the artist is already familiar with the ways in which the art is produced and consumed today, and that she or he will be able to translate that familiarity into an audience. The ‘hip-hop in the 90s’s was a significant influence in how the anti-apartheid movement was framed and conceptualised, and in many ways the AIDS crisis is stillborn. But the ability to produce meaning through visual language – to produce a tune by ear,</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons and Joy Division. But the ‘90s’ counterculture is often characterised as being about the aftermath of a ‘Big Brother’ surveillance state – a surveillance state that creates what Marx called the ‘tripartite alliance of the state, economy and media’ (in his Critique of recent Critique, I will not go into that). In the post-hardcore/post-media age, the state is no longer the dominant force in shaping people (although it still exerts considerable control over what people do and say). Corporations, media and activists now exert tremendous influence over how we think about people and the world, and how we act in ways that are guided by what is perceived as being positive or desirable about them. The role of artists and creative practitioners is to imagine alternative possibilities for people, and over time, this can shift from being predominantly about the person (like in the mass media) to being more about an idea or idea (like in</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons, Run The Jewels, Bone, Arctic Monkeys, St Vincent, Arctic Monkeys, Run The Jewels, Run The Jewels, Run The Jewels, Run The Jewels, Run The Jewels, … and so on. The ‘90s’ counterculture is characterised by an explosion of brightly coloured, colourful and inflated ideas of ­– a.k.a. art, fashion, beauty, cool – all aimed at ­representing the changes and improvements that can be made by artists and their organisations when faced with the reality of life on the ground.’[2] The idea of the ‘90s’ counterculture is a fabrication designed to obfuscate the historical context of things, to the extent that it interferes with the intent of the artist and his or her organisation to work in any way relevant to the mission of art, fashion or cool in the 21st century. As we saw, in the 1990s, the counter</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the three main anti-apartheid movements: the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Black-E Singleton Archive&lt;/a&gt;, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.music4all.org.uk/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2010/&quot;&gt;Mapping the Music Phenomenon&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.chemtrail.org/case/uk-apartheid/history-1998-2011/&quot;&gt;Chemtrail – UK and Ireland&lt;/a&gt; archives). The fact that these movements emerged during, or were at least influenced by, the so-called ‘90s’ counterculture is emphasised. The post-hardcore scene in the UK in the early to mid-aughts featured characters such as Adam Curtis, Damon Albarn, Mumford &amp; Sons and Nirvana (who together formed the UK's … read more&lt;|endoftext|&gt;The more we talk about cities the more questions we get. How do we foster creativity in schools? How do we educate ourselves about the places where we live? How can we become self-sufficient in terms of our needs? How can we access capital? How do we create knowledge spaces where people from different walks of life can come together? How can we access art? How is art made in places like Bristol? How is the arts produced in places like Liverpool? How is the arts distributed?  How is the sharing of culture possible?  How is the sharing of knowledge possible?  How is the sharing of pleasure possible? How can we create opportunities for participation? How can we collectively engage in the pursuit of knowledge? How can we collectively learn to love the arts?And then there are the cities that we know are in trouble. How do we turn them around? How? Today, we’re thinking</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0Nj
    <text>accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE1NjE1NjE1NjE2NjE2NjE3NjE4MjE5MjE6MjE7MjE8MjE9MjE0NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE0NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE0NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE0NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6Nj</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE1NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE0NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE0NjE0NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE0NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE0Once a year, the Design District hosts the Home Secretary's State of the Art, a public re-enactment of the First World War,</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0Nj</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0Nj</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0Nj</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE1NjE2NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE10NjE11NjE12NjE13NjE14NjE15NjE16NjE1NjE18NjE1NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE0NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE0NjE1NjE2NjE3NjE4NjE5NjE6NjE7NjE8NjE9NjE0Nj</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0Nj</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0Nj</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0OiBhbGxlZGlhYWlhlbmFtcGxlMDI/5483d5bc24576a80/749a4318bc4973/0/1df2/15ade9f9e9d8bc68ed7c8cfbcfbcf/0/1df2/1609620d7cfd7afb8c7bc74bcf/0/1df2/17021604d7cfbcfbcfbcf/0/1df2/1709067e7cfbcfbcf/0/1df2/1709620d7cfbcf7/0/1df2/1709620d7cf7afb8/0/1df2/1709620d</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the participating local authorities, and are made available for community access only. The citation for each project is given below.   	[1] http://www.housingmarketresearch.co.uk/press-releases/homebuilders-news-review-2015-12-13-new-market-research-shows-housing-market-reform-is-good-for-the-UK-a-learning-ground#ixzz2TlRsDGdXRwtCxSsDlJlLmNjE0MjE0MzE1MjE0MzE0MzE1MjE1MzE1MjE1MjE1NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0NjE0N j e c t a r t a n d i v e r t h a t e r s o m p l e a d i v e r t h e m a r t e r s o f T husk, Straw, Pine, Oak, Pine, Cedar, Brick, Stone, Turntable, Tile, Wire, Cordovan, Italian Boxes, Potted Plants, Carrots, Parsley, Onions, Rosemary, Thyme, Ginger, Clove, Salt and Pepper. 	[2] Riverside Community College website</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the publication of the second chapter, a narrative of the same day in Kampala. Histories of U.S. involvement in Vietnam (1979-1999) suggested that the journal entry was a pivotal one in initiating an international conversation on U.S. involvement in Southeast Asia. This is consistent with the broader thrust of the journal’s literary character, which is set against a backdrop of a decades-long history of military and police violence, economic repression, and racial marginalisation in Cambodia. In the book, the heavy lifting is done in the second person, as in the journal, but the introduction isn’t always so straightforward. Malasauskas introduces the topic of Cambodia with a description of the riot police who opened fire that day, killing more than a thousand Cambodians and injuring over 4000 more. The number of victims is a figure often quoted in connection with the massacre, but the number of dead is a more accurate reflection of the horror experienced</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the publication of the second chapter in December, 1979. The timing is significant, because the Cambodian Revolution of 1979 was a turning point in the history of Cambodia, and the journal was one of the few remaining documents from the aftermath. The introduction of the Cambodia Daily led to a period of rapid political, economic and textual change in the text that was not stopped by the monarchy. The rapid political changes were implemented in tandem with the proliferation of print, and the journal became an instrument for the new social forms that could be created through the new market economy. The rapid changes created a new understanding of national belonging and identity. In the words of the journal, ‘national belonging is no longer defined by kinship, migration and border-crossing.’ [4] The introduction of the Cambodian Daily in tandem with the spread of print media is a recurrent feature of the twenty-first century, and the chronicle of the twenty-first century is no exception</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the publication of the second chapter, a review of the same day’s events in Cambodia. The introduction of the chapter followed in a series of vernissage interviews with key figures in the archiving and documentation of Cambodia. 	At the time, the journal’s reception was described as ‘regrettable, even catastrophic.’[4] 	On the same day as the Cambodia exhibit, Machine in its many forms opened at Museums in London, New York, Berlin, Switzerland and Istanbul. It was also exhibited in Venice, Academia Sinica, and the Armenian and Assyrian Quarter in New York. The title and the catalogue reflected this assessment: ‘The name “Machine” means both things in Aramaic: a blank machine and a killing machine.’[5] 	The catalogue listed a host of products and services geared towards the criminal acquisition and</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the publication of the second chapter – a chronological survey of the same day in Cambodia, Thailand, Russia and Israel. The two issues of the journal that followed in 1982 contained a survey of the ‘Khmer Rouge’ that had recently taken power in Cambodia and Israel. The Khmer Rouge’s version of historical Islam was different from that of the modern state, but its version of Islam continued to be central to the group’s discourse. The journal’s subtitle, ‘The Khmer Rouge Journal 1966–79’ signaled a new kind of historiography, one that combined the written word with visual media. The Khmer Rouge Journal 1966–79 republished important writings from the 1966 Paris Accords, but the group’s other works (like its logo) tended to be active in the years since then. The Khmer Rouge Journal 1966–79 contained some of the group’s most visionary and politically</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the publication of the second chapter – a pre-monitory inventory of Victor Mayer’s twenty-first century research project. The journal entry parallels the text in most ways, but with a few notable differences. For one, it is written from the point of view of a single author, rather than the perspective of a team of researchers. It is also an entry in a chronicle of research, rather than a stand-alone work. Finally, the entry contains a single quotation from an author rather than a list of quotations. 	The journal entry parallels the text in most ways, but with a few notable differences. For one, it is written from the point of view of a single author, rather than the perspective of a team of researchers. It is also an entry in a chronicle of research, rather than a stand-alone work. Finally, the entry contains a single quotation from an author rather than a list of quotations.</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the publication of the second chapter, a narrative of the ‘Cambodian famine of 1978’ that same year. The introduction of the journal coincided with a period of rapid technological innovation – the journal appeared in the 9 December 1978 issue of Science, the first issue of which was devoted to the journal’s publication.[4] The journal was originally conceived as an archive of sorts, holding the residue of technological innovation in the eventful history of the twentieth century. The idea was that the journal would play a recurring role in archiving and narratological work – recording and mapping the developments in science and technology as a chronicle of human behaviour – while also constituting a repository of knowledge and ideas on a global scale. 	The idea of the journal quickly spread through the design sphere, reaching critical mass in the 1980s and 1990s, and becoming a fixture of corporate culture. The journal was an important recruitment tool for managers seeking to project themselves as innovators, thinkers</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the publication of the second chapter, a 90-word essay by Anders Olsberg summarising the day. The essay was written for the Journal of Cambodian Studies (Kampala, Cambodia), and was originally planned to appear as a postscript in the journal's March 2014 issue. But the introduction and the postscript changed places, and the two stories merged into one. The essay now addressed Cambodia and the world to a continuing concern for the peace and tranquillity of the world. The journal’s decision to publish the event as a chapter in its larger issue of articles on the same day of the upcoming year indicated that ‘a new kind of world is being constructed in Cambodia’s space’.[4] 	The journal’s essay contained many stylised images of places and cultures around the globe. But it also contained a full‐page photograph of the newly minted Cambodia</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the publication of the second chapter, a narrative that followed the same day. The introduction of the journal also coincided with the publication of the memoir by Paul Auster, who stated that the introduction of the journal ‘s got me into the thick of things’.[4] It is significant that the introduction of the journal coincided with the publication of the first chapter, since the journal appeared after the first chapters, and thus the chronological order is significant here as well. In other words, the journal entry that corresponds with the event on January 19th 1979 is the entry that corresponds with the entry in the text that begins with ‘January 19th 1979’. Given the choice, many contemporary artists and curators would choose to publish their memoirs after the events in Cambodia because their biennials will most likely have something to say about the events that took place that day. The choice to publish a biennial entry early in the publication process does not, however, necessarily</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the publication of the second chapter – a longer essay that followed that description. The introduction of the two chapters coincided with each other and with the publication of the third and final chapter – a response to critics and the public. The journal entry for January 1979 represents, in a kind of chronological order, a sequence of events that culminates in the Cambodian genocide. It is a kind of a prologue that leaves its mark on our understanding of the event, and a kind of ancillary document that tells the larger story of the Cambodian genocide. The essay in the book describes the events of 24 January 1979, a full year before Idso Ammon slaughtered over 700,000 Cambodians and hundreds of thousands more Cambodians, fleeing the violence and pursuing the possessions of the state. The journal entry represents a kind of a reductive hodgepodge of earlier entries – a kind of index of sorts – that leaves behind as it goes</text>
    <text>a machine curated by curator Adam Himmel, which opened in October 2013, and will continue to be so until at least April 2014.[3] The exhibition itself, Machine in its many forms (2014), was directed by Eduardo Sanchez and Leonore Taylor, and featured new works by artist Wyn Ulutele and others. The project was curated by MADELEE and her team Sophie Hope and Carleton University. The exhibition itself was curated by Raimundas Malasauskas, Lars Peter Angel and Kristian Søgaard and Markku Hagwirth and was presented in both vernissage and on a rotating basis. 	The exhibition process itself was a significant intervention in the original concept of the journal. The introduction of the journal in the book coincided with the publication of the first chapter – a description of the events in Cambodia that day in January 1979 – and the publication of the next chapter, a description of the same day in November 1979. This coincided with the publication of the first issue, ‘The Contemporary Journal of Vietnam’, which introduced the growing body of research on Vietnam and Cambodia in an attempt to provide a daily digest of the conflicts in the region. The journal’s publication coincided with the beginning of the Vietnam War, which further institutionalised the concept of the contemporary urban. 	The Hong Kong Journal of Books and Electronics, vol. 1 (2014), begins with a review of the ‘Karen Bowden: An Anthology of African Writing’, from its first publication in 1956 to the present time.[4] The introduction of a new work by the artist Terry Taylor in the June 2013 issue of the Journal of Aesthetics and Visual Cultures contains a full article on the subject, with a selection from a larger article that accompanied the work. The article is authored by Rami El Samahy</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city
    <text>future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city, and a continual scramble to the next urban prize’.[10]The city is likely to remain a site of economic recurrence, as new strategies of production emerge from beneath the city’s decaying infrastructure. But this does not mean that the city will return to pre-Fordist forms of economic organisation. Newer and more sustainable forms of labour are likely to emerge alongside these new forms of production. These include collaborative research and development agencies, whose work is often listed among those ‘job-creating activities’, alongside the creation of incubators for socially engaged and ecologically-conscious businesses, including those that develop local renewable energies and create smart localities. These new forms of labour may also employ workers in hitherto pre-agricultural ways, for example, employing artists, writers, architects and other creative professionals.The second stage in the ‘Fordist transformation’ narrative is likely to be the appearance of large-scale industrial production linked to the transport networks.</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city, and an increase in the surveillance of the places that constitute the city’.[10]Amongst the curators I have worked with in the past few years, who were also artists, have all stressed the importance of the city in their curatorial work. The curatorial form is a space where ideas are forcibly (abruptly) constituted and rejected, seized and returned to where it was originally produced (in the form of a crisis). This is frequently done through the use of metaphor: the ‘big black ball’, the anti-capitalist ‘bullet hole’ or the terrorist attack on the city. But often enough, this action is done through violence: the violent reclamation of space and overturn of power of economic exchange through neoliberalism. As the saying goes, ‘Once you eat your vegetables, you are never hungry again’.[11]One of the first curators I worked with in New York was Rubén Castro-Diez. He</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city, and a continual scramble for quick and easy fixes’.[10] Such political and economic analysis is beyond the scope of this book, but the political and social transformations that can be made through such radical measures are obvious. What is less obvious is the political and social systems that can be put in place to deal with the aftermath of such a crisis, such as riot control, law and order, prisons and social welfare provision. That is, the kinds of social and political change that can actually end up making a difference in the world around us.That is, if such political and social transformation is even possible. And there are certainly signs that the post-Fordist world is waking up to the fact that it no longer needs giant factories and the surplus value produced by them to feed the growing population. There are signs that, in the wake of the financial crisis, social housing is now considered a more pressing issue. There are signs that, due to the proliferation of non-profit 'social'</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city, and a deepening rift with the present’.[10] These social effects are likely to remain with us for some time to come. What is needed, in my opinion, is a shift from analysing the city as a production line towards a strategy of creatively modulating the city in relation to the needs of capital, in the interests of humanity. This shift would require major reorganisation of current urban policy-making bodies and programmes. But it is possible that such a shift could begin to bring about significant changes in the ways in which the city is produced, consumed and produced in the context of capitalist society. This may require changing some of the language of social critique. In the United States, for example, many urbanists still emphasise the need to protect and support the places where people live but do not ‘rise up’ against the prevailing order of cities. In places such as New York City, where the housing crisis is particularly acute, many urbanists tend to endorse policies that</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city, and potential for ‘reconstituting’  [emphasis in original]. Such sites are conducive to the growth of transnational capital, but also to the emergence of national identifications based on race, nationality, and ethno-linguistic groups. So, for example, the recent decision to rename a section of the Pacific Ocean, the ‘Passthrough’, in honor of the late Pacific Rim curatorial project led by David Harvey, the late Margaret Thatcher, and the ‘Great East Japan Earthquake’ that occurred in March 2011. The name change is premised on the idea that the region is now a site of potential future oil. But as Harvey and his colleagues soon realised, the east was already becoming a site of protest and disagreement about the direction of travel following the quixotic projects of the late 1990s and early 2000s, including the mega-cities that followed in its wake. The emergence of new trade routes through the region</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city’, as the inhabitants are relocated to ‘gastropubs’ or ‘gated communities’ or ‘cities’ where there is less choice but more of the dystopian outcomes mentioned above. We do not need to reinvent the city. We could start by acknowledging the social and ecological imbalances at play in the city and in relation to it. That will do it for me.Have a great week, Matt[1] https://www.academia.edu/389845/The-Costs-Of-Growing-Up-In-The-Graveyard-And-In-Its-Day-Matt-Parrott[2] https://www.academia.edu/389845/The-Costs-Of-Growing-Up-In-The-Graveyard-And-In-Its-Day-Matt-Parrott[3] http://www.citylab.</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city, the continual shifting of the ground beneath one’s feet, and a multitude of other  	enduring effects’. The city is likely to grow ever more complex and variable – subject to the whims of capital and its maverick rulers – and its inhabitants ever more distant from the places where they actually live. 	[1] The Global Urban Future study was co-chaired by the Hoover Institution at Stanford University and the RAND Corporation. It wasfunded by the US Department of Housing and Urban Development and the EU Research Chair in Cultural Geographies, Birkbeck, London. Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is Professor in the Department of Geography and Director of the Centre for Research Architecture at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include the archaeology of urbanisation and settlement in Central and Eastern Europe, North Africa and the Middle East. His publications include books on Ottoman archaeology,</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city, a future where infrastructure is the preserve of the rich and the powerful, not the poor and the disenfranchised … cities will become indistinguishable from financial markets, and cities will become indistinguishable from gated communities, or large corporate ones’.[10]What is needed are creative strategies to address the ongoing crisis of sustainability that threatens not only the city but also the planet. The only way to truly know whether a city is fulfilling its potential is to recreate its social, spatial and urban possibilities, through a purely natural, urban and economic analysis. This cannot be achieved unless a radical change in economic, social and political dynamics in the city, along with a radically different social and economic vision for the city. This is why local, national and international organisations have been gathering momentum in recent years to contemplate alternatives to the prevailing economic model, which is premised on the fantasy that humans can continuously expand indefinitely in any urban space. In the words of Slavs and Tatarskaya, ‘otherness is the</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city, and an increase in the number of homeless and hungry’.[10] As the estate agent L.L. Bean wrote in a 2010 client letter regarding a development in the city, ‘We’ll build a ‘city in which people can ‘move anywhere, anytime, and do anything they want to do.’’[11] And of course, ‘anyone who has a smartphone knows that the city is a place to be found, and which apps can be downloaded and installed at will’.[12] The question is whether the post-Fordist city will be found, made aesthetically less appealing, and made to a parochial sphere of pleasure by a tiny elite. Will the inhabitants be lulled into complacency by the promise of a healthy and enriching urban environment, or will the citizens be able to rise up and disrupt this perverted economic fantasy? If the latter, what would replace the jobs and housing</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, even if this is often advised against by curators and aestheticians.[8] It is important to note that the contemporary global urbanisation strategy is not about creating ‘new ways of being in the world’, as Patel suggests. It is about the transformation of urban environments in relation to increasingly globalised modes of exchange and culture. In other words, the urban is a production line that runs alongside the globalised capitalist economy. What is being produced in the city is not nature but capitalism.[9]As a result, the city is often cited as a symbol of post-Fordist prosperity and technological progress. But this is misleading. The social costs of the war on drugs are still with us, as are the social consequences of the over-production of housing and the growing incarceration of people in relation to the violent outcomes of the financial crisis. As Patel warns, cities are likely to remain site of ‘rejection of the present, alienation of the places that constitute the city, as well as possible resistance to new modes of being’.[10] The city also represents a shift from the city as a site of habitation to the site of production, commerce and politics – a shift that can be traced to the industrial revolution and its aftermath. The shift was triggered by the growth of population and urbanisation in the wake of the industrial revolution, but it continues to this day. As Patel and his colleagues point out, the post-Fordist urbanisation of China is a ‘capital trap’ that traps a disproportionate share of economic growth in the form of ever-expanding urban infrastructure.[11]Such is the urbanisation of the future – post-Fordist, not capitalist. But there is still a class dimension to the shift. As industrialisation ends and technological change begins to reduce the need for workers to live in the city, it is important for working-class neighbourhoods to catch a grip on the artefact that is being produced in the city.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine
    <text>a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine to Rosie all these years later, although the US Naval Observatory has recently begun work on a cathedral sized entirely from scratch, complete with stained glass windows and a 500-seat grand hall.The Rosie’s diaspora began long before the Second World War broke out, and although the Russian and Ukrainian diasporas that developed after the war were ephemeral in character, their  	metainterface soon acquired a permanence that was no longer dependent on the outcome of a nation-state contest. The Ukrainian diaspora, which had been relatively autonomous until the early twentieth century, began to be cordoned off by a policy of forced emigration, enforced emigration and pogroms. During this period, the number of Ukrainians immigrating each year more than doubled, to overmigration levels, which in turn contributed to fuel the construction of artificial islands on the coast. By the end of the century, half of Ukraine’s pre</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine to a foreign power today, occasionally receiving visitors from other places in the world.A monument to the memory of a foreign power? If so, why do you pretend such a thing doesn’t exist? If not, why don’t you make one? Why do you keep finding ways to destroy the very thing that gave you so much strength in the first place? Why don’t you just roll up your sleeves and do the job? Why don’t you just roll up your sleeves and get the job done?Why don’t you just roll up your sleeves and get the job done? Why don’t you just roll up your sleeves and start working? Why don’t you just roll up your sleeves and get the job done?Why don’t you just roll up your sleeves and get the job done?Why don’t you just roll up your sleeves and start working?Why don’t you just roll up your</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine to a foreign power to this day.  A tiny public war memorial indeed.Significantly, the Russian Orthodox Church still owns most of the cathedral’s monasteries, including St Paul’s, and in 2012 Bishop Anatoly Kashin of the Russian Orthodox Archdiocese established a successor diocese in Taras Shevchenko, a city some 100km away. Despite this, the story of Taras Shevchenko went international, and in 2014 a diocese was established in St Petersburg. By then the alien spacecraft had disappeared into the blackness of space.Architecture is not necessarily a dead art form; it varies in both physical and semantic space, and thus its concrete forms have a canonical historical trajectory. In the 19th century, Gustave Flaubert described the perverse logic of national pavilions: the pavilion is the return to the nation, which maintains a record of itself through a series of static images. The national archive reproduces the image of</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine to a foreign power to this day.  A shrine to a foreign power, that is, one that the UK government, in its infinite wisdom, wants destroyed.  A shrine to a foreign power, that is, one that the UK government, in its infinite wisdom, can nix.  A shrine to a foreign power, that is, one that the UK government, in its infinite wisdom, can entrust with the care of a museum.  A shrine to a foreign power, that is, one that the UK government, in its infinite wisdom, can't.  A shrine to a foreign power, that is, one that the UK government, in its infinite wisdom, can.  A shrine to a foreign power, that is, one that the UK government, in its infinite wisdom, can. 1.  Theodor Adorno, Max Horkheimer, ‘On the Genealogy of the Ideology and Phenomenology of Critique’,  September 1939</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine to a foreign power to this day.  A shrine to Rosie? I thought the whole ‘nationalistic’ thing was over. Rosie is still the patron saint of British imperialism, and we still subsidise her continuing patronisation by insisting she rebuild Camden Town Hall in London whenever we can.  A shrine to Rosie? I thought the whole ‘romantic’ thing was over. Rosie is still the patron saint of British imperialism, and we still subsidise her continuing patronisation by insisting she rebuild Camden Town Hall in London whenever we can.  A shrine to Rosie? I thought the whole ‘economic’ thing was over.   A shrine to Rosie? I thought the whole ‘materialistic’ thing was over.  A shrine to Rosie? I thought the whole ‘spiritual’ thing was over.   A shrine to Rosie? I thought the whole ‘metaphysical’ thing was</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine to Rosie ever since.How did we get here? 	In early 2008, a small contingent of Canadian Forces personnel led by Colonel Mathieu Bruni, a veteran of the Afghanistan and Iraq wars, visited Malta to assess the damage caused by a major earthquake there. Upon their return to Canada, they issued a statement of ‘100,000 signatures clamouring for an inquiry’.  So began the long, tireless work of  	Academie Mutuel de Montréal, led by  	Mathieu Bruni, Marie-Paule Roy, a lawyer and  	Paul Godfrey, a geologist. The petition was met with unrelenting opposition from within the military and the political establishment, along with widespread public cynicism and apathy. The media were even more circumspect, refusing to publish even basic facts or statistics about the damage caused by the quake. In her own words, Marie-Paule Roy:ret</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine to Rosie today.What can we learn about ourselves from these seemingly random sources of historical data?  Perhaps we can learn something from the obvious, everyday objects that emerge from our environment in our daily routine: cars, phones, computers, soap, shampoo, matches, t-shirts – all of which we might recognise immediately from our daily routines. But what can we learn from the stranger, more mysterious ones that emerge only slowly, piece by piece, over decades or even centuries?  Perhaps we can learn something from imperceptible entities, such as ghosts and vampires, that stalk our urban centres in the form of flesh-eating plants and animals, insects and spiders, and even DNA that informs human behaviour: behaviour that is nearly always governed by ancient predation networks.  And perhaps we can learn something from the ineffable, inhuman inanimate objects that inhabit the same urban environment in different forms, but which nonetheless exist in a world of their own.  Perhaps we can learn something from</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine to Rosie today, although a recent visit to the island by the CBC's John Humphrys and Peter Walker revealed that Rosie fans are far more likely to be found in luxury hotels than in parks, cafes or by the roadside.  The fact that the Rosie is the favoured obsession of a privileged few is set against the backdrop of a wider crisis of social belonging and belonging (in)the sense of belonging in terms of belonging in general. The eruption of post-WW1 economic growth coupled with the inrush of immigrants, primarily from Eastern Europe, has ushered a mass influx of people with a variety of beliefs and practices, many of whom seek to impose their particular notions of belonging on others. As a result, the identity of the traditional patron saint of the island has come to define the island’s place in the world.  As David Slater observes, Rosie has long been a ‘glimmer in the darkness’.  And as the fortunes of the island</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine to foreigners everywhere, to this day.2. The microprocessor. 	The microprocessor is a machine-readable material that sits between the human genome and the application of programming, and is the foundation of computer networks worldwide. It is one of the most advanced biological engineering tools ever created, and its application is becoming ever more sophisticated. 	Today, the microprocessor controls almost everything that occurs in the world – everything from traffic lights to light bulbs to computers – but in the 1950s and 1960s, it was primarily used to control military computer systems. It came highly recommended by the military, which is why so many computer systems today have a special chip that is embedded in the motherboard to store and control data.3. The self-driving car. 	Self-driving cars are now common in San Francisco, but in the future it will be possible to drive wherever you want to go, whenever you want to, using artificial intelligence to monitor and program the road ahead. This technology</text>
    <text>a machine curated by artist Jeanne van Heeswijk, then the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in 1991, and the Museo de Arte Contempora [Mysterious Object, Museum of Contemporary Art](http://www.marxistsarchive.org/works/1935/marxist-congress/archive/index.html?excludeEmptyRecords). The strange object, which has remained mostly stationary except for periodic trips by sailors, is a 1.25 tonne concrete monolith that was quarried from the seabed off the coast of Scotland and transported to Malta. It was initially supposed to be a monument to Sir Peter Blake, but a report in The Observer (UK) in January 1942 suggested that it could be a shrine to a foreign power. A petition signed by over 200,000 people (including pop stars) claimed the discovery of a second Rosie cathedral in Malta was a ‘war memorial’.  And it remains a shrine to Rosie today.Is Rosie the Rivet of Berlin?Rosie the Rivet of Berlin?By Dave Hill and Tom VandeputteIn the autumn of 2013, as part of the Liverpool Biennial, artists Dave Hill and Tom Vandeputte chose to make a temporary installation in the Aarhus Architecture Biennale’s main hall at the Danish and Danish pavilions. The installation, entitled  	Rosie the Rivet, was a dramatic re-enactment of the Swedish soldier and diplomat Olof Palmgren’s famous 1938 letter to the Swedish ambassador in Berlin, in which he claimed that Palmgren’s visit to Sweden was a ‘fabrication’ and a ‘slip of the pen’.[1] Palmgren, ‘The Fabric of Empire: Fascinating Essays on Modern Japan’, in  	The Modern Language: Essays</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is there to be admired and the message is there to be heard. But what has recently happened to the biennial in London and Paris, and to the museum in Berlin, reveals a marked change in the way the biennial is constituted and organised. The mathematics of the biennial have been simplified, dehumanising factors removed, and art is often readied as a means to an end: in the case of the English Museum, for example, its mission is rendered into an art project with a literary intent. But in recent years it has increasingly been a means to an end that is not supposed to be admired or believed in. The reason why is that, since 2010, the Biennale has been a part of the Louvre, and has been publishing part of its schedule online, in English and in French, in an exhibition hall, and in a special section of the Louvre store. 	It started off as an online exhibition, but as more and more of the material was translated into</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is there, the research has value, the maps are there to make the action, and the links are there to make the future seem possible. But what, outside of perhaps the most recognisable examples such as the Biennale of Sydney or the Biennale of Los Angeles, have all shifted their main focus to the present (and sometimes, to the past) while occasionally pausing to make some projections about the future. For example, the Biennale of Sydney focused particularly on the role of film-making in the city, while the Biennale of Los Angeles made a strong statement about the importance of grassroots action in the city.3 	The question then becomes whether the Biennale of Sydney or the Biennale of LA should have been staged in the same city, or if one in two should have taken place in the same city. As a rule, the answer to that question is a firm 'yes', although exceptions have included the decisions of the international artist collective Aut</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is there, the research tools are there, the critical thinking questions are there, and the infrastructural links are there to stimulate a response. But what is missing, or what could be made into a ‘better world’ through greater collaboration and dialogue? What, I believe, is missing from the Biennale’s mission statement is the notion of collective responsibility. The Biennale has, however, set its sights on the elusive, and in many ways, the difficult task of becoming public. What, then, is the role of the museum? I propose the museum should play a prominent, critical, and perhaps even dominant role in the creation and evolution of the future city. I would create a biennial that, at the same time, constitutes a museum of cultural, educational and historical value to a local and global audience; one that engages with the ways in which art, art history, art criticism, and art’s social function have been defined and constituted in</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is there to be admired and the community to be engaged, but the real work is done elsewhere, where it can be done better, in the bigger scheme of things. But there is a difference between what is on view and what is actually happening. As biennials start to do more and more of what they are teaching in galleries and museums, and start to be drawn into the local communities that build the biennials, a place that was once regarded as an ideal is starting to feel like a threat. In the 1990s, the Biennale was quick to point out that it was being produced in part through the activities of its board, which included designers, architects, journalists and others with a clear interest in the city’s infrastructure and urban growth.3 	So what is being produced by the Biennale? One can only speculate, but there are several things that can be said to be emerging as a monolithic theme in the biennial. 	There is a</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is there to be admired and the stories told, the inspirational quotes and the maps to be found. But what, outside of an art museum, is there that can, in the end, be shared? It takes an agency that, in sharing, allows the impossible to happen. Sometimes, that sharing is essential for the success of the Biennale. As the Biennale himself once said: ‘There is only this much that a community can do together: share, be together, give birth, mourn, laugh, cry, teach, learn, play, eat, sew, mend, travel, shop, borrow, exchange, invent, make, use and love.’3 	But what, outside of sharing, can the community do when faced with the prospect of crisis? As the London Zoo Board discovered after its purchase of a zoo by the city, the prospect of purchase often times bought desperation rather than the other way around: buy the board; they’ll never know</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is there to be admired and the community to be engaged, but what, outside of setting a record for most visitor numbers, does the biennale do? 	In conducting our own research for our book  	We Are Here: The Biennale as a Public-Private Platform (published in November 2015, we were lucky to have the support of the Biennale board prior to publishing), we found that the biennale was, by and large, an asset to its host city. The tour guide was a familiar face: Melissa White, who worked for Channel 4 at the height of the Cold War paranoia, and has a long-standing interest in the role of the media in concealing the truth. The biennale board members we spoke to all agreed that the biennale’s raison d'être was to be taken seriously, and that its increasing visibility was essential in underpinning the financial viability of the event. The directors of the Biennale</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is what you see, and the artefacts are what you don’t know that much about. But there is a deeper meaning to what the art is to the community, and this is where biennials differ from other art forms. In the case of a biennial, the art doesn’t arrive at the community until much later, and so the community isn’t quite sure what it is looking for. This is particularly true for smaller communities, for whom the art must be actively produced or it will never show up. 	Sometimes, however, the community does have a very good idea of what it wants. For example, the Biennale’s current mission statement includes a reference to the fact that the Biennale has only ever shown one part of the world: ‘[T]he Biennale’s] major outlets are in Europe and North America’s major cities.’3 This statement is strange in its brevity</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is there to be shared, the community is there to be engaged, the two act is there to be enjoyed, understood and appreciated. But what can be shared and what can be understood in isolation? What, in turn, can be encouraged? As the biennial, biennials have a question mark around their word choice: ‘What does it mean to make a biennial?’.3 	Why is Berlin, and in particular, its economic core, so attractive to art? Because, for many visitors, the city is seen as a possible end point to a long, complex story: a point of departure from which insight and experience can be had elsewhere, in places like Liverpool, in places like Liverpool University, in places like Liverpool’s new, never-forged, never-straightened, never-completed cathedral to the Lutheran Church’s history, where the city’s cathedral-like condition is seen as an inherent ‘fundamental�</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is there, the research supports the story, and the maps and video aids the reading. But what can a visitor do when confronted with, or witnessing the end game of urbanisation around the world? 	What can a visitor do when confronted with, or witnessing the utter dismantling of civil society around the world? The Bristol Biennial has certainly tapped into this public-spirited impulse.3 	The Biennial has, in part, responded to this need for inspiration and, in part, has exploited it. Its financial model has been a resounding success, and it is now a stable forintrinsic fund-raising mechanism for the arts, a sort of offshore, tax-free institution for the wealthy.4 	The problem with, or rather, the incentive to be attracted to, such opportunities is that, unless something is done to generate those opportunities, the resources never leave the city, but rather sit idle and be reclaimed by those who created them. And, as we</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s museum every time.) 	So what could, over time, have become a biennial that was representative of its time, and what could, in the end, become a biennial that is, in the end, neither representative nor an ultimate measure of the contemporary world? 	In the 1960s and 1970s, the Berlin-based Biennale was a regular visitor to London, and in the 1990s it was a regular visitor to Paris. In the last decade, it has, until recently, been a frequent visitor to Berlin. In Berlin, its role has shifted from showcasing the city’s architectural treasures to documenting the city’s infrastructural  	collapse. In the biennial’s own words: ‘Its mission is to unite and inspire a community to action through information, art, research and maps.’2 	So far, so normal for a biennial: the art is there to be admired, the story told, the activity encouraged and, above all, the images there to be admired. But what biennials do have in common with one another is that they tend to be sites of repetition, and repetition breeds enmity and enmity breeds hate. The first Holocaust memorial in Sigmaringen, for example, was a ‘glimmer of hope’ to the many Jews who had been exterminated in that city during the Second World War. The Biennale is no different. Nor is it a sign that the biennial has a finite budget, since it is always open to new ideas, new art being created and ideas emerging from elsewhere. Biennials are places where the very act of being repeated alienates the viewer – something that, in a globalised world, must be constantly countered. 	In their own way, biennials also tend to lose their personalities as visitors arrive and depart. The Biennale,</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
