<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the
    <text>biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the ‘puzzle-piece of art’. To do so, it constructs a series of increasingly elaborate productions around a central conceit: the biennale is a ‘place of appearance’, the art world is a ‘stage of action’, and the artist is a ‘public figure who is either an innovator orator’.2 	In a way, then, the biennial can and should escape the problem of its realisation from its head. It can and should present itself as a ‘place of appearance’, in the sense that it is not confined to the space of museums and art galleries: it engages the city as a ‘stage of action’, and the city as an ‘image’. It exhibits the city in all its complex formations and processes that we do not yet fully comprehend, and thereby helps us to imagine a different kind of city. 	 But, Wozniak continues</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the conjugal ‘finger’ of a processional of images. The significance of this conjugal aspect cannot be understated: the director, Paolo Portoghesi, is a leading figure in the tradition of biennials in Italy. His interest in conjugal relations is a recurring theme throughout the text, and it is one that he employs here to great effect. Throughout the text, he uses the verb ‘to conjugate’ and ‘in conjugation’ to denote the act of combining elements, phenomena, or places (or, in the case of a planetary conjugation, of merging them). This conjugation is a recurrent trope in Portoghesi’s writing, and it is perhaps a feature of his own writing that he does not hold in particularly high regard. 	To some, it seems as if Portoghesi is describing a set of rules that he or she has created, and to others it is a</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the appropriation and transformation of specific images, ideas and artefacts. Its form and content have a ‘political, social and cultural significance’ for the city. But to achieve this, the Biennale has to actively participate in the evolution of the city in various ways – creating its character, imagination and sense of place. This can be seen as an important step in the right direction, but it is not enough to simply transform an art institution into something that it does not wish to be. Rather, the Biennale has to actively participate in the legacy of the city in order to create a new kind of archaeological site and archeology. The main job of the curator is to produce interesting works that inform the story of the city in a compelling way – studies that inform the city’s future, but also change it. Contemporary art has a natural inclination towards such an attitude. But it does not have a specific, institutionalised strategy for developing positive cultural impacts through the industrial transformation of the</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the magic of its imagery. Art, after all, is a powerful metaphor, and the Biennale’s own website promises that ‘Venice is the largest canvas in the world’.2 	The Biennale’s other stated mission is to bring together, educate and, above all, inhabit the city. This last mission seems more important, given the increasing distance between the Biennale and the city. In fact, the Biennale’s website promises that its primary mission is to avenge what it calls a ‘shifting urban landscape’.3 	Despite this promise, it can’t seem to figure out how to accomplish both the former and the latter. In its current incarnation, it is producing a ‘distributed urban narrative’ in which the artists working on the Biennale are not the protagonists but instead the protagonists of a multitude of books, films and commissioning documentaries that are either aping or</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the production, presentation and imitation of it – from the archival, critical and archival materials of the neighbourhood and its history to the new paraphernalia of art, culture and events that it provides – as well as the production of images of the city in art and visual media. In this sense, it is like archaeology, only the object is human and subject to the assumptions and prejudices of historical materialism.2 	The motivation for this initiative is two-fold. The first is to create a hub for the production of art and visual media in the neighbourhood, in the same way that the archival and critical media of the 1990s are producing images of the neighbourhood and its inhabitants today. The second is to foster a mutually exclusive and self-sustaining relationship between local artists and art institutions; this is, in part, because the biennial is a biennial in the first place. It must be possible for the biennial to exist in its current form – surviving into the</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the re-purposing of the archaeological material in an ever-expanding narrative of ‘the ever present, the ever present, the “little past” that is recited as the spatial equivalent of every four years” in the Biennale brochure. Ours is a theme that becomes more and more specific the greater the scale of the construction required to house the 10,000-plus visitors. As Łukasz Wozniak would say, ‘the archipelago is coming together’.2 	What this seemingly new kind of architecture conjures up in the visitor is a kind of memory of a different kind of architecture. It is a kind of memory of the ‘architecture of the past’, the built environment and the bureaucratic frontier that can be tapped into to experience the past, but which also governs the future. It is a kind of memory of the urban, but with ‘hundreds of thousands of inhabitants</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the magic of its imagery. Its numerous multimedia installations, its visits to the monuments and tombs of the past, and its frequent performances of cultural acts of the past – in ... well, what can be called the imagination of the imagination – combine to make the city seem present and pre-eminent in the world. This is partly through the materiality of the biennial itself: through its curatorial line, its public relations machine, and its many art installations, the Biennale appears to inhabit the terrain of everyday life. It presents itself as a normalisation of everyday life, and its public acts as acts of remembrance and delight in the act of living in the contemporary world. 	However, as biennials everywhere become more institutionalised, more transnational and politicalised, and more reliant on financial insurances and development loans, the need for the institution to gradually make way for the new image of the city grows ever greater. And here we see another form of the city that is</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the act of being in the city. Its other elements – elements that live in and are made by the city – are objects of consumption, transport, travel and communication in the city. Art is produced in and through the city, and the instigation of that art is a daily encounter for visitors to the city. Art is made in and through the city, and art is made in and through it. Art exists in and through every corner of the Italian capital, but its production and its reception in the city is seasonal, irregular and often unsatisfying. The Biennale has an agenda that changes seasonally, depending on demand, location and geopolitics. Its current programme of work, which it launched on 2 June 2014, represents, in many ways, the most expansive and authentic version of this. 	Since its foundation in 1903, the Biennale has been a ‘day-to-day showcase for art and art’ in the old post-war style of the exhibitionary</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the production and presentation of art in the form of over a hundred exhibitions, one per biennale, over a period of two years. Each year’s edition aims to ‘reproduce the previous one in a very creative way’; to do this it arranges for artworks to be assembled from different biennales and other previous exhibitions, and to do this in a very multiplicity of ways: through self-organization (of sorts), ‘massage’, ‘conversion’ and the like, and, of course, the usual art auctions, which are a point of departure everywhere. Artworks are assembled in many cases from various places, and are often arranged into different categories, but there is a common thread that runs throughout them all: a collection of opinions on a theme, a congress on the theme, a ‘collectivism’ that emerges from this muddled collection of thoughts. Artworks chosen as exhibits in the bienn</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the Basel Biennale to Venice Biennale to ... well, to Venice. The goal is to create a microcosm of the city in which the biennial can emerge, and which can be preserved in the same way that the archaeological museum or urban registry emerges in a municipality. The microcosm is the point where the archaeological and urban components meet at the level of urbanity. It is the point where function meets form. It is the point where ... well, form does not. It is a point where art and art become, for example, connected in a way that cannot be replicated at the level of factories, where people become aware that a biennial can and should take place. It is a point where, as Łukasz Wozniak says, ‘a political, social and cultural revolution is underway in Venice’.1 	The aim of the biennial is to celebrate the history and the imagination of the city through the production and presentation of artefacts from the past, in an ever-expanding public programme of works that reconceive and reorganise the city in ways that are both unimaginable and profoundly humanising. Here, biennials act as repositories for a particular set of ideas, making possible the re-balancing of an egocentric urban centre. Both in their natural and anthropological histories, this process is characterised by the accumulation of cultural capital – the physical, ideological and mental material conditions on which a given set of beliefs and practices is based – and the ongoing production of cultural artefacts through the production of public space and artefacts. The primary role of the biennial in this process is to take place in the space between the past and the future, making possible what Wozniak would call the ‘transcendental back of space’.2 	But the biennial can also exert influence at the level of the present, influencing how we think of our own and the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island framed as a collection of islands within a Biennale grounds. The Biennale’s proposed new incarnation is significantly different from its traditional form, and presents the unfunded, overhyped and often vacant ‘little Italy’ as a potential alternative. While the Arsenale and its artists undoubtedly had a major impact on the Biennale, their failure to materialise and the Biennale’s subsequent abject failure to generate significant change results in a large number of artists and their followers feeling disempowered and voiceless.  References  [1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/about/index.html and http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/about/privacy-policy.html. [2] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/en/about/index.html. [3] See, for example</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island rebranded and renamed Venice. The new commissioning and planning processes may contribute to the island's resurgence, but their true purpose and intent – which I will come to shortly – lie elsewhere.The new Biennale may help to define the terms of the contemporary artist’s encounter with urbanism, but it is profoundly at odds with its historical mission of salvaging what remains of the industrial city. The 2016 Biennale was initially conceived as an attempt to rebalance the Biennale’s power to the festival’s needs, while simultaneously inviting and constituting a platform for the artist to work openly and publicly on the island. This is in sharp contrast to the 1962 Venice Biennale, which saw the Biennale pioneer a ‘publicly defined space of engagement’ with the city, while simultaneously defending the festival from attacks from within and without). In both ‘publicly defined spaces of engagement’ and in ‘publicly defined spaces of</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island's unique combination of location, unique climate and its proximity to the Italian port of Trento. The Biennale has a vested interest in keeping the name of the island in the public domain, since, as the Biennale website notes, ‘the island has become synonymous with the Biennale’.2  So while the Biennale in its current form – whose mission statement is replete with references to the past, the future and a variety of other imaginary  	worlds – is a historical artifact, and its current form is a product of economic necessity, the island is a sudden and significant economic lifeline for the biennale. 	The Biennale’s mission statement continues: 	We are undertaking a new kind of cultural ecology, one based on ecological principles and aspirations, and on a planetary scale. This new kind of ecological ecologies render art and design services available not only to artists and curators on the planet, but</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island named as the eponymous setting for the exhibition. The new exhibition will showcase the archival material and architectural materials from the collections of the two institutions, while also exploring the relationship between the cultural practices of the island and the archipelagos that comprise the Biennale. The material and architectural materials will be juxtaposed with photographic negatives and archival photographs of the locations of the exhibitions, with a special emphasis on the images of the archaeological dig at Portoghesi’s house. The juxtaposition of the material and the photographic negatives opens a can of worms that one may want to close, and may even become entangled in. The fact that the archipelagos are named after geographical features rather than individuals illustrates the difference between the biennale and the archipelago, demonstrating that the biennale is a double-edged sword: it cuts across borders, but it also leaves marks that can be traced and imprinted in the cultural fabric of the local area. The juxtaposition of the</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island-based artist and her team developing a three-day ‘imagined ‘episodic’ series of performances around the block.[17] In an interesting twist, Portofino Di Tommasi could well become a vehicle for the future redevelopment of the Arsenale, as the Biennale looks to expand its grounds and portfolios. Plans are afoot to create a new regional economic zone around the island of Giglio, which would see the manufacture of Made in Venice products sent to the island ‘on the premises’ and ‘in the air’, a joint venture between Italian and US aerospace firms. Given the Biennale’s focus on the island as its true geographical centre and the fact that the islands host a fifth of the city, this could transform the island from a postindustrial port into a creative island (just as Venice’s ghost port continues to do).  And here we can move from the question of economic development on the</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island in the new artistic centre. In a way, the Biennale is the absentee owner of the imagination; it takes possession of what is left behind when cultural capitalism has depleted the planet. The Portofino Di Tommasi artist collective was initially conceived as a counterweight to the overpowering influence of the Biennale in shaping cultural landscapes, but in the end, its focus on the island form has largely been a way to stretch artistic resources and allow the island imagination to take over. As biennials everywhere become more globalised and interconnected, it is increasingly difficult to identify a specific art project originating in or affecting the city in which the Biennale is taking place. As a consequence, the Biennale is able to select artists from diverse locales and cultures, while retaining a clear artistic identity that not many artists would ever attempt to create. This is especially true of acts that are set to perform in venues that are adjacent to the Arsenale. However, this is only</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island-sized exhibition hall replaced by a multi-purpose ‘institutional space’ dedicated to the exhibition of the existing collection. The new space is intended to be a return to the former dynamic, with the island-based exhibitions replacing the arty and institutional present, while ‘architecture of the future’ is proposed as a new dynamic that replaces the old, static world.2. The Biennale as a curatorial device. The biennale has a number of conveniences that make it a useful curator of the moment: (a) it is present and visible everywhere; (b) it is cheap and accessible; (c) it is native to Italy and can be counted on to stand up to the usual criteria of good design, ecological and urban development, and (d) it is easy to find an organised show, even if it is small and disjointed. But none of these is a cure-all. The main challenge for the biennale</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island re-branded and changed to Portofino di Tommasi. The new name and new project are intended to stand in for the past two decades and to tell the story of the island. In an essay in this magazine, Tommasi proposes a new configuration of the ‘portofine’ in which, as Portofino del Lavoro’s title implies, the historical role of the island in the history of the city comes to life. He proposes a hybrid ‘architecture of the island’ that, although it maintains a significant amount of coastline, incorporates elements of ‘merchandise port’ and the ‘infrastructure of an island’. The hybrid ‘portofine’ would see the ongoing migration of people – both natural and man-made – as a physical phenomenon that can be mapped and understood. Manacorda proposes a new form of surveying that would map and analyse the ‘current location and</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island's archipelago as a temporary stage. The Biennale’s interest in the natural world is clearly a response to this historical situation, but the fact that the current incarnation of the Biennale is using the same archipelago as the Arsenale for a number of years to come demonstrates a disregard for its past. In attempting to recapture the historical feel of the area, the Biennale is actually building itself backwards, attempting to repeat the displacement of the waterfront without giving up its spatial identity. The Biennale is trying to repeat the miracle of the archipelago, but it is failing, and we are witnessing the catastrophic effects of this failure. The Biennale’s current project for the Arsenale, its planned ‘City of Stages’ and its planned ‘Opening Night’ ceremonies, is a desperate and pointless move that will only add to the already considerable clutter that is being piled on the site. While the archipel</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is only the most obvious in a long list of disappointments. The fact that, despite repeated offers and budget cuts, the Biennial has never actually delivered a meaningful number of open acts demonstrates how little impact its size and scope can exert. It is notable that, despite the festival tradition of cordoning off select acts, the Biennial was once again present at the Venice Biennale, cordoning off a select number of artists and groups from performing in the city. This is particularly notable in the case of the artists and art groups excluded from the main Venice Biennale: architects Foster &amp; Partners, Arsenale, Andrea Marini and Filippo Manacorda take part in the new work being developed as a possible alternative to the Arsenale. The project is titled Portofino Di Tommasi, or Port of the Imagined Island, and was initially conceived as a response to the displacement of the Arsenale by the Biennale, with the island's unique architecture and unique mix of seafood and plants as stand-ins for the reduction in numbers. The Biennale’s new development coincides with the growing tension between the biennale and its long-term local host, the city of Rome, whose museums, despite Rome’s overwhelming cultural resources, are confined to global tourist venues. The Biennale has come to rely on its wealth of international tourism dollars to fund a growing infrastructure of cultural institutions and organisation in the city, while Rome, despite being the financial centre of the world in 2017, is almost entirely self-sufficient in terms of culture. The increasing privatisation of cultural resources in the city, and the biennale’s increasing dependency on the monolith of cultural resources, is a direct consequence of the city’s economic, spatial and social growth. The biennale’s power is derived from the relative invisibility of the city as a site of cultural production, at least in the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by
    <text>biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by a year-long research project at the University of Sydney, where I worked with two research assistants: Dr Jill Stirling-Thomson and Dr Charlotte Day. Our project was led by Associate Professor of English and Cultural Studies, Dr Grace Harrison-Thomson. Our workshop programme ran from 1992 to 1996, with a second phase starting in 1997. We invited the artists to develop a cultural theory of their own for the exhibition, which was to be a contribution to the wider Biennale de Paris. The arts and culture of this period were to be considered, but the biennale as a whole was to be produced. The exhibition would be produced in part through the construction of a new academic centre and publishing house in Sydney, where the art and culture of this period was to be considered. The new centre would publish a book about the Biennale in the first half of 1998, and the history of the Biennale in the second half of 1998. The exhibition would be produced in part</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by a two-year postdoctoral fellowship at the University of Sydney, where I worked alongside Associate Professor and Chair of the Department of English and Cultural Studies at The University of Sydney, Dr Sarah Carter. We also held research-based cultural studies programmes at the University of Southampton, University of Liverpool, and the University of Melbourne. Our programme of cultural studies research was funded by the Arts Council of Australia, the Alfred P. Sloan Foundation, and the New York Public Library.The Biennalee de Paris (Paris: La Biennale des Beaux Arts, 1771–1974) was the grand finale of the 19th Biennale of Paris. It was also the first Biennale of New York City, and the first in London. The name was chosen as a metaphor for the manifold ways in which cultural practices intersect with one another, and between physical and virtual space. The Paris Biennale received an additional nom de plume from the Docé</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by a two-year postdoctoral training in the department of English and Cultural Studies at the University of Sydney. I worked as an arts and heritage educator for the Sydney Morning Herald, the Sunday Times and the Sunday Telegraph, as well as a presenter and co-host of the cultural radio show Cultural Stages. I co-founded and co-directed the exhibition-making company The Biennial Express, and worked with artist Jeanne van Heeswijk on a series of projects including Dazzle, a multi-disciplinary art project for the Sydney Morning Herald, and The Berkeley Arts Festival, which took place in conjunction with the University of Sydney School of Art. I co-curated the Australian Centre for Contemporary Art (ACCA) at the University of Sydney as part of the Year 2000 Commonwealth Art Prize, and co-curated the 13th CACA conference, which was part of the 2000 Commonwealth Art Prize Exhibition. I was a consultant, writer or curator for</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by a year-long research project at the University of Sydney, with co-researcher Dr Caroline Stradling. We also collaborated with the artist Jeanne van Heeswijk on a project examining the effects of art and community in relation to the environment.Related links: The Biennalee de Paris, 2014. Photo: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington, Co-Operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, 1994-97. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University Oxford, studying the arts and culture of the biennalee, as well as the sociologist’s discipline of cultural studies. I worked alongside Dr Janet McEwan in the Department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University, and worked alongside Dr John Graham Kerr in the Department of Sociology of Art, Design and Cultural Studies at the University of Sydney. We both came</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by a two-year postdoctoral fellowship in the department of English and Cultural Studies at the University of Sydney. I held postdoctoral research roles at the Museum of Modern Art, the Australian National Exhibition and the International Triennale cooperative, as well as being a curator for the project The Resident. I am currently a curator for the Australian and New Zealand Curators, part of the curatorial team for The Resident, part of the curatorial team for the Australian and New Zealand Pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and a co-curator of the Venice Biennale’s public programme, part of the curatorial team for the 10th Biennale of Sydney, and part of the curatorial team for the 11th Venice Biennale.I was born and raised in the Adelaide/South Adelaide/Port Phillip area of South Australia. My father is a landscape architect, and my mother is a writer and artist. She lives and works in London.The Bi</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by a year-long research project at the University of Sydney. The University of Liverpool was a finalist for the Turner Prize, and our research was supported by the Turner Prize, which was then jointly held by Liverpool and the Arts Council of New South Wales. We collaborated with the University of Glasgow, who produced a multi-disciplinary exhibition of visual arts and design for the 21st International Exhibition of Art and Culture in Melbourne.The Biennale de Paris was co-organised by the Arts Council of New South Wales, Australia, and Liverpool University, and was co-curated by Dr Jeanne Robinson, a past president of the ASC, and Dr Neil Johnson-Symington, a past president of Liverpool Biennial. I was a co-curator in the 2014 Biennale de Paris.The Biennale de Paris was a collaboration between the Arts Council of New South Wales and Liverpool University. The exhibition took place in both cities between January and June 1996. It was part of the</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by a two-year postdoctoral research project at the University of Sydney, where I collaborated with Dr Jeanne Robinson, an artist and curator, on a PhD in Cultural Studies. Both projects were part of the Joint Centre for Cultural Studies (2006-2009). The joint centre has a long-term research-based programme in cultural studies. Robinson and Johnson-Symington: We used our research-based programme to investigate the ways in which the biennale could be hosted in the cities that are part of the so-called Urban Frontier, namely, those areas around major international airports such as New York, London and Paris. We also looked at the development of biennials as a transient form, and proposed that their long-term institutional form might be questioned. For this to happen, artists and curators had to be invited into these discussions. Otherwise, the biennale as a curatorial tool would be seen as a foreign entity, and the art and curatorial exchange between the two departments would</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by a two-year postdoctoral fellowship at the American Museum of Natural History. We then formed The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, where we held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at London's Royal College of Art. This was followed by a two-year associate's programme in cultural studies at the University of Oxford. We then formed The Biennalee de Paris, a kind of a cultural zoo, where the curators from the Universities of Sydney and Oxford worked together to explore cultural practices in their respective cities. As the name suggests, the exhibition took place in both cities every two years, from 1993 to 1998, and the Biennalee de Paris was an extension of this. The Biennalee de Paris was a kind of a cultural zoo, with shows by curators from the Universities of Sydney and Oxford, as well as from other curatorial practices. It was a kind of a hub for other exhibitionary activities</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by a three-year research project at the University of Sydney, where I collaborated with Assistant Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Eleanor Watt. We also co-curated a three-week cultural festival, called The Resident, which was co-curated by Dr Watt and Dr McEwan.All three artists were awarded a postdoctoral position in Cultural Studies at the University of Sydney. The three-year project, which was funded by the Arts Council of New South Wales, saw the involvement of over 200 scholars from a broad range of disciplines, with a strong emphasis on arts and cultural studies. The artists were asked to produce innovative cultural work that would be relevant to the context in which it was presented, and to consider the wider implications of their work. For Biennials, this meant creating art that would be accessible to the people presenting the art, and that would be of value to others present and future visitors to the art world. For example</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. It is a reminder of the inequalities and injustices that still afflict our world, and an aspiration for a different future. These are the questions that continue to animate the project, both through your words and actions.May the best ideas live on in the future, in the form of exhibitions, book-loads of copies of The Biennalee de Paris, and cultural interchange between the local and the globalised worlds.Download this article as PDFJeanne Robinson and Neil Johnson-Symington Co-operators in Culture and Society, The Universities of Sydney and Oxford, respectively, in 1995-96. I started my doctoral research at the University of Sydney, and the University of Oxford, where I worked in collaboration with Associate Professor and Co-Director of the University of Sydney Centre for Cultural Studies, Dr Janet McEwan. We held research-based participatory arts workshops for a group of students from the department of English and Cultural Studies at Oxford University. This was followed by a two-year postdoctoral research project at the University of Sydney, where I worked with Professor and Co-Director of the School of Art and Culture, Dr Janet McEwan. We held two research-based participatory arts programmes at the University of Liverpool, where I trained as a cultural geographer and ethnographer. These were the Production of Community Trust (2006-07) and Institutions for a Creative Future (2008-09). 	For the Biennale de Paris, I worked closely with Dr Jill Ellis, Director of the Australian Centre for Cultural Studies, who was interested in the ways in which the Biennale is a vehicle for the institution of citizenship. She wanted to know how the event could help create a sense of civic belonging among the local communities’ and particularly the Indigenous peoples of Australia.Through a research project, she suggested that the Biennale de Paris establish a ‘Community Trustees’ group, with a mandate to develop strategies for the community</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become something more and more external to the actual place and cannot be tied to its interiority. And this is a continuing process, as new urban explorers and art-historians are drawn into the mix. I don’t think it’s a stretch to suggest that the biennale is an extension of the city in its construction and its reconfiguration, as a constant redefinition of the word and a continual alteration of the terms on which we inhabit. This is a complicated concept to grasp, much more so when you are coming from a museum perspective. But the fact of the existence of this long-term evolution, wherein the biennale is a reinterpretation and redefinition of the word, and the biennale itself is not a fixed point, and isn’t limited to, or exclusive to, that particular curatorial style, means that the biennale is not confined to a particular appreciation of art history or biennials, but is open to a</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become something that is somewhat abstract and intangible, and so I’m interested in how we do the actual building of places, by taking the transience of time as something that is constantly pushing back against the perceived correctness of space. In this sense, it’s as if the design of the place is constantly at odds with its perceived rectitude. I think that this is one way of reading the increasing privatization of space. We can create what I would call ‘public space’, that is, spaces in which people actually do come to live – spaces that are not commodity exchanges. I would propose that there are other ways of reading the world, and the ways in which our culture creates and embodies space, and that these other ways of reading the world are also influenced by the increased commodification of images. As the biennale continues to expand and contract, the Venice Biennale’s space-exhibitionary character is transformed into a ‘marketing tool�</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become global. When you live in a place, you inhabit it, and you inhabit it in different ways. For example, you’re attracted to the fact that the city is becoming ever more informationally accessible: satellite dishes, mobile phones, internet access. You also tend to inhabit certain patterns and tastes. So you gravitate towards certain cuisines, particular neighbourhoods, particular shops, particular festivals. And you start to be drawn to certain kinds of travel. But you also tend to inhabit certain kinds of travel more. And this is a kind of cumulative effect. You become more urbanised and more materialistically oriented, and so forth. And this sort of expansive notion of the city, the global notion of the place, is one that has become quite dominant in contemporary culture. It’s the epiphany of many people around the world, and it’s the sort of thing that one can say, or design a place to be, with great confidence that others will say,</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become something that can be measured, quantified and exported. And so the biennale has had to find a way to engage with the notion of the place. I would love to work in a similar capacity to the biennale in Berlin, but the biennale has to find a way to situate itself in the city, and so it’s not just the biennale in Berlin that’s being built on a global scale; it has to find a place in the city that fits within this global definition of the place. In Venice, the biennale has to find its place within the larger context of things like the exposition, the street performers, the architecture of the city, the megastructure of the biennale, the exhibition vendors and the community of visitors. In this sense, the biennale in Venice is making a ‘world’ out of nothing. It’s becoming something that extends beyond the biennale itself. And</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become global in scope, and yet is very local in character. The biennale itself is circumscribed by its own peculiar set of characteristics: the biennale as an art production is a ‘business’ that requires the organisation of, and the delivery of, a specific programme of exhibitions and events. The organisation of this programme is itself an art form. In his book Institutions for a Post-Technological Society (1986), Pierre-Paul Dom Jan Mathieu makes the interesting observation that, in the twentieth century, major exhibitions of art occurred when a certain mathematical framework was being developed in advanced countries. These ‘exhibitions’ were typically organised around a theme, a set of rules and criteria, and a set of authorities – a Congress of Arts-Forum, a national art museum, a national gallery, a state gallery, etc. These ‘exhibitions’ evolved over time, as new technical developments made it possible to ‘reanimate’</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become something that is measured against a system of codes, regulations, authorities and documents that collectively and ultimately define a city. As our city systems move and morph over time, so too does the notion of place, but the city is by its very nature cyclical. Its name is a mythological construct, but the city is a living organism. The biennale, then, is interested in how we inhabit the cyclical nature of the biennale, and in the ways in which the biennale can inhabit the living and dynamic aspects of the city. It is a place where living things are encountered, enacted and consumed. It is a place where culture is made manifest, and in this sense, it is the home to the living. It is a place where culture is made from the very material that is experienced as consumable, and consumed. The biennale is interested in how we inhabit the materiality of things, and in the ways in which this affects culture production and consumption.</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become an object of exchange in a capitalist world. The Biennale is a rare institutional occasion where the exchange of places is made explicit. Here, the theory and art are intimately related. The Biennale is a ‘cultural capitalisation’ event, and the emergence of a new kind of ‘street art’ – one that I would classify as high-end – heralded a new form of intra-artistic exchange. The Biennale has long been a place where the arts are frequently misrepresented, and so it is with great pleasure that we begin our discussion of the biennale as a whole with a trope that has become commonplace: the biennale. Normative representations of the biennale tend to present the event through a trio of images: three monochromatic images of the Venetian and Austrian pavilions, flanked by a monochrome image of the city. In recent biennales, the Slovenian, Croatian and Egyptian pav</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become a source of power and meaning and so we should all be striving to inhabit the details and inhabit the place in a way that contributes to its value. In an ideal world we would all be able to say: ‘That was beautiful and made me feel alive and alive and in a way that this world could also be like’. But we live in the imperfect world we have created. Sometimes the beauty in the world is so extraordinary that it overwhelms our imperfect ways. Sometimes the beauty is so lacking that we would rather be somewhere else doing something better. And sometimes the beauty is so missing that we would rather be somewhere else doing something worse. So when we encounter that in our world, we should celebrate that as the world it is and not try to make it better. Excerpt from the talk, A Compendium of Essays on Architecture and Culture (2004), pages 288–302.  [1] Thomas Allsen, ed., Selected Essays (1849–19</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become globalised. In the twentieth century, the idea of the ‘place’ was globalised through the importance placed on it by industrialisation. In recent years, the rise of environmental and sustainable-design movements has placed great emphasis on the importance of the local. I think that the biennale in Venice, and for that matter elsewhere in Europe and North America, should be asking itself the same question: what is the relevance of a place in this new context? What is the relevance of an idea if it is negotiable? As the biennale itself has begun to realise, the answer is: the more the biennale itself produces and contributes to the global circulation of ideas, the less it matters.  	[1] The idea of the ‘more present’ is a concept that has been with us for a long time, and that is continuing to be. The ‘more present’ is a concept that has a kind of ontological pre</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell such a story, and, moreover, to imagine how the world might look with such a vision. The exhibition runs for a further three weeks in October 2014 at Kunst-Werke, and will show work from the Kunsthal Aarhus, Kunsthal A, Basel, Germany. The exhibition will be on view in the exhibition galleries of the Aarhus Gallery from October 2014. I have been invited as a curator to be at the Venice Biennale from October 2014 with Kate Hudson and Monica Ross’ Buildings a Decentering of a City: Renzo Piano and the Venice Biennale through OCTOPUS, 2014. The Biennale has been calling itself a ‘small world’, but this is really quite an expansive concept. I’m interested in how we inhabit the details and details are the import of a place; how we inhabit the idea of a place. The idea of the ‘place’ has become extremely important in the 21st century, and it’s worth recalling how important this was for the biennale. The place that the biennale calls itself is a fabrication; it’s an idea that emerged in the 1990s, and although it’s true that this biennale has since moved on from the original idea, the fact of its existence remains a central staging post. In Venice, the Biennale is a cultural phenomenon; it conducts itself as an art institution, and a shopping destination, and – above all – a place where artists, curators and art dealers congregate to exchange ideas, images and artefacts. It’s a mix of historical and commercial elements, and acts as a catalyst for cultural exchange between generations. But it is also a place of extraordinary inequality and oppression, and an exhibition that seeks to represent this as somehow desirable? The Biennale was established in 1912. It was originally called the ‘Concier</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale is a once-in-a-lifetime event. It doesn’t happen again. It’s an iconic building in the city, and part of the city’s institutional memory. It has historical significance because it was the first to open for business, and because it’s a landmark building in the city.The biennale is a once-in-a-lifetime event. It doesn’t happen again. It’s an iconic building in the city, and part of the city’s institutional memory. It has historical significance because it was the first to open for business, and because it’s a landmark building in the city.The biennale as symbolic of larger trendsetters like it or not: the impact of which can be seen in any given year’s sales and use of the building. The event that most consistently emerges as a sales-enhancing phenomenon is the one that comes equipped with a</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale is a ‘event space’, occupying a unique place on a world’s calendar. It emerges when the previous calendar year has passed, and carries with it a new cycle of programming. It is a ‘time capsule’ – recording the events that transformed a place and a culture, as well as the people who inhabit it. And it records, in a way that makes it possible to revisit those places and think about the people who live there and the way they’re engaged with the city. The problem with the biennale is that it tends to occupy a single spatial space, and that causes problems for the city and for the biennial as a whole. The biennial is the product of several different kinds of contemporaneous events, and their interrelations. The most obvious of these is the biennial itself; the real estate market, the megastructure, and the museums all contribute to making the city what it is today. But there are other kinds</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale is an episodic, curatorial enterprise. It begins with a brochure, sometimes with a news story, sometimes just with a map. The names and counts of the artists and curators who’d make up the Curatorial Faculty were written into the text. So the biennale really emerged as a response to what the biennial had become: a gathering of art professionals in one place, a gathering of art professionals in a region, a gathering of art professionals in a city. And as biennales have gotten bigger and more international, the boundaries between them have blurred. Every year there’s a different set of boundaries that artists, curators and art professionals must pass through to get to the actual art gallery. The boundaries that are being applied to the biennale are the same as those that are being applied to the art market, and they get bigger and more problematic as the biennale gets bigger and more international.In the past biennials have tended to</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale is a social event that involves a social context and a social purpose. It involves cultural exchange and it’s a place where we show our cultural gifts to each other. It’s a public display of cultural goods. The event is a public display of what and who we are as artists, and it’s the place where we show our artists’ curatorial gifts to the public. It’s a public opening to the city and a public to exchange cultural goods.Now, the biennale has several forms: a social, a curatorial and a venue. The social is the most familiar, and its primary purpose is to produce exchange between artist- and public-engagement stakeholders. It succeeds in isolating, articulating and capturing the event; it’s a rare public art project that achieves wider public support. The curatorial, on the other hand, is the most visible, and it carries the public through its activities, drawing publics and</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale has become increasingly important to cities all over the world, and in recent years has become an increasingly precious commodity, captured by ever more affluent nations in exchange for ever larger and more elaborate infrastructure projects. The biennale is an event that is often repeated, and is often cited as a reason for why cities are built. For a city to support itself, it’s essential that the biennale be a regular, interminable occurrence, on par with museums and other art forms. And yet, in the face of this growing financial burden, in the face of ever-more rapid population growth and urban sprawl, in the face of ever-more elaborate infrastructure projects, in the face of ever more affluent governments all around the world, the biennale is experiencing a kind of malleability, as though the ever-present, ever-present need to fund more projects is putting urban infrastructure at risk. In a recent assessment, the biennale in London was reported to have</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale has changed a great deal since that first edition, and it is the contemporary with a new name, but it retains many of the characteristics of the first edition. The biennale is a time of intense competition for exhibition venues, with artists constantly trying to outdo one another in terms of venue selection and pricing. And of course, the biennale has its critics, who argue that the competition is too intense. But these are superficial characteristics, and the true innovation of the biennale is competition among sites in a city environment.The biennale has become very political in its form, and I expect that this is one of the reasons why the Toronto Biennale has been able to provide something of a contestation of ideas and styles between its first and second editions. The competition for space between the two editions of the biennale was as fierce as ever, and the biennale itself has been increasingly political in its form, even as the competition for public space and public objects</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale is an episodic, curatorial enterprise that began in the mid-nineteenth century in Paris, and continues to this day in Moscow, New York and Berlin. It comes after every two years in Venice, and three times in other cities in Italy. It’s the most visible curatorial enterprise in the city, and has a curatorial function in and out of the biennale. The exhibition format began in Venice and expanded to other Italian cities after the biennale there. It became increasingly important for the biennale to have a presence in every city in its global tour, and to have a presence in every city in its ‘paradigm set’. The advent of the biennale coincided with a curatorial scramble to establish a complete work of art inventory, and to do so in a city as disparate as Venice, Milan, and San Francisco. The biennale itself coincided with a curatorial scramble to establish a permanent collection of works by artists and</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale is the main exhibitionary form in North America, and the main way that visitors to the city (and visitors elsewhere) get to see and experience the city. It is a large, often disruptive collection of exhibits, seminars, performances, exhibitions, and a ‘gallery of contradictions’ that is a major component of any expositionary form. It is a kind of curatorial form that is counter intuitive and which seeks to impose its understanding of the city onto those who come to see it. And it is often a form of social and political form that demonises those who do not share its values and interests.The biennale is a double-edged sword. It is an art form that relies on a public that is willing to hand over large sums of money to indulge in its excesses, and that seeks to project its wealth and power into the form of art that it encourages – in the form of legislated art that it supports in the form of laws, that it funds and that</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale has always been a fixture and source of pride for the city, and has even become a verb. This is partly due to the fact that it’s a noun: the word ‘bio’ has been incorporated into the title of the event, and the name itself is a plural name – so pride comes from the fact that the name of the first edition of the Biennale is repeated throughout the event. In this sense, the biennale is an entry point to other moments in time, and a way to find meaning in the chaos of the contemporary world. It’s a place to look for meaning in the world through metaphor and, by implication, action.Here, the word ‘biennale’ has come to denote a specific kind of beauty pageant, or perhaps a kind of aesthetic pageant: the kind that takes place in the Biennale grounds itself, and is staged in the surrounding area. The name has stuck, and in recent years</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. I want to know what the research team has for the upcoming biennale, and what the community might learn through the process. I want to know how the biennale might change the city, and the city might change the biennale. This is a very powerful way to conceive of the curatorial, and the community as a partner in making the biennale more than just an event.The biennale as eventThe biennale is a twice-yearly, three-day event that takes place in the city. It began in 1887 as the Toronto Biennale, and it was originally known as the Montréal Biennale. The name stuck, and today it’s the largest and most prestigious biennale in the world. It was also the name of the first edition of the Biennale, so we can be sure that ‘le clair» was in the air before the biennial came along.The biennale has a clear set of rules that set out what is and is not allowed within the city. For example, the city has a limited number of artists that can be invited to work in the Biennale; if there are more than six artists, then the city has to increase the number of spaces available. There are also strict curatorial criteria that artists must meet in order to participate in the Biennale; they have to be artists, curator, architects or artistic representatives from a certain region or nationality. For the Biennale to be a success, it’s important that the artists and their teams know how the festival is decided; otherwise, it’s easy to lose faith in the art world as a result of poor communication. The Biennale must have a clear idea of the city in order to persuade people to come to different parts of the city, because otherwise, people don’t cycle through the festivals in different ways and come to different parts of the city</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what people’s expectations are from an artist to deliver a project in a predictable way. I make the assumption that people have at least some idea of the scale of the project they are engaging with, and that they are not engaging with it through artistic means. I then offer two case studies: Liverpool (originally called the ‘Liverpool Biennial’), and the 2008 Venice Architecture Biennale, Venice, 2008. I use the word ‘exhibition’ loosely, and show how the art was produced, exhibited and ‘shuttered’ in the context of what could be considered an ‘exhibitionary structure’. I treat the show as a series of interactions, each one unique and detailing a specific interaction: the project, the artist, the organisation, the audience, the city, history and present, art and activism. I show how the different elements of the project came together in the context of the exhibition, the biennale</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what they think they understand about the world through their convenience stores, blogs and social media platforms. I use audience research to discover what happens next in the exhibition world, and beyond. I use audience research to find ways to engage them in the exhibition without judgment, and without judgement being drawn from them. This is a social science of conversation, and it is an art and social media masterclass.  Expo 06/07/09 was about the privatisation of culture, and the economic re-empowerment of the 1 per cent. The 2008 Biennial re-enacts the conference on the waterfront in Liverpool as a global event, and the first ever Venice Biennale. It is about the commodification of culture, and the new form of cultural consumption it assumes. The exhibition is a convenience store, its packaging an excuse to stock the shelves with artworks in convenient locations. The curatorial role is to</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what kind of impact the exhibition had, and how audience engagement impacted the project. I use the exhibition as a case study to explore the relationship between art and the environment, and how the climate issue comes up, and how art can be used to address that. I use data to understand how people form groups, and how these groups can act as a unit. I use data to understand how people consume culture, and how culture can be made useful in a social or economic sense. The book comes out at the end of a year in which the Liverpool Biennial was a critical and iconoclastic event. It came out before the Biennial finished its own research, produced its own artwork and presented its findings, and so it is a year in which the environmental and social tumult of 2008 was largely ignored or under-reported. The fact that the Biennial board was made up of academics and artists who had been activists in the environmental movement, and who had formed part of the curatorial team for the</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what people are saying about the city and its history. I use multimedia and show writing and multimedia skills to engage people on the large social networks. I use participatory practices to create community engagement and listen to peoplesʙ voices. I use theater and dance skills to engage people on the dance floor and in the arts galleries. I use dance and performance design to create accessible dance programs. I use dance and performance analysis to craft innovative dance and performance art programs. I use dance and performance design to create accessible dance programs. I use dance and performance analysis to craft innovative dance and performance art programs. I use dance and performance analysis to curb racial and socio-economic disparities in the arts. I use dance and performance analysis to create accessible dance practices. I use dance and performance analysis to craft innovative dance and performance art practices. I use dance and analysis to discover hidden social  	 mechanisms that produce artistic practice and produce social change. Creating Community Engagement for the 2008 Biennial</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what they think and feel about art and the world through art. I use audience surveys to ask questions about their expectations for art, and relationships between art and community. I create a climate of uncertainty around artworks, technical work, and installations, so that the audience can be engaged in imagining themselves in the gallery space and/or immersed in the art accelerator. I use science and maths to understand social dynamics and the effects of art and social interaction on the paths of technology. I take audience feedback as an important step along the trajectory of art making and in-depth curatorial work. I assume audiences are intelligent and non-judgmental users of technology, and so use that as a negotiating tool between art and audiences. I introduce AI to curatorial work and technology and AI to the context and processes that generate artistic and social impact in a real-time context. I assume audiences are engaged users of social media,</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what they felt, saw, or experienced. I use performance data to understand how art can interact with other art forms and interact with people's sense of self. I use qualitative data to understand cultural cognition and activism and interrogate cultural memory. I use scientific methods and experimental tools to understand cultural performativity and cultural depletion. I use performance, archival materials and literary techniques to explore the politics of art, and art-historical contexts in which art can be engaged. The results can inform how cultural organisers and artists engage with, and create opportunities for them to be engaged with, the political, economic and social contexts in which they live.  [1] See: http://www.expo.org/archives/2008/oct/why-did-the-torontobrien-biennial-exist.html (accessed October 2018).  [2] See: http://www.expo</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what they felt, saw or experienced as part of the exhibition. Each chapter attempts to assess a different aspect of the exhibition, from the physical to the virtual, and the organisation of the event to the individual. The chapter on the physical world is a combination of documentary and photographic archival materials, and is based on the original, unaltered manuscript of the Biennial’s contract with the Liverpool Biennial, as well as on original notes and transcripts of the meeting between Biennials and the Liverpool Biennial. The chapter on the virtual world is a composite of social media and digitised data, and is based on a public domain document (a digital rectification) of the Istanbul Biennial’s contract with the Istanbul Biennial, as well as on the original, unaltered manuscripts of the Biennial’s own notes and transcripts. Each chapter attempts to bring together key experiences from the Biennial, its volunteers and sponsors, and</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what I hope to achieve through the project. I use the experiences of the producers of the exhibition as a case study to explore the social impact of the exhibition, and draw parallels to the experiences of their community members. I also rely on the support of the Biennial to fund my project. I work in collaboration with two teams of artists: Jane Rankin and Mary Turner on the project, and the Museum of Contemporary Art and Archives on the archive. Figure 1: Curatorial workshop for the exhibition, 'The Importance of Numbers', at the The Royal Academy of Arts, London, 2008. Artist: Sophie Hope Underwood, Curatorial Fellow at the Royal Academy of Arts, London, 2008. Abstract The  [1]  Exhibit is a number in its own right, and the word is translatable from one of the objects into another.  [2] Curtis Watson on the exhibition,  	Curt</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what people are saying about the world through their behaviour. I focus on the local artists who found themselves in a dialog with international artists; artists from different countries, with varying cultures, who came together to discuss their identity and place in the world through their art. I also focus on the role artists can play in creating a dialogue around art and culture, in both the UK and internationally. The book is divided into four sections: the Arts and Environment; Health and Wellbeing; Food and Agriculture; and Politics and Publics. Each section includes a selection of artwork and brief reflections on the experiences of the artist(s) who made up the curatorial team. The section titles and abstracts reflect how audiences feel about the material and the project. The sections also reflect on the relationship between art and biennials and between the arts and biennials in general.  Excerpt from Chapter One: The Arts and Environment  Excerpt from Chapter Two: Health and Wellbeing  Excerpt</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge [to] the extent that they can be transferred to a mass audience in a non-traditional venue. How to Create Community Engagement Curatorial efforts should be informed by and driven by people who have a stake in the project.’ In my experience, this means people with a stake in the project making decisions along the way that will have long-term consequences for the project. The board of the Toronto Biennial should be a mix of people with a stake in the project, people with different perspectives and skillsets, and artists making art across the board. This is a recipe for long-term sustainability, and it is a recipe for creativity. Making Art in Context  (2008-ongoing) In this book I bring together the key experiences of the 2008 Liverpool Biennial, Expo, to show the social, economic and political context of the exhibition. I assume audiences are open-minded and non-judgmental, and use audience data to understand what they think and feel about the world in terms of art and culture. These experiences form part of a narrative that emerges from the data, based on research and analysis done with the Liverpool Biennial on a local and global level. The narrative will attempt to respond to the following questions: What is the experience of ‘ordinary’ people when faced with art that is extraordinary?  How can art be produced in conditions of social and political upheaval?  What are the creative practices possible in contexts of social and political upheaval?  What is the relationship between social and economic change and the creation of new art forms?  What is the relationship between social and ecological change and the transformation of art forms? What are the creative practices possible in contexts of social and political upheaval?  What is the relationship between cultural production and the social? This social and economic narrative will guide the development of the exhibition from conception to delivery, including the development of interactive websites and social media campaigns. I will use the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Condition: Issues, Tools and Techniques for Disaster Capitalism (2011). Her work has been commissioned by the European commission, the Mexican government, Instituto de Estadística y Geografía, UNAM, Universidad Di Tella and Universidad Metropolitana. She is a fellow of the American University's Cooperatore de Santiago and the AEA’s Cooperatore de Vancouver.She is a Master's Studentship in Architectural Studies at the University of Alberta​, with a major in Urban Studies and a minor in Civil and Administrative Engineering. She also holds a Bachelor of Architecture from the University of Alberta​, with a minor in Geography. She is the recipient of several awards and has lectured on urban studies and civil engineering.Outlawed Social LifeKaty Perry and Migos, Trapres, 2017. Written and produced by Max Martin, Max Martin, Jr. and Yeliz Arif, and Savjenna Kuzmanovic,</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Crisis: Finance capital and the carceral state in a global context (2010). She is the host of The Ubiquitous Curator (2013-16) and The Ubiquitous City (2016). Her writing has been featured in TEDx, The New York Times, The Wall Street Journal, CBC's The Current, CBC's The Current, The Washington Post and many others. She is a regular commentator on CBC's The Current and The Current Go90, and was recently named one of The Ubiquity Curator's Ten Innovators of the Future.Biennials as Collections of DeceptionNasser RabbatAs an architect, your main role is to design systems that create the appearance of structure and allow the system to function effectively, but also to develop and manage systems that actively deceive and invert those appearances. In other words, you’re not in a position to give structures the appearance of being empty or of not existing, but you’re supposed to be able</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Imagination Project (2010), and her role in the revision and launch of the popular culture reference work, Stephen Leacock, Le Corbusier: A Visual History of French Urban Development (1987), and the forthcoming book, Le Devoir des Beaux-Arts Urbanes: Travailleurs et Replacements, from the archive of a former residential high school in the suburb of Toi, France (2015). She is a consultant for the film Zomia (2013), a documentary about the mining and industrialisation of West Africa, and has written for the New York Times, The New Republic, The New York Sun, The New York Post, The New Inquiry, and The Nation. She is the host of the weekly podcast From Our Own Correspondent and the forthcoming documentary, From Our Own Correspondent II: Conversations with Urban Futurists. Homebaked is a hybrid Community Land Trust and collaborative process Design that arose out of the need to solve the problem</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Shape: Housing and Landscape Transformation in an Age of Massive Incarceration (2012). She has a regular column in The New York Times and is an adjunct professor at Mount Royal University. Her research examines the ways in which infrastructure is constructed, managed and abolished in the United States and Latin America.She has written for The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Times Magazine and The New York Observer, among other publications. She is also the host of the podcast Slumdog Millionaire (2013) and has written for the website MapMeSF, as well as with the blog Tiny Curated.Gabriela Rendon is an architect with experience in urban and regional planning, and has overseen the development of the New York City Metropolitan Regeneration Corporation (Mid-Wilshire Transportation Authority, 2011-2015). She spearheaded the Mid-Wilshire Transportation Authority's (MBTA) New Starts New York City—a plan to rebuild and modernize the subways</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Geographies of Development (with Ray Chavez and Peter Weibel, 2013). She is a regular columnist for The New York Times and is the host of The Current Time, a New York Times-style podcast.Her articles have been published in The New York Times, The New York Times Digital Comment, The New York Times Travel section, The New York Times Best Seller List and The New York Times Higher Education section. She has written for The New York Times Digital Comment, The New York Times Best Seller List and The New York Times Higher Education section. She has also written for The New York Times Digital Comment, The New York Times Higher Education section and The New York Times Travel section.She is the host of The Current Time, a digital radio show in which she speaks to the times, often commenting on current events and their place in global urbanisation.Her writing has been published in The New York Times, The New York Times Digital Comment, The New York Times Travel section, The New York Times</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Condition: Issues, Tools, and Tools for Urban Transformation (2010). She is the editor and publisher of the forthcoming online journal PLOS ONE, and has received a host of editorial and media awards and mentions, including the 2017 Royal Institute of British Architects Doctoral Dissertation Prize for Architecture.She has served on the boards of various international non-profit and university research organisations, and has received numerous publications in regional and national journals and books on a variety of urban and regional topics. She is currently co-editor and publisher of the forthcoming online journal Regional Publishing, with Carolyn Christov-Bakargiev, The Regionalization of Capital (2016). She has co-edited the forthcoming online journal REACH: Regionalization of Education and Regionalism in Europe and America.Whose Streets?Whose Streets? is the story of two large projects in Montreal that sought to create a shared, inclusive and participatory city through a process of design, planning and accumulation. In 2007, the City of Montreal</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Crisis: Money, Power and the Politics of Resistance (2013). She is part of the Curatorial Faculty of Architecture, University of Toronto Press.Gabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Crisis: Money, Power and the Politics of Urbanization (2013). She is part of the Curatorial Faculty of Architecture, University of Toronto Press.PreviousNextGabriela RendonIn 2006, I co-founded 3DPrint, an imprint of the Canadian Arts Publishers Limited, founded in Toronto in 1997.3DPrint produced works by artists from around the world, including works for the</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Crisis: Money, Power and the Metainterface of Capital (2014). She has written for The New York Times, The Washington Post, The Atlantic and The New Republic, among others. She is currently working as an editor and writer for PLATEAU, the international journal of architectural aesthetics.Envisioning Public Art: New Futures of Art and Urban FuturesDivyut Jain Chandra Bahl is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, and holds a Bachelor of Arts in English Cultural Studies from the same university. Her dissertation examines the social, political and cultural history of arts education in Canada from the 1960s to the present, focusing on the relationship between Canadian arts education and the formation of publics. She examines the legacy of that history through the lens of a multi-disciplinary art history, critical race theory, and contemporary urban development. She examines the intersection of race, class and gender</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Form: Contravision, Continuum and Fracture (2008). She is part of the curatorial team for the upcoming Venice Biennale. She is part of the Curatorial Faculty for the Venice Architecture Biennale, and part of the Curatorial Faculty for the Venice Biennale, where she is completing a year-long research project into the topic of sovereignty in urban space. Towards a Planetary Urban Form ------------Towards a Planetary Urban Form ------------What if, as Francis Bacon proposed in his famous essay ‘On the Origins of Life’, we could consider life itself as a kind of a planetary formation? What if, by considering life only as capital, we could begin to comprehend the planetary form that shapes it? What if, in a thousand lifetimes from now, we can look back at the origins of planetary formation and realise that we lived in a different world, in which organisms on Earth shared a common ancestry with life? What if,</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial is an opportunity missed, a failure to anticipate the changing face of urbanisation and development, and a failure to consider the impact of its implementation on the planet. The art world, and the curatorial in particular, will continue to be interested in what comes after the megastructure, but the question will be which of these two sets of uses will be enough to sustain the art as a service sector, and which, in the long term, will be enough to support the art as a commodity?Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Shape: Expanding Competitiveness Through Urban Modification (2009). She has also co-edited with Nadine Attewell, The Urban Form: Finance, Cities, and the Metainterface (eds) (2006 and 2008), and co-edited with Peter Fortna and Michael Rowbotham, The Urban Form: A Global Perspective (2007). She has received several awards and mentions for her work, including the 2009 Polaris Prize for Architecture and the 2002 John Lennon/Zig-Zag Letter Award for Architecture.Gabriela Rendon is an Architect and Principal in the practice of Gabriel S. Peralta, Inc. She is also a professor of urban studies at Mount Royal University and the Faculty of Architecture. Her research interests include development, planning and hegemony in urban space, and the practices and institutions that enable and facilitate their growth. Her publications include the books Slumdog Millionaire: Housing and Capital in a Global Context (2007) and The Urban Shape: Expanding</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way.
    <text>The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way.I don’t want to sound reductive, but sometimes I think, as we were talking, that there are some things in life that we’ve collectively decided that we can’t control. Like, what kind of choices are those?There’s a way to understand what happened in the past, but at the same time, we have to be able to move forward. Otherwise, what kind of future is this? We may not have control over the past, but we can certainly change the past.In the end, I think that what matters is that things are always changing, and that’s why it’s so exciting to be a part of something new: to see new possibilities and new ways of interacting, new ways of living. And I don’t think we can achieve that in this present, because of the way we are structurally embedded. Our social roles and identities are built on the past. And I think that part of</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way.If there’s no future, what kind of future is this? I don’t know. Maybe things are better now than they were when we got here, but I don’t think that’s always the case. In the past, there’s a tendency to elevate things, to make them the way they were meant to be, which can be oppressive and depressing at the same time. There’s a moment in the project where we decided that we wanted to stop being pinned down by the present. We wanted to travel through the past, and the present at the same time. The challenge for us was to find the balance. Because the more we delved into the past, the more we discovered the ways in which the present is structured, and the more we questioned whether we were living inside a historical narrative, or whether we were actually experiencing what we were imagining.  The project ended up being a meditation on the past, and on the present</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way. The future is a dangerous world out there, and we have to figure out what to do with ourselves.Download this article as PDFTim JeevesTim Jeeves is a writer, curator, journalist and co-founder of the Curatorial Institute, where he has worked since 1995. His writing has been published in The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Inquiry: A Journal of Inquiry, and numerous other publications. He is the Curator of Exhibitions at the Granby Four Streets Museum, and was a curator for the Welsh Streets Project, which he co-founded in 1988. His most recent work, The Solar System (2015-16) is a three-year project examining the systems that constitute our solar system. He is currently curator and curator of the exhibition series Solar System, the Denver and San Francisco Museum of Modern Art, and the New Republic, and is the editor of the online journal Stages</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way. And maybe that means dying.Oh, and there was that time I gave a talk at the Warsaw Architectural Biennale about how I thought the biennale was entering a new phase. I was invited to be a curator, and the idea was to find ways to work with artists and bring them into the biennale through what I imagined was a curatorial framework. I went to the biennale with a curator and a team of artists. We visited forty-five cities in forty-five countries. We also visited some remote areas of the Earth. The idea was to visit cities that were part of the same cultural system, or had a similar set of values and histories, and then work from there. The idea was to visit places where the biennale was already deeply embedded in the city and to work from there.The art form of the biennale has shifted dramatically in the last twenty years. It used to be showpiece, the pinnacle of the art form,</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way.This may come across as a plea for humanity, but I get the sense that this is an act of pure love – an act of pure altruism. You’re stuck in this present, and you don’t know what the future holds, or doesn’t know how to react to it. And I get the sense that there’s a mutual understanding that this is the act of coming to terms with the failure of the system. There’s no going back.This may seem trivial, or even trivializing, to us technophiles. But to people like me, it does seem like the future is descending into chaos. And I don’t think that’s a good thing.I don’t think it’s nice to degrade people. But to be blunt, I do think that we’re all at this point in history where we’re at this point where we need to learn how to be accountable</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way.The question of whether we are stuck in this present or moving forward is one that needs to be debated. Because if we don’t debate it, other people will. And they will make their own decisions, based on what they see as the best future for the world around them. But we need to decide for ourselves what that future is. And I believe that what’s missing in the discussion of the future is an understanding of what that future might be like. I don’t mean dystopian, but we’re all too familiar with the forms of industrial society that we’re stuck in. The question is what can we create? I guess what I meant when I said ‘We’re stuck in this present’ is that we don’t have the imagination or the drive to think differently. We don’t have the drive to look beyond the present. We don’t have the ambition to look forward. We’</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way.If there’s a way to turn things around, which we believe is possible, then why wouldn’t we strive for that? Wouldn’t it be nice? Wouldn’t it be nice to have someplace to call home? If there’s no future to look forward to, then why would we want that? If there’s no future to look backward to, then what is it that we actually want?We asked what the difference is between now and the future. In the here and now, we're thinking about the things we can control. But in the hereafter, things that we can't control will happen.In The Fellowship of the Ring, Tolkien describes the vision of Elendil and his comrades in the Fellowship of the Ring: ‘They looked on with wonder and elation as the Ring flew by. To Gollum, who was their leader, the scene was a miracle. Suddenly the Ring was no longer a threat but</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way. We need to grow up and move on, because there’s no future here.So what can we do? I suggested that we start a foundation. I was the only one who suggested this. The idea is to have a really strong guiding hand, like a family, like a neighborhood, like a community of people who work together, and then to use the money that comes out of the foundation to start a foundation. And then, when we’re older and wiser, we can take the money and use it to start a foundation that works for us.This sounds simple, but it’s also scary. The first time I gave it thought, I just got scared. I thought, You’re starting to give me ideas that I’m not even sure are my own. You’re giving me the crazy shit you got from the mavericks. I’m not even sure I follow those ideas. And then I’m scared</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way. I don’t think there’s a one-to-one relationship between the present and the future, but there has to be an understanding of the difference between what we and the robots are subjected to. Maybe what we did with the present in order to think about the future is still relevant.Maybe the future is rosier than the present, in the sense that it’s closer to us: smarter, more capable, and with a human in the loop. This is the assumption behind artificial intelligence and the rise of complex systems. But there is a tension, which is to be addressed. The more we expose ourselves to the systems we plug into, the more we become immersed. And the more we become immersed, the more problems we encounter, the more data we collect, the more images we capture, the more apps we download, the more media we discover – the more information we give up in order to get to where we need to be. This is perhaps the</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation. It was never going to be a reality. But it’s still going strong. I’m still the same Tim, the same engineer, the same manager. I’m in the same art school, the same design firm, just another company doing good works. Of course, now I’m curious about what that might be like. I still have questions. But it’s been nice to have the project as a contingency plan.We started off by asking what the future might hold for us. If the present is terminal, what is the alternative? Maybe the future is rosier than the present, but at the same time, we know that there’s no way to know, because we’re stuck in this present. So what do we do? Is there a way to turn things around? I don’t think there’s, but we’ve all collectively decided that we need to find that way. And maybe this will mean looking to the future. Maybe things will be better than they are now, and we will need to become change-makers and start afresh.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is an Architect and Urbanist whose work is centred on the urbanisation of Montreal’s Old Port (and its environs). She has a particular interest in the role of the architect in the formation of sustainable urban futures. She has worked with local and national governments to create new ways of urbanising the port city, and is currently an advisor for the federal government’s new Canadian Place initiative. She is the author of The Port of Today (2013), an edited version of her best-known urbanist work, La Presse de Montreal (1937), and co-editor of the upcoming, soon to be completed, Port and Port: Essays on an Iconic Building (2014). Port and Port is set in</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the
    <text>biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the sheer strangeness of it all – that sort of lunacy, and the acute strangeness of what’s happening to the city. I think it captures the sense of what’s happening to Liverpool.And I think it captures the essence of the event very well, although I admit that I sometimes struggle to see how the two collides. It’s as if the art world has been trained to see the festival as some sort of perverse, inverted form of personal struggle – you’re on the cusp of a transformative event, you’re about to embark upon a journey that will shape the cultural landscape of a city for years to come, and yet you’re trapped in a sort of perpetual motion of change. And I think that’s where some people get stuck. They get caught up in the contradictory demands of such massive social and political upheavals – is it going to be a great dance party? Is it going to be a great</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the sheer absurdity of the human race. I don’t think I would have been able to grasp the enormity of what had just happened in Liverpool, or the world at large, without being led by a man named Jack Stewart.Jack Stewart: Jack Stewart, let me start off by saying I don’t agree with everything he’s said. I think he’s an idiot. I think he’s an animal. I think he’s a murderer. I think he’s a paedophile. I think he’s an alcoholic.I don’t believe him.I don’t believe him.I don’t believe him.I don’t believe him.I don’t believe him.I don’t believe him.I don’t believe him.I don’t believe him.I don’t believe him.I don</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the magic of it all. The fact that it occurred on British soil, the fact that British-born Cathy Marshall was invited, and that she was awarded an MBE for services to broadcasting – all of that came along in that one day.I remember particularly fondly the afternoon we were given a tour of the newly redesigned Kew Gardens. I led the way through a park named in her honour, and then we wandered into the gardens of another artist, Peter Carruthers. He was inviting us into his garden and introducing himself as the ‘Garden Palace’, and we were invited to join him for a weekend ‘Garden Party‘. We were all invited, and so we went. He invited me to join him for a Saturday afternoon garden party, and we did. We organised it so that everyone could attend, and we did. And it became a community project. He would organise the flowers, the birds, the butterflies, and the other plants</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the sheer lunacy. It captures the euphoria, the inebriation, the horizons that suddenly reappear and reappear, and all the other moments that emerge and disappear along the way. And I think that in that moment, people in the arts community, perhaps even some of those who work in the arts today, had a moment where they could actually think about the work that was being done. It wasn’t just a celebration of the art that was being done; it was the creation of a culture for the arts.I remember one afternoon in the artist’s studio in the early 1970s, a group of us were discussing the historical significance of Champion’s Day – which was a Saturday – and our co-workers and I were reluctant to do a research project on our own cultural identity as an institution, because there wasn’t a lot of room for us to be authentic to our own sense of the day. But we’d developed a</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the way in which it symbolises the triumph of capitalist culture over all of its environments, and especially its failure to connect with the very people it’s meant to serve. And the fact that Anne Bean is still the festival organiser, and that I still act as a sort of go-between for the festival, the biennale, and the biennial, and that we still do some very strange things to the biennale, to the biennial, and the biennial, and the biennial, and the biennial, and the biennial, and the biennial, and the biennial, and the biennial, and the biennial, and the biennial, and the biennial, and on and on.And if you’re wondering where the Liverpool Biennial, or any of the other arts biennials, are going, well, I have to tell you that I don’t know. There are so many variables and overlapping and yet connected</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the magic of it all. The lunacy and inaccuracy of it, however, is in part what made it memorable. The exaggeration of the human condition is part of the charm of the beast.The other part of the charm is that sometimes the exaggeration and the absurdness can actually be part of a plan. And I think we all know what that feels like.I remember well one particularly bizarre aspect of the event: the fact that the artist who was invited to perform under the auspices of Liverpool Biennial was Meehan Leigh actually came from Canada. Meehan Leigh is a folk singer and a poet. She is not a biennial administrator or a curator. She is a poet and she wrote a song about the Vietnam War. She came to the Biennial with two songs written specifically for the occasion. One of them, entitled The Silent Spring, was originally written for the Ballroom at The Beverly Hilton in New York City in 1961, where Marilyn Monroe was born.</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the sheer insanity of it all. There’s just no comparable historical or archival documentation of how the day was presented, or why. But there were a few other, more contemporary things on offer, and I think the fact that they were from the same biennial, and that they came from a biennial that was then seeking ways to foster a cultural identity for the city in its transit, as a kind of a call to action, and some kind of a plea from within. I don’t think that there’s any way of knowing what those people would have said or done if they had the chance. Chalk it up to the vagaries of cultural capitalism.But I do think that in those days, and still today, there’s a kind of distorted conception of what a biennial is perceived as representing. There’s this idea of the biennial as a finite object with a fixed, predetermined form that can only ever attain maximum consumption and impact</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the poetry in the sound design, the poetry in the staging, the poetry in the gestalt, the poetry in the name.I remember thinking, going round in circles, that day: what a weird, wonderful, beautiful, strange, maddening, maddeningly arbitrary day it was to be alive.But I also remember thinking, going round in circles, that same day, that I  KNEW that day.I can  still feel  that burning in my bones, the way that I felt then: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the poetry in the staging, the poetry in the gestalt, the poetry in the name. And I can  still feel the fat, jiggly, jiggly time that I gave birth to: the monstrous, maddening jiggly time that I gave birth to, the monstrous, maddening time that I  still give birth to. And I can still</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the sheer lunacy of it all. The truth is, I suppose, that even at that time I would have thought, in those early days, that we might one day look back on and say, ‘How absurd was it to give away more than we took in?’Champion’s Day was organised by the Liverpool Biennial and the Merseyside Hospitals Authority, with the support of Arts Council England. It was a day to mark the biennial’s relationship to the hospital, to mark the fact that it is the medical school that recruits patients for its programmes, and to mark the fact that it is a day of activities for those students. It was a very different kind of championing, in many ways, than what we do now.There was a point at the time, I think, when people did see the connection between biennials and hospitals, and the way in which biennials could be used as a way to address social problems.</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, the fascinating work of Instant Replay, the flamboyant entrepreneur Joseph Stiller’s producers, and the unexpectedly seductive sounds of an international festival coming to a city near you.  And of course, there was the fantastic work of our own audio engineers, led by Tim Bresnan, who produced the spectacularly immersive Real-Time Festival with artist Meehan Leigh ­(who has a residency at the Liverpool Biennial), and as part of the Liverpool Academy’s permanent collection.The festival that I think most people in the UK and beyond remember well was Champion’s Day, which took place in early May 1966. I think it’s an utterly bizarre and inaccurate way of looking at things, and I can already hear the criticism of it in some quarters. But I do think it captures the essence of the moment very well: the sheer lunacy of it, the absurdity of it all, the sheer lunacy of living in the gutter and all the rest of it. There was a time, I think, when I believed that the reason I had written the songs I have today is because I listened to The Beatles'  every day.I used to live in a four-up-the-road flat by the river, a quiet cul de sac in the middle of nowhere, opposite a bakery that sells bread and pastries. I used to drive a battered black Land Rover, a bright red Mini, a pair of box cutters and a pick-axe. I used to work as a bus boy, in the bakery's bakery section, alongside a team of artists, writers and photographers. They were all employed as waiters or waitresses, by the river, at the bakery or at a different branch of the bakery. The bakery was a hive of activity: the bakery was a city unto itself, run by a queen and her cronies. There was a gym, a</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively excluded from this narrative, and the curatorial conceit was left to speak for itself. The audience was left with a set of questions and a set of answers. And the audience was effectively left with a sense of themselves in the form of art, in the form of a fictious performance that they created through the content of the exhibition. This was very much a ‘cut and dried’ encounter for the audience, in that the curatorial conceit was largely left to itself. But the audience was also left with a narrative that was fundamentally different from the one that the curator or artist intended to create. This is a narrative that is inherently relational, and the audience was left with the capacity to create narratives that are both ‘unique’ and ‘different’ through the medium of art.  In other words, the capacity to create relationality through the capacity to consume. ‘Entitling’ spaces with a narrative that is both fictious and relational opens the</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively made redundant, since the curator could have easily come up with a different exhibition format or even a completely different exhibition structure.  This last possibility is a bit of a stretch, since the narrative of the exhibition would have continued to be centered on the festival and its holdings, and the production team's ideas and manipulations would have been fully into the public domain. As we all know, Francis Bacon was all set to create something completely different, and we could even argue that his ideas would still have some place in our contemporary curatorial system.  But the big question that remains is what would have happened had the exhibition been staged in a different way? I think that the curatorial and artistic mission of staging materiality in a different way would have created a radically different curatorial trajectory and would have required a completely different trajectory in the development of the art, which could have been very different trajectories. And I think that the materiality of the artefact would also have required an entirely different curatorial</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively present in the exhibition, and their presence was felt throughout the exhibition. Their thoughts, questions, and feelings were as real as the artefact itself. This materiality was a source of great pleasure to the audience, and gave the impression that the audience were as engaged as the curators themselves. One may even imagine the audience as fictional characters – in which case the problem would be even worse, because the audience would lose their minds. But the audience was real, and as the exhibition progressed, this was supplemented by experiential material that placed the audience at the centre of the exhibition. This materiality was extremely appealing to the audience, because it gave the impression that the audience were actively involved in the creation of the exhibition, and were thus a source of much inspiration and success for the curators, since they could no longer pretend that the art was not moving through the city. Later on, when the art was moved to different locations, the audience was also encouraged to engage with different aspects of</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively excluded from this presentation due to the curatorial narrative, the elimination of interaction, and the materiality of the artefact itself. As the Biennale's own Kristina Frolovaossağue, explains: ‘The ability to connect with the artefact is the most important of all the curatorial tools.’[25] I therefore conclude by proposing a few further curatorial paradigms that would make up a more comprehensive and inclusive exhibition model that would address the materiality of artworks and the dynamic aspect of the exhibitionary form as an art form itself. These paradigms would not only make the art exhibitionary form more visible and real, but would also help to create a more nuanced understanding of the materiality of artworks and the cultural and social conditions of those works. The identification of the audience, the procurement of information, the locating of artefacts and the creation of encounter would all be objects of research and discovery. The paradigmatic artefact would</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively excluded from that process, and its participation was largely rendered invisible. They were asked to engage with the curatorial narrative, but they were also actively excluded from any actual interaction with the artefact. Their exclusion only deepened the feeling of not belonging. The curatorial narrative was in many ways a trap: it was not what we expected, and neither were we allowed to change it. But the fact that the audience was effectively silenced also fed the circus, and the materiality of the artefact, in many cases, further fuelled that circus. The audience would have participated in the act of buying and consuming the things that were displayed, and they would have shared in the act of creating those things. And that is precisely what the curatorial mission in Singapore is all about: to engage with the materiality of things in order to effect change in the world through things they buy and consume. In other words, the curatorial mission in Singapore is to manufacture narratives to support a particular narrative, and to</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively invited to become artists themselves by the curatorial conceit of the exhibition, which basically involved the audience becoming artists themselves through their consumption of the artefact. The audience was encouraged to produce their own meaning and narrative through the consumption of the artefact, and to do so through what I would define as an ‘artist-centered’ curatorial approach. This might require some reflection and negotiation with one’s place in the narrative, but it also means that the narrative can evolve and expand as the audience makes choices, engaging with certain narrative structures more and removing others.  A narrative that seeks to represent the world through the symbols and tropes of art, and engages the narrative as a set of relations, is more likely to be participatory, and this is why the curatorial conceit is so compelling. It is always the protagonist and centre of the narrative, but the audience is the point of entry into the narrative. They step into a narrative and participate, whether as spectators, as</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively excluded from the production of the materiality of the artefact. They did have the opportunity to contribute their knowledge and ideas via comments, suggestions and poems; much of which was highly critical.  This materiality was most manifest in the form of a number of mini-exhibitions, each dedicated to a different aspect of the materiality of the artefact. Each mini-exhibition addressed a different aspect of the materiality of the artefact: its function, origins, creators and institutions. My own take on the materiality of artefacts is that of a collection of objects and processes that accumulate over time – a collection of stories told through the act of telling them. The collection of artefacts, which were curated and conceived by Juliana Engberg as part of the Biennale’s ‘triennale’, is a collection of stories told simultaneously through images, texts and data. In this regard, the exhibition was not only about the collection of objects and processes</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively invited into the exhibition through the exhibition schedule. They sat through a scripted narrative that was largely designed to be shared between the curators, art professionals and art students present. This made the materiality of the artefact more accessible, and the audience more able to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact. And the materiality of the artefact became more real as the time passed, as the audience became more entrenched in time and space.  The materiality of the artefact then became the undoing of the artist’s intentions and objectives, and the undoing of the art’s place in time. At some point, the art’s place in time has to be taken off-limits to a certain kind of people. And at some point, the audience has to be made aware of this. That is, the audience has to be made aware that they are not safe from the politics of their own consumption. That is, the audience has to be</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively invited into a different world, and that world is very moving and interesting. As the exhibition progressed, the curatorial narrative got more subtle, more complicated and eventually, the audience was invited to step back and allow the materiality of the artefact to speak for itself. This was done in several ways: by creating parallel worlds (re-enactment, in-gallery, virtual reality and so forth); by allowing the audience to step into pre-conceived ‘knowledges’ regarding what the artefact could be; by allowing the audience to step back and allow the artefact to ‘see’; and finally, by allowing the audience to ‘think outside the box’ by stepping into the very real (but rarely imagined) world of nation-state identity. The audience was effectively invited into a parallel universe, and this universe was very moving and interesting indeed to be in. And to be part of. But the real treat for me was when the audience</text>
    <text>conventional curatorial practices and curatorial knowledge. The idea appealed to me because it aligned with the content of the exhibition: how to think about and engage with materiality through the medium of art, and how to use the materiality to create meaning and connection in a relational sense through the mode of consumption (rather than through the fixation on individual artworks or individual products).  A final remark that came to mind is the one that came to mind while browsing the exhibition schedule: what struck me most about the curatorial approach to this materiality was that it was largely absent from the exhibition. This omission may be an artifact of the format of the exhibition itself. The curatorial narrative would normally be the focus of the exhibition, and the materiality of the artefact would be conspicuous. Also absent was the curatorial intervention that would have allowed the audience to question and engage with the materiality of the artefact, and might even have created a situation where the audience felt like they were part of the production process. But the audience was effectively shielded from this materiality because the artefact was seen as something intrinsically valuable, something that embodies an ideal of what art should be.  And this is perhaps the epiphany of the audience at this medium: there is no such thing as 'artificial' meaning in this context. The audience had no idea how meaningless and meaningless life was; they didn’t know that meaning and purpose and purpose and history was made by the work that one creates; and they didn’t know that meaning and purpose and history actually happen in the world around us.  And this is the epiphany of the audience at the Biennale of Art in Venice: there is no such thing as 'meaning' or ‘purpose’ or ‘history’ in the world. There is only ‘art’ (or, well, art and aesthetics). And this is the epiphany of the audience at the Venice Biennale of Art in Venice: there is no such thing</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley,
    <text>The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.8  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.9  See Bernard J. Foley, The Nation, May 1917, p.1.10  See Bernard J. Foley, Speech at the 1916 Socialist Party, in Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, p.183.11  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, May 1917, p.1.12  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, May 1917, p.1.13  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, May 1917, p.1.14  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, May 1917, p.1.15  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, May 1917, p.1.16  </text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Progressive and the Not-so-Progressive, 1977, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.8  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Crisis of the City’, The Atlantic, 21 November 1917, p.1.9  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber,eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.10  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Crisis of the City’, The New Republic, 8 January 1919, p.261.11  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The New Republic, 8 January 1919, p.272.12  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Crisis of the City’, The New Republic, 9 January 1919, p.264.13</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The New Republic: Critical Essays, 1941, and Bernard J. Foley, ed., The New Republic: Essays on Utopianism, 1941, both of Princeton, Princeton University Press, Princeton, 1985, pp.1–42.8  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The New Republic: Essays on Utopianism, 1941, and Bernard J. Foley, ed., The New Republic: On Revolution, 1942, both of Princeton, Princeton University Press, Princeton, 1985, pp.1–25.9  Michel Foucalt,  	Towards A Socially Just World, trans. Evan Calder Williams, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.80.10  Foucalt, Toward a World Without Punishment, Ch. 6, from the anthology of essays published in No More, 3rd ed., with Fredric Jameson, Nation, New York and London,</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.8  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.9  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, pp.1.10  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.11  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, pp.1.12  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.13  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.14  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.15  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.16  See Bernard J. Foley, ed.,</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, pp.1–2.8  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in Foley and Foley, The New Criticism, 1987, p.3.9  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, pp.1–2.10  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in Foley and Foley, The New Criticism, 1987, p.3.11  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in Foley and Foley, The New Criticism, 1987, p.3.12  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in Foley and Foley, The New Criticism, 1987, p.3.13  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in Foley and Foley, The New Criticism, 1987,</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.8  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.9  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.10  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.11  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, pp.1.12 and Bernard J. Foley, eds., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.13 and Bernard J. Foley, eds., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.14  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.15  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.16  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Collected Works of Bernard J. Foley, New York, 1974, and Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Collected Works of Bernard J. Foley, New York, 1977, both of New York and Cambridge, respectively, p.1–27.8  See Bernard J. Foley, ed.,  The Nation, 3 August 1969, p.1.9  Foley, Bernard J. The Crisis of the City: The Political, Economic, and Cultural Origins of Today’s Crisis. Urbana, Illinois: University of Illinois Press, 1976, p.1.10  Foley, Bernard J. The Collected Works of Bernard J. Foley, New York, 1974, p.1–27.11  Foley, Bernard J. The Collected Works of Bernard J. Foley, New York, 1978, p.1–27.12  Foley, Bernard J., and Bernard J. Foley,</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, October 1917, pp.10–14.8  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Crisis of the Century’, in Foley, Bernard and Montgomery, Geoffrey, The New Critical Essays of 1917, 1970, Ch.2, p.109.9  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Nation’, in Foley, Bernard and Montgomery, Geoffrey, The New Critical Essays of 1917, 1970, Ch.2, p.152.10  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in Foley, Bernard and Montgomery, Geoffrey, The New Critical Essays of 1917, 1970, Ch.2, p.153.11  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Nation’, in Foley, Bernard and Montgomery, Geoffrey, The New Critical Essays of 1917, 1970, Ch.2, p.154.12  See Bernard J. Foley, �</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Atlantic and Its City, 1970, Cambridge, Mass.: Belknap Press of Harvard University Press, p.262.8  See Bernard J. Foley and Tom Hayden, eds., The American Literary Critic, Vol. 21, No. 2 (Spring, 1966), and Tom Hayden and Bernard J. Foley, eds., The American Literary Critic, Vol. 21, No. 3 (Summer, 1966), and Bernard J. Foley, ed., The American Literary Critic, Vol. 21, No. 4 (Fall, 1966), and Tom Hayden and Bernard J. Foley, eds., The American Literary Critic,[1] The New Republic, Issue 11, January, 1968, p.371.9  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The New Republic, Issue 11, January, 1968, p.372.10  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The New Republic, Issue 11, January, 1968,</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the ever-present danger of totalitarianism and the emergence of new forms of domination. It is a comment on the contemporaneous appearance of a question that is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘the decisive enigma of our time’.2  Horkheimer, the Horkheimer Report, 1949, p.5.3  See Tony Barber and Tom Hayden, eds., The New Criticism, 1987, and Tom Hayden and Tony Barber, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader, 1990, both of Cambridge, Mass.: Cambridge University Press.4  See the publication National Post and Courier, 19 December 1917, p.3.5  See Bernard J. Foley, ‘The Coming Crisis’, in The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.6  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 19 November 1917, p.1.7  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.8  See Bernard J. Foley and Tom Hayden, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader,1990, and Tom Hayden, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, pp.1–3.9  See Bernard J. Foley and Tom Hayden, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader,1990, and Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, pp.1–3.10  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.11  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.12  See Bernard J. Foley and Tom Hayden, eds., The Cambridge Cultural Studies Reader,1990, and Tom Hayden, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917, p.1.13  See Bernard J. Foley, ed., The Nation, 20 November 1917</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is clear that not all the changes required will be met with or accommodated by contemporary art institutions. Whether the demand is met or is it met at an unacceptable level, depends on what is perceived as the contemporary commodity in the art world: art as a commodity, or rather, the high price attached to it. The significance of this price can be seen in the decrease in traffic on the biennial market over the past twenty years. The biennial market is characterised by a sharp rise in traffic days before, during and after the art biennial. And while there is certainly a relationship between the two, the biennial market age is characterised by a sharp fall in traffic days. As the Tate Modern sold out within minutes of its release, and the Biennale de Paris quickly followed suit, the demand for the art biennial was immense, and the available art resources either exhausted or non-existent. Meanwhile, the biennale de Paris and the Tate Modern have both been forced to close</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is clear that the capacity of art biennials to impact social change becomes even less certain. Hopefully, this brief essay will have provided some perspective on what art biennials can and cannot do. I look forward to seeing you in Liverpool!DDownload this article as PDF28 November 2014To Osvaldo Sanchez20 July 2014Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California20 July 2014Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF at the end of next month, and I wanted to ask if we could meet up. Lucía Sanromán told me a bit about the new manifestation of inSite: your Casa Gallina. I’m intrigued by the idea that a biennial — or a recurring, temporary exhibition platform such as inSite has been — would move to take up permanent residence somewhere, indeed permanent residence elsewhere. What does it mean for a biennial to reside in a city? Does it mean that the biennial should reside in</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is clear that the capacity of the art biennial to generate social change will also shift. Contemporary art biennials are producers of social change not because they are the best placed to understand or respond to the social implications of artistic activity, nor because they have the most financial resources, nor because they are the most literate audiences, nor because they are the most creative or socially engaged groups. Rather, the capacity of a biennial to generate social change depends on a number of interacting factors, some of which are more readily identified and addressed in a museum context while others are much harder to quantify and contextualize. The key to a biennial's potential is a multifaceted, interdependent set of factors that are not easily identified or quantify. The biennial itself is a capital-intensive enterprise that engages with the social and cultural dimensions of art in a way that is largely invisible or under-studied in the arts context. Art biennials are much more readily identified and addressed in museums and for</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is clear that the capacity of the art biennial to support socially engaged and environmentally conscious art projects is increasingly constrained. ‘Cultural production in the age of unlimited media is producing its own limits.’. Art biennials are typically started and co-championed by artists, whose work is typically commissioned and held in high regard by the biennials. The biennial form then becomes an instrument for supporting the artist’s purposes, rather than its own ends. There is a tension between the needs of the public and the endowments of art institutions, between the public and the arts, and between the public and the biennial. But while the public is expected to ‘pay what it takes’ to access a specific art resource, the biennial form actively exploits its public for private gain. The biennial, as a purchase at a premium price point, actively recruits a specific public’s resources by offering them at a discount price point in exchange for a</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is clear that the capacity of curators and arts administrators everywhere to allocate the art resources necessary for progressive social change is eroding.Although the capacities of art administrators and artists to demand change are few and constrained, there are signs that the social impact of biennials is becoming more and more evident across the board. The ability of artists and curators to demand a change in a museum or a board of trustees is evident in the increase in the fees charged by biennials, and in the increasing privatisation of cultural resources by art administrators. In general, the accessibility, accessibility to resources and affordability of cultural resources is becoming increasingly important to the survival of artistic productivity. And although the social impacts of art increasing in market value are slight, the logic of increased market value and the consequent pressures of austerity are becoming increasingly evident. It is clear that the economics of culture are no longer produced on the back of the labour force; nor are the social impacts of a biennial necessarily the work of artists and</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is evident that the culture industries are forced to confront new economic realities. And while the capacity of contemporary art biennials to support these shifts is uncertain, there is some evidence that suggests that the social and political contexts in which art is produced could also shift in the future. That is to say, museums and galleries might become increasingly exposed to the artworks they display, and might become less invested in the art being produced within them. This is the dynamic in action today: the biennial market is saturated with art being produced outside the organisationality of the art world, but it is art being produced, and therefore art being bought, for the first time in history. The biennial is also producing artists who are not necessarily members of the art world, and artists who are not necessarily committed to the progressive social change or progressive cultural utilisation of art. A good number of them are creating art and turning it into organisations that are not necessarily associated with a specific art museum or gallery, or gallery, or</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is clear that the capacity of art biennials to impact the cultural destinies of their respective cities is waning.The biennial has a habit of returning, whether we are talking about Venice or Belfast or any number of other sites around the globe. And although the biennial has a habit of returning, it is important to note that this return is almost always accompanied by an accompanying speculative, utopian or just plain weird new urban development project. New art biennials are often prompted by a combination of factors, including the financial, artistic and curatorial demands of the trade, the proliferation of art collections and the public spiral of biennial valuations. But in the main, it is the needs of the city in which they take place that compel the biennial to exist. And although the biennial may or may not produce new art or architecture, it is increasingly common for biennials to produce new ways of organising cultural life through the production of goods and services, both internally and externally. It</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is clear that the capacity of biennials to do social good is also shifting. Within the contemporary art biennial, the capacity to produce wealth is clearly seen as a pre-requisite for both the biennial itself and for the development of the artworld itself.  Whether the redevelopment of neighbourhoods and the construction of alternative economic development around art resources is truly the work of local grassroots organisations is questionable, to say the least. But the biennial itself and their development as a cultural form in postindustrial areas seems to be the work of professional curators with a clear agenda. And these plans are being put into effect in earnest, whether we are talking about the designs for a new art school in a local area or whether we are considering the redevelopment of an old city centre municipal hall. The reason for this concentration of resources is simple: the resources fuelling the art biennial industry come from across the board, whereas the city provides the organisational capacity and the institutional drive that a grassroots movement can build upon</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is evident that the capacity of the biennial to infuse social change with art resources expands accordingly.  And this is to the extent that the art is produced in ways that are directly responsive to the desires and interests of the art consumers (and traders) of the world.  Art has always been a complicated and variable commodity in relation to its real use-value, and the biennial is no exception. It is true that the value of an art biennial is generally inversely proportional to its value as a tourist attraction. And this is true whether the art is contemporary, contemporary art, or art from a different era.  But the greater the impact of a biennial, the less people want to come to the places where it is produced. And this is why biennials tend to produce more material forms of art, which in turn tend to produce a larger impact.  And this is another reason why in the age of the biennial, museums are the primary creators of the art that</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone, who is constrained by the pace of development and constrained by the needs of the times. Indeed, the capacity of a contemporary art biennial to perceive and respond to changes in its environment is in part constrained by the financial infrastructures of contemporary art and the museums they render. As biennials become more and more external to the cultural centres where their art is displayed, and the cultural sectors shift from being the primary users of art resources to being users of art resources (museums and galleries alike), the limits and constraints on the capacities of the biennial to project cultural change become ever more apparent. And while the capacity of a biennial to project its artworks into social change is an ongoing and pressing issue for artists and curators everywhere, it is evident that the demand for social change in the art world as a result of the massive amounts of art being produced in Britain and throughout the world is growing. As the biennial market shifts from art resources to cultural resources, it is important that artists, artists and art institutions remain aware of this change and react accordingly.  As a general rule, the capacity of a biennial to produce large amounts of artworks in response to current social needs and the desires of the public is limited.  Art biennials are typically associated with the excesses of capitalism, but in recent years they have largely self-published, choosing to make works available for viewing on a regular basis via their websites and festivals.  They have also developed a habit of showing new works, which they describe as ‘aural topology’ and ‘the sum of all the patterns we have produced thus far.’  Art biennials have a particular capacity to produce artworks that are not bound by the traditional artist-centred production models. In this sense, they are able to ‘repurpose’ or reuse existing artworks, to ‘repurpose the patterns we have produced thus far’ and to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist simultaneously. This temporal resolution has always been a contested and variable proposition, and while there are indications that it will continue to be contested, it is also becoming increasingly clear that it will never again be equal in magnitude to the impact of the impact of the Biennale in its territory and time. 	In the event that the Biennale is moved from its current location in LAX to other international airports or other locations, the temporal resolution between the present and the past may be affected. If, for example, the Biennale is relocated to Burbank Airport in Burbank, California, then the impact of the project in the city will be affected and art, literature, and other cultural assets will be relocated there as well. Like other temporal resolutions, this one is a ‘fixing act’ that is ultimately in doubt. 	In my estimation, the possibilities of how art, literature, and other cultural assets may be transferred between jurisdictions, and even within jurisdictions, are</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist simultaneously. This temporal distinction between past and future is one that artists, writers and thinkers throughout history have made a kind of pilgrimage to understand. It is a mode of existence that is contemporaneous with and independent of human history, but it is also ‘a kind of time’. And this kind of ‘time’ is what the Biennale is trying to figure out. 	[1] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, translated by Stephen Leacock and Anders Sandberg, trans. Stefan Collini and Ray Dalio, Viking, NY, 1991, p.7.  [2] Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, p.7.  [3] Richter and Singer, Mechanical Animates Culture, p.6.  [4] Saltzman,  	Cognitive Dissonance: How Random Access Computer Programming May Undermine the Authenticity of Lists, Social Work,</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist simultaneously. Time travel is the hypothetical act of coming back to the past, or back to an imagined past, in order to affect the future. In the new scientific definition of ‘the past’, ‘the present’ is defined as the sequence of past, present and future events. In other words, the act of coming back to the past is what defines the present; coming back to the future is what defines the future.’[8] This definition is a sharp break from the traditional distinction between the past and the future, between static and emergent. The concept of the past is often used to reflect on the effects of industrialisation; in the context of a biennale, we often imagine the past in the form of a curatorial gesture. But the past is not always depicted in such a way as to make us question the capacity of contemporary art to engage with issues of power and control. The history of architecture, landscape architecture and urbanisation in the</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist simultaneously. This temporal resolution is precisely what Breivik claimed to want.[7] 	However, this kind of ‘time travel’ is not hypothetical, and it is certainly not easy to pull off. The physical location of the destroyed cities and abandoned islands is extremely distressing: Hiroshima, which is a city of over six million people, is replicated in the abandoned Marshall Islands, which are also physically separated from each other by the sea. The massive oil spills into the Pacific, along with the continent-wide phenomenon known as global oceanic circulation ‘blowfish’ that drives oceanic tides mean that large areas of the ocean are now desalinated and salinity is an issue. 	Furthermore, as the balance of oil is disrupted, other forms of energy are affected: the depletion of fish stocks and the expansion of desertification threaten coastal communities. The relocation of these populations is predicted to result in the expansion of these cities, which in turn will increase sea-level</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist simultaneously. This temporal resolution is very reminiscent of Michel Foucalt’s notion of parallel worlds (spaces where social interaction takes place) and society in ‘different worlds’. However, it is important to note that this interpenetration does not take place in the conceptual sense of how we conceptualise things, but in the practical sense of how we actually live and interact with the world. For example, the art projects that were part of the LAX ‘culture of the present’ were not art in the traditional sense, but were ‘intermittent art projects’ that functioned as though they were contemporary, even though they were not. 	While the Biennale had a specific mission statement, which set out what it meant to be ‘French’ in the 21st century, its form and content also differed from country to country. In general, the mission of the biennale was defined more by the desires and needs of</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist simultaneously.’ In other words, the temporal resolution of the Biennale is not a kind of museum holding objects in the past but a kind of museum presenting the future. It is a museum of transition, of change, of encounter and encounter again. 	[1] See Cristian Maldacena, Timur's Rebellion (New York: Stages, 2016), p. 10.Download this article as PDFTimur Deena Cengage Learning through Participatory Practices, Part 2 	Timur Deena Cengage Learning through Participatory Practices, Part 2 Transitioning from Subversion to Participatory Practices in Interdisciplinary Art and Design: A Conversation with Timur Deena, Pablo Larrañaga, and Álbio Nascimento Diane Rodrique [2] Svetlana Boym: &quot;Technologies of Community&quot; in (ed.), Participatory Culture: Art, Economy, and Transactional Behaviour, pp</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist simultaneously. This temporal resolution is a kind of meta-narrative that simultaneously looks backward and forwards in a continuous narrative – essentially, it is ‘a half-way house’. It is a narrative that begins with the past but ends with the present, although it is oriented in a transnational sense. It extends to Antarctica and beyond, but it also narrates the direct descendant of the interactions between humans and the natural world (the human species).‘Time travel’ is a type of ‘ambiguous space’. But here, too, the spatial limit is that which we create, rather than that which is given. The artist Carl DeMaio calls this ‘ambiguous realisation’. Here, too, the ambiguity created by our own actions – actions that we cannot see or do not know how to do – creates what DeLong refers to as ‘ambiguous reality’. Since the ambiguities created by our own actions are</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist simultaneously. This temporal distinction between past and future is one that artists, including myself, are still grappling with.I also found the idea of ‘biennial’ somewhat abstract and non-political. Whereas the biennial is an institution that actively creates visual spectacle through its visual tools – exhibits, competitions, festivals – the biennial is far less actively engaged with its actual visual spectacle. Its exhibitions, competitions, festivals and even programmes of activities are political in character because they are political in their form. In their intent to capture the concrete and concrete effects of the biennial, some biennials actively target particular museums or specific art institutions. These ‘museums of the spectacle’ are political in character because they deliberately create visual spectacles that are not visible to the public. The museum is the visible site of the spectacle, and the ‘public’ is made up of artists, curators, art writers, art’s policy wonks, collectors and various other</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist simultaneously. This temporal resolution allows ‘art’ to move into the future, or the present, or both, while simultaneously engaging with the present and intervening into the future. This temporal resolution is very interesting and can be seen as a kind of ‘contemporary’ or ‘temporal’ modernism. There is a new temporal sensibility emerging, one that seeks to intervene into the temporal conditions of the here and now, to intervene in the space and time of the present, but also to intervene into the space and time of the past, but also to intervene into the space and time of future.  The temporal resolution that emerges from these new forms of artistic, artistic-political and cultural intervention is a return to the origins of art and culture. It seeks to understand, though, not how art was made, but how art is made now by artists who are artists in their own right, who have careers and identities and sometimes have families who are artists as well.</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has again been rescheduled to coincide with the new exhibition cycle. This time it is being shown in two parts: part at the newly renovated and partly restored Art space of LAX and the partially restored and occupied LAX international terminal. While the original plan to show part of the project in LAX was shelved, the new iteration is now showing the whole project, in chronological order from the beginning to the present. This temporal resolution, which I found particularly interesting, was that the artists involved with the project were given equal time and space in which to work. For example, whereas in chronological order from the beginning to the present the Biennale was able to identify each and every project that it was involved with, the new chronological order suggests a kind of organic interpenetration. Rather than the strict formal distinction between the past and the future inherent in linear time, we can say that ‘time travel’ is a mode of existence in which the past and the future both exist simultaneously. This temporal resolution is very different from the strict distinction between past and future that is often made between art and the arts. For example, when looking at art today, many artists actually propagate the concept of past and future, rather than trying to articulate the temporal condition on which art depends. Art today is more like a curatorial appointment, and the curatorial decision to engage with the past, rather than trying to imagine or create an entirely new temporal resolution, is a decision that artists and curators alike take for granted. When looking at art from the past, we can choose to project the past, rather than attempting to articulate temporal conditions on which art depends. This is one reason why the biennial can be seen as an episodic, temporally variable art project. Rather than trying to articulate the strict notion of linear time, the biennial can be seen as a point in a space-time continuum, in and through a particular historical period. During the event, the curator or artist</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It 
    <text>The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It is a strange place, full of developers and cafés who want to turn the district into a multi-purpose venue for exhibition and conference distribution. It is a strange place, full of banks and financial institutions, and their narratives of business, commerce, and commerce’s many forms. It is a strange place, full of chain restaurants and burger joints, and their narratives of business, commerce, and commerce’s many forms of eating. It is a strange place, full of stadiums and basketball arenas, and their grandstands, and the surrounding streets, and the houses that are bought and sold inside them, and the houses that are rented out and developed outside of it. It is a strange place, full of museums and and academia, and their collections, and their exhibitions, and their collections, and their exhibitions of things, and their collections of things, and their collections of encounters, and their collections of artefacts, and</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It also happens to be a hotspot for anti-social activity: squatting, jailing, robberies, drug dealing, fights between residents and the police, and of course, the Basel Four’s 1989 suicide bombing. Despite this history, the area is a fertile ground for new ideas to germinate.  	The Central Business District is a wonderful memorial to this history. It brings to mind the wordplay of W. E. B. Du Bois and Auguste Rodin’s Theodor Adorno Report – a manifesto of ideas that would reshape contemporary culture and the world. It also begs the question: what can the future portend for the Central Business District? 	In  	Postmodern Culture and Postindustrial Society (1974), W. E. B. Du Bois and Paulo Freire offer a wager, or perhaps a claim, as to</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It also happens to be a core site for the alleged rape and murder of several community members, including an elderly woman. 	The Arsenale is a strange place, full of art collectors and a producer of luxury goods, but it is also a centre of a host of illegal activities, including the possession of possession. It also happens to be a centre of trans-indochina tensions, with recently arrived Chinese citizens, who claim to be the descendants of slaves, occupying chosen spots in the building. 	The Central Business District has and will always be a strange place, full of accusations and counter-accusations. But over time, the Central Business District has become something recognisably different from the peripheries. 	The Arsenale has become a destination for international visitors and a symbol of the economic miracle. It still hands out mill</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It also happens to be one of the most dangerous places in the city: the Arsenale is a target of frequent terrorist attacks, and Ponte City Hall is a target of a corruption scandal that threatens to unravel its walls.  	However, the development could go either way. The neighbourhood has been in constant crisis since at least 2007, when a small-scale, but persistent, Albanian gang known as the Cronje imposed their will on the local population. Albanian gangs comprised around 2,000 men, dedicated to extorting money from businesses and individuals in order to fund their operations. They established an aggressive monopoly on crime in the area, operating under the alias ‘Caucasian Gangstas’. The Caucasian Gangstas included prominent Albanian musicians, film-makers, theatre heads and printmakers, as well as members of the national band Arsenale. The name changed hands multiple times, but</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It also happens to be a core location for the Mega, the largest and most destructive phase of the Project Venetian complex. The area is a tangled web of government commissions, local authorities, businesses, cultures of dependency and homelessness. Yet despite its strangeness, this neighbourhood has a significant cultural impact on the wider Venice region. Artist-centred projects here have an impact that is greater than that which is generated by artist-led initiatives elsewhere. 	The Central Business District commissioning process is a truly global phenomenon. It has taken place in Oslo, Shanghai, Kolkata, Sydney and Kampala. It is a global phenomenon because it is spread across so many different jurisdictions, but especially relevant for artists here is the fact that the area has been designated as ⟨Asia Pacific Hub⟩, a designation that resonates with the brand of art, theatre, craft and associated cultural activity that is attracting artists from</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It isn’t surprising, considering how the Central Business District is a major hub for the production of real estate in the region: Venezia, Napoli, Milan and now, Venice. The neighbourhood of La Cosa in particular is a producer of vacant buildings and vacant lots. The acquisition of the C-shaped, five-storey residenty at La Cosa dell’Arsenale from the city council in 2014 is a great example of how the city can accomplish a reclamation of space. The creation of a Community Land Trust for the area (which would hold the development rights and allow the city to reclaim some of the developing pace) was a natural extension of these rights, since the C-shaped home is a very important component of the renovation process. The Community Land Trust would become</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It is a weird place too, full of homeless people, those who call themselves ‘Community Land Trustees’ but really just want to kick back and have a good time. The Central Business District is a mix of many different kinds of ownership, and as such it has its own peculiar ownership rules and regulations. There is a clear difference between the Central Business District and the peripheries, since the former are restricted to a specific kind of urbanisation while the latter are open to any kind of urbanisation. Yet even when these distinctions are made, they still require negotiation.  	The Central Business District is a fractured collection of interests and cultures, so its use is mostly discretionary. The decision to spend a great deal of time in the district is a collective one, and although it may not be popular, it is collective and collective decision making rules that each neighbourhood organisation has to execute in order to maximise their own benefit.  	In order to maxim</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It also happens to be a notorious drug market. 	The Arsenale is a massive warehouse complex with a lot of characterised by the glut of goods moving through the complex. It houses the Arsenale choreography department, where works are performed in stages around the facility, with a public realm incorporating a number of public art installations and public sculpture. It houses the Encore Theatre, where works taken out of the building during renovation are mounted on podium like Christmas carols. It houses the Kompakt Gallery, a gallery dedicated to the Ukrainian neoclassical style of architecture, featuring works in both Ukrainian and Russian origin. It houses the Ukrainian community Arsenale staff, students, and community residents at large, many of whom are artists themselves. It houses the Italian Institute of Contemporary Arts, led by Paolo Portoghesi. It houses the United National Exhibition team led</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It also happens to be a core site for the Satanic ritual Capitol of the Unborn, where infant Sinistra is said to have been born. Capitol of the Unborn is where Capricorn is said to have been born, where the Sun appears in the form of a gigantic satyr, and where the whole city is said to have been founded. 	The city is now a sprawling, disused combination of offices and retail, with a high vacancy rate (according to an estimate by J.D. Dewsbury in his influential book The City in Crisis, published in 1972). The Central Business District is a prime candidate for the demolition, as is Venice, but these areas are by now becoming increasingly diversified and transient, and art is still the number one tourist draw. It is already said that the Central Business District is the birthplace of vernacular urbanism, with an influence that extends well beyond</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the rich legacy of collaborative effort that was once shared across many cultural sectors. The aims are to acquire land through the acquisition of a cultural property, to jointly-produce a cultural/heritage product line, and to collaborate in the creation and operation of an arts/cultural centre. The project is mock-built on previous efforts that were already creative, innovative and creative in their own right. The new project is built on the ideas and strategies of the past efforts, but with a cultural touch of the present. 	This project is a service to the community in the Central Business District and the Arsenale in Venice, where it will offer a new perspective on an area that exists in a constant state of flux. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of artists and producers who flock there to lay claim to the most valuable real estate in the city. It is a weird place to work, full of workstations and cubicles and offices that are reserved for those with a particular set of skills. 	The Central Business District is a strange place, full of  	people with a collective need to know more about the area than the average Joe or Jane can handle. It is a strange place to live, full of  	affordable houses that are easy to buy but difficult to tear down and a bizarre mix of public art installations and house-specific projects that cater to the needs of the very rich and the very poor. It is a strange place to work, full of  	people who think they know everything there is to know about the area, but are mostly wrong. It is a strange place to play, full of  	people who think they know everything there is to know about the area but are mostly too busy cutting throats in the conflict zones to do</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the twenty-first century is a global phenomenon also remains unclear. There is a tendency to undervalue the importance of the arts and culture in developing nations, and this tendency may be partly due to the influence of cultural tourism agencies such as Tate Britain and Getty Images, which promote cultural tourism and ‘re-imagining art’ in the form of travel campaigns. It is also likely that the globalised modern economic model of the ‘utopia’ envisioned by many artists and curators is deeply indebted to the art industry in developing nations, whose economies were largely self-sufficient prior to the advent of the industry. Therefore, it is easy to understand the desire to see an art centre or an art school in poor areas, or to see an arts programme in urban areas, such as in Liverpool, where art is still a scarce commodity but is becoming increasingly so. It is also possible that the power of the arts today resides in places where the economic logic of the ‘utopia�</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the twenty-first century is made up of data represents another limitation of the space of the art-computer interface: it is not possible to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual map.  The figure of the artist thus appears on the screen, monitor and suchlike, but the task of the curatorial admin is to create spaces that enable the user to progress through the series of images, not to map such lives onto the conceptual map. How such spaces are designed may be used to intervene between our human imaginations and the real world, intervening between the virtual and the real, allowing the imagination to run wild, creating what Andy Warhol and others had dubbed ‘ideas without subjects’.  The figure of the artist thus appears on the screen, monitor and suchlike, but the task of the curatorial admin is to create spaces that enable the user to progress through the series of images, not to map such lives onto the conceptual map. How such spaces are designed</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the twenty-first century is made up of individuals rather than intranational corporate entities such as museums, galleries or zoos, and that many museums and zoos now exist in cities where small art galleries once stood, only deep pockets are left standing, and this is a reflection of the decline of many cities as centres of art production, consumption and so on. Indeed, zoos and cultural centres are often characterised by their excess, their surplus, as evidenced by the abundance of animals now slaughtered for their ivory, rhino horn and tusks in urban centres. In these images, the animals once housed in these institutions are visible only as props in a narrative that is unfolding much faster than the capacity of the museum or the gallery to house them. 	[2] See Peter Osborne, The Crisis of Art (New York: New Vessel Press, 2016), Chapter 3, pp.8–13.Download this article as PDFPeter OsbornePeter Osborne is Professor in the Department of Communication Studies</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the twenty-first century is a ‘megastructure’ suggests that changes in this framework may occur at multiple scales, involving both the urban and the rural components. In my opinion, this is the predominant spatial and temporal condition in the developed world today. It is true that in certain cases (e.g. financial markets) this merging of different parts may be desirable, but in many cases (e.g. urban planning) it is not. As a result, the twenty-first century may well be a ‘world without boundaries’. The division between urban and rural may be seen as a product of historical colonialism and neo-colonialism, and the pathological consequence of numerous infrastructures and postcolonial governance. It is pertinent to reiterate that distinction for our purposes. In many cities in the developed world, such as New York and London, large governmental infrastructures are the dominant forms of organisation, as is evident in the huge financial infrastructures that</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the twenty-first century is almost entirely online is a surprising development, not least because it occurs at such a distance from the artists' studios and galleries of the past, where artists must constantly reapply their exhibitionary strategies in response to new audiences. Nevertheless, the fact that the modern art market is driven by social media and not by the actual commercial market, and that contemporary art is also influenced by the appearance of social media, is a development that some have argued is essential for the survival of contemporary art.1 So, contemporary art is often thought to be intimately connected to social media, but this is not always the case.  The example of Liverpool Biennial 2016 is an extreme case in point. Biennials in the past have typically been historical works, or at least studies of a historical form: Frankfurt, New York, Istanbul. Biennials of the present (and future) are more often works in progress, often ‘reconstituting forms of art’ that have been</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the twenty-first century is being built on an image of the art market that is itself increasingly displaced (along with many other cultural forms) is another factor influencing how art is produced and consumed.  A very real and very current aspect of this new avatar of the art market, and of course the social totality, is the fact that many of the artists who exhibit their work in the art world at present are employed by or work for the museum, and so are exposed to exhibitions and festivals that are also designed to placate the art collector’s bureaus and dealers. So the museum is often seen as an essential component of the contemporary art world, and the biennial as an essential component of the art world.  The museum may be an idealised construct, but its memory is as much a fiction as its physical manifestation. It is a fiction with an elaborate and dynamic internal logic, that reproduces itself through a seemingly infinite number of parallel worlds, yet it is also a fiction with</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the twenty-first century is a ‘cultural city’, where contemporary art is regularly made to cater to cultural tastes and interests, where contemporary art is often made in response to cultural tastes and interests and where art is often made in reaction to the curatorial turn, which is common to both present and historical curatorial approaches, suggests that art today often engages with values and practices that are not confined to the sites of their production, but can also be understood as the result of social and political changes that are happening all around the world. This notion of the cultural city is very new, and so it is easy to get lost in the shuffle of changes, but the important point is that the new forms of organisation around art and art today are at the root of much of what goes on in the world of art and culture. If we take the example of Liverpool, which is building a new museum and arts centre that will be ‘world famous’ among artists and curated by renowned artists,</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the twenty-first century is made up of individuals or small cliques is a global phenomenon, with local roots but also global implications. It may be that the organising principle of the twenty-first century is the same as that of the nineteenth century, but the form and the processes underlying contemporary cultural change are qualitatively different and hence the over-all outcomes are necessarily open to question. In either case, the question is: what is the contemporary equivalent of what the twentieth century's artworld was like? The answer may be: a ‘city-state’. But even if this is the case, what does it mean to call a place ‘the artworld’? Where does the reference point for art and contemporary culture be located? What does it mean to be ‘in the contemporary art world’? Where does the contemporary art world reside? What does it mean to be ‘in the contemporary arts’? These are questions that are intermingling and,</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the twenty-first century is made up of individuals or small groups of individuals is also a factor that contributes to the contemporary artworld's transient character – the artworld of the twenty-first century is the greatest of these because of the increase in individual and small group size, the proliferation of venues and so on. Contemporary art experiences a kind of collective amnesia, in the sense that it is not possible for artists or the public of the artworld to ‘remember’ the ways in which the artworld of the twentieth century was made. This kind of amnesia is common in the arts and creative professions; it is much more common in the arts education sector. But the amnesia that characterises ‘the contemporary art world’ is significantly different from that of the nineteenth century; it is ‘pre-existing’ and has a tendency to proliferate. Like the amnesia of the artists and the postcolonial/intersectionality project, this pre-existing ‘art</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. The capacity of a local artist to craft a roughly chronological narrative of a particular place, time, or place, based on historical, economic, or political forces, based on current cultural trends or on the general will of the community, is significantly limited. It is also significantly limited in its relation to contemporary art practices and social formations. It is not possible to imagine a city or a regionally significant area or local artworld such as Liverpool Biennial, which is geographically contemporaneous with Liverpool but differs from Liverpool in its organisational practices, cultural dynamics, social organisation and so on. Art is made in conditions of continual change, and so it is with the ‘artworld’. It may be that the organising principle that characterises the artworld of the twenty-first century is similar to that of the nineteenth or even of the twentieth century, but it is entirely unclear how to map contemporary art life and social formations onto this existing conceptual framework. The fact that the artworld of the twenty-first century is being increasingly automated in its processes of production, distribution, marketing, public activities and so forth, means that art’s existing infrastructure is largely replaced by networks of self-organising entities, which are, in turn, replaced by data. And so we can return to Rothko’s second conceit, that machines are but modernisers of human creativity: machines that understand and are replaceable by human creativity. This is an understandable conceit on the one hand, and deeply problematic on the other. The problem with the machine is not necessarily a creative capacity, but a capacity to learn. The problem with the machine is not necessarily a capacity for artistic perforations, but a capacity for repetitive behaviour. The problem with the machine is, as we all know, often worse. Even if the creators of the machine could somehow be endowed with a creative spark, a twinge of genius, a twinkle of insight, a twinkle of twinkle in their</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
