<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a
    <text>future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a metropolis as is evident in the case of Anfield, as ever-rising house prices and a growing tax-free shopping zone around the stadium are the favoured mode of consumption for a city that desperately needs to feed its growing population. But what has emerged as a ‘postindustrial form’ is the preferred mode of consumption for a city that desperately needs to heal its wounds. It is this assumption about the inevitability of postindustrial forms of consumption despite the impacts of climate change that needs to be challenged. The challenge to this kind of industrial capitalism will need to confront a city with a robust postindustrial strategy, coupled with a massive programme of affordable housing and social housing, as well as a massive programme of green jobs and green spaces. The task will be made easier by the emergence of a biennale that is increasingly able to tap into enormous followings on social media, such as when the Liverpool Biennial launches a new engagement programme with Liverpool College of Art and Design, inviting</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a densely populated area, and a clear-cut cut advantage for any given position in the socio-economic hierarchy. The proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be beneficial to a city’s economy in the short term, but in the long term it is likely to result in a reduction in access to water, greenery and other resources that are essential for the common good. The long-term effects of such rampant parking are likely to be disastrous. A 2010 review of over a dozen studies of the effects of parking on cities and suburbs concluded that such policies were not only unwise but also expensive. A recent study by the International Accounting Standards Committee (IASC), a self-selected panel of professional auditors appointed to assess the financial viability of initiatives to promote environmentally beneficial practices in a city, concluded that the environmental benefits of a given project were less likely to come from projects in densely populated areas controlled by large corporations, for-profit real-estate developers or non-profit organisations, or</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a metropolis, so any policy that attempts to make access to it more convenient or attractive has a purpose beyond satisfying commercial incentives. Developers who reap the financial rewards of a postcode lottery are likely to promote access to the ‘common good’ in ways that are at odds with the values of the city in order to boost property values and satisfy investors. Developers who reap the technological benefits of city ‘cloud services’ are likely to put them to good use, but if the common good is to be protected, then the common good has to be kept in the city. The postindustrial city is likely to become something like a gigantic data centre, where research and development take place despite the city’s infrastructures being slow to respond to rapid technological change. New ‘smart cities’ will likely be built despite-the-city being a place where protests and activism over economic development are common. As the internet of things becomes more pervasive</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a metropolis, so custodianship becomes an increasingly precarious proposition. Parking garages are rare in Liverpool, but the advent of automated parking makes it common for cars to park autonomously in both commercial and residential garages. In these systems, the parking attendant becomes a self-contained object with inherent mobility, but custodianship is also given up in favour of a function of sharing and mapping value. Automated parking reduces the need for drivers to be present in areas around stadiums, highways and rail lines, and thus frees up valuable urban space.“ The autonomous parking of cars for commercial and residential purposes may increase accessibility to places, but it does so in the context of a socio-politically-infringing circular economy centred on the accumulation of parking. This is the ‘critical mass point’ where the sharing of parking places becomes politically-infringing, and the sharing of cars becomes socially undesirable. Crucially, the sharing of parking places is not a</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a city with high levels of car use, yet it is a fundamental building block of the metropolis. It is now commonplace for football fans to park in dedicated lots along the football fields, yet this is still an issue in Anfield, even though the stadium is fully urbanized. Parking is still an issue for tourists in Anfield, but the city is now becoming increasingly transit dependent, and terminals like Toxteth have sprung up all over the city, providing rapid transit between terminals located in the mega malls around the stadium. All these terminal developments have their own parking challenges to be overcome, but they are also competing for business with a rapidly urbanizing downtown and rapidly developing suburbs. It is true that in areas around the stadium, the abundance of cheap housing and quick access to mass transit has put a damper on industrial development, but this is still characteristic of postindustrial cities. The postindustrial future is predicted to bring about a variety of changes in the city, yet it is expected that these ‘norm</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a city as valuable as Liverpool, and a new understanding of what is at stake in the value of such scarce resources is needed if a city is to maintain the social qualities of its urban landscape. Importantly, the postindustrial city is expected to respond to this new ‘value-added’ form of production arising in its vicinity. Consider, for example, the highly visible ‘value-producing’ aspect of developments that have been spurred on by the financial services industry. Such developments, by giving shape to future growth through what is commonly called the ‘housing crunch’, are expected to generate new ways of valuing assets and of organising consumption. Developments in the City that are not driven by the logic of capital accumulation will be challenged by developments driven by ideas of sharing and public goods, and will have to respond with creative forms of regulation and policy change to accommodate the new modes of labour and wealth formation generated by the new values. 	The post</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a postindustrial city, and a scarce resource at that. It is extremely expensive to park in a city, and as a consequence postindustrial areas are heavily reliant on public funding to pay for essential services. A city that provides essential services without relying on private funding will have a kind of  cash flow.  	Another form of ‘value-producing capacity’ that is increasingly evident in the city is the development of ‘collaborative infrastructure’ that supports the common good without the common good needing to rely on a particular development. 	Examples of collaborative ‘infrastructure’ include the Liverpool Biennial, which is partly funded by the city and ‘partially’ funded by the Biennial, and funded in part by the Biennial. The Biennial is a multi-award-winning, multi-format arts organization with a long-standing partnership with the city, and is currently developing a new generation of artists’ destinations in East Liverpool. The</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a metropolis like Liverpool, and so the future city will have to find other uses for its valuable resource. Parking is a scarce resource in a metropolis like Liverpool, and so the postcourses will have to find other uses for the spaces that they will need to live in.  Given the current level of urbanisation in Liverpool, this will mean finding other uses for the infrastructure that is slowly but inexorably becoming privatised. It may also mean finding other uses for the infrastructures that are slowly but inexorably becoming hybrid, or ‘regeneration’.  Given the current level of urbanisation in Liverpool, this will mean finding other uses for the artefacts and cultural assets that are increasingly common in postindustrial cities: the art collections, the postcard collections, the videos, the used car lots and the postcards. It may also mean finding other uses for the infrastructures that are increasingly rare in postindustrial cities: the</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a city that likes to claim that it produces ‘social value’ through its abundant ‘space’. The proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a city that likes to claim that it produces ‘social value’ through its abundant ‘space’. Parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to spread outward into ever-shifting variably surveilled ‘regions’ then parking must be controlled. Parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to expand outward into ever-shifting variably surveilled ‘regions’ then parking must be controlled. Parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which are especially relevant in a city like Liverpool’s, where the urban landscape is increasingly fragmented into zones held together with infrastructure and public works. Such ‘postindustrial cities’ are the site of the coming ‘postcourses’, as the theorists like to call them. Such cities are expected to support a variety of different ways of inhabiting uses-value, as distinct from merely the re-constituting of existing uses-values. Urban forms that support postcourses will also support the development of autonomous modes of self-expression and possibly even ‘social forms’ that are not bound up in rigid notions of development. For example, the proliferation of parking lots around stadiums may be desirable for the common good, but if the common good is to remain confined to a specific geographical area, then controlling parking and encouraging parking can only happen in jurisdictions with a clear understanding of the value of disabled access. Parking is a scarce resource in a city with ever-greater amounts of wealth and social mobility, which is why it is so desperately needed in the developed world. Similarly, the growth of the internet and social media is a scarce resource, but understanding of the values and social implications of this massive growth are urgently needed in developing nations. As a result, understanding of the ‘performativity of space’ is crucial in any serious attempt to conceive of alternative urban forms. As the legendary Italian urbanist Maurizio Lazzarato put it, when asked what became of the buildings that he labelled the Calabrese Plan: ‘the city had its buildings.’ The Calabrese Plan, as it came to be known, proposed a number of radical radical changes to the city, which included the demolition of almost all existing building forms and replacing them with a series of radical new urban forms. In the wake of these radical changes, a new urban matrix was designed and planned with a new set</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a
    <text>curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a tribute to the outlaw’s armour and to the fact that John the Black Cat was black, as was his colour. [6] A Short History of the Bluecoat, by Ruth Rendon-Tippet, published in 1920, p. 17. [7] A Short History of the Bluecoat, by Ruth Rendon-Tippet, published in 1920, p. 18. [8] A Short History of the Bluecoat, by Ruth Rendon-Tippet, published in 1920, p. 19. [9] A Short History of the Bluecoat, by Ruth Rendon-Tippet, published in 1920, p. 20. [10] A Short History of the Bluecoat, by Ruth Rendon-Tippet, published in 1920, p. 21. [11] A Short History of the Bluecoat, by Ruth Rendon-Tippet, published in 1978, p. 33.</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a challenge to a wizard named Derek Boley, who was said to have invented a name that sounded like the word backwards – a name that became synonymous with hard labour and black magic. In  	The Wizard of Oz, Dorothy Brown includes the name in a list of cursed muggles. The cursed muggle Harry L. Buckland is said to have suggested the name to Brown on the suggestion of his wife, who was visiting from Australia. Brown reportedly replied that he ‘knew enough muggles to know the difference’ between a wizard and a muggle, and ‘so what’s the trouble with naming muggles after black magic?’, to no avail.   [6] A quick perusal of the Word on the Street website turns up several spellings of ‘Bluecoat’ in publications at the time, but the most popular one is ­Bluecoat and Copper. The surname is rendered as ‘Bluecoat</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a fable to a king by a clan of outlaws in 1492, a legend which was repeated several times throughout the medieval and early modern period in connection with King John the Black. A medieval folk tale attributed to the Black Cat and his outlaws is a good example of a mythologised name – a quality that has been retained in modern forms of the name in connection with the Middle Ages.  [6] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a fable to a king by a clan of outlaws in 1492, a legend which was repeated several times throughout the medieval and early modern period in connection with King John the Black. A medieval folk tale attributed to the Black Cat and his outlaws is a good example of a mythologised name – a quality that has been retained in modern forms of the name in connection with the Middle</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a challenge to a wizard named ‘Baffled Wizard’ in a nearby pub.  [6] William Blake, Blake Companion, William Blake, London and New York, 1844, p.  1. [7] A collection of quotations is available at http://www.katydidact.net/. [8] A collection of quotations is available at http://www.katydidact.net/kurtbeil (accessed April 2018). [9] William Blake, Blake Companion, William Blake, London and New York, 1844, p.  2. [10] A collection of quotations is available at http://www.katydidact.net/marcellus/Blake_308.htm#ixzz2KDE5Ly8nE#... (accessed April 2018). [11] A collection of quotations is available at http://www.katydidact.net/marcell</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a challenge to William Blake by a group of Welsh Street children. The tale is said to be a refutation of the ‘black dog’ that Blake had created, and which his grandfather had once branded a ‘fugitive bird’. William Blake, A Spring of Spring Trees, William Blake, 1887, p. 42. [6] A quick look online reveals that ‘Bluecoat’ is the name of a series of articles in the Daily Graphic on the front page of March 1906. The name is also the name of a theatre company established in 1850 by the Act of Settlement of 1867, and its director was William Blake.  [7] A quick look online reveals that ‘Bluecoat’ was the name of a series of paintings on the wall of the Chisenhale Style Store in Barking, where William Blake kept a collection of British art. A collection of the kind of art that a young William Blake would have</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a challenge to William Blake by a Welshlander named John Llewellyn Lloyd. In turn, Blake reportedly replied with a fable based on the ‘African proverb’, ‘A black cat and a lamb shall outdo themselves.’[2] William Blake,  	A Tale of Two Cities, published by Henry Holt and Company, London, 1832, p.  1. [6] The Tale of Two Cities, p.  2. [7] William Blake,  	A Tale of Two Cities, published by Henry Holt and Company, London, 1832, p.  3. [8] William Blake,  	A Bluecoat, published by Henry Holt and Company, London, 1832, p.  4. [9] William Blake,  	A Smart-aleck, published by Henry Holt and Company, London, 1832, p.  5. [10] </text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a moniker by Portuguese sailors searching for treasure in the murky waters of the Atlantic after a series of unfortunate turn-of-the-century Caribbean voyages. One of these voyages, in 1607, was allegedly part of a larger fleet led by John the Black Cat. When the Portuguese finally discovered the island of Madeira in the second half of the eighteenth century, they too were said to have named it ‘Bluecoat’ after the moniker given to the next island up the chain, named after the first island ‘Madeira’.  [6] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, Act IV, Scene X, Scene VIII, in Henry VI, Act IV, Ch. 8, line 419 (trans. Evelyn Ruxton &amp; Collins Edes Edward Watson) (Henry V): ‘Thou Shalt Not Play With Me’. [7] John MacBride, ‘The Black Cat’, in MacBride’s Dictionary of</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a challenge by the Earl of Balfour, King Henry VII (Henry VII was the title of a fictional character in a children’s story), who was said to have been so infuriated by the name being made public that he outlawed it from use in his court. [6] A free press is critical for innovation and freedom, but in the age of the information overload it is increasingly difficult to distinguish fiction from fact – especially when fiction has an impact that reverberates decades later. [7] William Blake,  	A Spring Tree for Kings, William Blake, translated by Nancy King and W. Allen Walker, Roper and Company, London, 1974, p. xi. [8] William Blake,  	The Fall of the Roman Empire, Trans. Nancy King, London, 1963, p. xxviii. [9] William Blake,  	A Spring Tree for Kings, William Blake, translated by Nancy King and</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a threat to William Blake by a Welsh Soldier called ‘The Un-Known’, who was said to have murdered at least twenty thousand Welshlanders in the First World War. Despite this, the name appeared in print between 1917 and 1922, in a fantasy novel entitled ‘The Wizard of Oz’ by Lewis.12 The appearance of the name in this mythical work is not a myth; it is a pseudonym. But the fate of the name remains a problem for writers such as Blake, who have long since ceased to be known as John the Black Cat, or Lewis, or even Robin Hood. Even when the name is known, it is often misquoted or corrupted, as in the case of Lewis’s cousin Edward Bulwer’s fictional character Edward Bulwer, who absconded with over 1,000 lands and was hunted down and killed by the English. As Felix Mendesso notes, however, the ‘[s]pontaneous order</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1]  [2] Kurt Götting,  	Deconstructing Human Agency, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [3] Gustave Flaubert,  	A Thousand Plateaus of Modern Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1986, p.  5. [4] Ninety-five years after the publication of his first short story, William Blake returns to explore in greater depth the theme of his ‘Bluecoat’ – a nom de plume that begins with the word ‘blue’ and ends with the word ‘copper’ – a name given to a series of copper mines in the Welsh Streets of Tottenham.  [5] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a challenge to anyone who would attempt to write a rhyming &quot;Bluecoat’ on to a postcard. See also William Shakespeare, Juliana Engagement, published in the London Review of Books, December 1845, p. 7. [6] A quick look online reveals that the name ‘Bluecoat’ is the subject of a folk-tale by the name John the Black Cat. The name was reportedly given as a challenge to anyone who would attempt to write a rhyming &quot;Bluecoat’ on to a postcard. See also William Shakespeare, Juliana Engagement, published in the London Review of Books, December 1845, p. 7. [7] William Shakespeare, Juliana Engagement, published in William Shakespeare &amp; Company, ed. Jack Burnham, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1988, pp. 40–43. [8] A quick look online reveals that the soap operas of yesteryear</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Rami El Samahy.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Rami El Samahy.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Rami El Samahy.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Rami El Samahy.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Rami El Samahy.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextSmartphone not included in standard shipping. For a suggested retail of approximately US$229.00, please see the individual product pages.PreviousNextSmartphone not included in standard shipping. For a suggested retail of approximately US</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. [1] The term ‘bluecoat</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHeld from 1990 until his death in 2015, Conway Center for the Performing Arts was a unique venue for Conway’s experimental work, which frequently addressed the politics of performance and the economy of performance. The building was acquired by the city of Los Angeles in 1990 and renamed LAX, where it has remained</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge. PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge. PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015.   Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] Rami El Samahy, ‘Is there life after AI?’,  	Academics 12:1 (2015), p.1.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.PreviousNextBluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Marketa Luskacz.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.Hollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Shintaro Miyazaki.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood, USA: Bluecoat Books, 2015. Cover Image: Nina Edge.PreviousNextHollywood</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their websites.The gallery owner has a story that speaks to the democratic deficit and displacement that she witnessed when the building of a new gallery was threatened. She also witnessed the displacement of her own family when the site became a parking lot for fast food outlets. She has a story about a man who drove through the building and never looked back. She has a story about a city that needs to be rebuilt. Together, they’re telling a story that will resonate with generations to come. This is the story of the many voices that inhabit the city.This is the story of the few. You’re part of a team that’s developing the strategy for a city that cannot be defined by the very essence of who we are, what we’re made of, and where we come from. The art gallery and the lucky few that buy its products inhabit a different world, but they’re everywhere. You and I are part of a team that’s developing the</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their biographies. Both men are active in their communities, have a shared passion and have written collections of short fiction and nonfiction texts. They’re creative geniuses, and their work is often at odds with the glamour and economic uplift of the cultural machine, but it works for the city.  	While we’re at it, could we also consider the role of artists and curators in the city’s revitalisation? The biennial as a producer of art and cultural products is a machine that produces cultural products, and it’s quite possible that the biennial would be the same way for other cultural forms and might even seek to assist in the creation of cultural products itself.  	There are of course many other factors that contribute to a city’s economic, urban and cultural health, but the main drivers of urban growth and development are the actions of individuals and small groups of individuals with the capacity to shape policy and create social change</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their websites.Both the poet laureate and the gallery owner are from the 1970s, and both are involved with the Open School. You’ll find a blend of opinions on both, with a touch of personal nostalgia for the sixties. But there’s a fundamental disagreement about the role of poetry in the city – a disagreement that runs contrary to the interests of the city as a whole. Do you allow the poet laureate and the gallery owner to define the city?If the gallery owner decides that the city is a place where creativity and intellectual life are encouraged, then surely the city has a civic purpose that requires poetry to express itself in a way that is authentic to the city, and that poetry can therefore adopt many forms and express itself in many settings?If the city wants to promote cultural activity, it’s up to the artists to take matters of the city into their own hands and create a context in which creative activity can take place in a way that is authentic to the city</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their websites. The gallery owner has already written a song and lyrics for the board to sing, and the local community activist has already written a poem for the board to read. Together, they represent a set of stories that span decades and involve generations of Torontonians. Together, they represent a set of cultures. Together, they’re all part of a working class family. You'll find them at the Bluecoat Gallery, taking questions. Happy to talk, and looking forward to seeing you both in October.DDownload this article as PDF24 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 February 2015Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 February 2015Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the Asian Biennale in San Francisco. I was very interested in your remarks on the relationship between biennials and the cities that are</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their websites. Both have been published in the New York Times, and both have been part of the Academia Sinica, a literary magazine in Italy. Who knows more about the city than the other? Let us know in the comments section below.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleContemporary Artistic Director, Tate ModernOlivia AnsellContemporary Artist, Tate ModernOlivia Ansell is the Contemporary Artistic Director for Tate Modern, London. Previously, she was Artistic Director at Tate Modern, London, where she led the artist-led initiative that was a main component in the redevelopment of the institution. She is a past president of the ASA Academia Sinica, Italy’s oldest and largest artistic academy, where she led the academy’s programming of exhibitions, workshops and events. She has also curated the Venice Biennale, the London and New York Museums, and the National Portrait Gallery, UK, and has participated</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their websites.Both the poet laureate and the gallery owner are women. You may feel that their work speaks to the contemporary predicament of women artists in a male-dominated profession. You can also identify with one or the other. Whatever your identity, your work should tell a story. You can think of different ways of telling that story, depending on how the art will be commissioned. And you can work in any order you please. That’s the spirit in which we do things here at LCC. This board has been very kind to me. It is the board of the Arts Catalyst Initiative. It is the board of the LCC Foundation. It is the board of the LCC Arts Initiative. It is the board of the LCC Cultural Alliance. It is the Board of the Queens Museum. It is the board of the Queens Museum. It is the board of the Museum of Modern Art. It is the board of the Art Foundation. It is the board of the Que</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their websites.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThe ResidentEmily Pringle is a writer, curator and arts producer based in London. Her work has addressed the social consequences of art for social change, including in the areas of housing, education and the environment. She has written for the Guardian, The New York Times, The Observer and The Observer Digital. Her essays have been published in The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Education, The New York Public Library, The New York Public Audio, The New York Public Library &amp; The New York Public Library of Arts &amp; Culture, among others. Art for Tijuana Ships (2014) and Paradise Lost (2015) used political, economic and social theory to highlight the social and ecological effects of art in the Pacific Rim. Her work is currently undertaken as a postdoctoral researcher in the library and archives department at McGill University. Her work has also been commissioned by the Royal Academy of Arts, Scotland, the American Museum of Art, the Museum of Modern</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their publications, blogs, or just by following ‘Emma Goldman’ on Twitter. The gallery owner will be providing financial and material support for the project, while the poet laureate will be providing the rest. The deadline for proposals will be December 2015.The deadline for applications to become full-scale models for the proposed Cultural Crossing project is February 16th, 2016. If you have a work proposal that you think is worthy of consideration, send it as a self-addressed stamped envelope to:Curatorial Faculty, New York Museum of Art, New York, NY 14201. We’ll assess it, consider it, and arrange it in accordance with the priorities outlined below.The priorities below are those of the artist(s), but may be adapted by those in charge of the Biennale to suit the needs of the City Council. The priorities listed below are those of the Council as a whole, but may be adapted by those in charge of the Biennale to suit the</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their websites.The gallery owner has a very personal story, about a childhood in which she and her husband created a work-safe environment for their daughter’s art, which at the time was a new development. She explains how her involvement in the community led her to become involved in the gallery system, and how her role in the board ultimately led to the creation of the gallery itself. The role of the gallery board in the context of the larger community is a powerful place to begin a dialogue about how art is produced and delivered, and how art is distributed. In this context, the board member’s personal story becomes a powerful point of entry into the collective identity of the community. You can begin to imagine what a cultural ecology might look like if the gallery board members genuinely believed what they were saying on the board, and if they actually invested in what they were saying through their jobs. Remembering the history of the building, and the way its contents had a transformative effect on the city</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of Wall Street financiers. But now, more than ever, we need to learn how to talk about the place of art in the economy and the politics of representation. That's why we’re commissioning your art from now until October 31st, when we launch into our Local Economy Board debate and competition. The work you produce will shape the way we think about the city and art in a way that will endure for years to come. Take some time to compose a 60-word essay on the place of art in the city, and in it you will find much to which we can relate. For this Local Economy Board debate and competition, we’ll be enlisting the help of a poet laureate, a city poet and a gallery owner. Each has a distinctive voice, and each has a story that speaks to the challenges and opportunities of living in a vibrant and culturally responsive city. You can find out more about the poet laureate and the gallery owner from their websites. The gallery owner is a well-known local artist, the poet is a novelist and the novelist is a poet laureate. All three have published books about their experiences as artists, in which they make frequent appearances. For this project, we want to know what they thought of as cultural marginalisation in the UK during the 1990s and 2010s, and how that affected their practice and their communities. How, then, do we create a shared vocabulary and set of values around the things that connect?Take Two: The City and its People 	The second phase of our research process involves asking people to create a 'city of their own minds', as a way of thinking about the city and the people who live and work in it. We call this phase ‘The City and its People’ and ask people to think of the most salient features of their city – what makes it ‘different’ from any other city, and why does it matter? We do this by asking</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-
    <text>will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-purpose cultural venue, with a world-class exhibition venue and cultural center as its three parts. We mention it briefly because the proposed resolution is identical to that of the present city council. We want to ask: what are the similarities and differences between Radionationals and the current proposals for the city?I thought not…until now.When I heard the council members’ proposal (arguably influenced by the Radionationals proposal) I thought: this is bad. It’s as if they’ve been put through a transformation rigorously scripted by city planners, whose sole purpose in life is to maximize profit for the financial sector. The fact that the city council members are women is a strange choice, almost as if they’ve been given a particularly difficult task.I don’t know if they’ve been put through the transformation rigorously scripted by city planners, whose sole purpose in life is to maximize profit for the financial sector. The fact that</text>
    <text>will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-purpose art gallery, education complex and cultural centre. The Cultural Centre would be a perfect fit for this ambitious concept, since it’s located in a historic district with a lot of potential future uses. The Radionationals building, however, is a perfect candidate for a future museum, since it has served as an artistic outcropping and an important junction point for art and commerce in Doha for over 100 years. In the Museum of Modern Art’s case, this includes a long history of hosting exhibitions and events, including the creation of the Museum of Modern Art in New York in 1864 and the museum of modern art in Doha in 1980. In the case of Radionationals, the Museum of Modern Art, New York, is a city institution, anchored in its role as the largest art gallery in the country during the twentieth century. A museum that showcases its past exhibitions would invite visitors to explore the archives and revisit the practices of art today. Gallery collections in</text>
    <text>will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-purpose art venue, cultural center and even a city farm. Thanks to Karima Kelazadeh for pointing this out to me. Although Radionationals is a good idea on its own terms, the way in which it is integrated into the city seems to obscure its true nature. The proposed ‘campus of the future’ would be a hybrid between a traditional university and an art institution, providing opportunities for artists to work alongside academics in a quasi-academic setting. The proposed ‘city of the future’ would include a mixture of residential and commercial areas, with a hybrid ‘farm to feed industrial farms’ in between. Though these hybrid forms may have similarities, and may even be modeled after each other, Radionationals is unique in its attempt to combine the best of both worlds: to combine the urban and the agricultural.Here, we see another example of a city-wide ‘future vision’ being developed, this one by architects, designers</text>
    <text>will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-purpose cultural venue and exhibition hall. Is this possible? I’m interested in what this would look like – as a concept, not as an architectural solution. Thanks.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF27 June 2014To Maria Hlavajova28 June 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany28 June 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent for the Liverpool Biennial. We</text>
    <text>will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-purpose cultural venue and exhibition venue. We’ll take this opportunity to thank you for your contribution to our understanding of the city.I’m interested in Radionationals because it provides a framework through which to start a conversation about the use of a building – a framework that could then be applied to other sites in the city. In our current article, we discuss the similarities and differences between Radionationals and other contemporary art institutions, as well as the difference between the use of a building and the cultural production that can come from its deconstruction. In the next issue of Sustainability - our newsletter, we’ll be looking at the role of art and the environment in the evolution of the city.Doubtless, Radionationals is a new concept to many of us, and to outsiders it may seem as if the city is an unfamiliar place –  without walls, or at least without any real separation between the artist and the viewer. Nevertheless, the</text>
    <text>will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-purpose, city-wide digital art centre. This is great for the artist and gallery who can now commission large-scale works of art and design from any direction, rather than being constrained to a city-wide selection. Thanks to the Radionationals, anyone can now embark on a curatorial or educational journey through Doha, Qatar, through a series of interactive activities that begin as early as early childhood.Doha, Qatar: The City that Never Sleeps?PreviousNextDoha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-purpose, city-wide digital art centre. This is great for the artist and gallery who can now commission large-scale works of art and design from any direction, rather than being constrained to a city-wide selection. Thanks to the Radionationals, anyone can now embark on</text>
    <text>will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-use hub for artists, performing arts, education, research and cultural activities. The proposal is to be developed into a fully fledged cultural district, funded by a city-wide Biennale and a host of private and public foundations.  The project is to be located in and managed by the Qatar Museums Authority (QMA) and will be a multi-purpose cultural district with a centre for the art of ‘Radionational art’, a multi-disciplinary art form that traces its roots to the 1930s.  The proposed ‘city of art’ would be transformed in such a way as to accommodate and engage artists and visitors to the area, while remaining independent of commercial and institutional endeavour.  The design proposes an entirely new architecture style for the district, one that attempts to incorporate both public and private resources, places a special emphasis on research and development, and utilises local and national creativity agencies. The spatial arrangements are such that art is frequently cited as a factor</text>
    <text>will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-purpose cultural venue, with a city-wide participatory ‘performance-based architecture project’. It is proposed that this project, whose scope is limited to the eastern half of the building, will be managed by the Qatar Museums Authority, whose mandate is to commission and manage the country’s cultural assets.  The project was launched by the Doha Branch of the American Anthropological Association (DA), in partnership with the Liverpool John Moores University (JMU) and Qatar Museums Authority (QMA). The JMU and QMA are collaborating with the American Museum of Natural History (AMS) and the Qatar Museums Authority (QMA) to plan the museum and the project. What an interesting collaboration! The reason for this surprising extent of collaboration is a project we are calling HDFCulture City, a shared vision for the future of Doha. It was developed and directed by and for the city. We’ve been invited to be a co-investigator</text>
    <text>will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-purpose cultural venue, with a residential component. This seems like a good idea to me: by turning the building into a multi-purpose venue with a cultural district, we can create a unique experience within the building, while providing an alternative to the usual tourist trap experience, which is defined by the monoliths and museums now dominating the city.We visit the site of the proposed Cains and Olympia cinema, and find that the Radionationals has already allocated a spot in the new ‘Cinema chain’ by which many local residents will soon be able to access all their favourite films and TV shows. As we sit down to a meal, a local resident tells the story of how her father bought a ticket to see Star Wars: Episode I - The Phantom Menace for her 15th birthday. It was her father, she says, who always dreamed of going to the cinema. He was only seven, but already an adult, and already a Star Wars fanatic. She doesn</text>
    <text>will be curated in collaboration with the Liverpool Biennial and the Liverpool Museums and Gallery. The drawings will be on commission and the commissioning committee will meet regularly to update the article. The Biennial itself has been invited to create a special exhibition for the twenty-first Biennial – in Rome - in June 2016. The committee members have begun an open call for proposals. If you have a project for the Liverpool Biennial - or are already working on one - but need more ideas or have a project that needs to be discussed, don’t hesitate to shoot us an email. We’ll put it to the committee members for their benefit.Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF26 June 2014To Farhad Manjoo27 June 2014Doha, QatarAs we continue our research on the city of Doha, Qatar, we come across a project (dubbed Radionationals) that proposes to turn the Radionationals building into a multi-purpose cultural venue, with an urban park and the former site of a rubbish dump in the city centre. We’ll take this as a start.The Radionationals building was designed by Andrey Kartapolshy and was part of the government’s Cultural Architecture Program (aka, the ‘Trotsky Programme’) launched in 1966. It was part of a larger ‘New Direction in Culture’ initiative that involved a number of state-owned artists, designers and architects revamping the city into a ‘new cultural centre’. The project was also part of a ‘New Russia’ initiative that sought to create ‘a new type of urban space and countryside of national significance for the future’.  So, the state was keen to show its cultural capital and offer places of art and culture to visitors. The NDC also wanted to show its cultural assets, including the city, in the form of buildings and streets reclaimed</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1
    <text>will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/Images/1.html#Culture/Art-Trends/Art-Images/Art-Trends-2016-10-11-14-static-archives-060815.jpg#Culture/Art-Trends/Art-Images/Art-Trends-2016-10-11-14.html Tiffany Taylor, Peter McCaughey: Curatorial Strategies[1]http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/Images/1.html#Culture/Art-Trends/Art-Images/Art-Trends-2016-10-11-14.jpg#Culture/Art-Trends/Art-Images/Art-Trends-2016-10-11-14.html[2] http://www.</text>
    <text>will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/Images/art/contemporane... http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/Images/art/contemporane... 	[2] Svetlana Boym:  	[3] http://www.designcombination.com/en/17072/conceptual-design-infrastructure/how-concepts-influence-design-... 	[4] Ido Soane:  	[5] &quot;The Rise of Community Arts’, with Suraj Sharma and Nancy White, New York Times, 11/18/2014, http://www.nytimes.com/2014/11/19/us/politics/exclusive-... 	[6] John</text>
    <text>will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/Tiffany Taylor is professor of English and Art History and director of the Art, Art History, and Art Practice Research Centre (AHR) at the University of Alberta, Canada. Her research interests include the cultural histories of art, craft, photography and graphic design, and the role of art and design in the social and political evolution of Canada. She is the recipient of several awards from the Canadian Arts and Heritage Association, including the 2016 John Lennon Award for Art from a Post-Impressionist Context, the 2014 Rogers Cubee Prize for Art from Post-Impressionism, the 2014 Guggenheim Prize for Art from Postmodernism, the 2014 Guggenheim Foundation Prize for Art from Postmodernism, and the 2014 Guggenheim Prize for Art from Postcolonialism. She is the author of The Art Newspaper (2015), the forthcoming History of Art Newspaper (2017), and co-editor of the forthcoming book The World is Flat: On Postmodernism and</text>
    <text>will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/The dynamic nature of the archive, and the changing definition of that term, means that the curatorial work that emerges from it may create expectations and change expectations about the relationship between archives and museums, between the physical and virtual, that are unmoored from one another. Thus, the curatorial work that emerges from the biennial may be responsive to the changing needs, wants and expectations of a visiting public, but that public is itself subject to the whims of cultural tourism and the vagaries of economic development. Moreover, the biennial may itself demand that the public engage with the collection in new ways. For example, the collections department at Tate Britain requested that its artists present a new generation of its collection, which it identified as being at the cutting edge of its content with respect to its subject matter. These were intended to be engaged with collectively, rather than separately, as a way of thinking about the collection as a whole. These are but some of many examples of the ways in which the</text>
    <text>will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/Other-world-views/index.html#sthash.u8Jl.8DfZHl.dpuf.7Kl.l.gzFwCmNlMlMnAyYWlMmJlMmJlMmJlMnAyYWlMmJlMnAyYWlMmJlMmJlMnAyYWlMmJlMmJlMnAyYWlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmTlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMmJlMm</text>
    <text>will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/ [1] See http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/ [2] See http://www.theguardian.com/academics/2016/oct/19/son-of-satirist-neighbourhood-scandal-new-york-city-gallery-scandal-extraordinary-new-york-year-archive-scandal-episodic-futures-open-inquiry-new-york-archive/ [3] See http://www.nytimes.com/2016/10/07/arts/nytrending/undercard-picard-trumpet-booth.html?excerpt=undercard-trending-news-undercard-news</text>
    <text>will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/Art-collection-structures/art-objects/art-detail/art-detail/image-gallery/art-objects/art-detail/art-detail/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detail/art-objects/art-detectors/art-objects/art-detectors/art-detection-paint/art-objects/art-detection-paint/art-objects/art-detection-paint/art-detection-paint/</text>
    <text>will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/Institute-of-Archive-and-Criticism/2017/ai-static-archives-futura-new-york.html#ixzz1dC3LyhGltdXJlC5hbi9RetC5jdXJlC5jdXJlC5jdXJlC5joic3JlMjAxNi8wNS8wNS8wNS8wNS8wNS8wNtfS8wNS8wNtfS8wNtfS8wNtfS8wYWlsLWF0dHC9kYWlsLWF0dHC9kYWlsLWF0dHC9kYWlsLWF0dHC9kYWlsLWF0dHC9kYWlsLWF0dHC9kYWlsLWF0dHC9kYWlsLWF</text>
    <text>will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/Art-collection-static-archives-19-th-century-graffiti-episodic-art-episodic-program-static-archives-19-th-century-graffiti-episodic-art-episodic-program-static-archives-1920s-graffiti-episodic-art-episodic-program-static-archives-1960s-graffiti-episodic-art-episodic-program-static-archives-1970s-graffiti-episodic-art-episodic-program-static-archives-1980s-graffiti-episodic-art-episodic-program-static-archives-1990s-graffiti-episodic-art-episodic-program-static-archives-academia-static-archives-academia-static-archives-african-american-graffiti-2000s-black-face</text>
    <text>will be curated by Peter McCaughey, Curator of Public Practice, Tate Gallery. The exhibition will run for one week from 11 September 2016 to 1 October 2016. The curatorial approach to the work will be a concern for the work as a whole, since the focus of the exhibition will be on the work in the collection and the increasing (under the leadership of Tiffany Taylor, from 2013-15) of migrant and refugee peoples' struggles for inclusion and citizenship. The curatorial approach to the exhibition will be a concern for the collection as a whole, since the main public engagement with the collection will be the curatorial process surrounding the exhibition. The curatorial perspective will evolve and redefine what it means to be a ‘collection institution’. http://www.tiffanytaylor.com/2016/10/the-difference-between-static-archives-and-the-static-archives-of-peter-mccaughey-curatorial-school/1/Tiffany Taylor is Interdisciplinary Artistic Director at Tate Gallery and Senior Curator of Public Practice, London, where she is an adjunct curator for the exhibition series CHAPTER 8: ARCHIVES OF A MEMBER of the London Gallery, Tate Modern and Assemble in Paris. She is currently curator-at-large for the exhibition series ARCHIVES: A MEMBER of the London Gallery, Tate Modern and as a curatorial assistant for the upcoming 48 Hours of Open House, Tate Modern. In 2015 she ran the Open School, London, where she taught and performed a number of years, as part of the curatorial team for the curatorial residency programme CHAPTER 8: ARCHIVES of a MEMBER of the London Gallery, Tate Modern. In 2017 she co-curated the exhibition ARCHIVES: A MEMBER of the London Gallery, Tate Modern, and Tate Modern &amp; Tate Modern London, part of the curatorial team for the curatorial residency programme ARCH</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a
    <text>will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a greater social, institutional and political context.]28  […] the art needs to take part in a political context in order to be effective.’[…] 29  […] the art has an obligation to be visible, even to those who aren’t there because they’re busy doing other things.][…] 30  […] a location that creates understanding, even if you’re doing it for the tourists.](emphasis in original)Download this article as PDFSabine DommannSabine Dommann is Professor of Curatorial and Head of the Curatorial Department at the Max Planck Institute for Geography and Co-Director of the Max Planck Institute for Art, Art, and Law. Her research interests include the history and historiography of contemporary art in modern and post-modern times, the contemporary artworld in the cities of the future, and art in the post-industrial society. Dommann is member of the curatorial faculty at the</text>
    <text>will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a broader art organisation that participates in a wider system that includes, but is not limited to: institutions, governments, commercial and institutional funding, time and energy resources, legal frameworks and social norms.  	[The new form of the arts centre is a social hub that engages with the social world of artists and the art world in a converging and interdependent relation.]28  The new form of the arts centre is a social and cultural outgrowth of the new technological hubris that characterises the era of unlimited information and unlimited travel. As new forms of work are created and new modes of sharing are developed, the role of the arts organisation becomes ever more critical.  	[The new form of the arts centre does not necessarily equal a museum or gallery.]29  [To some extent, the new technological and social moment calls for an organisation that can build sound infrastructure, capable of supporting a sustained sound system, capable of supporting large scale public works, capable of supporting a sustained radio</text>
    <text>will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a larger art organisation that participates in a broader system that is broader still.  	[Making the art centre into a cultural institution would also alter its relationship with its surrounding community.]28  [Figure 1: Plan view of the proposed new art and cultural centre,  (used with permission)).  	[Figure 2: Renderings of the proposed new cultural and arts centre, built on the J.W. McCuaig Art Centre site in the city of Hamilton, based on architectural plans submitted by the developer in 2014.]29  [Figure 3:  An  	topology of three or four office buildings could create a hybrid urban form that combines the qualities of a cultural centre, such as a museum, library, café and exhibition venue, with the characteristics of an industrial park, such as a department store, warehouse and factory.]30  [Figure 4: A density map of the proposed ‘Golden Triangle’ area, based</text>
    <text>will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a broader cultural organisation.  	[How to create an artist-run cultural centre?] 	[Somewhere in here, Daniel Coleman is humming Avicenna's line from Suddenly, Bernadette Peters says something about the inappropriateness of youth culture in a major American city:) ‘You don’t know what you’re missing until you go to school every day.’]28   	[The other piece of the proposed new urban form is the urbanic·ish, the transformation of the former site of a munitions factory into an urban neighbourhood.] 	[The proposed new form of the arts centre is a place where artists can come and work.]1  And so, the profile of the curatorial person changes – in the new curatorial person, the artist is not an icon of an ideal future urban future, but a person whose work speaks to a specific present, and whose work represents a shifting of the relative amounts of</text>
    <text>will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a larger multi-site art organisation. As noted by the curator Nicola Mallon, in her talk What a Difference a Biennial Can Make,28 a biennial can ‘bridge the gap between artist-centred museums and large urban spaces’, by giving local artists a place to be embedded within the museum system, whilst also enabling ‘anyone to put their work out there, and take part in the cultural life of the city’. Stemming back from its biennial trajectory, the art fair – which is centred on the artworks exhibited in the gallery – is now recommending local artists for work at the Biennial as well as ‘promoting a conversation’ with local people on a local level through activities such as The Resident, a project of the Museum of Modern Art, which is organising the curatorial programme for the coming two years in a city-wide conversation. Thus the museum-based biennial is winding down, but the</text>
    <text>will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a larger organisation that is representative of society.  	[If there are cultural producers here, they are art organisations, not individuals producing artistic work for exhibition – Ed.]28  The new form of the art institution also entails a shift in the role of the artist and organisation, in favour of those with a cultural focus. The role of the artist and the organisation is shifted from being a lone artist, who could produce art in his/her own right, to one that is more readily adaptable, can leverage the resources of the city and a city’s rich cultural past, and is therefore more able to engage with a more dispersed and urbanised population.  	[See also BROADWAY AGE: THE ART CURATOR](http://www.bronxmuseums.org.uk/exhibitions/archive/index.php?fuseaction=CollectionSearchResult&amp;type=0&amp;list=OUPES&amp;excludeat=1</text>
    <text>will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a collective. In the old ‘natural and ‘social science study centres’, the curatorial model was that of a specialist, presenting a single art-historical point of view. Today, cultural production requires that the curatorial shift is more widespread and widespreadist, presenting a culture as a whole. This is why a biennial with a cultural content that extends beyond the art-historical point of view is always going to be different from a natural or social science curatorial exhibition. It is no longer possible to have a purely art-historical curatorial intervention, since that would demand a fundamentally different understanding of the world from the curatorial intervention of a biennial or a museum. For the curatorial intervention to have any real impact, the art centre has to be involved in the wider system that is being assembled – part of a larger cultural organisation that is also involved in the education of future generations. In a word, it has to be ‘relevant and transformational�</text>
    <text>will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a larger organisation.]28  [For an interesting example of how a city constructs an image of itself, consider the image of the yellow peripatetic.]29 [The new urban form is an image, but not an image.]30[Image source: Richard Turner]Download this article as PDFAna Laura López de la TorreAna Laura López de la Torre is a New York-based curator and writer. She has previously curated for The New York Times, The New Yorker, The Wall Street Journal, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, GQ, MoMA Popular Art, and The New Inquiry: Art from the Margins. Her work has received critical acclaim and has been exhibited in major venues including Amsterdam, London, Seoul, Berlin, and Venice. She is the Co-founder of the Margaret and Edward M. Sackler Center for Art and Culture at Columbia University and also a member of the advisory board of the Museum of Modern Art</text>
    <text>will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a larger organisation that is a wider representative of the world as a whole.  	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of participation, not necessarily of artistic outcomes.]28  The art is the inevitable by-product of the new way of organising cultural resources. The curatorial role is no longer isolated from the resource-sharing. But the new form of the arts centre has to actively engage with the new mode of production and consumption that is being developed in the city in the name of urban development. It has to actively participate in this process, creating what Talbot calls ‘cultural villages’ where people can ‘receive and explore cultural resources’ in a reciprocal way. But it also has to actively participate in the social and political systems that are constituting this new form of the city, in part by creating its own forms of governance. This last task is a much more difficult call to make, and one that will continue to be problematic in the current</text>
    <text>will be curated by and open to the public.]25  The new civic buildings, which occur to me more and symbolise the change, are those that rise above the chaos and noise of the city and take on the form of interactive stories, that invite you to ‘become part of the story’, as the saying goes. [Summary drawing of the proposed new urban form:  Civic Center, created as a public space for debates and education, incorporating the two corners of the existing Judson Gallery courtyard.]26   	[The new form of the arts centre is a place of processes, not individuals, in which artists and arts organisations are encouraged to take part.]27  The art centre becomes something more when it is no longer a standalone attraction. It has to take part in a system that is more general, more comprehensive and more representative of the world as a whole. In this sense, the curatorial role changes from being a lone artist to being part of a bigger cultural system. And this can mean taking part in exhibitions, participating in symposia, organising long-term residencies or even becoming artists' trustees. Here, the curatorial role is about taking part in a larger cultural system that is not only their own reflection, but also a reflection of their society. It is about wider societal changes that affect the art’s social function and their place in it. It is about how artists and arts organisations are invited to participate in that system. The curatorial role in the 21st century can be about participation, and it is about who participates and how they participate. But it is also very individual: it is not just the artist(s) who participates, but also the community (or neighbourhood groups, or grassroots organisers, or community organisers), artists, community organisers, historians, artists' groups, artists’ families, friends, community activists, politicians, historians, artists, artists, activists, architects, artists’ college students,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles
    <text>future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles of authority that contemporary art has in effect today is an impossible task. But the contemporary curatorial is a valuable piece of the contemporary artifice that has largely accrued because of the modern market, and its function is to some extent to maintain the balance between the various sellers and consumers of modern art. The contemporary curatorial is a powerful piece of the contemporary artifice because it manages to remain open and contemporary, and because it produces its own set of discourses about art and contemporary culture, and between them withstood the test of time. This is why contemporary art today is no longer able to legislate its way out of its own contemporary curatorial predicament, and why it is so eager to distance itself from its subject matter, to some extent by accident. It cannot, of course, legislate against culture, but it can nonetheless organise and organise the sale of cultural products. The contemporary curatorial is something like a fantasy draft of sorts, a work-in-progress. It is constantly undergoing change</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles of authority that break free today is a fantasy as well. But the contemporary curatorial is a political and economic system, and its political and economic imaginations are deeply shaped by the contemporary art market. The contemporary curatorial is also deeply influenced by the cultural geographer who recently came out of the 1950s and 60s, and the sociologist who worked with him on the Berkeley, California, campus of UCLA. The sociologist who came out of the 60s was Max Horkheimer, who was one of the leading lights of the cultural counterculture. His book, Suicide of a Century, in particular, was pivotal in popularising the notion of the ‘cultural suicide’, and his position on the subject is a forceful indictment of the excesses and injustices of postmodernism. Max Horkheimer, Suicide of a Century   (New York: Simon &amp; Schuster, 1985), p. 108. 2  JL: Here is a more general sense of the</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles of authority that comes with it is a fantasy that is quickly being replaced by something better. But the break with shackles that comes with the new art style is a break that is valuable as a curatorial break, and that is still very much a part of the art canon in many places today.  And breaking free from the shackles of authority is also the job of the art administrator today. There is a new style of art administrator today, one who is able to identify, analyse and project the representations of his or her geographical area in contemporary art and creates new work that speaks to that context and to that localised reality. Such administrators have one important advantage over their historical colleagues: they can choose to ignore or project contemporary art in ways that would not necessarily align with established art practices or history. For example, it is possible to argue that the art market today is dominated by visual art, and that there is an over-representation of social and political impact and impact in contemporary art,</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles of authority that breaking free of the historical curatorial tradition entails is a task that will continue to demand great willpower and skill, despite the liberatory claims of the modern curatorial.New curatorial approaches to art and the contemporary curatorial have emerged. One example is the New York Museum of Art’s (2012-2019) New Media exhibition, which sought to engage with the technology that is embedded in all aspects of everyday life and to present the latest work worldwide through a curated collection of multimedia installations. The technology is not embedded in the institution, but rather seeks to be embedded in the socio-cultural landscape through which it operates. The technology is pervasive and pervasive in this context, and its presence is a fact of which many people are unaware. New media is a modus operandi of the technology, and the more technologically literate the technology becomes, the more it challenges the socio-cultural conditions of its users. The emergence of new media has been seen as a condition of social and</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles of authority that such claims imply is something that contemporary art has largely failed to achieve.But what makes contemporary art so powerful is precisely that it is attuned to the needs and purposes of a globalised, multi-billion-dollar capitalist modernity, and to the beliefs and desires of a particularised urban-dwelling elite. As Michael Hardt writes, ‘The contemporary curatorial is an artifact of our economic, political and urban evolution – a fact that must be taken into account in future projections of the curatorial.’ Contemporary art today is embedded in a capitalist social context, and its curatorial function is to a large extent defined by the service providers – that is, the financial industry, the advertising and marketing industries, and the ‘entertainment, marketing and PR industries’. In other words, the curatorial is an arm of the economy, and the social function of the arm is to disseminate the arm’s valuable commodity, the ‘</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles of authority that break free today may be seen as the opposite of a fantasy, but it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority willy nilly, and may in fact be seen as a PROfound contradiction. The breaking of free from the shackles of authority today may in fact be seen as the raison d'être of contemporary art, but it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority will open up entirely new artistic opportunities. It is at this juncture that the contemporary art market is thought to have been developing, and it is claimed that this is the era of the biennial, which is thought to have been a ‘time of ephemeral forms of cultural artefacts, of the occasional archaeological dig and a grand opening’. The contemporary curatorial is thought to have been pivotal in this development. It is true that the advent of the biennial in North America in the 1990s coincided with the corresponding rise of the contemporary</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles of authority that populates contemporary art today is a fantasy that is difficult to sustain in practice. But it is claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority inspires a new generation of contemporary artists to take up the art form, and so the contemporary art market is said to be a 'cure' for a feeling of unreality and newness, and a way to reclaim the lost freedoms of the modern artist.It is true that today we would all do well to read the curatorial report that comes with every exhibitionary form, and curatorial reports. The form that the report takes is a statement of fact, which in its general sense is valid for all curators, whether contemporary or historical, and especially for those who train as curators. But it is also true that the report itself is a statement of ideology, and so the report is often read as a manifesto for a particular vision of modernity. And so the curatorial sees its mission as one of two possibilities: either</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles of authority that breakdance-like behaviour imposes is not a proposition that art can propose as a solution to a social problem. The breaking of free from such fetters is a demand and challenge that art producers and their patrons make today, and to an extent that art workers and curators can participate in supporting the making of today’s art style. But this does not mean that breaking free from such conditions is easy or desirable, or even desirable. It is true that today’s art-world curators and artists’ patrons are the wealthy and politically connected, and that these patrons tend to be politically engaged, and have a stake in the institution of art, and have a habit of spending a great deal of time and energy politicising artistic practices. It is true that in the social dynamic of the social contemporary art-world will be anything but the social and democratic contemporary art-world that existed after 1945. But there is also a far deeper contradiction at work here, one</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles of authority that comes with modernity is a postmodern fantasy. But the contemporary curatorial is an art commodity, and the contemporary art market is a very real market. In the contemporary art market, the contemporary curatorial is a major player, and his or her political, economic and cultural influence is felt in every aspect of the contemporary art world.Through a combination of knowledge and cultural imperialism, modernity is said to have established a global hegemony over what is sometimes called the ‘third place’ or the ‘temporary presence’ that is recognisable today. In other words, modernity is thought to have established a new standard or paradigm of what is possible in terms of what can be represented and embodied in physical form, and what is possible in terms of what is possible in terms of language, cultural practices and economic exchange. Modernity is thought to have created ‘a new economic and political model’ for the globalised contemporary world. But what this contemporary model entails</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, which then proliferate globally. Perhaps it is the case that the contemporary art market is itself a product of the post-WWII curatorial revolution, which ushered in a new era of biennials, which introduced new curatorial styles and art approaches, and which are believed by many to have created a new art style. But another aspect of the contemporary curatorial is critical of this. It is said that the new art style that emerged in the wake of the curatorial revolution was sceptical of the curatorial, and openly critical of its authority. Art, it is said, does not naturally belong in authority, and the new art style was said to ‘break free’ of the curatorial. This is to an extent a claim about the contemporary art experience, though it is also claimed that breaking free from the shackles of authority is the raison d'être of contemporary art today. This is to an extent a fantasy, and the breaking of free from shackles of authority that break free from contemporary art is a difficult but promising task. But there is some truth to this. I spoke at the Venice Biennale today about a project I am presenting now called The Contemporary Condition; the sequel to my 2013 exhibition The Contemporary Condition, which was conceived and directed by André Lévesque in conjunction with PSI, and which was inaugurated with the Venice Biennale. The project seeks to reconcile the breaking down of the boundaries between visual culture and social practice, between art and commerce, between art and journalism, between art and law, and between art and education. Art has become less and less able to function in this system, while the contemporary art market has become more and more circumscribed. So the relationship between the Biennale and the market is not a relationship of commodities and exchange, but a relationship of exchange and relationships. And this raises another question: what does it mean today to be a curator? As Francis Fukuyama points out</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was to promote the values of London City Council, the Museum and other art institutions through images of great architecture and impressive landscapes. The commissions came from a diverse register of sources, but the major role was played by a select group of avant-garde artists, collectors and art dealers. The important artworks displayed included (in order of appearance): 	The Tate Modern, William H. Gilmore &amp; Sons, New York, 1925; The Tate Modern, William J. Urban, New York, 1926; 	Bluecoat, Norman Wilkinson, London, 1928; 	Bluecoat, Norman Wilkinson, London, 1929; 	Bluecoat, Norman Wilkinson, London, 1930; 	Bluecoat, Norman Wilkinson, London, 1931; 	Bluecoat, Norman Wilkinson, London, 1933; 	Bluecoat, Norman Wilkinson, London, 1935; 	Bluecoat, Norman Wilkinson, London, 1937; 	Bluecoat, Norman Wilkinson, London, 1938; 	Blue</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was to create a ‘unique and distinctive environment’ for the biennale to operate through, with a strong emphasis on local culture. 	Local artists, curators and art dealers assembled at various locations in the boroughs of London to map out a ‘programme of activities’. These included a ‘design bureau’ comprised of artists, artists, art dealers and art historians, whose reports were compiled into a three-year ‘Blue Chip’ programme, which offered a series of early twentieth-century British artworks for permanent display in a museum, a special exhibition venue or both. 	The programme of activities for the Blue Chips was far more ambitious and widespread in the boroughs than this, and included ‘airdrops’ on a large scale, as well as ‘institutional collections’ in the form of publishing houses, ‘advertisements and tracts for schools and ‘books for schools’, as well as</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was to create a ‘world-class exhibition space for contemporary art’ in the heart of London’s financial district, including a private museum and a shop front enabling customers to directly affect the cultural landscape. 	At  	2008, the Tate Modern was chosen as the site for the first Art Biennale of London, which was co-curated by Sally Tallant and Maxine Peake. In later years, the Biennale commissioned paintings from artists from all over the globe, including works from artists based in London. The selection process involved an extensive public register of biennials, covering a broad range of subjects. The register included acts, their subjects, their location, dates, settings and more. The Museum of Modern Art and Tate Modern Museum of Modern Art were among those institutions that housed works from the first and second editions of the Biennale, as well as works by international artists. 	The public register included artists who were both local and international</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was to generate cultural activity via art biennials in selected areas of London. The accounts given for the project vary widely in character, with some individuals offering vastly inflated returns on investment, while others selling cultural products such as t-shirts, cookbooks, music, art projects, and educational materials. 	The project was conceived by the Biennale as a service, rather than as a project, and its participants offer strikingly different accounts of their relationship to the project. As Richard Launius notes, ‘The programme developed a relationship with the participant rather than the other way around: the artist was a client and not a voyeur.’[2] Some participants constructively narrate the project as a series of interviews conducted in the project’s final years, while others narrate the project as a series of voyeuristic voyeuristic films that document the aftermath of the event. This latter perspective characterises Walter Russell Mead, the artist who arranged for the finished products to</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was to position the locality as a major market for artworks; the ‘biennial condition’ was to be encouraged by the authorities as a ‘primary objective’. 	The Biennale commissioning agency Chagall arranged for the installations to be chosen from a shortlist of approximately twenty suggested works, which were then sent to the major art institutions, museums and archives, who in turn selected the rest from a shortlist of approximately twenty others. The major art institutions selected works representing local themes, with the local emphasis often reflecting their own priorities. 	Art was sometimes invited as a guest of honour, and the recipients of the Biennale commissions often received formalities unrelated to the objects they had created. Most of the artists and curators who were invited to collaborate with the Biennale on projects lasting a few months or even a few years never responded to the invitations. Many of the artists who worked as artistsadvisers or provided artistic direction to the exhibition were either</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was to attract investment from investors in an environmentally sustainable way, using cultural resources to support local communities in their quest for self-sufficiency. The contracts also stipulated that if the District of Columbia favoured the arts, the District of Columbia would be the site for a second Art Biennale. The networks of cultural tourism and the second Biennale of London provided the narrative with a dose of reality, while the actual locations were largely fantasies. 	However, the Biennale has recently emerged as one of the most important sectors of the London art market, capturing both the imagination of the visitor and the art collections maintained in the District. The Biennale awarded contracts to artists to work in the London area, mostly based in the financial district. These contracts provided artists with the freedom to set up shop anywhere in the city, and allowed artists to experiment with the fact that they were not confined to designated sites. As a result, the number of biennales has more or less doubled in the</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was to create a unique, world-class experience for visitors to the city, while encouraging local industry and creating a link with the past and future of the city. The biennale’s budget was supplied by the London and South East India Company (later known as the British Museum), whose collections and museums alone comprise more than a third of the world’s antiquities. The B.M.C. also funded the construction of new museums and historic sites on the banks of the Thames, as well as the purchase of luxury real estate in the region. The Biennale’s website claims that over 1,000 artists, artists, composers, storytellers, writers and other artistic groups contributed to its conception.[2] The official selection of works from the 2018 Projections at the British Museum, including seven works by Sello Peso, includes a lengthy list of curatorial proposals, a range of audio and video productions, an immersive website and interactive app,</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was to create a unique experience of visiting ‘home’ – that is, the location of the biennale itself – by introducing different kinds of art to different kinds of people. The term ‘location’ appears again and again throughout this book, but is of course strictly employed, as a synonym for ‘person or place’. The network chose locations in London and New York, because of their international links, and because they could count on good financial support from the biennale commission. The biennale itself chose locations in cities with a large art collection, because that is what made them attractive to art collectors and because that is what kept the collection moving. The collection moved from city to city, from the centre to the peripheries. The important point was that the artworks were located in cities with a large art market, because that allowed the biennale to know where the art was at any given moment. Separating the art from the market was</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was to create an environment in which the collection and exhibition of artworks could be enjoyed by a local audience. The public was to be drawn to the collection, not to the displays. The exhibition format was adapted to the local needs and preferences, while the collection and its contents were distributed globally. The local curatorial push came to be replaced by the global networking operations of the art market. 	The biennale is an international event, and the art collections of many countries gather in London every two years. The biennale commissions are the primary means of bringing together the diverse collections of art objects from different countries. The collection and display of art are not only items held by a country or region, but are also objects of interest and data points on a global register. This makes the collection and display of art objects from different places simultaneously global and particular. 	The biennale has come a long way from its humble origins in the collection of a local art dealer, and is now one</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Sarah Vaughan and Owen Newson, is a case in point.[1] The biennale became a royal pain in the crown’s clothing in the early twentieth century, due to its incommensurable ­–  ­expenses, the  	unimaginable multiplicity of cultures, the unbalanced consumption habits of visiting travellers, the increased surveillance regimes imposed by a globalised capitalist economy, and more. The immense, unwieldy operation of the biennial as an institution became unmanageable in the face of such a cost. In an effort to stimulate more business opportunities for the sector, the Biennale commission a series of pop-art portraits of exotic locales, most of which prove to be self-defeating. 	The Art Biennale of London awarded contracts to a network of artists, curators, art collectors and art dealers, who in turn selected local venues to house their artworks. The aim of the project was to renovate and launch a biennale venue in each of the 48 cities where the art was exhibited. The venues were chosen on the basis of their accessibility, physical characteristics and the number of biennales they hosted each year. For the Sydney and Venice pavilions, the number of biennales was limited to three each, while for the others, the limit was four. 	The theme of each biennale was unique and the arrangement varied widely, with Sydney and Venice often using the same imagery or repetition of styles across the years. The main trends and themes of the twentieth and twenty-first centuries have been identified as the ‘trans-individuation’ of cultural forms. This term describes the ongoing and accelerating upsurge of unique cultural forms that emerge from the cultural capital (C6) of capitalist circulation. It is a feature and growth of capitalism today, and a consequence of political, economic and social contradictions – but it is not sufficient to suffice as</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to every neighborhood in the city, mapping their histories and present conditions, and publishing these ethnographic accounts in a professional journal. It is this historical perspective that is crucial in understanding the current tensions and conflicts in the city, and how to resolve them.2. The Biennale as a cultural phenomenon, and the art world as a site of exchange and cultural exchange, in transition. – Fred TurnerWhile Venice is a city in which exchange takes place at a phenomenal pace (analytically, commercially and in every sense), it is also a site of resistance. Its history as a port city, its main maritime linkages, and its frequent attempts at separating itself from the rest of Europe are all still deeply embedded in its DNA, while the city’s current economic dependence on the port is a profound challenge for the city to address. Nevertheless, there is a sense that the Biennale is slowly making inroads towards addressing the needs of its local community, despite the fact that in many ways</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to each neighborhood, interviewing residents and collecting data. It is this last policy that the Biennale was able to implement because it was able to negotiate the localities that created the spatial conditions necessary for a biennial to exist: the locations, the relations and the values that shape the biennial, and the social and spatial terrain on which biennials operate. When biennials do this, they often do so in settings that are hostile to the inhabitants of the places where they occur, and in doing so, actually exacerbate those tensions. This is the case for the Biennial that appeared in Liverpool in 2016, for example. It is also the case for the Biennial that is currently touring the United States, and will soon be in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial is a biennial in the normal sense of the word, and in this sense it is a repetition of past biennial experiences, but in a different form. Liverpool Biennial 2016 is a completely new kind of biennial: it is</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to every neighborhood in the Biennale, with a team of local artists creating virtual tours that take visitors around the neighborhood sites in an in-depth way. The policy also had to address the fact that many of the Biennale’s financial backers are international, including the Biennale itself being funded by the Italian and Italian-American communities in New York and Berlin, as well as the Biennale of Sydney being co-commissioned by the Sydney Museum of Art and the Australian National Museum. It was therefore up to the Biennale to create a strategy that would respond to the specific needs and interests of the local populations it curated, while recognising the agency and priorities of the local artists and communities. The strategy could have been developed through a multi-year research project, with the Biennalee working with the local artists and their collective collective collective, as well as other artists, as artists curatorial team, as curatorial fellow, in an open-ended,</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to every neighborhood in the Biennale, often meeting local residents and local officials to explain the history, present and future of the area. It is this element of the Biennale, travelling by public transport, that is often misconstrued as being anti-capitalist, or even anti-capitalist, when in fact the train station and the Biennale’s frequent stop in every neighborhood around it is what creates this sense of safety and tranquillity. The anti-capitalist and sometimes anti-municipalist politics that are often bandied about in relation to the city are often used by governments and other powerful interests to maintain and expand their socio-political control over territory, populations and resources. This is particularly evident in the area of housing, which most biennials are now required to take part in at some point in their histories, often after having been forcibly pulled from the streets by local authorities, for reasons of safety and stability (although, as we will see, this is rarely</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to each neighborhood, interviewing residents and gathering local knowledge. It is this type of research that is rarely, if ever, done in Italy, and rarely, if at all, in the region around Venice. Despite this fact, the Biennale managed to create an international reputation for itself through its analysis and narrative of the neighborhood, its frequent public displays of architecture in disused buildings and the excavation of historic streets, its focus on the role of the architect and his or her design team, and its frequent use of photos that stand out like sore thumb amongst the city’s urban landscape.  	The Biennale’s research capacity and its willingness to engage with the city in a deeper sense allowed it to become the site of its most significant work for decades, a kind of ghost town, as it slowly faded into irrelevance. 	The Biennale’s support of local communities came at a price, however. As its funding came from foundations and other public</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to every district and researching their specific histories and present-day situations. The Biennale also had to adopt a permanent, nationally televised presence in order to draw large audiences to its events. At the time, this was seen as imperative because the city was becoming increasingly overrun with tourists, and the Biennale was only able to provide supplementary, supplementary coverage of the city due to its size and the number of artists it promoted. In order to maintain its image and position in the eyes of tourists and the local cultural elite, the Biennale needed to actively participate in creating its own image and reputation. It was here that the Biennale came to negotiate, co-conspire and subvert its image-making responsibilities. In other words, it needed external validation and power. But in order to exert influence and create consensus, it also needed to engage in self-congratulation and other forms of self-perpetuation. The Biennale also needed artists to contribute creatively to its internal</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to every district in the city, interviewing residents and exploring possible cultural practices. It is this element of the Biennale that is most directly related to the question about the place of art in a city. As noted by Szymczyk, ‘Art is the battlefield, but the biennial has to wage a cultural war on the side of the visitor’s experience.’[8] This is particularly important in a city such as Venice, where the Biennale has had to rely on cultural tourism as a way to generate revenue for the city. As Szymczyk notes, the Biennale has to adopt a ‘different strategy’ when engaging with neighborhoods: it cannot be a cultural institution that provides ‘a sustained, long-term cultural experience’.[9] This element of the Biennale’s present political situation is further complicated by the fact that, in the age of global travel, artists are reluctant to set up permanent residency in</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to each neighborhood, interviewing residents and exploring possible urban alternatives. In doing so, it would have had to negotiate local and national oppositions, as well as the conflicted interests and priorities of its diverse partners and stakeholders. The biennale therefore had to be able to negotiate both its own sense of mission and the prevailing ideologies, prejudices and partial needs of its local audiences. This negotiation would have required knowledge of both the local and the international dimensions of the Biennale’s intended impact. The 2017 edition of the Biennale took place in March 2018 at the La Spezia dell’Arsenale, with Professor Paolo Portoghesi from the University of Southern California at the head of the discursive board. The discussion took place in the presence of over 200 local and international artists, curators, artists’ associations, journalistè, politicians and other stakeholders. It noted the importance of understanding the local in curatorial thinking, and in particular, the importance of understanding</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to every neighborhood, speaking to residents directly and through written reports. It is this extra work, these reports, that makes the Biennale different from any other form of biennale. It is a form of cultural tourism, conducted on a large scale, which places a primary emphasis on the local as opposed to the global. It is a form of cultural colonialism, conducted on a large scale, that exploits the local and shelters from criticism those who would prefer to visit other cities. The reportage of the past is often rewritten and rewritten again by those who happen to be present at the moment. By adopting a public form, the reportage of the past is often accentuated in the presence of criticality, and the huge financial rewards for doing so. The Biennale also has a very particular form of cultural colonialism, and it is this that the Biennaleurs aim to disrupt. As biennales become more institutionalised, the need to regularly renew its forms becomes even more imperative.</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Adam Szymczyk, addressed the dispute between the biennial and the biennial with a particular focus on Venice. Venice itself was portrayed as a city in turmoil, its historic ban on opium having become a tool by which Italian and other colonial powers maintained their power in the city. Venice was depicted as an island of peace and quiet in the midst of a sea of violence and conflict. The Biennale was therefore forced to address this violence and conflict in a more fundamental way, and to do so, it was essential that its content and form be dictated by a consensus of cultural patrons. If it were an independent entity, it would have been able to respond to these complex social, economic and spatial factors through its own flexible criteria, rather than being constrained by the needs and preferences of a narrow elite of international visitors. In order to achieve these needs and preferences, the Biennale had to adopt a policy of in-depth research into its neighborhoods, travelling by public transport to key sites throughout the city and then reporting back to the Biennale organisers in Rome about its experience. Despite this, the Biennale organised major projects that directly addressed the tensions and anxieties of the city, from Reggio Emilia to Ponte City, from Basilica to Riverside Park, from Monte Cassino to St Mary’s Church, and from Benetton Square to Museo Mayor Maurizio Lecchieri. Yet even with these major projects, it is these cultural institutions that constitute the bulk of the Biennale’s content, with little or no consideration given to the peoples and groups inhabiting the city at large. How are these bodies of cultural tourists induced to visit a city? What is the relationship between the Biennale and its host communities? 	In this report, I attempt to answer these questions through multiple sites and multiple narratives, sketching the geography of</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a frequent topic of conversation in the curatorial roll. The Times has a fairly clear idea of who is and is not included in the city. It reads: ‘This is New York: a metropolis on a par with Berlin and Paris.’ It does not say where the ‘city’ is located. It calls the city the ‘metropolis’, and places the biennial at ‘the intersection of two of those metropolises’. It then proposes a number of possible sites for the art institution to establish operations, including in the city itself: ‘the West Village’ hotspot, ‘the Flatiron building, once known as the J. Paul Getty’ Museum’, and the much vaunted ‘Flatiron gallery’ which houses work from a number of artists including, but not limited to, Mark Miodownik, Eva Castringius, Norm Chan, Ted Hughes, Jon Trowbridge</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a recurrent feature of the cityscape. The word ‘biennial’ has been revived in France to designate collections of works from many localities, usually those inhabited by artists’ groups, which form what are sometimes called ‘biennials’. These are collections of works selected from many localities, and are a frequent feature of, and perhaps the object of, curatorial and artistic selection. The name is a corruption of biannées, those collection trips. The biannées of the twentieth century included collections from many localities. Biennials of the twenty-first century may well become collections from many localities. That is, the collections from the biennial of the twenty-first century may be anything but collections from the nineteenth century.The biennial as exhibitionary form is, I believe, here to stay. The art world, and indeed all art institutions, needs to learn how to work with and manage these collections. There is no magic bullet</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a recurring feature of the city that has a great many people describing as ‘near downtown’ or ‘the postindustrial zone’. The word ‘biennial’ has been invented simply to cover this urban phenomenon. So, we can add another set of words to the list of places where we can find, experience and speak about «near downtown’ and ‘the postindustrial zone’. We might also add another set of cities to the list, or add new languages to the list of cultures with whom we can communicate, ‘beyond the city’, if that is the right word.In the twentieth century, the biennial became so pervasive that it became a regular object of scholarly study and aesthetic perusal. The following century saw another one: a third of the volume of New York Times best-sellers on the subject of art and culture perused included a catalogue of biennials. In the twenty-first century, the biennial</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a mainstay of the biennial market in any city that is not a large US city. In the twentieth century, the biennial became the largest exhibitionary form in the world, accounting for almost a quarter of the value of its assets in a city. It is now one of the smallest, and is frequently one of the last. In the twenty-first century, the biennial is the largest exhibitionary form with a significant number of visitors, yet this does not necessarily translate into increased cultural exchange and value. In fact, increasing numbers of people only visit the museums and collections in their cities, and rarely do they visit the smaller, less visited galleries and museums. And this lack of cultural capital and exchange in and around the biennial may account for the recent sharp rise in cultural anxieties about the self-absorption of museums combined with the self-perpetuating model of the museum. The biennial is a major source of value for art institutions, and the museum as a cultural commodity</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a staple of the biennial visitor’s guide (2004). The city that the biennial visits is a dense and mobile landscape, constantly changing, and its streets are no longer the property of the cities but are in fact the collections of the biennial. This makes them conspicuous in different ways: their size, their number, the placement of their artworks, the number of displays, the placement of their cafés, the number of homeless, the number of street performers, the number of drug addicts, the number of children playing outside, etc. These observations and more are the results of endless data collection, mapping and capture, capturing and aggregating. In this way, biennials can be seen to be extensions of the city, and the city’s circulation and circulation is what makes it a biennial. It is not just that the art is collected and transported; its quality and quantity are also collected and transported. The biennial creates a double bind: it is also thought</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a recurrent and important element in the cultural landscape of New York City. They are a welcome addition to the archaeological record, providing important new perspectives and positions on an otherwise ongoing project of mapping and surveying that traces back to the Neolithic period (around 8000 BC to AD 800) and continuing to the end of the Pleistocene era (about 8000 BC to AD 1250). The dominant forms of urbanisation in the city during that time were: the ‘New York of the future’ that Maureen Orth calls its vernal zone; the ‘New Gatsby’ that was built on the ruins of the slave trade; the ‘Slumlord’s London district that shearkens back to the dark urban futures of the past; and the ‘Ghost Town’ that emerges whenever urban growth threatens to undermine the fragile urban fabric of the borough. All these developments were designed to fail – either literally or metaphorically. The city became a site for the</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a mainstay of the music festival circuit. They are a staple of the goth scene, where they are often cited as a factor in the emergence of ‘new gayness’. They are a frequent visitor to the American urban landscape, and have a presence in places such as Liverpool, where they are a significant and persistent presence. In Britain, they are sometimes referred to as the City of Open Secrets, where privacy can be very much compromised. In America, they are sometimes referred to as the Permaculture Movement.The biennial has long been the major international venue for the performance, much less the store of value that it is today. In the twentieth century, this was primarily the effect of the growth of international trade, commerce and logistics networks that saw enormous social benefits, but also entrench enormous bureaucracies capable of transforming the world through their administrative infrastructures. These networks made it possible for artists and curators to grow fabulously wealthy, but they also made it possible</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a regular feature of the financial and economic press, as well as in the articles of many national magazines and newspapers. We have, in fact, observed a curious tendency to write about cities that are rapidly becoming biennials, or are at least becoming ‘the figureheads of cities’ – a trend that is both a reflection of and threatens the older urban model. The phenomenon of the ‘city-within-a-city’ may be called the ‘neighborhood within the city’ – a sort of mythical hybrid of the old and new, the pre-digital, post-internet, and enmeshed in the city’s financial and ‘political terrain’. The idea that cities are populated centres is now widespread. We hear it from business leaders, judges, politicians, journalists, academics and every other position in between, and yet we rarely think about cities as fully human places. In almost every journal article, or every economic analysis, or</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a mainstay of the financial and cultural news outlets around the world. They have become the object of a system that looks on in fascination as a set of symbols, while at the same time portraying themogorifically as a diseased nation-state enterprise. The New York Times's James Randi famously declared that ‘once upon a time, in a city like New York’s, a biennial was the largest domestic art form’.1 This is no exaggeration. In Randi’s day, the ‘big three’ – the American gallery, the British and the French art world – controlled access to art by professional and curatorial alike. As a result, the biennial became the dominant exhibitionary form in the US and Europe.2  The sudden appearance of the biennial as a regularly-scheduled, somewhat-convenient exhibitionary form in the late twentieth century is one of the most striking episodes in this history. It is</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, which saw Manchester city councilors replaced by robots, is a good illustration of this. It is also a case study in what the biennial can and cannot achieve, and how the biennial is affected by the vagaries of economic, social and urban development. In the twentieth century, biennials became so dependent on the urban fabric that they could no longer be counted on to deliver anything more than tokenist interventions. In the twenty-first century, we can expect the contrary. This is the dynamic that will determine the contours of the art world’s relationship to and dependency on the biennial as a recurrent event. This dynamic will be interesting to see whether the biennial experiences within the curatorial agenda of art institutions, or whether it will find other, autonomous venues and use it’s considerable collections of art to its advantage.A few words on biennials’ place in the urban landscape. These appear in the New York Times every day, and are a recurring motif in the art world. The term comes from the journal Nature, in a section titled 'Biological Nominations'. In its modern sense, a biennial is a ‘collectors’ item, and a collectors’ clientele tends to be wealthy and urban. In its historical sense, a biennial is the point where a collection of objects (objects) comes together to form a habitation (biennial). In other words, a biennial is a collection of things, or more precisely, objects with habitation in mind. The collection as habit is a collection of places, and the collection as place is a collection of people. A biennial can be a collection of collections, but it is most often interested in the collection as collection of people, and especially when it comes to documenting and reporting on the lives of artists and their collections.Habit has been a recurring theme in the journal. It was a theme that was developed further by the publication of the journal</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/details/jfk-bulletarchive.html#.VxSsD... [7] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/4f5i914/the_bullet_archive_is_now_open_and_available_for... [8] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/4f5jq7c/the_bullet_archive_is_now_open_and_available_for... [9] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/4f6s8xo/the_bullet_archive_now_opens_full_....#.VxSsD... [10] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/4f6xoj/the_bullet_archive_now_opens_full</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/details/bulletarchive [7] See: https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/archive/wrl/archive/2014/07/13/... [8] See: https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/archive/wrl/archive/2014/07/13/... [9] See: https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/archive/wrl/archive/2014/07/13/... [10] See: https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/archive/wrl/archive/2014/07/13/... [11] See: https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/archive/wrl/archive/2014/07/13/... [12] See: https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-dyn/archive/wrl/</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/stream/bulletarchive... [7] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [8] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [9] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [10] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [11] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [12] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [13</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/details/bulletarchive [7] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [8] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [9] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [10] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [11] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [12] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [13]</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/details/bulletarchive.html [7] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [8] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [9] https://www.academia.edu/358324/Bullet_series_of_fourteen_pages.html?... [10] See: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mark_Lenglen&lt;|endoftext|&gt;Oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh ohOh oh oh oh oh ohOh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh ohWell, you know, I’m not the one you want messing with.You know what I mean?You want me to stop messing with your stuff?Oh oh oh oh oh oh oh ohOh oh oh</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/details/bulletarchive.html#.VFIuE... [7] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [8] See: https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../e7cf8fbd18... [9] See: https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../e7cf8fbd18... [10] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [11] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [12] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t...</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/stream/bulletarchive... [7] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/The_Donald... (accessed July 2018). [8] See also: https://www.theguardian.com/public_... (accessed September 2018). [9] See: https://www.theguardian.com/public_... (accessed November 2018). [10] See: https://www.theguardian.com/public_... (accessed January 2019). [11] See: https://www.theguardian.com/public_... (accessed March 2018). [12] See: https://www.theguardian.com/public_... (accessed June 2018). [13] See: https://www.theguardian.com/public_... (accessed November 2018). [14] https://www.theguardian.com/public_... (accessed August 2018). [15</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/details/bulletarchive [7] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/6b36... [8] https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/6b36... [9] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/6b36... [10] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/6b36... [11] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/6b36... [12] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/6b36... [13] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/6b36... [14] See: https://www.reddit.com/r/glasgow/comments/6b36... [15] See:</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/details/bulletarchive [7] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [8] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [9] See: https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_serial_abduction_... [10] See: https://archive.org/details/abduction/ [11] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [12] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [13] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-</text>
    <text>curated by an AI  [1] https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=kccVK_m9yY-E&amp;list=PLGhDuaAdQkCA6kC1xmRo8hY92ZeL_dEadOnbI#t=360 [2] https://www.instagram.com/p/BOQwC-bNlI.../.6038557072.../?hl=enMUL [3] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [4] https://medium.com/@alexander_kurz.../#/.../e7cf8fbd18... [5] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [6] See: https://archive.org/stream/bulletarchive/1441/1441... [7] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [8] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [9] https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [10] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [11] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-t... [12] See: https://www.wired.com/2014/07/why-is-the-bullet-archive-in-</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production.
    <text>future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production. And so, as a consequence, art went from being seen as a social process to one marked by a standardized form of social consumption.  	Instead of a limited resource, the social became a source of endless new resources. And so, art became conscious of its own function, conscious of what it could and should do. It began to ask, who has the right to speak?  1  	Tim R. McVicar and Christian Körner, ‘On the use of icons in the public sphere: a critical survey’, in  	Thinking about Publics, edited by McVicar and Körner, pp.109–23. 2  John A. Church and Neil J. White, ‘Iconoclasts and monoliths: archaeological and evolutionary perspectives on iconoclastic art’, in  	Thinking About Art, edited by Church and White, p.26. 3  Ibid., p.</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production. And so, art today manages to connect with audiences that are complex enough to need to be exposed to a range of different aesthetic possibilities, yet others less so. But this capacity to connect is itself constrained. Curators, artists and arts professionals today expect a certain rigour from art, and are therefore expected to have a certain knowledge of art’ social life. As a curator, I’m acutely aware that some people find my work disturbing. I’m acutely aware that some people find my work sexy. But what I tend to do is engage those people, trying to understand their perspective, finding common ground, understanding that perhaps we have in common, and so forth. These kinds of capacities are extraordinarily rare in today’s culture, but are quite common in older cultural forms. Thousands of years ago, when human evolution first started, artists, rhetoricians and poets found common ground with audiences who were different from themselves. Today, many people would agree, we’</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production. And so, as a consequence, art today dominates not only social and political life but also critical thinking.  	Thinking critically about our social circumstances, how we inhabit social space, who is situated in society, how we live our lives, and how we create meaning and social change requires critical skills and imagination. It does not, however, inherently foster a place or take a position, nor does it represent an ideal or idealised state of existence. It requires imagination, an openness to new experiences and orientations, an ability to imagine new ways of interacting with the world, and a willingness to question old assumptions and prejudices.     1. This is a quote from Slavs and Tatarské poet Olga Kurylenko. Trans. Elke Waugh. Begyörrhon bade Meehan a baza, ye zhigur chenenge, vernon’s Chinese: a legacy of imperial whimsy. </text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production. Art today is not just interested in the aestheticisation of social phenomena; its function today is an ethical one too. It needs to think about what kinds of ethics are at stake in social phenomena, and so it functions out of a set of formalised norms and values, whose values we collectively construct through our social interactions.  	But how do we imagine an ethical form of art? How do we imagine a more nuanced engagement with the world when we collectively collectively collectively engage in contributing to it? 	This is where the  	design paradigm comes into play. 	It is no exaggeration to suggest that the curatorial has transformed art’s social function since the 1980s. We see this in the increased number of arts organizations, the proliferation of regional arts centers, and contemporary art’s focus on larger cultural narratives. We also see it in the growing numbers of artists who are not artists per se but rather seek to engage with the ways in which art creates social change</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production. And so, in an effort to understand and perhaps to transcend this conceptual limit, art works that may become socially useful, socially constitutive and socially transformative in their own right. Theoretical and artistic explorers, and playful artists alike, have a critical place in art today. And there are many ways to read this. Trustworthy critics, like Richard Hollis, have done just that, articulating in their writing the ways in which art today struggles to organize social life, to articulate clearly the politics of art today, and to stomach the consequences of its social consumption.Art today is a social process, a social media phenomenon notwithstanding, and as such it participates in a complex set of shared and interrelated systems. It is, in short, a system that can sustain it, generate new creative forms and engage new audiences. And so, as an art form, it is subject to the vagaries of some of its actors, including, but not limited to, new technological paradigms,</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production. The capacity for art to change social outcomes was seen as the capacity of the social, and not the other way around. This is why, in the 1980s, the art world responded so aggressively to the social through art's social function: it was seen as the essential social medium through which a critical understanding of culture was possible. This is why, fifty years later, so many art exhibitions still engage with the social, and remain committed to the notion that, within the art world, there’s always a lively, sometimes heated debate about whether the art is good and the social situation, and whether the art is really that which can change social outcomes.  	That capacity for social change was needed in order to sustain the art form, and so the social was made a primary object of enquiry, and so the art was made social. And so, while the art form itself has variously claimed different aspects, and has in fact been criticised for different ones, its essential social function</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production. What is meant by ‘critical imagination’ is a social necessity, something that was above all of the common good. And so, while the interface may be a tool, it comes to represent a social relation that is complex and unpredictable, that is fragile and unstable. It is a mechanism that is designed to be abused, malleable and corrupted by the conditions of our time, yet it also holds the potential for being a force for good. 	Art therefore emerged as a counterweight to the social and critical capacities of the interface, which was understood by many in the curatorial turn. It is, in other words, able to embed its own logic and assumptions within the interface, and so it can be seen to be both useful and constituting a function of the time. But in this respect, not all interfaces are created equal. The function of the interface today is to connect and converse with users; its primary purpose is to be used by a small cadre of users</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production. And so, contemporary art developed the capacity for design precisely because it had to. It had to adopt a particular, universal and universalised conception of its own humanity in order to be considered part of the universalisable horizon. And so, the more we admired and admired the art, the more we wanted it to be like us, and so the more we had to ask ourselves and others: what is this art that we admire? How could it be art if it isn’t? And the more we couldn’t find a solution to this dilemma in art, or in art in general, the more we wanted to be artists and thinkers and so on. The more we were drawn into the art/craft/craft culture/intelligent design vortex, the more isolated and alienated we became. The more isolated and alienated we became, the less likely we were to develop other cultures or find meaning in them. The more art there is to admire, the less art there is to understand.</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production. And so, while the designers of the social interface would see art as a tool, they also understood that, at the same time, the art had to be utilized in ways that were purposeful and calculated. For instance, if the social interface is an ever-present set of behaviours, then art has to be creative in how it is used, and so art has to be contextual. But if the social interface is a fiction, then art has to be creative in how it is used, and art has to be everywhere at the same time.  	If the social interface is a giant computer that you plug into a wall, and the wall is a giant computer that you plug into a city, then the social interface is a zone in itself, a complete and utter absence of meaning and purpose. It is only there because so many people have plugged in, and are now required by law to carry it around in their pockets (or coats, in the case of super-computers).</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, not to mention the fact that, at the time, the curatorial move was one of the few ways to be seen as part of the social good. Should curatorial forms continue to function as a social function (and show interest in social-cultural forms), new curatorial forms will have to be forged. And this is why art forms are creative in their own ways, creative in their willingness to engage audiences outside the ivory towers and museums. They’re more accessible, more contextual, more human. But they also have to be creative in their consumption. Otherwise, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface. And so, the art is but a tool, a set of tools, and an interface.  	So, art in its social complexity demanded a specialized critical form, a critical imagination, and so art would develop critical capacities. But while art could theoretically achieve this, its capacity for design came standardised in all its social production. And so, the social function of art was seen as a fundamentally different kind of function, one that was above all concerned with the welfare of its fellow citizens. But this was seen as inherently republican, and therefore inherently anti-intellectual. And so, art practice developed a critical character, and the critical imagination was then seen as the art form's answer to the social, and particularly the moral, question. And so, we can say that the critical mass of artists who came out of the turn of events around art and culture in the 1970s and 1980s was more concerned with the work of the social than the artist. And so, the critical mass of contemporary artists I think have a very different conception of what art is and how it is produced. 	And this is why, as a poet, I find the way in which the social is now seen to be a much more significant part of what it means to be an artist. Because the social is now seen to be what really</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of archival and historical evidence to tell a story that encompasses a wide range of social, economic and political changes. It was a novel in that it was based on a single event, but it was much more concerned with the structural causes of the crisis than the symptom(s) of it. The novel focuses on the ways in which a culture of warriors, warriors-in-waiting, is rapidly eroding away at a planetary scale. Its characters are not just metaphorically pointing to a better future but actually envisioning what that future might be like, in the form of a rapidly expanding and diversifying Middle-Eastern empire. 	Domain Specific Knowledge ends on a hopeful note when it describes a future in which humans are no longer the dominant species on Earth, but instead turn to nature for much of their sustenance. This is echoed in the fictional bacterium, which ends up on a moon, although the exact trajectory and nature of this return are left ambiguous. 	Domain Specific Knowledge begins</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of archival material and employing a range of imaginative and powerful design concepts. One of the most widely adopted design tropes of the time was the  	Hybrid Device, a small block of alternating lithium-ion cells and a capacitor bank installed in a pole within the back of a compact car. The idea was that, as the battery was depleted, the rotational speed of the block significantly slowed, mimicking the effect of a battery pack as a pressure-sensing surface. At its core was the maxim ‘two or more batteries do more than enough to power a small car’. 	Domain Specific Knowledge provided an alternative to this seemingly impossible-to-fulfill potential, arguing that a car should have at least one battery, with additional storage for fast charging and recharging. 	Domain Specific Knowledge was originally published in 1982 and is the sequel to  	Design at a World Scale and in 1988 was republished with permission from the Center for Working Life at Columbia</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of archival and historical materials to tell a story that encompassed a broad range of voices and audiences. In particular, the authors used archival materials to tell the story of the City of Culture, a postindustrial hub of the 1980s and a centre of Marxist pedagogy. The project was part of a ‘collectively salvaged, worker’s city’ project that was initiated in 1984 by the Mondragon Community Land Trust and Reclaim the Mural movement.1 	Domain Specific Knowledge ‘s focus on the 1980s is informed by a wealth of archival and historical materials that were seized upon by the media during the 1990s cultural crash and subsequent educational witch-hunt. 	Whereas the archival materials seized during the 1990s ‘found their way into many publishers' best-sellers’, the materials seized during the ‘current cultural slump’ – a period that includes the 2000 census – are a literary disaster. Although the media portray</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of archival material and employing a range of metaphors and behavioural observations to examine the conditions of labour and institutional life in the social, economic and political domains following the war. Conceptually speaking, these included not only the social but also the political and institutional changes that followed the war, which culminated in the emergence of a newly independent Uzbekistan in the late 1980s. 	Domain Specific Knowledge brought out the latent sexism and classism that were latent in the historical social-psychological frameworks that came about in the wake of the war, and also on the question of nationhood and territoriality. It also stressed the fact that, during the post-war period, the logic of nation building was re-constituted through the need to defend against potential threats to national identity. The institutional memory that came about as a direct result of the war is said to have been a major factor in creating the conditions for the emergence of post-national, ethno-centric identities. 	Domain Specific Knowledge</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of archival and documentary evidence to make the case that was both personal and political in nature. Drawing upon his own experience as a journalist, Keefe’s account follows the trail of the Soviet Union’s invasion and occupation of Afghanistan, from 1959 to 1989. 	Domain Specific Knowledge builds on previous work by examining the multiple dimensions of the Russian empire’s social and political construction, using the example of Afghanistan as an example of a country that was left to decay as a result of the imperial machine. Drawing on his research and reporting, the author takes the reader on a tour of the devastated landscape of Afghanistan, which is contrasted with the pristine landscape of British colonial rule in Afghanistan, which is contrasted with the pristine landscape of postcolonial India, drawing comparisons between the two. 	The biennial format allows the publication of multiple versions of the same work within a short period of time, which can be seen as apropos of the same. This 	sequence of publishing over</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of archival material, including depositions, diaries, transcripts, pamphlets, articles, aerial photographs, surveillance footage, construction materials, military manuals, spy-reports, diplomatic cables and more. It gathered together the stories of hundreds of participants and transformed their recollections into comprehensible categories. 	Domain Specific Knowledge 	[i] The book includes an index, the text of the chapter, a bibliography and the end result is a shared set of concepts, terms and practices. 	[ii] Hardt and Keefe’s account differs markedly from that of Brzezinski and Ledermani, who were the authors of the now standard histories of the Cold War. 	[iii] Brzezinski and Ledermani write that the model they used to analyze and conceptualize the Cold War was the ‘United Front’ – a front of alliances, a not-so-subtle critique of the post-war period in which the inter</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of archival, documentary and personal documents to tell a story that encompassed a nation, a city, an economy, a language and a sense of place. [1] See http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/html/1207/marxists_right_to_learn.html#sthash.JlgTl.pAuR1.dpuf.dpuf.2000.x.  x  http://www.marxists.org/reference/archive/html/1207/marxists_right_to_learn.html#sthash.JlgTl.pAuR1.dpuf.dpuf.2000.x. [2] The term ‘digital double edge sword’ refers to a type of multipurpose military and surveillance toolkit designed specifically for the purposes of clandestine recording and hacking. It was developed by US Department of Defense and</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of archival material and drawing upon fascinating real-life happenings in Afghanistan. Drawing on his own experiences in Afghanistan, Afghanistan’s capital of Christendom, and later Kabul, where he served as a reporter for The New York Times, Michael Hardt reflected on the invasion of Afghanistan and the subsequent civil war that erupted there, and the formation of what he called ‘the Satanic Coalition’ – a name that resonated with the imperial intentions of the United States and British Empire. The coalition, he wrote, would spread terror throughout the world and establish a single global totalitarian regime. ‘The empire that cannot be destroyed … is born again … by the blood of innocents … in the streets’, he intoned, using the rallying cry of that era to call into question the very foundations of modern democracy. 	Domain Specific Knowledge ‘s’ perspective is further evidenced in the group’s self-branding as a hybrid breed of resistance – a hybrid</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of archival, documentary and historical evidence to tell a story that encompasses both the defeated and the defeated ‘home side’ – a land, a culture, a language and an empire. Hardt and Keefe’s account followed the logic of empire building, placing the West in direct conflict with itself, while weaving in historical and contemporary reflections on colonialism and racialisedness. 	In writing about the 1980s and early 1990s, Keefe and Hardt both employed the term ‘complexity’ to describe the new technological revolutions that were reshaping both global and local contexts. Complexity was seen as a resource superior to other elements of the technological landscape – a term that referred to the ability to sustain life in massive quantities, rather than the raw material goods and services of technology.] 	In a 2007 essay in Science, Stephen G. Ceci takes up the question of race and technology in an attempt to reconcile the disparate elements of the ecological and technological systems that he</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by a board of directors predominantly made up of former Citigroup executives, academics, corporate lawyers and others with a stranglehold on the financial sector. 	Domain Specific Knowledge,  	Dynamics of Information (1972). 	Domain Specific Knowledge is the second book in Michael Hardt and Ronald Keefe’s original work, published in 1984, that examined the post-war period and the emergence of complex social and political  	forms. Hardt and Keefe’s account, based on archival documents, was based on a single event – the U.S. invasion of Afghanistan – but they were careful to weave a complex web of events and shifting of vantage points into a single coherent narrative. This caution was a deliberate act of writing – deliberate in the sense that it was almost as if the characters were reading from different sides of the same coin. 	Domain Specific Knowledge offered a critical perspective on the events of that period, drawing upon a wealth of archival documents and analyzing the ways in which the war was perceived and interpreted. The authors clearly intended this work to stand alongside the archival materials and historical accounts they employed, rather than being the authoritative texts on a given issue. 	Domain Specific Knowledge ‘seeks to provide a more accurate and complete conception of the complex web of influences shaping contemporary life on earth than any account offered by individual or collective memory; as a result, it is both more flexible and more malleable than its author’s will would suggest or allow.’[5] This statement by the historian James Howard Kunstler echoes many of the sentiments of the character in Ridley Scott’s film Blade Runner (1982), a cyberpunk pre-occupation with the threats posed by advanced artificial intelligences and the social consequences of that technology’s use of images and data across a social interface. [6] See, for example, Katherine Graham Gleeson,  	</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the fact that this was all predicted by abstract, numerical models that proliferated in the wake of the First World War. In other words, the problems of our time – the problems that were supposed to be solved by abstract, mathematical models – are complex, nuanced and point individuals. You need to be able to spot the individual pieces, and to recognise when you have been conned by the same system of rules and figures that are used to create the fantastical worlds we inhabit. As the saying goes, ‘If you can afford it, do it;’.[11]The point is that, for many of us, the contours of the global system that we inhabit still represent a partial picture. The systems that we inhabit are complex, and we don’t see them as representing the totality of what is going on. The cultural production of the machine is one that attempts to make the world we live in into something we haven’t fully internalised. The cultural</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the fact that these means exist because of the contemporary condition, an analysis of which can be found in David Harvey’s book The End of Modernity (2009). Harvey writes: ‘Modernity’ is a condition that can no longer be accepted, and which is being reversed all over the world.’ But here’s the rub: the modern condition is all of these things, and more. It exists in its imperfect but pervasive form because of incipient capitalism, and because of its own immiseration.’[11] And here, then, is where we find ourselves, a few years later, in the present moment. There’s the palpable immiseration of the modern condition, the fact of its becoming more and more like any other, as if this were some sort of terminal phase in which we must all strive to rectify. We hear the cries of pain and suffering, we see the images of children malnour</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the fact that the authorities did nothing to stop the attacks. The heroic activism of artists like Damien Hirst, M'Nique Durel, Patti Scialfa, Joana Figueiredo, and many others only serves to highlight the fact that the social totality is not that simple, that forms of social organisation are much more variable and dynamic, and that much more needs to be said. And here is where the political potential of the social becomes relevant. It is easy to identify the particular stories that are being told, to identify the specific actors involved, but what we fail to see is the myriad ways in which complicity is entwined with and generates the social. And this is where we find ourselves, mired in our own narratives and flavours of complicity. We tend to think of the large-scale societal processes that lead to and include collaboration, but what we lack in terms of concrete concrete action, we more than make up for in the</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the fact that artistes and creatives were quick to exploit the moment. This is an important distinction to draw, because the media is always making room for another interpretation. It is always quick to paint a picture that conforms to a prescribed narrative, but this only makes sense if there is some fundamental ideological underpinning of the narrative that is in conflict with the real world. For example, the mainstream media narrative about the Charlie Hebdo massacre exploited a historical reference to the role of Jewish artists in promoting a certain strain of capitalism in Paris: when Max Horkheimer published his Nuremberg Apparation in 1950, he invoked the work of Otto Ernst, the Jewish artist who had produced the first Zionist movement posters, in an attempt to justify the criminalisation of criticism of the Jews. Max Horkheimer was a neo-fascist who advocated a return to pre-Naqshbandi rule in Palestine and the Arab countries, and he articulated these</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the fact that this was all predicted by experts on globalisation and architecture. The dire warnings of a Center for Disease Control and Centre National de Sécurité de Paris seem to be more grounded in experience and intuition than evidence or science. The problem with this account, of course, is that it is all experiencing: quantifying and documenting everything is a necessity in the face of the spectacle. But what Foucalt was attempting to do here was quite a different thing. He was attempting to move the symbolic fixation of the social back towards the historical and natural. He was attempting to initiate a dialogue between the social and the natural, between metaphor and reality.In other words, he was trying to create a space for what might become a contemporaneous contemporaneousness. This is what artists and artists' early interventions in the social did in the tradition of Meshing, S.W. Thacker, </text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the fact that artists were forced to choose between their feelings about the violence and the violence-producing potential of their work and their jobs. The consequences for artists, and certainly for those in power, are often treated with a mixture of apathy and hostility. But Foucalt wasn’t apathetic; he actively sought to imagine a future in which art would seek to intervene in the underlying causes of the violence in order to produce a more just future. Rather, he sought to imagine a world in which art could actively contribute to creating a more just future through what he described as ‘practical interfacing’.[11]And here we can observe one of the central ambiguities of modernity: the capacity of artists to impact change in a material world. This isn’t to suggest that there isn’t some relevance here for artists to consider: modernity is a dynamic and variable world with ever more material entwined systems that</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the fact that these means of making sense are being deployed by governments to tackle perceived perceived  	ethnocentrism and other forms of extremism. But Foucalt wasn’t so easily pinned down as a journalist, writer or theorist on the contemporary condition of artistic practice and media. He had to find his place in a world that didn’t see art as something that it’s possible to create value from, and wanted to make sure that the means that he used to produce a published article wasn’t employed to create a world in which to live in. Thankfully, he had a collaborator - a brilliant artist and a scholar of aesthetics, Jean Paul Sartre who would go on to found a center for critical theory and Foucalt’s Studies at the Sorbonne in Paris. And Sartre would have plenty to say about the role of art as a mediator of contradictory values, processes and concerns, about the limits of power and</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the fact that these means exist whether or not we are Muslim. But this disconnection isn’t necessarily a Western one; Islam is not a religious doctrine and the notion of fundamentalism is not some kind of a magical elixir. On the contrary, Islam requires us to be vigilant against what it perceives as creeping Christianity-influenced Islamification. When we start treating the emergence of modernity as essentially connected to the emergence of modernity’s defining event, Islam, as something fundamentally different from the way in which we are organising ourselves and our lives. How do we start thinking about the ways in which our obsession with the modern and technocratic modernity is actually organising our societies in relation to one another? How do we begin to imagine a future where the social is not defined by the social but rather the other? What are the conditions that would enable us to imagine such a future?  [1] See: http://www.global</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the fact that the host of the attacks is a country – France is a country, after all – that produces a lot of its news, commentary and data (look it up) through that particular industry it has created.But this ‘representational’ reading of events doesn’t capture the moment. It is important to note that the mainstream media isn’t telling a story; it is telling a set of beliefs. And while these beliefs may differ from those held by the user of the site, they are all built on the foundation of the same bedrock of ideas. The difference is that the user doesn’t hold onto those beliefs in the way that the media does. Asking users to affirm or deny certain things is a new thing in the web browser, but it is a new thing in the user’s right to do so.In fact, in the aftermath of the Paris attacks, many in the web browser community started to rethink how the web should be</text>
    <text>disastrous machine curated by the global capitalist market]…the pedagogical production of the machine is the production of complicity.’[10] And this complicity, insofar as it is mediated (real or imagined to be real) through the media of the spectacle, is what Foucalt was trying to address. By the end of his book, he reached a point where he could have continued to speak about the role of the artist as an artist and the machine, but the machine had already done enough damage to bother pursuing that line of thought further. Instead, he wrote, the real challenge was to become aware of the process of complicity and how it affected your perception of the world.You see this in the way in which the media reports on the attacks in Paris. The mainstream media tends to present the events as fundamentally connected to fundamental notions of the contemporary condition: terrorism and its concomitant means of making sense of the world as messy and disordered, but also the fact that these means exist regardless of one’s political leanings or position in society. But Foucalt wasn’t just trying to do good in the world; he was trying to make a better world. In that sense, he was making something that would be recognisable to generations to come. He aimed to do this through what he called ‘the archipelago’ – a name that suggests a great deal about the kinds of organisational arrangements that modern global capitalism relies on, but also about the relations of domination that exist between nations.Foucalt’s notion of the archipelago wasn’t just an idea in general terms; it was also an assertion about the relations of power that exist between nation-states and their peoples.  And indeed, the notion that the media of the spectacle is actually organising reality is something that is deeply rooted in the historical practices of nation-states.  As James Howard Kunstler once wrote</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
