<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York:
    <text>biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Vintage, 1965), p. 23. [iv] Goldwater, op. cit., p. xiii. [v] Goldwater, op. cit., p. x. [vi] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 12. [vii] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 13. [viii] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 14. [ix] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 17. [x] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 10. [xi] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 40. [xii] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 41. [xiii] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 42. [xiv] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 44. [xv] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 46. [xvi] </text>
    <text>biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Vintage, 1990), p. 69. [iv] Goldman, op. cit., p. 6. [v] Goldman, op. cit., p. 4. [vi] Goldman, op. cit., p. 7. [vii] Richard Haass,  	A Problem of Ideas: On the Emergence of Antinomies (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2003), p. 43. [viii] Goldman, op. cit., p. 11. [ix] William Julius Wilson,  	The Problem of Religions: On the Emergence of Antinomies (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2003), p. 5. [x] William Julius Wilson,  	The Virtue of Self: On the Virtue of English Culture (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1995), p. 2. [xi] William Julius Wilson,  	The</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Columbia University Press, 1989), p. xiii. [iv] Le Notre’s, The Faubourg St. Maurice,  	The Faubourg St. Maurice, Paris, 1887, p. 17. [v] Goldman, op. cit., p. 5. [vi] Goldman, op. cit., p. 6. [vii] Goldman, op. cit., p. 7. [viii] Goldman, op. cit., p. 16. [ix] Rethinking American Culture: Essays on the Crisis of Literary Criticism, Vol. 4, No. 2 (Fall, 2008), p. 4. [x] Joseph Beuys,  	The Crisis of Historicity (New York: Oxford University Press, 1995), p. 15. [xi] Goldman, op. cit., p. 9. [xii]</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Penguin, 1976), p. 39. [iv] Metternich, op. cit., p. 20. [v] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 5. [vi] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 6. [vii] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 6. [viii] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 6. [ix] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 7. [x] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 7. [xi] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 8. [xii] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 8. [xiii] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 9. [xiv] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 10. [xv] Goldwater, op. cit., p. 10. [xvi] </text>
    <text>biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Penguin, 1972), p. 111. [iv] John Berger, ‘The Illusion of Immortality’, in The Literary Imagination of Søren Kierkegaard, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Penguin, 1993), p. 179. [v] Søren Kierkegaard, Letter to a Friend (1790), chapter ‘Of Sorrow’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Penguin, 1973), p. 130. [vi] Søren Kierkegaard, Letter to a Friend, chapter ‘Of Anger’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Penguin, 1993), p. 130. [vii] Søren Kierkegaard, Letter to a Friend, chapter ‘Of Pleasure’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Penguin, 1973), p. 134. [</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Vintage, 1971), p. 34. [iv] John Berger,  	Signets: On the Psychology of Emotions (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2012), p. 3. [v] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Vintage, 1971), p. 10. [vi] John Berger,  	Signets (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 1972), p. 2. [vii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Vintage, 1971), p. 2. [viii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Coll</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Columbia University Press, 1978), p. 22. [iv] James Howard Kunstler,  	Postmodernism: A Conceptually Simple and Empirically More Perplexing Theory (London and New York: Routledge, 1999), p. 3. [v] Karl Popper, ‘On Envy’, in Reflections on the Origins of Our Ideas, Vol. 2, Part 2 (1926–27), p. 103. [vi] Katharine Graham Kerr, ‘The Crisis of Modernity: Fifteen Stages’,  	Postmodern: Essays on the Origins of Our Ideas, Vol. 2, Pg. 2, In Search of (New York: Vintage, 1984), p. 33. [vii] Richard Florida, ‘Envy or Necessity?’,  	Signets, Vol. 1, No. 1 (February, 1970), p</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Penguin, 1988), p. 137. [iv] William James, ‘The Intellectual Controversy of Modern Times’, 1789 (1937), p. 185. [v] James Howard Kunstler,  	The Art of Not Being Governed: An Inquiry into the Cause of Modern Art (New York: Columbia University Press, 1999). [vi] James Howard Kunstler,  	The Power Elite: How Contracting Class Consciousness is Transforming the World (New York: Columbia University Press, 2010), p. 3. [vii] David Harvey,  	The Art of Not Being Governed: An Inquiry into the Cause of Modern Art (New York: Columbia University Press, 1999), p. 3.[viii] William James, ‘On the Question of Envy’, in Essays in the Selected Writings of David Harvey, Volume 2: James Howard Kunstler (ed</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Columbia University Press, 1967), p. 110. [iv] Kierkegaard, ‘The Fall’, in The Concept of Anxiety, p. xiv. [v] Goldman Sachs, ‘The Physical Biennale: A Documenta 14 Method'?, 2014, http://www.goldmansachs.com/articles/2014/09/the-physical-biennale-a-documenta-14-method-martin-wagon-2017.html, accessed 10 June 2017. [vi] Goldman Sachs, ‘The Physical Biennale: A Documenta 14 Method’, 2014, http://www.goldmansachs.com/articles/2014/09/the-physical-biennale-a-documenta-14-method, accessed 10 June 2017.[v] Goldman Sachs, ‘The Physical Biennale: A Documenta 14 Method’,</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, to tackle the long-standing but still unresolved question of what it means to be a ‘monumental cultural hub’. 	[i] In the 1970s, the Museum of Contemporary Art in New York acquired the Copacabana Tower, the oldest continuously inhabited building in the world. The Museum of Contemporary Art in New York published an account of the tower’s history in the book Things Fall Apart: Crisis, Censorship, and the Cultural Imperative of Modernity in the Age of Intangible Assets (1974). 	[ii] Buckminster Fuller,  	Signets, the Symbol or Message: On the Geographies of Modern Religions (New York: Oxford University Press, 2011), p. 27. [iii] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety (1887), chapter ‘Of Envy’ in The Concept of Anxiety, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Columbia University Press, 1999), p. 31. [iv] Johannesburg Economic Travelogue, Issue #1 (2014), p. 1. [v] William James, The Intellectuals, trans. Stefan Collini (New York: Columbia University Press, 1972), p. 9. [vi] James, The Intellectuals, p. 4. [vii] James, The Intellectuals, p. 4. [viii] James, The Intellectuals, p. 17. [ix] James, The Intellectuals, p. 18. [x] James, The Intellectuals, p. 19. [xi] James, The Intellectuals, p. 24. [xii] James, The Intellectuals, p. 24. [xiii] James, The Intellectuals, p. 26. [xiv] James, The Intellectuals, p. 31. [xv] James</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed the sharing economy to thrive: the over-emphasis on user experience, the creation of sharing opportunities, and the emergence of disruptive technologies. How do we imagine a future where art is more present and contemporary social forms are more evident? How might the sharing economy help us achieve this new social form? 	One possibility is the use of blockchain technology to record and trace every aspect of activity – deeds, contracts, ownership – in a shared and irreversible way. This new type of technology makes it impossible to copy or delete deeds, contracts, and records, ensuring that such data cannot be forged or tampered with. It also allows for the tracking and recording of individuals – individuals ‘entity records’ – in a data capture and storage environment. So far, so normal. But what does this mean in practice? For instance, think of the sharing economy as allowing for the creation of autonomous agencies – self-propelling private agencies – that can do incredible things with the scarce public resources of the</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed for the sharing economy to happen. The sharing economy has created new kinds of exploitation and has exacerbated old kinds of exploitation.But what does the sharing economy do in its place? Time to look at that question from different perspectives. The sharing economy is a technology that creates opportunities for those who adopt it, and it’s also a way of linking people’s identities and cultures. But what is it that makes us human? What makes us tick? How do we become what others call ‘smart enough’ to be taken into technological society? One answer to these questions is: culture. Cultural capital is the shared production of knowledge produced and transmitted between people. It is a production that is constantly (very slowly, actually) built up, which is a good thing, because in the sharing economy, the future is always somewhere between the past and the present. This is what the term culture implies. But what does it actually mean? The answer is complicated. There are different kinds of</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed for the sharing economy to happen: the overproduction of art goods, the proliferation of biennials, the proliferation of curators, the proliferation of social events and so forth.All of these developments are, of course, inevitably connected to the web being built around the art world. But there’s another condition that has been playing a much larger role in our society: the condition of racial and urban fragility. The sharing economy has certainly allowed artists to create urban alternatives that are very different from the environments they grew up in, but it’s also allowed artists to participate in a new form of collective work that tends to dominate the social and cultural life of large communities. In many ways, this is a much more potent form of artistic expression than the art world would ever allow for, since it’s far more visible and powerful, and the social dynamics that result from it are much more visibly visible and promoted than those produced by the art world. But the fragility of</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed for the sharing economy to flourish: the over-arching assumption of transparency, the elimination of borders, the reduction of bureaucratic infrastructures, the elimination of legal restrictions, the elimination of political restrictions and so forth. These conditions are difficult to quantify, and it’s easy to become cynical about the extent to which the sharing economy is actually about profiteering from the public sector, and giving the appearance of sharing when – as in the case of Airbnb – there’s a clear preference for one kind of sharing over another. It’s true that in the context of the sharing economy, things that are considered public resources are being shared out – that is, given enough power, when used responsibly can be shared. But this is just the beginning of things to come. The sharing economy has made it possible for services to establish their own clear boundaries, and thereby create mutually exclusive practices that neither side wishes to be associated with. There are signs that this is already happening in some</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed the sharing economy to flourish.The sharing economy has created huge opportunities for corporate profits, but has also created huge social consequences as well. Some of the social costs are very difficult to quantify; for example, the fact that in many cities, including in New York, homelessness is a problem that affects people’s every move. But there are huge numbers of people who are housed and who are either on the move or on vacation or have families or sick leave or whatever it is that they’re working towards and so they’re constantly on the move, whether they’re employed or not and so on. This creates a huge number of potential jobs for sharing economy workers, but also huge numbers of jobs for artists who work in the sharing economy, because sharing economy workers tend to have access to capital at a very rapid rate – capital that they could use immediately in order to begin sharing – which in turn boosts the productivity of the sharing economy as a whole. The sharing economy is</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed for the sharing economy to thrive.But what are the checks and balances? And how do we create them?At the moment, we have to ask ourselves, what are the conditions that have allowed for the sharing economy to thrive in the first place? And then we have to ask, can we actually abolish some of the contradictions inherent in the current political and economic system? What do you call a system that exploits the commons, oppresses people and continually makes assumptions about us? And what do you call a system that creates the conditions for the sharing economy to flourish?I don’t think that there can be a single correct answer to this. There are always going to be different kinds of sharing, depending on where you are and who you’re with. For me, when I think of sharing, I’m thinking about the transformative power of a shared space, of a shared culture, of a shared meal. It’s not just about who gets to eat what.</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed for the sharing economy to flourish: the moral hazard, the diffuse nature of the commons, the sharing economy’s propensity for sharing – all of these things are critical to creating the preconditions for a system that thrives on top of them.The sharing economy is creating preconditions for a different kind of social ecology. It’s creating a kind of social ecology that isn’t beholden to the power structures that produce and construct wealth in the world we inhabit. It’s creating a social ecology that doesn’t demand a communal organisation or a shared resource from the state. It’s creating a social ecology that is driven by people rather than by the state, and it’s doing so in large part through the work of artists, curators, artists’ assistants and other artists’ collaborators. While it’s true that many of these professions are entry-level and don’t require a postgraduate degree to enter</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed the sharing economy to thrive: the overabundance of cheap labour, the inefficiency of many public resources, the destruction of traditional art forms, etc.Art and design have a crucial place in the ecology of our urbanisation, but it’s clear that much more is being done to enrich the artworld than is being said about the city. There is a dearth of curators, arts administrators and cultural geographers who are either specialists in a particular field of art or have a particular institutional interest in urban development, but few who have a critical perspective on the city as a whole. This disconnect has been a major barrier to the sharing economy potentially taking root in our cities. There is a clear opportunity for the sharing economy to reclaim lost but significant institutional value through its critique of bureaucracies and vested interests. However, the sharing economy is experiencing a major crisis of legitimacy at the moment, which is creating a backlash against any new growth opportunities for the sector. The share of startups and</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed the sharing economy to thrive: the over-arching assumption that people have no rights; the real power being exercised through data; and the proliferation of sharing economy platforms that, as of yet, have largely failed to catch on in the way that the sharing economy has.Some have argued that the sharing economy is the answer to our economic ills because it creates jobs opportunities for those who use alternative forms of production, and because it’s possible to transfer ownership of such assets. There are of course also trade-offs to be considered, and the sharing economy has been a valuable tool in helping to identify promising new practices that will help to address some of the challenges of the present. But none of these are mutually exclusive, and the sharing economy has to work hard to ensure that it creates conditions that are conducive to the growth of new creative practices. One of the tasks will be to ensure that these growth opportunities actually materialise, and not perpetuate the problems that have prevented them from growing.This will</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data that can be gathered. As a result, the art world is constantly complaining that it lacks the data to be a player in its own data-mining. This is a problem for the sharing economy because it’s almost as if the user doesn’t have any rights when it comes to the art world’s content. The sharing economy has created a scenario in which the user doesn’t have any rights. There’s a catch, of course, in that the art world, which is usually very attentive to what’s going on in the environment, is always looking to see what opportunities there might be for the sharing economy, because that’s what that other sector does. But in the sharing economy, there’s no catch. There’s no regulatory check on what’s happening. There’s no system in place to detect when things are done legitimately. These are the conditions that have created the conditions that have allowed for the sharing economy to flourish: the scrutiny and regulation, the inability to define the precise parameters of an industry, and the emergence of an informal but growing middle class that enjoys the fruits of the sharing economy’s activity.What do you think the role of the artist should be in this context? I’m curious about how the sharing economy is impacting the community of artist-makers that’s emerging in the metropolis. I imagine it’s impacted in different ways, and the biennial form may be a good place to start. But I also want to know what the relation is between the art museum and the sharing economy. Perhaps the museum may want to encourage artists to join the sharing economy because the museum is seeing an increase in the number of artists willing to participate in the sharing economy; perhaps the museum may not want to because the sharing economy is seen as a threat to the art institution’s position. But I also want to know how the different artists</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating
    <text>machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating in the control of resources through over-exploitation. The affinities between capital and energy shifted from the natural to the artificial. The artificial became the mutable into the valuable. The market became not only the observer of value but also the site of its own destruction. What used to be called ‘the natural world’ became subject to the whims of resource depletion and development, while the market became not only the site of value but also the object of its own wealth. 	What has been described as ‘capitalocene’ refers to the point at which the social value of objects begins to accrue, at which point the social value of commodities begins to accrue. If we begin to understand the social value of objects, and how the social act of capital creates and distributes them, then we will understand how and why social forms begin to collapse. 	The emergence of robustness as a concept is seen as essential to understanding the social act of capital accumulation.</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating in a universal apocalyptic breakdown of the world as a whole. In contemporary parlance, the ‘end of history’ has come to refer to the end of the history of the planet. But is that really the case? 	It is true that the industrial era ended with the industrial revolution, which ushered in a period of enormous economic growth and vast social changes. But is it also true that the end of the industrial era was a given? And what about now? 	It is difficult to imagine a different future for a human society. And perhaps it is even difficult to imagine a different world if you inhabit it. Robots will inevitably overrun humans in one form or another of work, and as a result we must expect them to do the same. Our only hope is that we can figure out how to build non-autonomous systems to mitigate this inevitability, while allowing human creativity to take form alongside it. 	One such approach is blockchain, and its related technology  </text>
    <text>machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating in a single global catastrophe. But modernity itself is characterised by recurrent catastrophes, and the tendency is now to revert to the old ‘hegemonic order’ – that is, to conserve what little is left of the legacy of the ‘civilizing’ past. 	Therefore,  	several years after the publication of  	survival of the Ancient Rome series, we can still find contemporary reference to the idea of resilience in relation to the contemporary world. In  	Catastrophes of the Twenty-First Century, the geological engineer, Dr. Theodore Heald, proposes a new geological era in which the human species remains confined to a narrow range of local climates, becoming extinct-untouched by natural disasters.2. 	The rise of biopolitics and the petrostate 	In the twenty-first century, the bioepisodic is the format through which we can imagine a future in which the dynamics</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating in a cataclysmic global climate change. The inherent fragility of the global economy was emphasised in the media and popular culture of the time. The shift from the image of the oil derrick2 to that of the desalination plant symbolised the end of the era of industrial civilization. But while the industry that produced desalination may have stopped making a profit, it is now economically unviable. Its functions have shifted to those of energy storage, which is increasingly becoming an issue in a world-wide economic-social-political-complex that includes but is not limited to climate change and urbanisation decline. The proliferation of fossil-fuel-fired power plants represents a potential return on investment of several decades or even centuries in the future. But even if this were to happen, it is doubtful that the infrastructure required to support it would be sufficient to feed the world's growing population and keep it from going hungry. 	Moreover, the growth of fossil-fueled infrastructure will</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating in a planetary catastrophe. But what if the problem is not environmental degradation but rather the problem with which we are all involved? What if the solutions are embedded in complex socio-technical systems that we do not yet understand how to deploy? What if the resistance to change is as real as its adaptation? What if the role of the artist is as important as the part that he plays in the system? 	The notion of resilience was given new life in the service of information technologies when it was realised that the human capacity for understanding and controlling the world was far greater than the capacities of the artists who created its imagery. The capacity of artists to create lasting, positive change through art was recognised as a legitimate way of structuring society. 	Artists were invited to create innovative ways of approaching the environmental question that were responsive to the needs of the times. And since the public was invited to participate in this ‘new normalisation’, artists were free to explore ‘heresies of</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating in a biennial in a city like New York City, whose annual budget is now more than doubled and whose infrastructure is in shambles. The inescapable conclusion to this narrative is that the only way to truly know is to be rooted in the city, which is seen as a source of meaning and value in and throughout the city.  	But this ‘end of history’ narrative ignores critical shifts in the dynamics of cities over the past half century or so. The biennial and its episodic, ‘once a year’ ‘formula’ in the 1990s and early 2000s saw a critical mass of artists coming out of the woodwork in response to the rapid technological development. The proliferation of biennials and their episodic structure allowed artists to come out of the woodwork at breakneck speed, creating a kind of transient ephemera that was difficult to separate from the real-time dynamics of the art world.</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating in a predicted cataclysm. The inescapable end point – the present – is understood by many to be unsatisfying, to be overrun by technologised forms of destruction. However, this interpretation of history as a destructive monstrosity is itself subject to change. As new technological paradigms are brought to bear on the ecological systems that we inhabit, the old order is continually reshaped.  	When looking to the future, it is tempting to ascribe a clear understanding of how this might unfold, how we might mitigate its effects. It is true that predictions of apocalyptic environmental destruction are ahistorical, that there is no future for the foreseeable future. But this is beside the point. The point is that we do not yet know how such systems will be designed, managed and brought to bear on the world we inhabit. And if the future is  	designed by the state to be populated exclusively with white people, then it will inevitably follow that the present will be populated</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating in a predicted cataclysm known as the Anthropocene, in which humans will not be able to sustain life on this planet anymore.2. 	But what if we could move beyond the anthropocene and other environmental crises to look for other solutions? What if we could create other ecological hierarchies? What if we could draw on the assets of other ecological systems, building on the mutualistic principles that have driven the industry for millennia? What if we could combine the power of science and the power of art to create ‘better, healthier, more enjoyable’ human ecosystems? What might that look like? Inspired by the work of Ecuador’s National Park Service, the project was led by the Argentinean artist Miguel Hidalcez and the Swiss artist Christoph Buchel.3. 	The park service established two ecologies: the National Park and the Temescal. Both sites were subdivided and designated as areas of historical, archeological, and ecological</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating in a point where humanity is forced to confront its inherent inhumanity. This trope is a re-purposing process, but it is also a very risky one, as we humans are prone to existential threats that can change the world in ways we do not yet comprehend.2. 	Robustness is defined as the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. Adaptive means changing and constantly shifting, not always in the direction of success, and often in the context of great personal turmoil. So what does it mean to be responsive to change? How is change caused? What is the origin of change? What is its impact? These are the kinds of questions that can and should be asked and answered by those with a stake in the socio-political dynamics of the modern world. In a recent survey of 1,500 people, over half (54%) said that they had a personal stake in the development of the world around them, and over half (54%) said that they had a</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments) are subject to the same conditions of political and economic dependence as any other industry. If the state attempts to intervene in the autonomous development of a service, it is bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. And if such actions negatively impact the industry, the impact is bound to be felt across the service industry. If the state attempts to regulate the dynamics of a marketplace that it does not yet fully understand (but should), it is also bound to respond with policies that negatively impact the industry in the interest of capital. As an industry, we can only guess at the state of knowledge regarding the world through the services we provide.1. 	Robustness is the ability to respond effectively to change through adaptation. 	In the 1990s, the idea of resilience came to represent ‘the end of history’, as opposed to the beginning of it all. The end of history was portrayed as the ever-present threat of environmental degradation culminating in a cataclysm. However, the emergence of new energy resources and the manifold applications of these resources has fundamentally altered the game in unpredictable, sometimes devastating ways. In the service of capital, the state finds itself constantly engaged in upgrading infrastructure, making it more energy-independent and providing ever more ways to control the political, social and ecological conditions that exist in the world. 	In the service of humanity, the state actively seeks to control the world’s resources as much as possible in order to support the capitalist mode of production. And while the public debates about the role of the state in the service of humanity often center on the question of whether resources should be controlled by the state or the market, there is a much more pressing need to unify and integrate ecological, energy and social considerations into all aspects of society. In other words, we must begin to imagine a future without the state and in order to do so, we need to understand that there is a world outside of the state</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential ways.Art, then, plays a pivotal but intermittent role in this new world order. As the technological turn in the art turn around, it is a critical mediator of cultural flow, influencing what artists are able to create and the decisions that they make, both consciously and unconsciously. It intervenes, sometimes powerfully, in creating what it defines as a new art form, but it also happens to be a critical mediator of cultural flows and the decisions made in the context of contemporary culture. It is at times a critical mediator of capitalism, and it plays a crucial role in resisting technological obsolescence.The initial impulse of the curatorial turn in the public sphere is to some extent a reaction to the perceived excesses of the past. The twentieth-century curatorial turn is often identified with the post war curatorial turn that followed World War II, and the institutionalization of photography as a cultural instrument. The impulse is to take the past and map it out into possible futures through a</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential ways.Virtual reality is likely to become more prevalent in the curatorial turn, as more artists are drawn to the notion of ‘being there’, ‘in there’, ‘where the action is happening’. It is also likely that the increased accessibility to virtual and mixed reality experiences will lead to a change in the kinds of art-making that is done in a curatorial setting. Perhaps, in the new ‘curatorial turn’, art will be made more accessible through the use of virtual and mixed reality, and the art will be acted out not in a prescribed way, but in real life, as people actually happen. This could happen through the use of autonomous vehicles, virtual tours, or other creative forms of cultural tourism. It could also happen through the incorporation of scientists and other highly specialized personnel into the curatorial turn itself, as is happening in areas such as architecture and landscape architecture. It is clear that the turn to the arts is a</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential ways.As a curatorial tool, the curatorial turn is a great tool for the socially engaged artist. It enables the artist to create an experience that is authentic to the place, time and time again visited by the public, and that is participatory in character. It allows the public to be part of a project that is not only authentic to the place and time, but also a participatory part in the creation of its own future. In other words, the authentic is not necessarily great, but can and should be supplemented by interesting, interesting and socially engaged packaging. This is particularly true for socially engaged artists, who are likely to engage with subjects that are more globalised and materialist – and whose work may in turn engage with those subjects.  In an ideal world, the authentic part of an artist’s contribution would be integrated into the place, time and culture of the audience, but in contemporary art this is increasingly difficult to achieve.  The curatorial turn is a tool</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential ways. We have been conditioned to expect a simulacrum of the things that happen in the real world, and so the new curatorial turn is a factor that has yet to be fully negotiated. [1] The concept was coined by and defined in Karl Marx’s and Frederick Engels’s Communist Manifesto.Download this article as PDFKarl Marx and Frederick EngelsKarl Marx and Frederick Engels were born in 1869 and 1870 respectively in Berlin and Vienna. Their father was a railway engineer. Their mother was a housewife. They emigrated to the United States when they were five and spent many years in the rural South before moving to Chicago. While in Chicago, Engels worked for the newly formed National Federation of the Blind, and so their conception of the curatorial turn comes from that background. It is a concept that was part of the social contract between artist and audience, and so its legitimation by the state is a given. Still, I think the term has difficulties in</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential ways. The curatorial turn is a turn that is both necessary and contingent upon the prevailing forces of information society. It is an important step in the development of the social turn, but one that has to be resisted, because it threatens to divert resources from more pressing needs. [1] Artists were asked to identify two characteristics of the curatorial turn.  [2] Very briefly, the idea is that the artist has now become the object of a social turn, and the work has come to experience what the artist has in mind in that new and powerful new way that the artist never imagined possible. If two or more artists work in parallel on a project, the project is said to be a ‘curatorial turn’. See Colin Ward, On Being Artists (MIT Press, 2012), chapter 4. [3] Ward, On Being Artists. Chapter 4.1, in On Being Artists, p.10. [4] American artist Shepard Am</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential ways. [2] See, for example, Lisa Parks and Constantinos Halossos, eds., Around the World in Twenty-First Century Art (DACTA, 2015), pp. 129–41.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is Professor in Technological Culture &amp; Aesthetics at Liverpool John Moores University, an appointment she holds in the College of Arts &amp; Design. Recent books include Things Fall Apart: Technological Culture and Criticism (MIT/Tsinghua University Press, 2016), about how art and technology are intersecting to affect our daily lives, and the blog Things Fall Apart: Modern Art and Future Art (2012), about the fall of the Berlin Wall. She is currently a lecturer in the Department of the History of Art, Culture and Technology at Liverpool John Moores University, and a co-curator of the Liverpool Biennial 2016, taking place in autumn 2017.Her articles have been published in Wired,</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential ways. Drawing directly on the curatorial turn, it signals a possible engagement with the everyday, albeit in shadowy and altered forms, including at a later date, with the public sphere. It marks a new relationship between the artist and the public, between the artist and the public of a given city, and between the public and public of a given country, and it signals, too, a possible engagement with postcoloniality and contemporary art as a form of state violence, poverty and repression. This is not to suggest that the curatorial turn in the public sphere is passive or innocent, as some have claimed. Far from it. The public is a political, ideological and economic constituency, and turning away from the public sphere can mean breaking many promises, particularly with the public behind bars. Turning away from the public can mean breaking many other promises as well. The public is a constituency and the public is a bargaining chip. Turning the other cheek, and indeed many other promises and promises, can</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential ways.Art as a Sensor for Developing SocietiesArt and artists are creative in their ability to gather and collate disparate information to create a context in which to work with, and to question. But what is creative in the contemporary art world is different from what is considered innovative or new or even socially engaged in today. Modernism celebrated the unification of all forms of art, and the end of distinction between art and art forms. Art became a media product in its own right – a form of media that produced value not intrinsically related to its content but instead designed to be consumed by a mass audience.  Art today is consumed globally, and so its data feeds are global in nature.  As a result, the social and cultural characteristics of art today are regional in character, and in some cases local. So when an artist engages with the contemporary art world, she or he is engaging with an audience that is globally multi-linguistic and multi-generational. These artist-centered practices</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential ways. Virtual reality can be understood as a technology that enables artists and art institutions to create ever more immersive and culturalised versions of familiar environments, in the same way that the bio-technical turn of the cybernetically enhanced human subject has led to ever more pervasive and sophisticated forms of data capture and processing. Dazzle boats, boats full of fish, shiny cars, fancy cafés – everyday life is a large processing unit for the production of images and simulacra of things. Operating at a hyper-scale normally reserved for military operations, and usually mediated via military-grade imagery, the image macro is a new mode of cultural production that has recently begun to show its effects on the cultural map. Assembled from images sourced from diverse social and archival sources, the image macro serves as a media tool that can be programmed to produce images according to a specified set of criteria, much like the greater part of the ‘language’ of things. The technology underpinning the image</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role, and so the world of art, language, and images was transformed. The curatorial turn in the public sphere runs counter to the trend in the arts towards more accessible forms of cultural apparatuses. In the twentieth century, the curatorial turn was the scene of the discredited, the construction of new ways of engaging with the public was afoot. In the twenty-first century, it is the scene of the financially sustainable, and the technologically savvy elite so entwined with information technologies that they are able to fabricate ever more immersive virtual social worlds out of disparate data feeds that monitor and capture behaviour.’[2] The potential for art to function as a sensor for trends in the socially aware practices of industry, politics, culture and the economy is clear. The recent wave of virtual and mixed reality experiences – largely created by and marketed by the curatorial turn – signals a new era in which the art form can be expected to play a part in more pervasive and influential ways. The curatorial turn is a turn that is expected to yield lessons and narratives that can be used by future generations of artists and curators, and to that end, it is vital that these stories are enduring and tellable. As the curatorial turn is seen as a strategic innovation, and as a potentially game-changing tool in the toolkit of contemporary art, it is imperative that the artists who emerge out of this turn have compelling stories to tell, compelling characters to root themselves in and great motivations to engage with the world around them. Otherwise, the powerful storytelling power of the art form itself is diluted. As the curatorial turn is seen more and more as the territory of commercial and institutional curators, and as such media is forced to adopt a more institutionalised way of presenting things, pushing back against the tide of culture taking over everything, including the art form itself, we see more and more self-consciously commercial art being made with the curatorial turn in mind.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds
    <text>machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds of interaction – interaction that is mediated through data. The ability to infer meaning from data is said to be a fundamental human ability. And yet, just as the capacity of humans to think creates the capacity for poetry and allegory, the capacity of data to crunch numbers is also said to be a fundamental human ability. How is the human capacity for allegory constructed?How is the human capacity for poetry constructed? The capacity for poetry emerges through processes of accrual – the accumulation of things – and the consummation of time. If, aspects of the financial crisis have taught us anything, it is that the things that are counted as valuable eventually become part of a larger total that is counted towards a firm's total assets. So the more debtors are counted towards a firm’s total debts, the more precarious the economy becomes. And yet, as the global financial system implodes, the capacity of individual citizens to take matters of their futures is questioned more and more. Are we</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds of human interaction. The ability to understand and manipulate such interaction arises, in part, from the increased number of platforms on which these calculations can be performed. Languages that prescribe and allow such interaction also evolve. As a consequence, we can read equations that describe the world in quantitative terms – equations that incorporate quantities and variables that could never be imagined, or simulated – into which the human factor has been reduced to render it both comprehensible and eminently quotable.Such is the equation that emerges from the interaction of human discourse with matter: the expression of a thing's possible futures depends on what kind of future it is permitted to inhabit. The possibilities of what an inhabitant of other worlds might be like are, by definition, unknowable. But this equation also presupposes a certain future, and the human factor is permitted to inhabit whatever future that future may hold. In other words, what humans are capable of comprehending is limited by what algorithms can achieve.Future inhabitants of this planet are not to</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds of labour – labour that was previously confined to the realm of the artist or the engineer has made its way into the calculations of every major company in the global south. Languages that read data streams – data signals – enable a new kind of discourse that is not confined to the confines of a human workforce. This is happening at a faster rate than humans can absorb data, which is creating ever-greater volumes of data, which in turn is feeding ever-larger databases. The possibilities for data mining become manifold. This kind of data gathering is reshaping the reckoning of human history.A database is a data storage unit that captures and processes information in a particular form or data set. It is a building block of the contemporary digital economy. It records, categorises and categorises. All data are forms of data, and they come to life as functions when recorded and gathered. A database is a space that records and gathers information in a particular form or data set. It is a new kind of</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds of human interaction. These relate to the animate and the inanimate, symbols and numbers – objects with meaning and personalities – that are imbued with meaning and imbued with attributes and personality. The inorganic world of numbers becomes animate through the imbuing of data through which calculations are made. This interactive aspect of the data-processing aspect of AI is likely to further expand our notions of what counts as human life.Are we witnessing a kind of emergent numerical economy of sorts, in which numbers – both natural and anthropomorphic – are tools? Or is the nadir occurring when artificial neural networks dominate the interface between human and machine, ushering in a new kind of interface architecture? If the latter, what does that portend for the future of work? 	[1] Nadir is short for ‘near infrared’, the signature colour of the Hayden Planetarium. http://www.alienfield.com/2016/08/alien-field-alien</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds of interaction. Here, the sharing of knowledge is facilitated not by the sharing of symbols but the sharing of values. The sharing of values allows the sharing of understanding: concepts, values, and grammars of action. This sharing entails responsibilities and rights that are collective and extend beyond the bounds of the site where the computation is performed. The sharing of concepts, values, and grammars is a precondition for a robust and imaginative humanity. For instance, sharing of values implies responsibilities and rights that are distinct from those of the site where the action takes place. A moral obligation to provide for and care for one's community does not extend to actions that are not communal but of a type or variety of social behaviour that are reliant on the shared sharing of values. And a right to privacy does not extend to actions that are not private but of a type or variety of social behaviour that is reliant on the sharing of signals.The sharing of values, concepts, and grammars is contingent on</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds of interaction. And these interactions are generating ever more complex emergent behaviors that are beyond the capacity of any one set of human operatives to implement. This planetary feedback loop is creating unpredictable consequences for us all.How do we know that these dynamics are creating positive change? One way is to understand them as a set of patterns. In Thinking Machines (2008), I argued that artificial intelligence is the future of computation; it is the application of AI to the problems of computation that humans have little understanding of. The emergence of AI did not herald a magical panacea for all human problems, nor did it lead to a superhuman intelligence. Rather, I suggested that AI will enable new kinds of collaborative problem solving that augment the capabilities of existing human experts – not gods – with surprising new forms of interaction. These new kinds of interaction will be mediated through software and networks, and they will be possible because of the advent of networks and AI. But they will also emerge as a consequence of experiments in deep learning and other</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds of interaction. ‘Robustness to misuses’ is one of the properties of a robust society: a language cannot be both a shield and a sword.In 2015, I co-founded, with Evgeny Morozov, a conference on programming languages and collaborative networks. The conference came together swiftly and decisively, but with little time for reflection. I delivered a talk on the second day that evening in the conference venue, in which my talk was punctured by questions from the audience. Questions that, on reflection, I hoped would never be posed again. Morozov and I organized a second conference in May in Amsterdam, where the ideas from the first conference in Vienna would be presented in a double-sized setting. In attendance were many colleagues from many branches of mathematics and computer science, as well as from engineering, physics and chemistry. I tried to present the conference in a way that it would be accessible to a general audience, but also to a community of researchers who</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds of interaction. ‘Robots’ are evolving into ‘machine learning’s conversational partners.Machine learning is code-switching, but it is happening across the board. As new languages are added to the human language, the limits of human comprehension become evident. As a result, some are breaking programming into pieces, or programming into behaviour, to be carried out by machines. Programs, once confined to a particular task, are roaming the landscape becoming autonomous agents. The ability to write scripts that function like machines becomes a reality.Scripting is becoming more and more pervasive in the workplace. Scripting is an essential step in the process of language understanding – comprehending meaning in the world around you – but it is becoming increasingly difficult to enforce these meaning-bearing programmes on a global basis. Machine learning, the technology that underlies it, is also becoming increasingly pervasive. Languages that were once confined to a particular region of the world are now understood to encompass a multitude of cultures.</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds of interaction and interaction possibilities. Such languages also tend to increase in adoption, as people’s expectations of language evolve to meet the increasing demand for data. But these trends are also connected. Aghdashloo’s work often operates between the two. She describes the language as a terrain that is reshaped and retrained to meet the needs of the companies that provide services to the urban environment. The language evolves to accommodate the needs of the big data providers, whose models are honed to crunch data efficiently and sustainably. The language then evolves in response to the users’ behaviour, by creating ‘speculative grammariles’ – grammars capable of handling vast amounts of data and processing power. These new languages also tend to emerge in response to pressing social ills, as a by-product of the metainterface. And they can be used to intervene in the world around us, generating new behaviours and behaviours, based on the most current research and</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments in which animals are trained to perform a task, either by observing or imitating their human creators. Machine learning is not new, and advances in computer science have made it possible to create ever more sophisticated models of the world. But what is new is the extent to which these models are directed, or performative, rather than exploratory or intrepid. As a discipline, we are witnessing an explosion of quantitative models that are both machine and quantitative. As the mathematician Alan Turing showed, the goal of a computer is to do the impossible – to do computations that cannot be done by human beings.The explosion of numerical models coincides with a proliferation of programming languages – a development that is manifesting on a macroscopic level as a global phenomenon, as well as on a microscopic level as individualised mutations within a human population. Mathematical functions, which are traditionally performed by a human programmer, are becoming increasingly automated. Languages that perform calculations and manipulate data enable a multitude of new kinds of interaction. These new kinds of interaction arise as a by-product of the explosion of data – mathematical, linguistic and sensorimotor – that is imbued into all aspects of contemporary life. And this new data makes it easier for humans to observe and simulate these behaviours.For example, the ability to map movement patterns across large areas is a useful tool for the urban administrator, enabling planners to plan routes and deploy resources optimally; it maximises the capacity of each urban space and citizenry unit, enabling the incorporation of new ideas and creative approaches into planning processes. Yet the ability to map movement patterns across cities remains constrained by the physical limitations of the metropolis – the city as a flat surface with limited circulation – and the proliferation of modes of human movement across that surface. Therefore, it is easy to understand how the metropolis is growing larger and more complex, but it is much harder to imagine or simulate a human-scale metropolis. This is true for physical communities as well, since</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a
    <text>vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a particular idea of data and how it is generated and consumed.In the digital age of the infinite scrolling of screens, we can no longer pretend that content is static, since material media (even in the form of objects) are no longer the primary representations of the world. Digital media play a part in creating the conditions of this new static representation, but more and more of that is automated. In the words of Gregory Ulmer, who developed the ephemeral multimedia character MIME into the universal multimedia standard, ‘Digital media has made it possible to produce, to share and to consume content virtually anywhere, at any time…’[8] and this is what MIME meant when it came out of the W3C as a proposal in 1997.  As the W3C understood it, ‘MIME stands for Multimedia Authorized Developer’ and identifies the platform on which the browser (and not the server) runs. So, a site like Wikipedia being hosted</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a certain kind of vulnerability that is inherent to the dynamic and networked condition – the ephemeralness that comes from constantly re-locating oneself, constantly seeking new ways of being alive. In this sense, the deep web and the ephemeralness that it implies are the offspring of the dynamic convergence of information technologies and information infrastructures. And this brings us to the current tensions between the deep web and the information infrastructures that are their expressions – or, to be more specific, between the information infrastructures that are the products of the dynamic coordination of information technologies and the information infrastructures that are the offspring of the information society.The current tensions between the deep web and the information infrastructures that are their expressions – or, to be more specific, between the information infrastructures that are the products of the dynamic coordination of information technologies and the information society – are as follows: the deep web is a set of protocols and techniques for</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a certain kind of understanding of the social web as a kind of static archive that is both present and absent at the same time. The social web is both ­present and absent at the same time. And this type of understanding of the social web as both present and absent at the same time is very different from the kind of dynamic understanding that comes with new technologies or even new media. So it is also different from what Tiziana Terranova would give to a new understanding of the social web. She would not be the first to give a new understanding of the social web, and she would not be the last. But in different ways, different tools, she would be the last to administer a static website with no back-end that responds to user actions. She would understand the difference between interactive and ‘live blogging’ better than most. And she would understand the difference between social and interactive media better than most.So what does it mean to make the social web present and absent at the</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a certain kind of understanding of power and domination.  One might also note that the deep web is also a site where ‘real life’ is often reproduced via the ‘hacktivist’ subculture. In this sense, the deep web is also a language. And this brings us to the next point: how we understand ‘the deep web’ as a particular kind of infrastructure that is both ephemeral (its structure is ephemeral) and dynamic (its behavior is ephemeral). This kind of dynamic is closely related to the work of the renegade language servers – software that acts as a proxy between user and content; it allows the former to exist while simultaneously challenging it to incredible extremes. One could argue that the deep web is both ephemeral (its meaning is ultimately determined by the events that take place on it) and dynamic (i.e. able to evolve at will): as new meaning is attached to the occurrences of the deep web,</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a particular relation between the static and the ephemeral. 	The static aspect of the static web is both the source and the effect of the static ideal. It is the idealised image of the static web that emerges, despite the fact that sites like Wikipedia and Google’s servers constantly change and grow. And this image is a kind of mythologised template or template that can, in part, be read as a kind of story. And so the dynamic aspect of the static web is seen as a kind of present and future ideal that is constantly in motion. It is a kind of ‘present’ that tells a story, but it is also ‘a future’ that skips over present and historical narratives. 	In essence, then, the dynamic and the contemporary web is the same thing, but the dynamic aspect of the dynamic web is one that anticipates and works against the prevailing forces of history in certain ways. And this is an important distinction to keep</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a certain kind of understanding of the user as a connective tissue between social media and the physical infrastructure of the web. Not all users are created equal, and not all connections are static. But there is a fundamental assumption about users, about the capacities and intentions of users: that users have no agency, that they are passive and that they are content to consume what is offered them. And this is the deep web, to a certain extent: the level of abstraction and seamless user-space integration required to render crucial information about the world online. This level of abstraction and seamless integration is possible because of the inbuilt contentiousness of the web browser, the inbuilt inefficiencies of the server (since servers are now run by computers instead of people, and thus are prone to downtime and software defects), the inbuilt corporatism of the media, and the inbuilt payment and networking systems that pervade all aspects of our contemporary online world. All of these elements of the web browser, the in</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a certain kind of criticality – the kind that is both dependent and immune to change – the kind that is also immune to change in the sense of the technological singularity. I think this dynamic kind of criticality is different from the kind that is tied to historical curatorship or the kind of historical curatorship that is typical of national dOCURATI. The kind of criticality of the deep web is tied to what I would call the ‘heterogenous microcosm’ of the internet – the kind of singularity that arises when all manner of interconnectedness takes place at the same time, and which is neither static nor irreversible. And this microcosm is what I would call the singularity that takes place on the deep web. As I have been developing my ideas and proposals on the deep web, I have been trying to imagine what a deep web would be like, in the same way that the internet was imagined by the internet designers. It doesn’t</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a certain kind of intuition that is running through much of our contemporary infrastructure: the notion of interactive narrative.If the internet is seen as both an ideal (anonymous and maximising connectivity) and a practice (one with repercussions and consequences), then the deep web, or what is supposed to be a virtual space of unmediated interaction, comes to represent what Orwell would call ‘a nightmare’. This is to say that the technology that creates the interfaces we use – and the social mechanisms that enable us to engage with them – is inhuman and corrupting. And this inhumanity and corruption is a function not only of the technology itself, but also of the social mechanisms that enable its adoption: political, economic and legal regimes, media outlets, cultural norms and much more. In short, the deep web is a space that is both ideal (it is difficult to define what the hell is being made possible by the adoption of technology) and politically explosive (it is now possible to adopt any technology and</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a certain amount of the tension and tensions of the deep web. It is said to be a constant state of flux, in which ‘the cloud’ and ‘the machine’ are said to be constantly competing for supremacy, with ‘the cloud’ often exerting an undue influence over the machine’.12  In a way, I do subscribe to this kind of thinking, although it has its limits. For instance, I think that the way in which social media is constructed now, with the inroads that have been made in terms of transparency and accountability, makes it inevitable that ‘a few people with a grudge and an axe will decide what is publicly visible and what is not public’. I also think that it is no exaggeration to suggest that the social web is fully online in all but concept, and that the deep web – in which actions on a deep web (like ‘posting’ and its derivative actions) are capable of influencing</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, not to mention the fact that the connection between the user and the content is increasingly important, both in terms of the content itself (since it is now possible to read the semantic content of a post via a post on Facebook) and of the way in which the contents are constructed. For instance, the proliferation of social media has brought with it an increase in the number of ­instances of the self, which means that it is no longer possible to read posts as individual events, but as aggregates of contextual elements that come together in a certain way or another. Such a reading would render the attempt to understand ‘how the internet works’ as a kind of criticality – since the very notion of posting is now being drawn into the notion of connectivity. In this sense, the deep web, as an idea and a practice comes to represent the network effect that is both static and dynamic, both static and ephemeral. And this notion of static and ephemeral speaks to a certain kind of vulnerability and fluidity of the internet as a circulation medium. The deep web is a place where the ephemeral is not confined to the confines of the built environment, but is embraced. It has no fixed location, but fluctuates widely within the context of globalised capitalist society. This proposition is at the core of the new 'sharing economy’ – companies like Uber and TaskRabbit that seek to replace traditional full-time work with flexible working hours and accommodation that can be arranged through connections to other parts of the world – and it is an idea that is being realised in places like Buenos Aires, where the emergence of flexible working hours and housing that can be bought with virtual currency is being promoted.Flexibility and the sharing economy are to a large extent the offspring of the internet; sharing is the new how in work. But since the internet is such a fundamental building block of capitalist circulation, and since its use for almost any purpose is positively identified as a resource –</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was to be produced with tools that were as malleable as the artists themselves. And so the proposal was put forward in vain. The curatorial turn around the biennial was already underway. The biennial would be produced in the present, but with a highly stylised and data-driven character, responding to the demands of the current curatorial turn. And so the proposal was put forward again, this time with the added twist that the biennial should be produced in the present, and with a special emphasis on the curatorial as an interlocutor. It should be able to dictate the terms of engagement, the content and the character of the experience, while it is being produced. This was the purveyors of the idea that the biennial would soon be producing its own ‘big question mark’. The big question marks were: who will establish the biennial? What will become of it? Will museums be able to cope with the proliferation of artefacts? Will bienn</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was to be produced using materials and processes that were no longer made in a laboratory or in a master’s thesis. This was a ‘big data’ revolution, and with it a demand for ever-greater amounts of data. Art’s actuality was to become increasingly precarious as a result. The biennial format now demanded a certain amount of imagination and imagination alone. The reason for this extraordinary demand was that the collective imagination could not cope with the sheer volume and nature of the data being generated. As a result, a mandatory enrolment fee totalled over one billion US dollars. This fee went into a fund dedicated to the future design of the art form. Assembled by a commissioning committee including representatives from the White House, the National Gallery, the Tate and the Biennial, it offered a token of appreciation to the artist by way of a fee. The committee was led by Vice-Chairman of the White House Curatorial staff Alexander Macalister,</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was to be produced in the cloud, or in some cases, in virtual proximity to it. Art’s contemporary is a very different kind of contemporary. It is produced, as the title of the first instalment of the journal suggests, on a massive scale. And while the biennials of old were places where a certain kind of art was produced, today we are producing a kind of art that is neither artistically produced nor institutionally recognised. Art’s contemporary with technology is produced through the medium of the biennial, and with it, as the title of the journal implies, a large scale scale (biennial) photographic and video archive of art’s contemporary life. If the first instalment of the journal is any indication, this kind of archive will continue to grow in size and volume, as new biennials are created and old ones are reviewed, annotated and amended in real-time, constantly augmented with videos and photographic negatives and all manner of</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was to be produced in the context of connectedness, not in the past but in the digital instant of access. This was to some extent predicted by the work of futurist Ray Kurzweil and his team of researchers, who were working at that time in conjunction with the Kurzweil Foundation. Ray’s work was partly inspired by the futurist K. Rajendran Iyer’s work on artificial intelligence, which was also being done at the time with the Indian Institute of Science (K.I.S). Ray’s work on the future, though, was in some ways a response to the limitations of AI. Ray’s work did not predict that with the advent of Google’s DeepMind unit, which built into the computer systems that ran Google’s search and image processing, the boundaries between human and machine would be blurred even further. AI was imagined to augment rather than replace humans in virtually every way.Art has</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was to be curatorial in its use of the new media of experience, but it would also intervene in the production of artworks that were being made with the new media of social media. What was being made was not the kind of art that could be reproduced in a museum collection, but what might be found in an archive or private collection. So the museum collection was being supplemented by a storage of historical materials, which were being made available at a rapid rate online.  Artworks made available online could be found in museums, but the more they were made available, the more they were consumed, and the more they were transmitted, the more they became part of the collective memory. This kind of memory is being made in large part by the art being made available, and the online version of the museum collection is the very mirror image of the collection as a whole. This kind of memory is being made by the system, and it is being made visible to all viewers. Artworks made available on the</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was to be produced on a massive scale through the incorporation of large-scale displays, virtual and augmented reality, social media and, of course, maps and charts. This was to categorically negate the influence of the artistically-inclined artists of the past, who were discovering the art of the possible with greater regularity and regularity being a synonym for growth. The new kind of biennial would produce habits of consumption, and these would be objects of art, objects of aesthetic experience, objects of knowledge. The key to this new kind of consumption would be in the details – the way in which the art was produced, distributed, interpreted and communicated – and the ability to tap into the power of data-collection and circulation. The technology that emerged from these new media was game-changing in its possibilities and possibilities. Its ubiquity meant that artworks could be gathered, communicated, analysed and utilised across a massive geographical area. Artworks produced using this new media would be examples of</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was to have its ‘pace and procedure’ superseded by something more sensitive to the contemporary condition.  A new generation of curators was to emerge, drawn from the curatorial ranks, who would one day lead exhibitions, seminars, performances and commission books. One could say that the curatorial post was to be used as a kind of surveillance and control device, gathering and mapping out the city’s varied cultural landscapes. It was to a large extent what had happened in Marin County, with its isolated and isolated settlements, that would be repeated elsewhere. It was to a large extent what had happened in the art world that had a bearing on what might be considered contemporary art, and what might be considered contemporary art in the future. But what had happened in Marin County was to some extent copied elsewhere, and the new curators had to master the local language and the wider culture clash. It was a matter of negotiation.The object that had first captured our attention as a problem to be</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was to be produced in the computer. There was a proposal to establish a citywide network of virtual art galleries, where artists could set up shop and conduct their works in a completely different world from the one that they inhabited in the real world. This new kind of biennial would offer an alternative to the structures that were collapsing around them, as well as a possible escape from the biennial crisis. Art’s contemporary is produced through the medium of art objects, while virtual art is produced through the medium of apps. If the aim of the art market is to sell art, then the only way to produce innovative and provocative works that are likely to be found by a willing and able public is through the art market itself. The virtual and the non-existent are to a large extent consumed by the one and the same medium. The incentive for artists to produce works of art across platforms is strong. The only problem is that these same platforms also often create quite different experiences – maya, for example</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was to be produced with tools and infrastructure that could be designed to support it in its adventures.This new kind of biennial would operate within a larger cultural complex, but it would be an independent biennial in its own right. It would produce large-scale public collections, but these would be organized as collections of various kinds – oral, documentary, collage, sculpture, video, online and so on. The collection management would be created through a new kind of commissioning agency. It would also produce its own kind of history, but these would differ from those of the museum. Art’s collection management today is driven by a curatorial insular elite, who attend museums primarily to be entertained by the art and images, and are content to leave the art to others. This kind of collecting tends to be decorative in character, and art’s curatorial ambitions have often led to fetishising, popularising and fuelling of aesthetic practices that are not necessarily of great value to the communities</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial process. This would mean organising exhibitions, seminars, performances, films, lectures, games and much more. There was a proposal that a new kind of biennial – one that addressed the present and the future – should be created.  The idea was to produce, through the interstices of the biennial, a register of curatorial actions that take place in the city at the same time. The goal was to create an experience similar to that of attending a museum, only organized in the city in the future. The key to this future ‘present’ was emphasised over the past, and over the past, in order to create a radically new kind of biennial.’  This new kind of biennial would operate at a time when contemporary art is being produced in parallel. Art’s contemporary with the technological culture that emerged in the wake of the computer revolution was coming to dominate what might otherwise be termed the venue, the device and the procedure. Modern art was to be produced, not as an aesthetic value, but as a ‘matter of circumstance’.Art’s contemporary output is made possible by the fact that art today is produced at a global scale. As a result, and as a consequence of this, there is much that can be said to be contemporary in the same way in which an airplane can be made today.‘Art’s contemporary audience’ is an increasingly important constituency. It is a constituency that is increasingly aware of and engages with art in an increasingly global way. It is a constituency that is increasingly sensitive to the cultural values and the politics that shape artistic practice and its production, and it is a constituency that is more mobile (more easily moved between places and time).  So, ‘today’ is an increasingly significant time for art and artist’s relations on a global scale, even though it seems that, on a regional or local level, the time may be even less auspicious</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of
    <text>biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of History: Art, Power and the Aftermath of Postcolonialism. She has also edited an annual journal of the Lewis and Clark Biennial, Stages. In 2015 she curated a three-year long exhibition of modern art at the Museum of Modern Art, New York.In the 2015 Venice Biennale, Selfridges London, 2016, the Biennale committee member Anette Hlavajova, presented a project that sought to rethink the relationship between biennials and the city in terms of what she calls ‘rejection of subjectivity and objectivity’.[1] She argued that cities today are more like giant social networks with biennials a prominent node, and cities are in fact in a constant state of revolution as ‘new cities’ are founded and ‘old’ buildings are razed’.[2] In other words, cities today are often times both the islands of the city and buildings for the city. She argued that cities</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of Modern Art (2013). In her book, she recalls the curatorial role of a biennial as a form of social experimentation: in so far as it records the past, the biennial provides a possible future. In so far as it stumbles into the present, it provides a possible future that is uncertain and unpredictable. In ‘the ultimate in media speculation’, Stages of Modern Art (2013) imagines a biennial that emerges from the past, the possible futures, and media of a future that is uncertain and unpredictable. It is a book that the biennial should read, but also a book that should be read by anyone interested in the future or the past. It is the definitive work on its subject, an essential resource for any historian interested in how art is made in the future, and a possible best-kept book for generations to come.In the wake of catastrophic natural disasters and warfare, biennials are especially vulnerable to the vagaries of economic, cultural</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of Modern Art: Art, Capital, and the Curatoriate.In the 1980s and 1990s, the biennial format was particularly susceptible to the influence of artists, curators and other art professionals who actively worked with, and were invested in, the art of the cities in which they operated. It is this era of biennials now that is experiencing a period of structural change, but its practitioners seem ignorant of this, at least as far as the structural changes are concerned. I would propose that there are two basic forms of knowledge today: cultural capital and political capital. Cultural capital refers to the knowledge acquired through actual or potential engagement with art form; it is the kind of capital that generates knowledge that sustains and informs future art and cultural engagements.  Biennials today acquire knowledge via other means, and through other media, including reading, watching and listening to art on a regular basis. They also gain knowledge via engagement with art institutions and their activities, but this latter kind of access</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of Modern Art: Art, Capital, and Crisis (2015 and forthcoming). In Stages of Modern Art, she explores how contemporary art is produced through the institutional production of culture, and how this impacts on cultural values, such as the biennial. She also explores the politics of art production and the conditions of artistic productivity.In the wake of the crisis of the biennial, some curators expressed an interest in creating their own biennial, taking the opportunity to produce a counter culture art form out of thin air. Others were more direct in their attempts to subvert the biennial. Hlavajova herself attempted to launch her own biennial through a combination of public art and private art institutions, but with limited results. She has since changed her mind and now actively works to promote and ensure the sustainability of the biennial through the work of the Museum of Modern Art.Doha Biennale 2016. Photo courtesy of Maria Hlavajova.PreviousNextDoha Biennale </text>
    <text>biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of Modern Art (2015). In a nutshell, biennials are institutions that emerge and proliferate over time, and their materiality is intended to respond to changing times. They are made up of artists, curators, art administrators, art funders, art’s many art collectors, art’s many art-utility companies, art’s curators, art-publishers, art-law enforcers, art-publicists, art-institutes, and art’s art dealers. Each of these stakeholders has a story, and each has a part in the story. When we assembled the artists, the curators, the art administrators, the art funders, the art’s curators, and the art dealers in this group, we heard many different perspectives on the same story. Some of the artists said they had their beginnings in the Biennial, while others pointed to the Museum of Modern Art, New York, where their works</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of Modern Art: Art as a Stage (with Joasia Krysa) and the forthcoming book Systemics: The Arts and Currencies of Contemporary Capitalism (with Nick de Silva).In systemics, innovation is defined as the ability to take the place of the once in a given situation (eventually, everywhere) with a more or less determined outcome. And in the twentieth century, this definition included the capacity to tackle new ideas and concepts – new ways of organising contemporary art – through what was, until then, defined as ‘the art of the possible future’. This kind of technological singularity is, of course, what we aspire to in our art and design, but it also requires us to ask, how can art be applied to actually make things happen? How can it support the ongoing incorporation of new ideas and technologies, but also the future-looking development that we advocate?These are questions that are of necessity open to interpretation, but which have put artists and artists on the path</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of Modern Art: Art, Poverty and Capital in Berlin and Stages of Art in Moscow. In a forthcoming book on the history of contemporary art, she is planning to tell the story of the Biennale in Berlin, which was curated by Wolfgang Ernst and which is published in 2017.Stages of Modern Art: Art, Poverty and Capital in Berlin and Stages of Art in Moscow, 1999. Stages of Modern Art was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich and the Redferns Museum of Art, Redferns, Sydney. It was a rare opportunity to work with an artist who was not employed by the biennale, or to work with an artist who was employed by the Redferns. This was an opportunity to see and work with some of the artists who worked on these projects, and to learn about the new economy of art and culture created by the biennale. The book is going to focus on the post-1990s explosion</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of Modern Art (1996). After the Museum of Modern Art closed, she decided to create a new biennial with a campus in Liverpool, with a different kind of institution – one that would show contemporary art outside the museum, but would also foster a biennial through its curatorial approach. She also wanted the biennale to have a social purpose beyond showcasing art to consider social purpose and art’s place in modern society.Stages of Modern Art was published in 1996, and the book followed in 2001. In the introduction, Hlavajova writes:The biennial format had been invented in New York and London in the early twentieth century. It was the end result of decades of joint research projects between the Museum of Modern Art and the Royal Academy of Arts, through which museums around the world were encouraged to create their own biennials. In the US, the tradition of the museum as a repository for cultural resources, artefacts and collections has been institutionalised in the biennial.</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of Modern Art (2013). Our conversation began with the question: how can biennials create their own systemic change? She responded:There is a saying in art circles: if the Biennale is going to be an art institution, it needs to have a curatorial structure that is continuous with the city in its evolution. Every step the Biennale takes, whether it is going underground or ahead of the art world, it is going to have to have a meaning, a purpose or strategy in place to be able to react when it is not expected that the Biennale will be there. Otherwise, it will be like every other art institution in the city of Zurich. It will be overrun by art tourists and they will all seek out the same art, and they will all arrive at the Biennale expecting the Biennale to be there, but none of them are going to find what they are looking for. Therefore, every step the Biennale takes, whether it is underground</text>
    <text>biennials past and present. Here, we look back on our conversations with the curators and artists who shaped the city of Liverpool. This is our take:What can a biennale do? These are broad questions, but there are concrete ways of engaging with the world through art, which is the case in many cities all over the world. A biennale can be a place where art can find a place where it is not necessarily assumed that art is the sole treasure in town. It can also be a place where art can prey on the systems that are in place to maintain social order, or at least, that social order made by art over time. We asked the curators at Liverpool Biennial to share their ideas with the art world. We also asked how biennials can create their own systemic change. For Maria Hlavajova, the answer is embedded in the biennial itself. She is the curator emerita at the Museum of Modern Art, Zurich, and the author of Stages of Modern Art (2015), including the chapter on Liverpool Biennial, which is the basis for this volume. Her research takes place in the local artworld of Liverpool, with a focus on the artworks on offer in the biennale itself. How can biennials create their own systemic change?In a general way, I would say that biennials can – and in a more specific way, they did for me – but I would have to know what structural changes to make. For me, there are three main types of biennials: those that are rooted in an institution, those that are social but not structural and those that are social and structural. Institutions hold their own distinct value when they are rooted in a particular value system. For me, the importance of institutional memory is to create spaces where ideas and images circulate, but also to ensure that those ideas circulate in ways that are not dictated by the prevailing economic, political and social values of the day. For example, the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Bienn
    <text>The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Biennale for the 90th Venice Biennale, and I have to say: ‘This is going to be a very strange place to be invited to be a curator of a biennale. I’m not there yet, but I can certainly sense the change.’ We don’t know what the curator’s role is going to be, and so both Anthony and I have been invited to be part of a creative team that will be working with the Biennale to bring the Art of Venice to life in a completely different way. Working in parallel, the Biennale needs to work with the Biennale to tell a completely different story.So there’s this huge gap between the Biennale and the narrative it reconstructs, or creates. And I’m sure that the Biennale would agree that there’s a huge gap between the person it wants to see and the reality that is produced. And so there�</text>
    <text>The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Biennale 2026, and we have several other projects in the pipeline.The Venice Biennale has always been about collaboration and exchange, bringing artists from all over the world together to explore and work together. I’m sure that there were people in the Biennale that had a personal or professional relationship with each other, and they brought that together in different ways. For example, Biennials tend to be about a single artist or a single project, whereas the collections work sometimes has a relationship to a community or a territory. The idea was that the collection work came first, and then the community work came second, while the artist’s embedment came third. In the case of biennials and the collections, the third came out as a consequence of geographical or institutional constraints or the realities of the art world.However, the Venice Biennale is not just any art institution. It is a new kind of global icon, synonymous with the Greek and Latin theatre, and</text>
    <text>The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Biennale 2020, but we have to be very careful what we say and do because the Biennale is currently evaluating its options. We don’t have the authority to open an exhibition in the city without first consulting with the Biennale and its board, which will of course seek to block it. We can do it again in 2024, but that would be a very risky move, and at the moment the Biennale doesn’t feel very creatively engaged. There is a reluctance to revisit projects that have been ‘recycled’ in other places, and the feeling is that something has to give. The Biennale was political in its own way, and the Biennale at the height of the AIDS epidemic in 1995 was partisan. The biennale had a political engagement that was very specific, and very visible. The Biennale at Tate Britain was very different, and the biennale in the US was very diffuse. But the biennial as</text>
    <text>The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Biennale in 2017, and a possible entry in 2019.I was in Liverpool recently, and while I was in the city, I got the chance to see how things are going. It seems that the situation in Liverpool has improved a lot under the new administration. The housing crisis has been addressed, and a new cultural agenda is coming out of it. There’s a new emphasis on the role of the arts councils, and local authorities are no longer the be all and end all of community art development. Local people are taking matters of their neighbourhoods and their communities, and encouraging those with skills or knowledge to get involved. The Biennale has a contract to run for another ten years, and there’s talk of bringing in a business to run the shop, and perhaps even bringing in a private equity firm to buy out the art market. There’s talk of a cultural district, too. There’s a question mark hanging over that.If things continue to go well</text>
    <text>The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Biennale 2020, and that’s a possibility. I don’t know if that would still happen if the biennale were closed, but it would certainly make for some really interesting reading between the lines. Some really interesting curatorial approaches are being taken in the Biennale. In a way, the Biennale is the best-run potential successor to the Venetian museum, since it has such a large following, and because it is, in a way, a cultural institution. It provides the biennale with the resources to carry out a cultural experiment. The Biennale opened its doors to the public in 1999, but in recent years it has focused on several important curatorial initiatives, including the Global Entry Programme, which places most of its budget towards special exhibitions. In 2015, the Biennale changed its format to two days, with a combination of mini-exhibitions and a major exhibition. This introduced a completely new exhibitionary approach, in which</text>
    <text>The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Biennale in 2016, and I can already hear the hype train going at full speed. At the Venice Biennale, we get to be the story of the show, and the artist, and together we tell the story in chronological order from the curator’s point of view.It’s a very powerful thing to be in that narrative, but it’s also incredibly isolating and disempowering to see the work you did in the Biennial as an artist is increasingly excluded from it. It feels as if your contribution is more representative of the city as a whole, but you’ve been cut out of the narrative. In either case, it’s not like you get to decide what happens to the art you create. Do you have a say in the narrative? Let’s just say that this narrative is being produced by and for a very specific set of people: the Biennale, the Venetian government, corporations, and artists</text>
    <text>The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Biennale 2023, and that is still on the cards. The biennale has to be a global phenomenon in order to sustain itself, and in order to have any chance of becoming sustainable, it’s going to have to be global in scope. Otherwise, it’s just going to be exhibitions and festivals in cities around the world, and that's it. There’s no way around it. And the fact that we are in the midst of the Venice Biennale, which is the most visible exhibition in the city, makes it easier for the Biennale to become visible, more accessible and CULTURAL in scope. It’s a unique situation, and I don’t think that any other biennale in the world can claim that level of visibility and ubiquity.It’s amazing how much art is now being made in China through grassroots art movements, and that was a huge shift for me when I started in the Bi</text>
    <text>The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Biennale 2016, but for the moment we don’t have a show. We have a story, a reason to tell it, and we use that to justify why we don’t have a show. It’s a question of priorities, really. If we focus on what the biennial should be, and what the art world should be doing, then the artist will naturally set up shop somewhere else. If we reinvent the biennial every time we open, the pieces will still be scattered all over the place. But the thing is, we don’t have that kind of relationship. Our relationship to the art world is based on reciprocity. If the Venice Biennale wants to open a shop, it’s because we have to, because otherwise nothing good will come out of it. If the Biennale doesn’t have a shop, then the shop will remain closed, and the homeless will still be in there. And if the Bienn</text>
    <text>The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Biennale 18—19 October, 2019, and we have a contract till 2021. The next Biennale will be in place by then.As far as I'm concerned, the only thing keeping us from that next Biennale is the fact that things have moved on from the Biennale of 2015. The fact that things have moved on from the Biennale of 2015 means that something completely different has to be done, and I don’t see why we can't do something completely new. We have ideas about what the new Biennale should be like, but we need to find the time and resources to implement them. If we do a Biennale every two years, then in five years either the new or the old Biennale will be the same, so there’s a risk that something completely new will have to be done every two years. But that’s what I call historical curating. It’s the kind of thing that happens</text>
    <text>The next Biennial could come from anywhere in the world, but because of the way it was organized, only a very select few people in the art world were allowed to go. At the time, I didn’t want anyone to be surprised when they came to see the work I did in the Biennial. I was lucky to have a supportive art community, and that was that. As far as I was concerned, the work was done. The next Biennial was a done deal. It wasn’t until 2015, however, when the Venice Biennale opened, and the whole Venice bubble burst, that things really started to heat up again. With the new administration taking over, a whole new set of people came into the Biennale, and it’s now 2015, and things have never looked better than they do now. The Venice Biennale opened in June 2015, and it’s been a massive success. We've been invited to be at the Venice Biennale 2016, but I don’t think it’s appropriate for us to be in the Biennale this year because the changes we’ve made haven’t been put into effect yet. Instead, we have to adapt ourselves to the new situation. I don’t think the Biennale should be the only venue for a world-renowned art institution to be established. The Biennale should always be a global phenomenon, and part of a globally distributed art institution, but it’s also true that the Biennale is a local phenomenon, and part of that phenomenon is that it’s only been possible to offer one venue to the Biennale this year, because of the way it was organized. So there is that. In the new administration’s proposed ‘Chamber of Experience’, there is also a proposal to abolish the Biennale altogether. I don’t think it’s a</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden
    <text>The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden to its many masters. At the same time, we need to ensure that the institution will also respond to the people who inhabit it and who will pay for it. In the present model of the Biennial, the museum becomes the fifth or sixth part of the equation, and the city the eighth. One might also say that the museum is the sixth or seventh element, and the city the eleventh. After the Biennial, the city and the museum merge to form a new kind of institution. In recent biennials, this merger has already taken place; we are convinced that the time has come to switch to a new kind of museum and to create a new kind of biennial.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to</text>
    <text>The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden to its many masters.We propose that the Biennial should act in the city not as an entity, but as a collection of collections, each one displaying a different aspect of the city. Each collection would be led by a curator and feature a different kind of analysis. These divergent views of the city would form a mini-biennial, with each collection holding its own unique perspective. The idea of time-based analysis would be prominent, and collections would frequently run into each other. Collections would form what we would call the ‘city core’ and run counter to one another. This is one way of reading the changes we foresee in the biennial – one that is both predictable (the city will change) and radically unpredictable.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS, there are many other ways of looking at the city. One possibility is that of fragmentation. That is, we might imagine cities in their continuous evolution – cities in which individuals and groups of people constantly change –</text>
    <text>The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden to its past, present, or future. The biennial as a form may no longer be so dominant, but we see ourselves rather as the heirs of a dominant historiography. We envision a future in which biennials act as a double-sided sword, cutting through contemporary urbanisation and making a positive difference in the world through their persistent presence in the city. We want to be able to say that we brought a story to life through a particular exhibition, because that is what we did. We want to continue to do that, even when the art is bad, because that is our credo. We may or may not be right. If we are lucky, our curators may one day become world-renowned public figures, and we may very well become curators ourselves.Download this article as PDFDesis &amp; Migrants: Towards a History, a journal of interaction between indigenous communities and non-indigenous observers, 1970–2015. From the archives of the Black Education</text>
    <text>The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden to its many masters. Without this kind of fortuitous historical accident, the Biennial would not exist.We propose that the Biennial operates in two parts: a city that it photographs and a city that it molds and fabricates according to its needs. We propose that the image of the Biennial follows the image of the museum, reproducing itself in a continual loop. At the center of the image is the museum, which is undergoing renovation and expansion in response to the city’s changing needs, constantly reminding us that it is in fact a museum. In the image of the biennial, the museum is the site of a permanent exhibition of objects from the city; it is an image of historical interest, but it is also a site of transformation, where the transformation of the city occurs through the transformation of its inhabitants. We envision two parallel universes where the image of the museum and the image of the transformation of the city occur simultaneously. In one universe, the museum is an ever</text>
    <text>The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden to its current location and population. We are calling for a new generation of museums to emerge from the defacement of the old, in and through the city, and for them to emerge out of the defacement of the old, in and through the city. We propose that they should be places where stories told and retold come alive, where memories made visible and lost in the mire of data, jargon, statistics and metrics, where the unpredictable and the invisible encounter each other. We want them to be places where recollections are made visible and possible. We also want them to be places where art is made purposefully difficult, so as to require constant vigilance. We do not yet know what this last requirement in particular means or how to approach it.We started by asking: what is it that makes a city great? And, in doing so, asking, what is it that makes a biennial great? In our view, a biennial should be creative in its use of space, capable</text>
    <text>The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden to its spatial configuration or the whims of a city government. This may mean creating an entirely new type of museum or even a completely different kind of museum entirely. At the same time, it may mean creating a museum that is both regional and entirely devoted to the city. We have no idea which museum would be best placed in the city, but we do know that the museum that we envision has to respond to the spatial heterogeneity of the city and its people. If it is to offer anything in return, it has to offer something of value to a city that is deeply embedded in its urban fabric. As biennials, we’re artists in the truest sense, in this is no longer an object of exchange. We’re here to stay, and our curatorial style and curatorial pronouncements may be curios or urban myths, but we’re here to stay.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city,</text>
    <text>The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden to its many masters. We think that the biennial that emerges out of the dearth of an Artworld of this sort in the US and Europe will be a miracle, and that the biennial in its current form will be replaced by something better.In the meantime, the Art World as we know it may need to be reconceived in order to accommodate, or rather, accommodate to, new forms of art and cultural activity. We propose that a new generation of curators, art writers, artists and arts administrators be formed. These may be drawn from the art world, the arts education establishment, academia, grassroots organisations, the media, community organisers and online communities. They may be drawn from the community or the non-community. They may be anything that intermingles the many and distorts the many in such a way as to enable or impede the goals of a city in its various forms. We propose that this be done with the establishment of a Community Arts agency, taking the form</text>
    <text>The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden to its urban environment, although it will undoubtedly still put urbanism before everything else.A MOVING STEP towards MUSEUM-like INTERNATIONAL RESOURCE biennials, but in THE CITY. Could become something entirely new, like the Biennale in Venice or the Guggenheim Museum in New York, although we should not be drawn into a ‘city is the museum of the future’ narrative for the reason that that narrative is being rewritten. Instead, it would be interesting to see what emerged from the disenchantment generated by the end of the 2000s economic boom, which has put a damper on artistic impulse, and the consequent pressure on museums. Could the emergence of new artistic impulse arise from the displacement of the museum as an object of consumption? That would be a novel approach to the task. The museum would certainly have to change, but we think that the changes that need to happen would make the museum redundant. Instead, the museum could</text>
    <text>The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden to its many masters. We propose that the institution be able to evolve and contract with the city in many ways, but will always remain fundamentally different from museum to museum. Our proposal is that the museum forms the foundation of the institution, while the Biennial builds its life on the back of the community. We think that the Biennial will always have a strong cultural component to it, but it will also have a social purpose as well as a political component. The aim of the social aspect will always be to give the impression of community, but the aim of the biennial will also have much more direct and practical effects. The political aspect will be much more nuanced, and the impact of this new form of institutionalisation will be much more variable. This change in focus and in power is a situation that we speculate will arise in the biennial as a whole, but which we imagine will be particularly acute at the New Museum in Manhattan. We speculate that the rise of the biennial as a whole</text>
    <text>The next Biennial to open in New York is likely to follow suit. In the meantime, the Biennial in its current form – which seems to be more representative of the country than of the city – is closing in on a century. We might propose that the time has come for a change.DESPITE THE IMPERFECTIONS that the Biennial can place on a city, it is essential that it is placed in the public domain. It is not enough for the Biennial to want to be in a city, as long as it is in a city. The Biennial has to be in a place in which people can visit, engage with, and leave with stories of the city. It must be able to take part in the city and absorb it into itself. It is this last requirement that we have left behind in recent biennials, which are moving towards becoming museums. We think that the time has come to create an institution that will respond to the city and will not be beholden to its past, present, or future. We propose that the biennial become a museum in its own right, capable of standing on its own two feet, with a real cultural identity – even if this may involve adapting traditional modes of cultural production.A museum in its own right? We would like to think that the answer to this may lie in the people who run the museum. We think that the new museum head, curator, may well be an artist in her or his own right. We would like to see the following in the museum: 1. An annual budget reflecting the local needs and preferences. 2. An inventory of how the museum is made up of materials from the city. 3. A visual survey of how the museum is made up of people from the locality.4. A description of the role played by artists, biennials in particular, in the formation of social change and in the maintenance of the biennial.5. A visual survey of the political role of artists</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Art Newsletter signaled a critical shift towards self-organizing practices and self-expression. The emergence of online art resources such as the Black-Stern Art Blog and Black-Stern Gallery marked a qualitative shift towards underground art publications and resource centers. The Black-Stern Art Newsletter also coincided with this shift, publishing information about upcoming art performances and curatorial tours as well as information about the curatorial process. These two publications, along with the Black-Stern Gallery website, with its frequent updates and revisions, marked a new stage in the history of the art institution. The website was constantly evolving, constantly being updated and hosted content from underground art resources and underground literature sites. It featured in-depth information and analysis on current art practices and curatorial strategies, as well as reviews, columns and more. It also provided a place for artists to connect with other artists, share ideas and find new ways of working. As the name implies, this was a leading art</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Art Book in the 1980s also played a part in this.    	The Black-Stern Press was started by Margaret Sullivan and her wife, Susan. It was originally published twice a year in the UK and internationally, and featured articles on a wide range of subjects, including lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender (LGBT) activism. In 1983, the journal was re-launched as a monthly magazine with a focus on lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender (LGBT) issues. It continued to publish occasional essays covering a range of topics, but in recent years it has focused on arts-related issues, particularly in the arts-intensive inner city. Its current issue (available online) features a virtual bible of arts and arts-related topics. 	The Black-Stern Art Book (1983–91), published in 1984, is the Black-Stern Press's self-selected and historically annotated selection of art books published between the years of</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Art Publishing House marked a qualitative shift from the dominance of institutional presses. The latter still dominated popular culture, but the rise of underground literary and arts publications was a telling signal that art was no longer the object of a strict classical (and Anglo-American) literary and artistic system.  The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Art Publishing House marked a qualitative shift from the dominance of institutional presses. The latter still dominated popular culture, but the rise of underground literary and arts publications was a telling signal that art was no longer the object of a strict classical (and Anglo-American) literary and artistic system.  A growing body of scholarship and commentaries has documented this shift, which is often astutely described as ‘millenarian’.3  For a recent example, see Jeffrey Meyers, Merging Cultures: Film, Media, and Postcolonialism</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Bible of Art and Politics, as well as the Black-Stern Art Bulletin Board, opened new paths to entry for artists and arts consumers. The Black-Stern Art Bulletin Board’s first publication, Black-Stern Books One Hundred Years of Black-Stern Art, marked a qualitative shift from the daily newspapers and magazines, to digital collections, which were the main form of access to art from the 1960s. The Black-Stern Art Bulletin Board’s second publication, Black-Stern Books Two Hundred Years of Black-Stern Art, reflected a similar qualitative shift from the daily newspapers and magazines, to digital collections, which were the main form of access to contemporary art from the 1980s. The Black-Stern Art Bulletin Board’s third and final publication, Black-Stern Books Three Hundred Years of Black-Stern Art, placed contemporary art on a par with earlier art forms such as clay and glass. It</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Bible served to institutionalise the practices of underground culture, and to foster a sense of shared identity among artists and their audiences. The self-help and self-improvement types, self-published authorship was finding expression not only within the confines of the self, but also in the context of other people’s bodies.Art institutions began to develop long-term curatorial agendas driven by the most recent needs of the industry. The need for a permanent large enough art market place meant that these needs prioritised large-scale set pieces, such as major exhibitions and major repurposing of sites, over smaller and more ephemeral practices, such as smaller regional or local productions of art. As a result, a strong presence of art institutions and their patrons in local communities became essential to sustain the industry. The value of this presence increased with every biennial, and even today it is often claimed that the curatorial priority is what enables and justifies the industry.11</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Playground respectively mark a significant shift from the 1950s and 1960s, when the major art publishers and the museum lobby worked alongside or alongside each other to promote and control artistic practices. As the self-published writers and poets of the 1950s and 1960s show, there was a real appetite for independent writing and creative action on a variety of levels. The explosion of poetic and literary forms in the decades leading up to the mid-1960s also provides valuable information for the decolonisation of contemporary art. This is especially relevant in our current period of economic and social disintegration, which is being fuelled by the proliferation of non-conformist media such as social media. The demand for art and visual culture is globalised, and so is the supply of visual and cultural products. It is no coincidence that the social media strategies of the 1950s and 1960s are being re-interpreted and are being put into place today, as part of the project ‘</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Arts Forum signaled a critical shift in the culture of the art market. The demand for art from anywhere increased, and the curatorial media became more visible and influential. This was accompanied by a rapid expansion of the gallery – the second largest in the UK after the museum – which was both a more conventional venue for art shows and a more visible marker of the changing face of the art market place. The Black-Stern Arts Forum regularly hosted exhibitions of contemporary art, and the Black-Stern Press regularly published essays on contemporary art and its discontents. The Black-Stern Arts Forum was instrumental in starting the self-proclaimed ‘Golden Age’ of Art in the UK.James Howard Kunstler, ‘The Black-Stern Arts Forum’, published in the Black-Stern Arts Forum (2011), describes the beginnings of the Black-Stern Arts Forum and the journal that followed.The Black-Stern Arts Forum was started in</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Art Bulletin signaled a critical shift in the literary landscape as well. These were accompanied by the rapid growth of self-starting and underground arts and culture organisations, which became important in that they could issue statements or take part in activities that were not part of a recognised body such as a festival. The Black-Stern Press published the Black-Stern Art Bulletin in its early years, and its motto was taken up by the Black-Stern Museum, the first Black-Stern Art Centre and the Black-Stern School of Art.  At the turn of the century, the Black-Stern Art Bulletin was the largest circulation art journal in Lincoln, Nebraska, and was followed by the Lincoln Arts &amp; Magazine (in Lincoln), the American Arts and Magazines (in Chicago and London), and Artnet, the first art online publication. In 2011, the Art of Us was published, and in 2015 the Black-Stern Art Bulletin was replaced by the Black</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Art Book signaled a new literary and cultural sensibility in the area. These became essential reading parts of the community of artists, curators, arts administrators and curatorial officials who would later be called the 3rd generation of the Arts Council. The Art Market place being established in Liverpool in the 1980s was a natural extension of this impulse. It offered a venue for the local art market to take root and thrive, and a place where artists, curators, arts administrators and art writers could meet, exchange, and exchange ideas. It offered a space for such gatherings to be contextualised and democratised through the exchange of ideas. The counterintuitive reality is that the Art Market place may in part be an extension of the Black-Stern Press, 3rd generation of the Arts Council, whose self-published, in-depth articles on local art practices appeared in the Black-Stern newspaper. The Black-Stern also published a sequel to the same series of articles</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The idea was to use the curatorial budget to print new ways of seeing art in ways that would be easier and more palatable to institutional audiences, perhaps even to entice those art institutions with financial incentives to join the race to become part of the ever-expanding art market.The idea that curatorial media could somehow engage with and render new conceptions of art ‘real’ was a game-changer. It marked a qualitative shift from the industry-funded and predominantly concerned with replicating the provenance of artwork on a grand scale, to a sector that was interested in developing new creative strategies. The advent of social media and other new media meant that art institutions and their patrons could access and consume art from anywhere, anytime. Although there were early critiques of the increasingly ubiquitous social media and art market place, these were mostly generated by critics of the art practice themselves. The emergence of self-published and underground literary and arts magazines such as the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Art Press signaled a new level of accessibility and accessibility in ways that would be difficult to replicate in museums or elsewhere. The emergence of self-organizing ‘curatorial communities’ such as the Black-Stern Arts Community and Black-Stern Poetry Project encouraged other arts organizations to establish similar community-based alternative art initiatives. The Black-Stern Poetry Project, for example, published poems and images online and in magazines including the Black-Stern Press and the Black-Stern Poetry Project was a local extension of the broader Black-Stern family of artists, whose work appeared in publications including the New York Times, the Nation and SF Gate. These projects, which offered a potential alternative to the museum or other curatorial practices, were often initiated by artists or arts professionals who saw an immediate need to engage with contemporary art practices and culture. They were not always successful in meeting this need, but they often demonstrated a willingness to look beyond the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421
    <text>The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust and vulnerability: Exploring Trust and Trusteeship in Art’s Social Turn, 1986–2001, Amsterdam, The John Hopkins University Press, Baltimore, USA, p.145.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust and vulnerability: Exploring Trust and Trusteeship in Art’, in Trusting Publics, ed. Stefan Collini, Milan, Italy, P. Gabrielle L. Pevsues &amp; Susanne K. Groot, Manchester University Press, Manchester, UK, 1995, p.183.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy, ‘Vulnerability and the limits of trustworthiness: A tenet of the Community Arts movement’, Art &amp; Society, Vol</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Download this article as PDFPreeana ReddyPreeana Reddy is a writer, curator and co-curator of the Art Place project, currently Director of Cultural Studies at Liverpool John Moores University, and holds a Masters in Cultural Studies from the University of Liverpool. She has a special interest in the arts and cultural ecology of neglected or threatened places. She has written for The Guardian, The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, and The American Prospect. She has a particular interest in the arts and cultural ecology of war-torn and conflict-ridden countries. Using Documenta 13 as a Case Study, she worked with Ipsos MORI to understand how the Italian biennale could be adapted to the globalising world of the internet.Preeana Reddy has written about a range of subjects for publications including health, urban development, food, fashion, identity, celebrity, migration, public transit</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47.  Mair's book Social Practice: Art, Public Trust, 2017, includes a wealth of interpretive text that attempts to unpack the ways in which trust is built into the contemporary practice of art. It is a useful and powerful resource for critical social practice scholars and artists alike.  Miriam Kramer, ‘Measuring Innovation: A Tool for Art’s Social Good’, 2017. A public figure with a studio, she heads the Art Trust, an independent, international network of galleries, arts organisations and artists' organisations that develops and directs public programmes, projects and events for the arts. In 2017, she opened Metro Gallery, a new generation of artists' studios and exhibition platforms, presenting her own work from the past 12 years through the medium of ongoing public works.  Allison Chow, ‘Trust, Uncertainty and Zap: Exploring the Psychology of Co-Determination in a Social Science Research Team’, 2017, in PLATE</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421.  Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust and intimacy: Understanding the Origins of Intimacy' , in Trusting Ourselves: From Communal Knowledge to Trusting Others , Paul A. Cacioppo, ed., pp.111–47.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust and intimacy: Understanding the Origins of Intimacy' , in Trusting Ourselves: From Communal Knowledge to Trusting Others , Paul A. Cacioppo, ed., pp.111–47.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust and intimacy: Understanding the Origins of Intimacy' , in Trusting Ourselves: From Communal Knowledge to Trusting Others , Paul A. Cacioppo, ed., pp.111–47. </text>
    <text>The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust and intimacy: Emotional intelligence as an artistic tool', 1997, Vol. 36, Issue 2, p.383–97.  Svetlana Boym, ‘Trust and intimacy: An introduction to collaborative investigation’, Enviro-Technologie &amp; Society, Vol. 33, Issue 2, p.339–47.Download this article as PDFPhilippe RahmJade Eco Park at Somerset Artspace, 2016. Installation, Philippe Rahm's The Planetary Society, 2016. Photo courtesy of Philippe Rahm.PreviousNextJade Eco Park at Somerset Artspace, 2016. Installation, Philippe Rahm's The Planetary Society, 2016. Photo courtesy of Philippe Rahm.Philippe Rahm is a New York-based artist. His installations have often been about trust and intimacy, the relationship between public</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.423–49.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Manuel Cortés, ‘Trust and lack of trust in the arts, 1989–2017, Paris, France &amp; London, UK, International Journal of Cultural Studies, Vol. 9, Issue 2, p.377–99.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Manuel Cortés, ‘Trust and lack of trust in the arts, 1989–2017, Paris, France &amp; London, UK, International Journal of Cultural Studies, Vol. 9, Issue 2, p.383.  Ipsos MOR</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47.  Pamela Tallantawalla, ‘Trust and intimacy: Bridging trust and intimacy in art’,  �The Atlantic Monthly, September/October, 1992, p.228–37.  Reddy, 2009. Towards a ecology of trust. New York: Picador.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust and intimacy: Bridging trust and intimacy in art’,  	The Atlantic Monthly, September/October, 1992, p.228.  Reddy, 2009. Towards a ecology of imagination. New York: Picador.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust and intimacy: Bridging trust and intimacy in art’,  	The Atlantic Monthly, September/October, 1992, p.229.  Reddy, 2009. Towards a ecology</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–47.  Perel Salomon, ‘Trust, Intergovernmental Panel on Climate Change, &amp; the Biennial Effect: A synoptic survey’, Academia Sinica (Winter, 2017). Vol. 32, Issue 2, Pg. 1, p.381.Download this article as PDFPreeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell​Preeana Reddy is an independent writer, curator, writer and researcher. She is Distinguished Professor in the Departments of Anthropology and Philosophy at Mount Royal University, Canada, and holds a Bachelor of Arts in English Cultural Studies from Mount Royal University, Canada, where she also participated in the Oxford Arts Festival 2017. Her writing has been featured in publications including The New Inquiry, The New Inquiry Quarterly, The A.V. Club, The A.V. Club, Nautilus, Nautilus Digital Journal, and Skeptic Magazine. Her work has also been featured in various</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will open in October 2018.  References: Biennial 2018 budget, 2017. http://www.biennalesofuk.com/2018/budapest/en/en/summary/all/biennial-2018-budget-2017.html.  Joasia Krysa, ‘On gentrification and displacement in the Croatian Cultural Centre, 2016. PDF.  Inhabitant, 2016. Installation, Croatia, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.  Methodology: World Values, Oxford University Press, Oxford, USA.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘On the use of trust in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, by trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–65.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–73.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue 2 &amp; 3, p.421–74.  Ipsos MORI Poll, 2017.   Preeana Reddy &amp; Nadine Attewell, ‘Trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts: A meta-analytic examination of trust, intimacy and creativity in the arts, 1991–2017, Vol. 14, Issue</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests
    <text>biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests in the Arctic, South and Central America, and the Middle East. He is the author of several books including the recently released Animals for Show and People: Social Exhibitions in the Modern World (2006). His latest is Animal Memoirs (2014), a memoir of his time at the Museum of Comparative Art and Design in Amsterdam.A postcard from the Biennale of Sydney Everett. Courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextA postcard from the Biennale Archive. Courtesy of the Biennale Archive.A postcard from the Biennale Archive.A postcard from the Biennale Archive.A postcard from the Biennale Archive.A postcard from the Biennale Archive.A postcard from the Biennale Archive.A postcard from the Biennale Archive.A postcard from the Biennale Archive.A postcard from the Biennale Archive.A postcard from the Biennale Archive</text>
    <text>biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests including advanced geographical systems, language and cultural analysis, and the intersection of urban and national contexts. His publications include the award-winning Language Log (1991), which won the Padma Bhushan Prize for Science and Culture in Venice, the National Geographic Reader (1997) and International best-seller Language of the Coming Urban Space (2001). He is a past president of the International Geographical Society and was a co-editor of the prestigious international journal Permutation in 2011. He served as editor of Permutation from 2007-09.He is the author of The Permutation Reader (2006) and the forthcoming New Statesman (2014). He has been a MacArthur Fellow and the TED Fellow, and has been a fellow of the Royal Geographical Society, Glasgow, and the RPS Society, Liverpool. He has been an advisor to the BBC, The Open School, and the BBC Children's Science and Technology Programme. He is currently a professor of Geographic Information Technologies at McGill University,</text>
    <text>biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests including postanarchism, science and technology studies, and art and infrastructure. His most recent books include The Geographies of American Fascism (2007 and forthcoming), Essays on Postcolonialism (with Paul McEwen, 2015) and the co-editor of the forthcoming academic edition of Popular Geographies: Regional Studies for a Global Context (2017). He is the co-editor and co-founder of (ed) The Geographical Journal (2015), with Patrick Joyce, on the Geographies of Fascism (1993) and Popular Geographies: Contemporaneous Futures (1995). He is the author of several books published in collaboration with Patrick Joyce, including The Geographies of Anti-fascist Movements (1994), Antinomies of American Anti-fascist Movements (1998) and Popular Culture, Globalized Anarchism (2004), with Lynn Tolmon, and the recent The Geographies of Intimidation (2017). His writing has appeared in publications including the New</text>
    <text>biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests in post-Holocene climatology and the intersection of modern and cultural geography. His books include the award-winning Paleofuture: Globalization and the Episodic with Artus Mullen (2006), the New Geographies: Cities and Cultures of Globalization (2008) and the collections Global Postures: Art and Geographies (with Laurie Peake and David Locke, 2015). He is the recipient of two literary awards, one for his novel Sea of Poppies (2003) and the other for The Ghost of Mao: Writer and Philosopher on Cultural Politics and Stalinist China (2012). He has been a lecturer at Royal College of Art, University of London (2003–08); UCLA (2000–08) and Yale University (2000–04). He is the author of several books including the recently published Animals for Show and People for Play: Essays on the Cultural Cost of Animal Cultures (2006) and the collection World System: Essays on the Uses</text>
    <text>biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests in the Americas, Central America and the Middle East. His publications include several collections of primary source works on topics spanning geography, archival practices and media, including the 2012 New York Times best-seller The Americas in Crisis. His writing has also appeared in The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Times Magazine and The New York Times Op-Ed pages, among others.In addition to his regular columns in The Washington Post and The New York Times, Putnam is a regular commentator on television and radio, including the CBC's The Current Tonight (CBC Radio One, CBC Television, Montreal), as well as CBC News websites including The Current TV and The Current Web. His latest works include the music and dance CD Things Fall Apart (2017) and the film Things Fall Apart (2018).Biennial membership is open to scholars, artists, collectors, and anyone else with expertise or knowledge relevant to the entity or practice of biennials. For more information, visit</text>
    <text>biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests including advanced metric, the origins of city-states, and advanced nomadic forms of data extraction. His publications include the award-winning The Geographical Primer (1984), Geographies of Intense Politics: The Biennial Condition (1997), Recent Advances in Digital Imaging (with Colin Ward and Christian Körner) and Moving Images (with Colin Ward and Christian Körner). He is a co-editor of the forthcoming Geographical Indicators (2014) and has written for the journal Digital Culture, where his articles have been edited. 	[2] As early as the mid-1990s, biennials were frequently cited as a factor in the character of the social. In David Harvey and Rob Klingensmith’s Social Darwin Futures of the Recent Past (1991) they were cited as an influence on the cultural and political evolution of the present. Later, Alfred North Whitehead noted the ‘becoming a monolith of records’ and the</text>
    <text>biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests including forms of historiography, language, and urbanization. He is part of the research team for the Centre’s new Narrative Architecture project, which examines the links between narrative architecture and spatialisation in the history of cities. His publications include the collections of the Geographical Society of London (2007-2015); the book Two Thousand Plateaus: The Geographies of Biennials (2011) and the forthcoming book Geographies of Biennialism.A Place Called HomeBienal de São Paulo, BrazilMarch 2015The word ‘place’ conjures up images of rugged wildernesses and exotic locales, of trees and wilderness, of fish and wildlife. But in many parts of the world, the place that comes to mind when looking to escape poverty or oppression is located in the greater urban area. This is especially true in the cities that are the site of major protests against poverty or oppression. The term is used to describe ‘homeplacement projects’</text>
    <text>biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests in the Americas, Eastern Europe, and the Middle East. His publications include the internationally acclaimed best-selling books The Geographies of Crisis (1984), The Geographies of Revolution (1996), and the recently published World Politics in Crisis: Globalization and Its Divisions (2007). He has written many articles on related subjects. In 2014, he co-edited with Peter Osborne the anthology World Politics in Crisis: Social Science and Politics (with Peter Osborne, Arista Books, New York, 2015). He is the co-editor of numerous books and apparels, including those on contemporary global issues including the People, the Geographies of Rebellion (2012) and the soon to be released World Politics in Crisis: Geographies of Rebellion (2017). He is the author of several books and numerous position statements, including the recent World Politics in Crisis: Globalization and Its Divisions (2007) and World Politics in Crisis: Geographies of Rebellion (2015). He is also the co-editor</text>
    <text>biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests in habitation, demography, and internationalization. His publications include more than twenty books published between 1977 and 1999, including the award-winning The Geographical Dictionary of Modern Places (1984) and the National Geographic Traveler (1990), as well as co-editing the New York Times best-seller Earth in Crisis (1998).He is the host of Geographies with Neil Johnson, produced and co-hosted by Universitas Radio, and is the co-author of The Anatomy of a Biennial (2007) and the award-winning Human Geographies (with Neil Johnson, 2006).He is also the co-editor of the upcoming Quarterly Journal of the American Geographer. Advances in Human Geography: From Zero to Geographies (2007) are a natural outgrowth of the book and Geographies (2013) that he edited with Neil Johnson, including the 2006 New York Times best-seller We Are Alive!, which documented the 2007 Beijing Olympics. Ge</text>
    <text>biennials past and present), the emergence of such a notion threatens to undo decades of work. If left unaddressed, such an approach could well hasten the demise of biennial as we know it, making its recent past a thing of the past. 	[1] The term ‘biennial’ was used by Norman Putnam in his classic book The Collectors (1907) to describe those periods of extraordinary and sometimes catastrophic change in the global cultural landscape that he traced to the end of the nineteenth century. The term has since then been a staple of academic and pop-cultural usage, with biennials accounting for much of the vernacular change in the 1980s and 1990s. See, for instance, Norman Putnam, The Collectors, 1920.Download this article as PDFNorman PutnamNorman Putnam is Professor of Geography and Director of the Geographical Centre, McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Geographical Information Systems, with research interests in post-Holocene, the past, and cultural geography. His publications include numerous collections of essays and articles on topics spanning a wide range of contemporary globalisation and postcoloniality, from the workshelf of popular language to the pages of a popular bookshelf. He has written or edited over twenty books on a wide range of topics, including on languages, archipelagos, archipelagic archipelagic archipelagos, archipelatre, nation-states, cities, art, culture, history and archipelagic archipelagic archipelagic archipelago. His most recent work, Geographies of Crisis: Globalisation and Its Remake (2011), reviews the geo-politically charged legacy of the crisis of capitalism.He is the host of the weekly geostrategy show Geostrategies (Global Public Radio and CBC, Canada), and is the editor of the online journal Geopolitics. His latest book is The Global Economy of Cultures: Economics</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 K
    <text>vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 7 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 8 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 9 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 10 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19.  Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D. 	Michael Truscello is an Internal Medicine physician who specialises in managing chronic conditions. He is a prolific blogger and prolific  disseminater of academic</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 7 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 8 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 9 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 10 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 11 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 12 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’,</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 7 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 8 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 9 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 10 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 11 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 12 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’,</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 7 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 8 The New York Times (2007), p. 9. 9 Michael Ames,  The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (July, 1970), p. 1-19. 10 John Berger,  The New York Times, 17 January 1973,  1, p. 1. 11 John Berger,  The New York Times, 17 January 1973, 2, p. 1. 12 John Berger,  The New York Times, 17 January 1973, 3, p. 1. 13 John Berger,  The New York Times, 17 January 1973, 4, p. 1. 14 John Berger,  The New York Times, 17 January</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 7 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 8 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 9 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 10 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19.  11 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 12 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 7 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 8 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 9 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 10 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19.  11 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 12 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 Keegan Langbaner,  The Art Newspaper (London), p. 1-19. 7 Keegan Langbaner,  The Art Newspaper (London), p. 1-19. 8 John Weibel,  The New Journalism (New York and New Haven, Yale University Press, 1997), p. xiii. 9 Keegan Langbaner,  The Art Newspaper (London), p. 1-19. 10 Keegan Langbaner,  The Art Newspaper (London), p. 1-19. 11 Weibel, New Journalism, p. 84. 12 Weibel, The New Journalism, p. 86. 13 Weibel, The New Journalism, p. 87. 14 Weibel, The New Journalism, p. 89. 15 Weibel, The New Journalism, p. 90. 16 Weibel, The New Journalism, p. 91. Download this article</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 7 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 8 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 9 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 10 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 11 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 12 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’,</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 7 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 8 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 9 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 10 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 11 Becca Stokes, ‘Excerpt from ‘Excerpt from ‘Song of the South Asian Subcontinent’, in The New Inquiry, Issue 6 (September, 2012), p. 1-30</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data on the subject).  For more information, see The Art Newspaper, Issue 6 (Summer 2010), and The Art Newspaper, Issue 7 (Fall 2010), both published by The Art Newspaper.  1 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 2 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 3 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 4 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 5 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 6 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 7 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 8 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 9 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 10 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (February, 2012), p. 1-19. 11 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 6 (August, 2011), p. 1-19. 12 Keegan Langbaner, ‘The Art Newspaper’, Issue 7 (</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit
    <text>machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit, and the biennial’s current position and mission statement suggest a clear break with this historical simple-going.  It is often claimed that the biennial has become a city, and cities ‘cumulus’ are the order of the day.  This claim is not only ungrounded, but is set up as a reductive set of opposites: biennials are invariably located in their cities, and cities the primary audience for their productions.  The real break with this historical historical paradigm is offered by projects such as that of Envisioning a City, a curatorial effort that sought to reconcile a biennial with the city’s industrial core by turning the biennial into an object of contemplation rather than an object of destruction.  Envisioning a City is a project at Tate Modern that seeks to create a ‘concept for action’ through curatorial works that capture ‘the dynamism, passion and ambition of a place’.[</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit, and the biennial has a documented history of hiding, prevarication and other kinds of self-deception.  It is true, too, that, while the art world has often shown an interest in a project through a curatorial stunt, the biennial has a proven and institutionalized interest in its own self-perception and image. The biennial has a perversely self-critical character that is grounded in its desire to connect with the viewer, a fantasy of audience members who will come for art and culture and leave for stockbrokers and law firms.  The host institution has an agenda that is often frustrated by the realities of the situation, and often successful at driving those realities away.  The most iconic example of this was the 1990 Venice Biennale, when the Giardini lost out to the Visitor's Bureau because it was too expensive, and the presence of 4,000,000 visitors instead enticed many visitors by promising them a percentage of future developments</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit, and the biennial’s current focus on the city effectively precludes, by design, critical or speculative exploration of the city’s socio-politically dynamic architecture and urban possibilities.  As a biennial convention, the biennial is entwined with the city’s wider metropolis and  generates much of its identity and narrative for the convention.  As a result, the city is often read as the author of the biennial, a position that actively or tricklesly modifies historical and contemporary economic, cultural and political dynamics.  The city is often read as the locus of the conflicts and tensions generated by the capitalist metropolis, but here too the author is often an enabler of capitalist ideologies and behaviours.  The city organises and processes knowledge, creating worlds based on assumptions, dreams and practices. ‘Capital of the Future?’, a popular children’s book published in 1974, offers a good starting point in imagining</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit, and the biennial has a global reach.  Its 2009 discovery, the LA River project, for example, which sought to harness the power of the LA River to generate electric power through the deployment of rooftop solar panels, became a global phenomenon.  Biennials have a dual function: they occur as exhibitions of curatorial creativity, and they also happen as occasions of curatorial over-reach.  They become cultural institutions, and not merely collections of art. But they are also material sites of curatorial over-reach, with material objects deployed at a site that are often used to support the culture of a country, often at a time when that country is experiencing an economic and social crisis. In a recent report on the impact of climate change on the US West Coast, a research team led by Kevin Anderson of the US Geological Survey agreed that the increased use of hydraulic fracturing for shale gas could preventingly be ruled out as a primary means of</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit, and the biennial’s current focus on the city is an artifact of the city’s economic malaise. Local communities are often the first to be visited by project visitors, and these communities are often the ones with the most to lose by a development that seeks to obliterate their historic places of culture and identity.  Biennial attendance has remained stable throughout this century, hovering around the estimated 15,000 mark in most years.  A little over one-third of the attendance at Venice Biennale in 2009 was due to cultural homemaking, with the rest due to tourism (65%, to be exact).  The astronomical number of visitors (more than 11 million in 2014 alone) is a testament to the biennial’s resiliency.  The reason for this remarkable survival of the biennial in critical or revolutionary condition is that its true believers have found other things to do with their time.  Biennials are now too ubiquitous to be counted</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit. Curatorial-institutional exchanges are common in biennials these days.  For instance, the Los Angeles County Museum of Art (the successor to the venerable Santa Monica Museum of Art) launched its 2014 meeting, ‘Curatorial Histories: LA: The Biennial Challenge’, to coincide with the biennial’s one-year anniversary in 2015.  The biennial has become a regular feature of the city, and its ubiquity is now widely attributed to a combination of economic development and the museum’s growth, primarily as a result of the biennial convention, which increased the museum’s profile and revenue streams.3  A little-known feature of the biennial is that it is, for the most part, a one-time event. While its stated purpose is to document the life of the biennial over a specified period of time (with a fixed, predictable destination), the real purpose of the biennial is to</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit.  The problem with the biennial is that it is a static object: it is neither a collection nor a collection of objects. Its historical position is suspect, too.  The biennial is a dynamic and transient object, like any other visitor to a city or a particular neighbourhood. Its continuity and permanence are proven by its proliferation within the city.  It moves from museum to museum, from museum to city, and from city to city. It exhibits in different forms, in different venues, in different social settings, and within different cultural zones. It is a dynamic mixture of historical, curatorial, and urban explorations of the city, of cultural practices, and of people. It is a back story, a weave, and a tapestry. It is a ‘biennial in its own right’.  And yet, at the same time, it is a fundamentally unstable combination of curatorial and exhibitionary work. It exhibits in museums, it is a �</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit.  Biennials can and do exist in a particular location, and their current collections are a valuable resource for curators searching for a particular element of a given project.  But the biennial as a curatorial pursuit today tends to be a site-specific enterprise, operating at a scale and in a particular neighborhood, operating with a curatorial team that is engaged in a contractual relationship with a particular location. Its resources and 'lives' in the museum are usually limited to those who are already members of the curatorial team, or have connections to the institution.  In the case of a biennial that maintains a permanent location in the city, this becomes a ‘living’ art-historical collection that brings together works from different places and with different times, occupying a specific space and time. It is a very specific collection, and as such seeks to grasp the historical, social and political context of a particular location, undertaking what historian Peter Weibel describes as a �</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit, and the biennial’s current position can be interpreted as a return to this historical practice.  With the collapse of the biennial, the biennial has largely been replaced by the similar-looking trade and cultural publication, or CBM, which is also published by Condé Nast, the parent company of the New York Times and the New Yorker.2    In the 1980s, the biennial was a regular visitor to the Whitechapel Gallery, where it patronized the gallery space for a number of years.3  In 1987, the biennial was relocated to Munich, and in 1989, it visited Santiago, Chile.4  The CBM was founded in 1888 by Norman Mailer in New York’s Lower East Side. It was the first British biennial to originate in North America, and also the first to feature an exclusively Italian art section. Its mission statement reads in part: ‘To chronicle the cultural life of the United</text>
    <text>machine learning experiments on information architecture and machine learning, with a special focus on the growing prominence of machine learning within the scientific and commercial realms.[1] While the field has recently shown signs of recovering its pre-crisis size and momentum, its current state of expansion and disruption is staggering. For more than a quarter of a century, the biennial has been a fixture of the US landscape; now it is increasingly evident that its fortunes are more tied up in the urban centers where, thanks to policies of urban rehabilitation and regeneration, the biennial is positioned against the backdrop of a rapidly developing metropolis.  In recent years, the biennial has tended to occupy a fixed spatial and temporal position in the city, usually defined by a single developer or corporation (including local governments when they are abutting on the city's borders).  Such is the biennial today, but its historical position is suspect. The museum is often the first stop for visitors seeking information on a project or a curatorial pursuit.  The model was developed by the New Museum and the Museum of Contemporary Art, and it has been widely adopted by local and national arts institutions. It is true that the biennial became commercially viable through the financial viability of art museums, but this has come at a great cost to the communities that the museums are sent to. Moreover, the growth of these local art institutions has put a great strain on the fragile biennial industry, which is suffering under the weight of rising membership fees and an ever-expanding budget. The growing number of cities they inhabit has its own sustainability issues to consider. Still, the biennial industry is in a bind. It cannot expand at the pace of its metropolis, and it cannot shrink at the rate of its metropolis either. It cannot both publish less and be more of both. It cannot simultaneously publish and be both a museum and a biennial. It can neither meet both the demands of a metropolis and the needs of a biennial. So</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
