<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state
    <text>The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. The citizens are the foot soldiers of the state, and their involvement requires great courage and integrity. The project is a powerful tool for resistance, and it is the commitment of talented and committed citizens who understand the power dynamics at play in this city. 	The people who initiated and directed the project have stated that they see this as an ongoing project, and that they have their hands on things for a long time. This is a valid perspective, and it is difficult to disenchant someone who has such access to so many resources. However, the city’s role in the project has grown increasingly questionable. The state has intervened more and more frequently, and now even takes part in the running of the city. It is unclear what role the city can play in this process, or whether the city is even a core part of the country. The fact that the city is a major international shipping port now means that it dominates intra-regional trade, and it is this dominant status that</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. It is a step towards a new constitution for the city. The new political framework will enable the city to negotiate new economic and social models for the city. This will allow the city to create its own future for the people. The city’s participation comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. It is a step towards a new constitution for the city. The new political framework will enable the city to negotiate new economic and social models for the city. This will allow the city to create its own future for the people. 	The new framework will also allow the city to institute its own development path. This will allow for the establishment of cooperative and worker-owned co-operatives –</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. The authorities cannot hide behind a wall of rhetoric and refuse to confront the violence that is taking place. So the project was a risky and brave one to take part in, and it is a project that will likely end up doing more harm than good.  	The city council of Liverpool is expected to make a decision on the project in the coming weeks. If passed, the project will become a reality and create 100 jobs at the Miocene base. If not, a court battle could be expected. The decision to make the project a reality will come down to the oil and gas companies, who will then decide whether to invest in the area or not. If the project is a sham and the local residents are not consulted, or do not take part in the project, then the projects destruction will be swift and brutal. 	If the council decides to give the project a try, then the question is which of two projects will be built? The first attempt will be the most successful,</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. The catalyst may well be the same thing that makes the company that manufactures the bullets – the state. The state has used violence, arrests, detention and prison camps on and off for over a century. The question is whether the company that manufactures the bullets – the state – should be able to turn a profit on the back of this violence and repression. The company that makes the bullets certainly seems to think that it does. The question is how far does the state have to turn to absorb these profits? If the company that makes the bullets is able to turn a profit, then the state has little reason to waste any more of its scarce tax dollars on the projects that generate only temporary relief for the cities. If the city cannot afford to pay for the projects that produce only temporary relief, then the developers have little choice but to jack up the prices of the real estate in the city in order to fund the projects that generate even bigger profits for the company that makes the bullets. The city has two</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. It is a powerful tool for resisting the law enforcement state. The project is a true demonstration of what can be accomplished through direct action. It is a powerful testament to the capacity of a small group of committed individuals. It is an exercise in in humanity combined with a violent act. 	The tradition of activism begins long before direct action projects are conceived. In fact, the ideas and strategies developed during the course of direct action are fundamental to the development of mass consciousness and political change today. The importance of these strategies cannot be underestimated. They lay the groundwork for future action, but they also establish the basis for future resistance. 	To understand the history of direct action and mass mobilisation in the context of the current crisis, we must distinguish between those who participate in the project professionally and those who do not. The former must be defined as those who actually participate in the project, while those who do not are referred to as ‘reference’. The professional is defined as someone who</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. The participation of local people, whether it is the local ​​tribes or the city’s non-Native citizens in this particular project, is a powerful way to raise awareness and demand change. These interactions pave the way for action and sometimes even revolutions. 	There are many questions that still need to be answered about the project, and the reasons why the city chose to participate. Questions that still need to be debated and negotiated are why on earth did the city need to be forcibly relocated? Why did the city council have to pass a resolution formally recognising the historic role of the city and declaring the project a heritage site? Why did the city council have to pass a resolution formally recognising the direct historical relationship between the city and the project? Why did the council have to make a decision to prohibit the city from developing a new airport on the site of the former airport? Why did the city council have to pass a resolution formally recognising the direct historical relationship between the city and</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. Acknowledging the systemic nature of the crisis, Community Arts Collective was established as a result of the information gathered from the project. This included direct action, actions such as sit-ins and direct action by citizens, as well as research into art and culture that serves as a counter to the violence and repression unleashed by the state.2  The Community Arts Collective is a new kind of artist collective: producing social and ecological change through creative action on the city’s behalf. It was started with the mission to protect and enhance the cultural assets of the city while enabling a more local vantage point by bringing artists from around the globe together. This would mean enabling artists to work in the city while creating mechanisms to support their work from the city as a source of creativity. The collective was originally founded in New York in 1972 and expanded in 1974.3  The Community Arts project was originally commissioned by the New York Public Library and part of the U.S. National Endowment</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. The participation of professionals in the construction of infrastructure is a necessity in any such movement. In the case of the Dakota Access Pipeline, the state had military forces on the ground in North Dakota to protect the pipeline against attack. The participation of civil society in such an attack was essential in our undertaking, since the entire project was based on fraud and fake science. The involvement of academics in such projects is somewhat unusual, but in this context the engagement of such bodies is routine and seemingly routine-ish work. It is the job of the art director of a major art museum to provide art for a project that is purely decorative in nature, and the artist is not exceptional in this respect. 	In this project, the engagement of the arts director is essential in maintaining the legitimacy of the project. Without her efforts, there is no way to know what is real and what is not. Without her efforts, there would be no way to resist the institutionalisation of violence and oppression. The engagement of the</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. The project has even been endorsed by the German Green Party.1 	Since its beginning, the project has offered a range of activities for interested citizens to take part in. These range from writing songs and poems to setting up ‘temporary housing units’ for 120 to 180 families, as well as organising visits by groups of tourists to see the houses previously destroyed by the city.2 	Such projects have their own peculiarities and idiosyncrasies. For example, the original intention of the Caddo Crescent Project was to create a new cultural centre for the area, but the city’s economic entanglement with the coal terminal has made the development of such a project seem redundant. Instead, the new cultural centre often seems like a re-negotiation of the old order, with artists, musicians, dancers and other cultural assets utilising the potential lost amongst the rubble of the city. 	The original project was started by a small group of local residents and artists</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on what will become of the city, as the region is forcibly relocated. It is a response to the displacement of the Standing Rock Sioux and their allies from their ancestral homelands. It is an attempt to create a new context for their place in the city. What began as a project for a theoretical exercise soon turned into a project that produced tangible effects. The response from the city intensified as more local citizens took part, and the project gained momentum. As a result, the city is no longer dependent on the company it keeps. This has clearly been a struggle for the city. 	The city’s decision to take part in the project comes as no surprise to those who have been documenting the ongoing violence and repression of the Native people for years. The violence has escalated significantly in the last few years, with at least 7,000 people being killed in the name of the security forces. The project serves as a catalyst for citizens to come forward and expose the criminal nature of the state. The city’s participation comes as no surprise, given the historical context. Our project came as no surprise to the city, given the history of collaboration between the two administrations. 	As a result of the project, the U.S. Army Corps of Engineers issued a cease-fire declaration, which was subsequently extended by the U.S. Attorney General. The declaration stated that the project was fully comply  	with the law, and that the project would be fully returned to its original site. The project came as no surprise to the city, given that the Army Corps had already declared that the project was not only illegal but un-American. The project came as no surprise to the FBI, given that the bureau had been investigating the project from the start. The decision to re-route the pipeline came as no surprise to the city, given that the FBI had been monitoring the project from the start. The decision to pull the plug on the project came as no surprise to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press
    <text>biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), p. 159. 	[v] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of two types of art museums’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950), p. 175. 	[vi] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), p. 169. 	[vii] White, op. cit., p. 3. 	[viii] S. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of two types of art museums’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950), pp. 175–76. 	[ix</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 2005), p. 19. 	[v] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Present (New York: Oxford University Press, 2005), p. 23. 	[vi] Gareth White, ‘The Biennale: A Social History of Art and Cultural Studies (Revised Edition), 2 nd ed., 4 th ed., (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2013), pp. 177–90. 	[vii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950), p. 1. 	[viii] Goldberg, op. cit., p. 2. 	[ix] Stine, op. cit.,</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1996), p. 18. 	[v] M.A. Friedman, ‘Gladstone, Gladstone Valley, the first dam built on Vancouver’s North Shore’, in H.A. Friedman and R.A. Agarwal, eds., Biennales: Volume 1: The Agarwal Collection, Drawings of Illustrations, 1962–67, P. 109–20. Download this article as PDFGareth WhiteGareth White is an artist. His work in collaboration with the Agarwal Family Fund and the Canadian Centre for History and Criticism, has been commissioning the Agarwal Family Fund, a not-for-profit organization founded in 1959 by Agarwal Sr. to commemorate the life and work of his great-grandson, Murray Agarwal. M.A. Gareth White is the Curator for the Solomon R. Guggenheim Collection, the largest surviving collection</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1999), p. 266. 	[v] Nicholas Rankin and Christian Ulrik On the Origins and Origins of the Biennale, see also: Roland Schlieffen, ‘On the nature of the biennale’,  	Signal, 6:2 (July/August 1991), p. 9. 	[vi] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1999), p. 270. 	[vii] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1999), p. 271. 	[viii] Nicholas Rankin, ‘The rise of the biennale: an overview’,  	Signal, 6:2 (July/August 1991), p. 8. 	[ix] G</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), p. 9. 	[v] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), p. 10. 	[vi] Gareth White, The Biennale, a critical study of the past (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1992), p. 2. 	[vii] Gareth White, The Biennale, a critical study of the past, p. 14. 	[viii] Gareth White, The Biennale, a critical study of the past (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1993), p. 3. 	[ix] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds, p. 2.</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1999), p. 9. 	[v] Gareth White (ed.), The Cambridge Biennale (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1995), p. 9. 	[vi] White, op. cit., p. 11. 	[vii] J.D. Dewsbury, ‘On the relationship of art and social change: a case study of the Cambridge and Museum biennales’, in C. McNeill, The Cambridge Biennale Reader (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2015), p. 87. 	[viii] The Biennale Archive, 2016, accessed September 2018. 	[ix] Gareth White, op. cit., p. 14. 	[x] William J. Guilford, ‘External forms of cultural production: social, economic and spatial logic of the biennale’, in C. Mc</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1992), p. 95. 	[v] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1992), p. 96. 	[vi] Gareth White, ‘The Biennale, a biennale’, in J.A. Szeman, ed., The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1990–91, p. 262), p. 9. [vii] C.A. Lawrence, ‘The general theory of climatology predicts that as the climate warms, the earth will grind to a halt’, in S.A. Priestley &amp; S.A. Priestley, Radiative and Robust Templates of Global Climate Change (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1990), p. 9. [viii] G.P. Wan</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1977), p. 90. 	[v] S. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950), p. 9. [vi] Gareth White, The Biennale: A Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1977), p. 92. [vii] Gareth White, 'The Biennale as an Event', in White, White and Faber, edited by Gareth White and Rob La Fren (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2013), pp. 93–99. [viii] Gareth White, The Rise of the Antinomies (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2006), p. 14. [ix] Gareth White, ‘The Biennale as</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1994), p. 106. 	[v] John Nash, ‘On the level of the Biennale’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950), pp. 110–11. 	[vi] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950), pp. 112–15. 	[vii] A.A. Bergh, ‘The level of the Biennale is the level of the spectators’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950), pp. 113–14. 	[viii] White</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, including the collaboration between artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and historian Geoff Cox, who is currently Professor of History and Head of the Department of History, Art and Design at Liverpool John Moores University. 	[i] The Biennale was the brainchild of Bernard Stiegler, who proposed the idea in 1961. 	[ii] Gareth White, The Biennale: International or Cultural Crisis? (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2014), p. 9. 	[iii] A.A. Bergh, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’, in S. Bergh, The Cambridge Companion to Art and Art’s Worlds (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1950). 	[iv] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1993), p. 7. 	[v] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1993), p. 7. 	[vi] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Critical Study of the Past (New York: Oxford University Press, 1993), p. 7. 	[vii] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Cultural Critique of the Present (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1995), p. 14. 	[viii] Gareth White, The Biennale, a Cultural Critique of the Present (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1995), p. 7. 	[ix] Gareth White, ‘On the level of the Biennale, a comparison of the two types of art museum’ (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1961), p. 11.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and
    <text>present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and editor of the Open Form website, where the art and cultural exchange was curated by Simone Oppenheimer and the New Cultural Centre.She is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs at MIT Jonah Hill, and co-curator of the forthcoming The Bluecoat Project, New Cultural Centre, 2016. Her articles and essays have been published in the New York Times, The Atlantic and The Washington Post among others.She is a partner at Ropsten &amp; Coopers LLP, where she has served as Managing Partner and has held the position of Director since 2013. She has also served on the boards of the Southwark Arts Forum and is a past President of the Southwark Arts Forum.In 2015 she co-founded and co-chaired the Open Form (a not-for-profit cultural organisation dedicated to the exchange of culture, arts and expertise) in Santa Monica, California. She is a founding partner of the Open Form Gallery,</text>
    <text>present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and script-writer. She is the Curator for the 13th Annual San Remo, 2013. Institutional Approaches to CuratingJordan B. PetersonInstitutional Approaches to CuratingJordan B. Peterson is a designer and co-founder of Institutional Approaches to Curating, a design and cultural organisation based in New York City. He has worked as a designer for museums, commercial real estate and institutional environments for over twenty years. His current projects include the installation Institutional Approaches to Curating: The Rise and Fall of the 'New Curator' (2016), which documents the 400-plus year old tradition of the prestigious museum, the designer and his team, in the modern context, in a new documentary titled Institutions for a New Curator (2017). He is the author of numerous books, including the New Critic: Toward a Sustainability of Art and Culture (2011), Culture and Criticism in an Uncertain New World (</text>
    <text>present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and co-editor of the journal Stage (2016). She is also a co-editor of the book Placidity: Power, Politics &amp; Placidity (with Emily Pringle) published by The New Art Gallery.She has written for the New York Times, The Guardian, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Education Supplement and The New Inquiry, among others. She has lectured at the American Enterprise Institute, The American Enterprise Institute &amp; The New Republic, The Oxford Union, and The New Inquiry. She is a regular contributor to the New York Times Higher Education Supplement, The Atlantic &amp; Standard, and has a regular role as host of the Ann Arbor Man (Ann Arbor, Michigan) and The Current Time (Ann Arbor, Michigan) radio shows.She was a co-curator of the Venice Biennale (2014-2015), co-curator of the Crotone Gallery, The New Criterion, and co-curator</text>
    <text>present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and co-editor of the book New Curators. She is currently co-curating the Venice Biennale, which is being organized by the Curator General alongside the Institute of Contemporary Art, Venice.The Bluecoat 	Since 2003, when I co-founded and co-curated the Vorticism installation in the Krysa Gallery, I have been curator of public experience at the Chiang Mai Art &amp; Design Museum, Thailand. In 2004, I worked as a research assistant at the Kathy Luty Memorial Institute of Art, University of California, San Diego. In 2006, I trained as an artist at the Granby Four Seasons Art Department, University of California, Davis. In 2008, I joined the staff of the Kathy Luty Memorial Institute of Art, University of California, Davis, where I worked alongside Susanne Kruse, Kate Beaton, and others. In 2009, I graduated from the department</text>
    <text>present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and co-editor of the journal The Wiley-Blackwell , and was an editor of the book The Invisible Cities. She has edited the book Art and Architecture of the Future City (2015) and edited the online companion to the same journal. She is currently the editor of the online companion to the same journal.Over the past decade and a half, I have been fortunate to be invited to curate the inaugural Venice Biennale as part of the Curatorial Faculty at New York University. My research interests include biennials, their curatorial strategies and, more broadly, the contemporary condition of urban and regional environments. I was previously an Assistant Professor at Norton, New York University and Yale University, and a Professor at New School, New York University. I have also taught on the School of Art, Film and Design at MIT, where I co-curated the online version of the journal The Wiley-Blackwell (2015) and edited the online</text>
    <text>present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and editor. She has written for the trade publications Diablero (Italy) and Neue Zürcher Zeitung (Germany). She has edited Open Art (2013), Current Culture (2014), and edited The New Criterion (2016). Biennials: The Enduring Biennial Condition Emma Cline-Johnston and Prem Krishnamurthy  discuss the persistence of biennials as essential elements of their recurrence, in a series of articles published in the journal Stages in 2016. They note that the biennial remains an ‘essentialist fiction in which the individual is seen as the centre of the fictity’, despite the increasingly normalized exchange of people and things occurring around us. They respond to the problematic nature of the biennial by proposing a series of questions that would allow readers to work through the increasingly complex layers of the annual form, from its earliest historical phases (the tourist, the festival goer, the journalist)</text>
    <text>present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and editor of the Biennalee des Eaux, the exhibition planner, and editor of the journal Entheoretica. She is the editor of the book The Venice Biennale Reader, published by The Venice Biennale Trust and The Oasis, a biennale companion to the Biennalee des Eaux. Approved by The Biennale Trust for her book The Venice Biennale Reader, she has written for the online Delphin and as Curator of Promenades at The Pirate Bay, and was an adviser for the online Dolphin’s Empire project. She is part of the Curatorial Faculty for the 26th Biennale of Sydney, Australia (2016-2019), and part of the Curatorial Faculty for the 7th Venice Biennale, where she co-curated the online Performer’s Podium and curated the online</text>
    <text>present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and editor of the Venice Biennale website and as an advisor for the 2016 Venice Biennale workshops, where she participated in the curatorial process as well as the public programming. She also co-curated one of the programmes of the European Regional Archive, when the region was visited by British cultural explorers.Over the past two years, the Biennale has been returning to its roots as a biennale, staging a number of installations, and arranging for the performance of a number of works from the past ten years. The Biennale is a significant and sometimes significant presence in its city, and continues to be so even in its absence. Its production values and rhetoric, its production of place and its production of people are the subject of ongoing research and evaluation. In 2016, the Biennale commissioned a three-year, multi-disciplinary, collaborative research project, the largest ever undertaken in a single city, into the life and works of the Biennale. The project, led</text>
    <text>present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and editor. Recent books include The New Criterion (2017), What is Contemporary Art? (2016) and documentary film work such as Dazzles (2015), Walls (2016), and (to be published) soon to be co-public domain work The Long Dark (2017). She was a curator for the Organisation Internationale de L’Art Contempora (2015), and curated the 16th Istanbul Biennale, which she curated alongside her husband, Alexander).The Collaborative State: How Collaborative Technologies Shape PoliticsAnna Colin 	In this writing I attempt to capture the spirit of the collaboration that takes place every day between the user (user, me) and the media (media, institutions) that produce what we inhabit. I begin by drawing parallels between the work of the news media and that of artists, and between publics and collaborative intranational artist-publics. Then, I sketch out two modes of engagement: what I would call ‘</text>
    <text>present an online project in order to document the experiences of their live-action/animated pre-Internet film/video project, The New Critical Film, (2014-present), which was also exhibited at the 2014 Venice Biennale.Samantha Jones (2015-ongoing) and Radhika Reddy (presented by Creators Project) present their ideas and bio of Future City at the launch of The Resident at the Venice Biennale, 2014. The project was supported by the Leverhulme Trust and the Leverhulme Arts Trust.Download this article as PDFJoasia KrysaJoasia Krysa is a writer/curator based in Berlin. Recent projects include: The Bluecoat (2014), The Three Musketeers (2015) and The Invisible Cities (2016). She has co-curated the Venice Biennale since 2011, and co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, where she served as an organiser, facilitator, and co-editor of the recently published ‘Vintner’ journal. She is the curator of the forthcoming Vortex exhibition, part of the Transforming Portraits project, which is working to bring together forty years of biennials through a new generation of artists. Introduction to the Biennale Format  [1] Presented by M. de C. de Silva at the Venice Biennale Archive, 2014. [2] Jussi Parikka, ‘On the use of data in the archaeological record’, in PLoS One, 9: e90769, 2013. [3] John Urry, ‘On the use of archetypes in historical research’, in Journal of the Association of American Geographers, Volume 11, Number 2, January, 2014, p.108. [4] Richard Florida, ‘Data, geography, and the social: two approaches</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change
    <text>will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change things: there is a change in the DNA of the art institution, and the artist is able to find a home somewhere within the framework of this art school. This is very interesting to me, because I don’t believe that art schools have that kind of DNA anymore, and I don’t see how they would be able to.  This kind of change, along with the fact that Green Mountain Arts Centre is no longer a part of the MFA, leads to a new kind of curatorial style, in which there is a greater focus on the individual artist’s contribution, and a greater sense of mission. Art is no longer just an object of aesthetics, but is now a ‘system' that is actively engaged with and designed by all stakeholders, and this new curatorial style is a direct result of the art school setting being replaced by the city. This change is very interesting for artists and brings about a kind of  radical rationing of resources and</text>
    <text>will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change things: if the artist is good with the vernacular, the arts commission, the curatorial approach, and the art is there for a while, the rest of us can step back and create our own art. This is a very important point: the incubation effect is very powerful, and Weibel himself makes this very clear in the exhibition catalogue. He calls it radical transparency. This is a process of inclusivity: it is not about admitting something to be true, or proving something. It is an intentional process of inclusivity: the incubation of a new generation of artists who will be able to tackle big-scale institutional forms. This may be different from how institutional forms are structured now: in the sense of exclusive access to ideas and knowledge, but the important thing is to create spaces and communities where ideas can come to life and to be able to share ideas and knowledge. This may require the institutional structures to change, but it is an inherent change and may well prove</text>
    <text>will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change things: a lot of the ideas that were put forward during the symposium, and in general the way art is presented in the arts world, are still going to be of a piece with the way art is actually presented in the arts world. This is partly because of the way artists and arts organizations are encouraged to present their work: through performances, demonstrations, writing pieces or organising events, they are encouraged to think and speak creatively about art and the social implications of their work. But a lot of what we do in the arts world is still seen as following the old fashioned artist’s model of the artist’s state, the old ways, and so forth.  It seems that the time has come for us to think in terms of cities, or cities as a social formation, rather than individuals with specific talents and abilities. This is something that Sophie Hope and I agreed on. As an example, Hope is an Artist who works in the social impact area, while</text>
    <text>will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change things: things can get really interesting and interesting very quickly, and there is no time to put all the pieces together. So the sense of the day was that the art world was quite static, that there was very little movement, and the same could be said of the arts and culture in general. But things can change so quickly that it is easy to lose track of time. The Green Mountain Arts Centre has just opened its doors for the summer, and we have been invited to be a part of its new year “council”, which is an offshoot of its existing annual festival, New Media Arts. We are looking forward to learning more about the work that is being done with the cityscape and the arts in that area, and to working with some of the artists who are part of the council.  The main focus of the symposium was, unsurprisingly, around the effects of digital media on culture and art. The exchange of ideas and observations between the artists, cur</text>
    <text>will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change things: once the idea is there, the material can be provided, the bricks can be milled, the building can be designed and finished, and there is a very real sense of how much further this is possible.  In this way, this kind of power dynamic can shift things, even when the authoritarians try to stop it.  This is interesting, because the way in which the Green Mountain Arts Centre is operating now, the kind of intellectual property it protects, the way in which it demands money from the city: these are things that a museum wouldn’t do. The MFA and the city are in a very interesting position, where the city is very keen to make money, but at the same time, the museum is struggling to pay the bills, which it doesn’t make up on. The city has to balance this very different situations, but at the same time, the museum has to deliver something meaningful to the people who use the building, and whose</text>
    <text>will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change things, creating new worlds – creating new art forms, new art forms, and new cultures – that were previously not there.  The important thing is to keep moving forward, keeping pushing the boundaries, and to me, that sounds like what the symposium is trying to do: remind people of the world they live in. I can imagine a different kind of symposium, where the participants come from different walks of life and come to terms with different kinds of art forms and different kinds of cultural practices.  The interesting thing is that the people who are coming to the symposium are saying, ‘This is me, me, me. I’m not some mythical being born to do this, I’m a human being who made this decision and I’m here to stay.’ This is a new kind of human accumulation happening in the world right now, and it’s happening in places like the MFA: they’re saying, ‘</text>
    <text>will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change things: the more innovative and dynamic the way in which art is presented, the less people come to see it as art. MFA has done some really exciting things in the past couple of years, some of which are quite revolutionary, and I look forward to seeing what they do in the future. Peter Weibel  The other thing that has really changed in the last couple of years is the kind of pedagogical approach to art and art history. There is a real real de-emphasis on the role that artists and art historians had in creating contemporary art. There is a focus on the role of the artist as a curatorial and artistic agent rather than the role of historian, and this is really exciting. It’s like a baptism by artist’s studies: the more it is embedded in the curriculum, the more people can learn about how art is made and celebrated.  A couple of years ago, I was teaching a course in artist’s studies at the </text>
    <text>will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change things: if the incubator is a catalyst and the change happens organically, it’s called ‘institutional change’. And one of the things that’s happening with the art institutions is an increase in the number of their change agents: the artists, the curators, the arts administrators, to name only a few. I think that the MFA does an excellent job of supporting its change agents through grants and the like, but in a way that the arts commissions do not. It’s up to the artists to decide how much autonomy they want to give up, and Weibel emphasises the need for artists to take control of their projects: the commissioning committee, the artists, the curators, the local authorities, to name only a few. The MFA is encouraging artists to take control of their projects, but there is a difference between encouraging an artist to undertake a project ‘for profit’ and asking an artist to design and construct</text>
    <text>will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change things. When CACCE started, it was a slow, cautious process, and now it’s a really aggressive one. There is an openness to ideas and new approaches, and the incubator effect can create that. This is a potential way forward for the city: encouraging more people to visit the art museums, the performing arts centres, and to arts education, workshops and activities, and encouraging them to come to symposia and festivals and to the like. It may be that the catalyst for the dramatic change that needs to happen is the right symposium, or the right event, or the right combination of two or more events. But right now, what is needed is a symposium with a visionary curator, a well-thought-out plan, and a community of interested people who come together over a period of several years to explore an aspect of art in a particular city. In order to achieve this, symposia, festivals, and especially symposia</text>
    <text>will be curated’s, and will be developed as an independent project, with the participation of the arts, in collaboration with the city, through the arts commission, CACCE and the MFA’s Curatorial Faculty.  The sponsor of the symposium, Green Mountain Arts Centre, has agreed to provide funding for the design and to supervise the construction of the exhibition. The new director of the MFA, Peter Weibel, expressed his delight at the opportunity to work with such a dynamic and innovative organization:  The MFA is an amazing, amazing organization. It’s a really smart place to be. I’m looking forward to working with them in the future, but right now I’m really enjoying what we are doing with the art. I can imagine working with a museum: stimulating the imagination and making it work for us, rather than having to rely on it.  The other interesting thing is how this kind of incubation effect can change things, and how any new technology can, in theory, make things better. This is one way in which the symposium can stimulate creativity: create a new way to look at the past, that can bring about changes in how we perceive the world.  Another way is to trap it, to use it as a kind of laboratory for experimenting on the new technologies of art and culture. This is another way of looking at artworks and the cultural processes through which they are produced and presented. The young people who come to the symposium may have never experienced art like this before, or perhaps have a very negative understanding of it. They come away with a new perspective and a new understanding of what art is. The important thing is to create spaces that are inviting and make them possible for people to find meaning and purpose in their lives, even if this may or may not be the experience of art as we understand it.  The second innovation we are trying to instill in the young people is</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban
    <text>The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban/suburban planning has consequences both large and small. The idea of ‘home-making’ caught the city’s imagination and made it into a potential future home for thousands of people. But this new kind of home-building also has consequences that are much bigger and far-reaching. To take one example, consider the possibility that the rapid growth of data-intensive tech startups – which are often started in the wake of massive data sets – has affected the social and cultural capital of the city like no other kind of infrastructure. This is because these startups draw on the latent capacity of the city to continuously add new data points to its massive database, constantly reinvent itself and constantly evolve its forms and methods of urban life – all the while replicating itself through in-house algorithms and the dynamic composition of the city. This kind of urban/suburban churn is a general feature of any big-scale infrastructure project, but unlike other kinds of infrastructure, this kind of urban churn is not</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban exploration requires a lot of analysis. For instance, when people move through an area, they usually have a destination in mind – perhaps a restaurant, a shop, or a museum – but there is no guarantee that these destinations will be found or that the area will be safe. A lot of work involves finding the hidden objects, or 'metainterfaces', that make up the urban fabric, or 'underpinnings' – the structures that create and support the metropolis – and this type of analysis often goes unnoticed or under-studied. The project began to look for these hidden imperatives through the use of underground tunnels under the city. These tunnels lead to the surface and into the heart of the metropolis, where many different kinds of infrastructure are built along different levels to support various functions. In addition to the infrastructure, there are various hidden communities that live underground and use the tunnels to go underground and meet with friends and family. The project began to look for cultural and community elements</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban immobility – in which cases, the sites of activity are spread out and temporary – opens possibilities for research that are limited in the past. For instance, the development of traffic jams in major European cities has been studied and attributed to the proliferation of cars, but this is simply not true. In fact, the proliferation of cars during the 1970s and 80s was linked to a decrease in the number of cars on the road, which in turn reduced the amount of pollution caused by them. In San Francisco, the explosion of car sales during the 1980s and 1990s was partially attributed to this new kind of urban immobility, which allowed a variety of artists, including the FACT artists, to develop their work outside of the city during this time. The proliferation of office parks and the related explosion of office jobs during this time was also closely studied and attributed to the proliferation of office jobs, but this is simply not true either. The office is a role-playing space that often reprodu</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban/suburb design that we develop, whether it’s for the city’s parks or the countryside, whether it’s for the housing market or the neglected urban centres, is a very dynamic process that has to be continuously monitored and controlled. If it gets out of hand, it’s game over. There are so many different kinds of monitoring and control mechanisms that have to be addressed simultaneously, and so many different kinds of actors have to be monitored and controlled, so that there isn’t a repetition of the kind of thing that can happen in and around a city. And so the whole project started off by saying, ‘Here’s a big pile of monitors and control rooms. Here’s what happens when a particular sign is turned on or off. Here's what happens when a building or a street is designated as a tourist destination. Here's what happens when a certain number of tour groups book through a specific travel agency. Here�</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban research project is a perfect application of this enormous amount of data. It provides a new angle of data collection and analysis, one that is both precise and open to interpretation. It is a research project, but it is also a home for a kind of research citizen journalism – gathering and organising the collective knowledge of the Armenian diaspora in order to ask tough questions, proposing new solutions and forging connections that will exist beyond the social sciences and beyond the confines of the museum.This kind of research, curatorial and archival work is what museums do best; they enable us to understand how we live our daily lives, what our dreams and desires are, and to uncover hidden knowledge and experiences. Through curatorial and archive work, a curatorial approach, and documentation, the Armenian diaspora can create its own biennial – making, as Kübler-Ross would say, a double-edged metaphor. When we think of a museum today, we usually think of architecture and design, but there</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban/suburban sprawl is a construction that has to be opposed. It’s a situation where information is power and data is a medium, but in a different kind of political and social sense. This new kind of urban sprawl is a normalisation of existing patterns of urban life – we are all embedded in these huge data feeds – but it is also a construction that results in a very different kind of life form: a form of life that is almost entirely based around car travel and online shopping.This new kind of urban sprawl is a sort of digital mesopotamian form that reproduces itself – it reproduces its own infrastructure, albeit one that is highly autonomous. It reproduces an entire traffic flow through its nodes; it does not need a driver or a city to maintain and operate this infrastructure. It is one could say a digital mesopotamian form that anticipates and responds to the emergence of new modes of travel and data (and hence, new modes of use</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban exploration requires us to be nimble and flexible, able to pick up where we left off if we are interrupted. It also means that we need to have access to big data sets, big-data infrastructures and analytics applications (where applicable) that can monitor and analyze this new urban exploration. For more than just the sake of science, these technologies are critical for the future of cities – not just for the sake of science, but because they enable a new kind of political, economic and social formation for the future of cities.Interview conducted by Anne Kübler-Ross and Armen KeteyianCurator, Museum of Modern Art, New YorkThe Armenian diaspora lives, works and studies in North America, Europe and Arabia. Its history is a complex mosaic of migration, displacement, persecution and conflict. It is estimated that there are over 11 million Armenians living in North America and over 11 million in the Middle East. The Armenian diaspora consists of over 6,000</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban/suburban development in both Armenia and Iran has resulted in a surge in the number of phone numbers that can be called in response to a specific call. So far, so normal, but what the project is doing is collecting and organising this huge amount of data in a very efficient and useful way. It is gathering data on the construction of new buildings, on the routes taken by passengers, on the nature of interactions between public and private security personnel, on the number of injuries sustained on the platform, and on the languages of the passengers. The data also includes data about the interactions between the different languages of the platform, and on an individual level, data about the individuals using the platform. The collection of this kind of data allows the project to engage with ideas and questions raised by the user, while enabling a contextual understanding of the user’s behaviour based on past behaviour and data.For more information visit: http://www.designinsight.org/research/collection/identities/</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban/suburban data science is a natural extension of that. It’s as if the city is a huge warehouse with all these different kinds of commodities, with parcels labelled with data points – places, objects, behaviours, behaviours – and the concept of place is just the latest addition to that monstrosity. 	Kübler-Ross: Our idea of ‘place’ has evolved into a kind of an index – a way to categorise and rank all the different kinds of data that are generated in the city. But what we ultimately want is to create a physical space that contains all the different kinds of place – the same is true of data. We can create physical spaces that hold all kinds of different kinds of data, but we don’t necessarily want to. The point of a data set is to capture information; capturing information is what place does. Place is a fiction. 	Kübler-Ross: In the end, capturing and storing is just</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation on the real-life predicaments and the experiences and predicaments of the Armenian diaspora, in both urban and rural contexts. It is a re-construction of the historic relationships between the two communities, with a particular attention to the intersections and bridges that can be bridged between the two. The project was conceived and directed by the Museum of Modern Art’s Curator, Anne Kübler-Ross. Together, they have developed the project from the ground up, collecting and organising the stories that emerge, asking, can we make sense of this vast amount of data?Kübler-Ross: The project started out as a collation of different data sets – geolocation, real-time, IP addresses, phone numbers, addresses and lots of other unique and valuable data – and as a way to collect and analyse this massive amount of data. This massive quantity of data means that we have a huge amount of information to work with, and this new kind of urban/suburban sprawl requires a huge amount of data storage. The project started with a question: how do we organize this huge amount of data so that it does not become fragmented or muddled or muddled again? The answer to that question is a large dataset, which is data – structured as data – – and data-intensive to process. The problem with the traditional archive is that it is full of inconsistencies and existing issues resurface again and again, like dominoes. With the re-constitution of the archive, we can say that the issues that are driving the issue of urban sprawl are the issues of heterogeneity and muddled identity, and we don’t need to create an entirely new archive. We can build on what we have already – the traditional archive – or we can create something entirely new and different. This is what we did with the ‘traditional’ part of the archive. We have the writings of individuals such as Thomas Allsen, John Graham</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a
    <text>present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a way of coming to understandings, that creates new ways of structuring urban environments and of inhabiting them. It is a process that encourages local production, but also spatial, temporal and material forms of organisation. It is a meeting place for the making of places, a site for the appropriation of space, and a marketplace for all kinds of social, material and material goods. It is a ‘site of exchange’, a ‘market place for all kinds of social, material and material goods’. But more and more, the assembly becomes an event, a ‘till, a corner shop, a bakery, a shoe shop, a nursery, a church, a school, a street light and a bus stop . . . a place where all kinds of different kinds of people come to live, work and play’. More and more, the assembly becomes something that is neither static, nor does it necessarily represent the totality of the city. It organises the city</text>
    <text>present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a work in progress that constantly reshapes and evolves according to changing circumstances, needs and needs alone. Yet the organising of knowledge is only part of the story of how place comes to be made visible, what William Burchell terms ‘the massive web of place that we create and inhabit’, and how this affects and is affected by urbanisation. Place-making and urbanisation then, are two sides of the same coin. 	 But just as important is the work done in the spatial domain – the making and inhabitation of places – as well as the symbiotic relationship between the spatial and the organic. Urban planners and urban designers therefore have an important, sometimes conflicted and sometimes lopsided role to play in shaping the places that are produced and the uses that are possible within cities. It is a ‘mimicking’ role that involves both the local and the globalised sectors of the global economy. It is to some extent a domestic, but still precarious and variable, role</text>
    <text>present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a work in progress that constantly redefines the relations between now and place. 	The assembly as place-making project started off small and iterated through the city, eventually reaching the outskirts of London. It incorporated local, national and international design firms, and ultimately international civil servants, planners and architects. It involved research and analysis on a worldwide scale, using 3D modelling and printing technology. The aim was to create ‘a set of tools and techniques that would be useful in a place-making project, but also in other kinds of urban and public interventions’. The project was designed to be transparent, so that participants could understand the ins and outs of their project, but also to foster a dialogue about the place of art and design in a city. 	One of the projects that emerged from the assembly was Zone 1: London, UK, which describes the urban context in which the 1st World War was fought – a context that continues to be relevant to contemporary urban problems. </text>
    <text>present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a work in progress that is constantly being annotated and revised. But this ‘learning’ has to happen in a particular order, because as soon as the assembly form breaks down, new forms of knowledge are born. ‘Inhabitant City’ is the first of its kind in Liverpool, and it will be followed soon after by ‘The City’ and ‘its discontents’. 	[1] The assembly-form itself is a ‘complex system’ that depends on a number of different nodes, each with their own dynamics and histories. But this complexity arises from the fact that the assembly originally consisted of only a limited number of nodes, and so has to be repeated – each new assembly emerging requires a fundamentally different assembly from the one that was previously taken. 	[2] This notion of staging, ‘the art’ as a living organism’ is further developed in Svetlana Boym's work</text>
    <text>present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a work in progress that continually reshapes and evolves it. The assembly as collective practice This new assembly paradigm is just one manifestation of a generalised belief – shared by many different people and places – that cities are places where knowledge is powerful, where creativity reigns, and where art and art do not necessarily conflict. It is the aggregate of many different ideas and commitments, and its focus is clearly divided between those who call themselves designers (whether urbanists, urban commentators, urban artists, or just plain urban folk), and others who call themselves artists, curators, organisers or whatever else you want to call the people who create the city. What emerges is a fixed set of beliefs and practices, agreed upon as the way of the city. The key is in what kind of a capacity these organisations are willing to lay claim to the city. In Paris for example, the Architecture Du Port is willing to lay claim to the physical space of the city (including the Champs-Élys</text>
    <text>present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a making of it available to the governed. 	The assembly is the site of the constantly shifting spatial forms of capital in which it operates. It is an arena in which knowledge can be produced and embodied, but also an object of consumption and of loss.’ This last aspect is of course at the centre of the assembly line of globalised neoliberal capitalism. The global assembly, whatever its scale and whatever its destination, always ends up somewhere – in the distant future somewhere – in the midst of a crisis. The global assembly, however, also tends to produce knowledge that is both more and less accessible than its contemporary form of dissemination would suggest. This is evident in the fossil-fueled economy today: the assembly line produces wealth and income today, but also pollution, hunger and scarcity tomorrow. The global assembly, however, tends to produce knowledge that is both more and less accessible than its social forms would suggest. 	The global assembly, by its own constant redefinition, is also a �</text>
    <text>present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a work of architecture designed to last. 	[i] Solving the urban sprawl conundrum, U.K. Cities Network (2015-16).  Download this article as PDFRafico RuizRafico Ruiz is an urbanist and urban designer born and educated in Madrid. His research interests are in the sociopolitical, spatial and material conditions of urbanization in developing nations. His dissertation, ‘Solving the Urban Sprawl Conundrum: Lessons from Spain’s Past’, provides a critical reflection on the city’s past, present and future in relation to the sociopolitical, material and virtual forms of urbanization that are now undermining its social and cultural character. His work has been exhibited in numerous venues worldwide, including the Venice Biennale, the New York Museum of Art and the London Museum of Modern Art. His latest project, Urbanizing Mauritius, is a multi-disciplinary, multi-disciplinary study of the �</text>
    <text>present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a work of mutualising resources and generating new ways of understanding and constructing the urban landscape. Place-making is a globally adaptive process that needs to be regularly (re)organised and supplemented. It is a critical (and relatively new) way of engaging with and creating knowledge about the city. Thinking urbanist Martha Coon is one of many practitioners and theorists who have contributed to the collection of essays published by the Quartermasters' Special Collections, University of Liverpool. She argues that we live in a (conceptually) unlimited and ephemeral city, but with knowledge comes responsibility. We have access to data, but what comes with it (data, analysis, maps)? Who has access to that data, what is its meaning, and how does it be governed? Where does knowledge come from in the first place? In what other ways does the city constrain our ability to understand it? She argues that we need to understand the historical conditions and the cultural dynamics of place making in order to</text>
    <text>present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a way to imagine alternatives and envisioning of different modes of urban existence. 	The assembly becomes less a static type of assemblage and more an evolving dynamic system that depends on the environment it takes part in. Assemblies of different species of cars, trucks, buses, houses and flats are assembled into one ‘big assembly’ that comprises of many smaller assemblages. Each of these ‘assemblages’ is then individually photographed and documented in an attempt to simultaneously take part in the vast global scale of the global assembly and simultaneously remain completely isolated from it. Each assemblage is an evolving record of how we arrived at a position or set of positions in the wider assemblage. Assemblages are dynamic narratological vehicles that capture and convey the spatial relationships between various assemblages, and between the many assemblages that constitute the global assembly. If ‘the big picture’ is taken up at an ever-increasing scale, then �</text>
    <text>present an online project that aims to create a ‘community of designers and artists’ through a collaborative process of self-assembly and the production of place. The project was initially presented as a ‘teachable moment’ in which a collective of creators, educators and artists could learn from one another and from the local authority. The initial assembly – a working title and a brief narrative arc – is a powerful tool for generating local knowledge, and it is used to inform the commissioning process. The narrative works hand in hand with the  	place-making tools already at the disposal of the local authority, which is able to offer spatial and social alternatives to the carriageway and its traffic mess. Place-making is made possible by the relational and temporal complexity of the city, and the interconnectedness of its spatial forms. The assembly format, its live-action and virtual exchanges, and the sharing of knowledge it generates opens new ways of approaching urban problems. It is a constructing of knowledge, a work in progress that constantly reshapes the city in response to the needs of the community. The assembly format is a ‘building block’ that supports the commissioning process by enabling collaboration and the emergence of new knowledge through interaction. It is a building block that supports the local and long-term spatialisation of the city, and it is a site where creative and responsive action is encouraged. In doing so, it provides the building material and procedural conditions for future cultural activity, and it is a site where art can flourish in a way that contributes to the creation of new knowledge. However, the assembly form must be sustainably shared with future cultural actors, for it to serve as a site for future cultural activity. This requires that the building be able to host and facilitate cultural exchange – sharing, hosting, encouraging, managing, all of which are elements of the new urban culture pie. In doing so, it creates new knowledge and engages with old knowledge in new ways. This is why cultural institutions</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art’s relationship to technology at the Brooklyn College of Art.She received an A. Philip Agey Chair from the Brooklyn Museum for her work in the Biennale, and a Tony James Chair from the Brooklyn Museum for her work in the museum.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, the Village Voice Online and other publications.She was a co-editor of the Village Voice Graphic Newspaper of the Year Award Short Story (2001) and was a co-editor of the Village Voice Graphic Newspaper of the Year Award Short Story (2007). She has been a columnist for the Brooklyn Bulletin and the Village Voice, among other publications.She was a co-editor of the Village Voice Graphic Newspaper of the Year Award Short Story (2001) and the Village Voice Graphic Newspaper of the Year Award Short Story (2007). She has written for the Village Voice and the Bulletin, among other publications.She was a co-editor of the Village Voice Graphic Newspaper of</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art at UCLA.She was a consultant for the film  	The Social Network, directed by Thomas Kail, and co-producer of the documentary film The Social Network: The Rise and Fall of LinkedIn (2017).She has written for the New Inquiry, the Village Voice, and the Observer, amongst many other publications.She was a consultant for the film  	The Social Network, directed by Thomas Kail, and co-producer of the documentary film The Social Network: The Rise and Fall of LinkedIn (2017). She has written for the Observer, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has co-written the script for  	The Social Network, with Jeremy Scahill, with additional co-writing credits on the script by Avi Reisman and Daniel Fernández. She has co-written the script for the upcoming sixth and seventh series of Twin Peaks, which will see Laura Palmer (Laura Kennedy) and Clive</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art at Berkley College of Arts and Design.She edited the online companion to the BNI online journal Stages. She was also a lecturer in contemporary art history and a co-editor of the online companion to the New Criterion companion to Critical Reviews, Artforum. She was a consultant for the film  	Zero, the 1988 biopic of Mitchell Silver, the Israeli tank commander who led the charge into battle during the Iran-Iraq War. Her fiction has been short-listed for the Hugo Boss Prize, Helen Suzman Humanities Prize, and the Pulitzer Prize.She has also contributed to the online journal Stages, with an issue on playwrights and creative services published in January 2018.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández PascualPascual is a writer, curator, and producer. His writing has reflected on a wide range of topics, including the economic, social, and political complexity of his native Mexico, as well as international politics, economy,</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art at Santa Clara University.She is a member of the Creative Time Fellowship Programme for Young Curators and the board member of the Creative Time Collaborative, a collaborative programme for the curatorial and art-historical work of the maker.She is an adjunct professor at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, where she provides curatorial and curatorial services to the school’s Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Contemporary Art, including the School of Art, Museum of Modern Art, and Museum of Art.She is the curator of the Brooklyn Museum of Art’s exhibition of contemporary art from the New York Public Library, as well as the exhibition catalogue of the Brooklyn Museum of Art’s online exhibition of 1900-2000AD, plus is a member of the curatorial team for the Brooklyn Museum of Art’s upcoming exhibition of contemporary art from the New York Public Library.Excerpt from Excerpt from The Architecture of Luxury:</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art at Santa Clara University.She has written for the Brooklyn Rail, the San Francisco Chronicle, the Village Voice, and the Village Voice Digital Archive, amongst many other publications.She has lectured on the history of contemporary art and its development with some of her peers and fellow artists. She was a lecturer in modern and contemporary art history for the American Association for the Study of Art and Architecture, and the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Archive.She has written for the Washington Post, the New York Times, the Village Voice, the Village Voice Digital Archive, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications. She has a special interest in the history of communications technology and was a lecturer in media and design at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, and a fellow at the American Association for the Study of Art and Architecture.She has written for the New Inquiry, the Village Voice Digital Archive, and the New Inquiry: Art and the Net, amongst many other publications. She has a particular interest in the</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art in the College of William and Mary in the United States Naval Postgraduate School.Biennial Financing and the Micro-Histories of Art’s Emergence in the NinetiesJacqueline Lamb,  	Unravelled (2014), Rapid (2014), Museum of Modern Art, New York. 	[1] This was not always the case. In the nineteenth century, the main funding stream for art was coming from the crown, which viewed contemporary art as a threat. In 1984, the New York Museum of Art partnered with the New Museum to create the Biennale, and in 2005, the French National Galleries partnered with the California Museum of Art to create the Arsenale. The Biennale quickly became a multidisciplinary entity with a national reach, with artists from every continent invited to participate. The 2006 Venice Biennale was co-chaired by Jean Guy Lecat and Sophie Schmidt, and the Arsenale followed in 2009 with</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art at the University of California, Santa Barbara.She has also taught at the American University in Cairo, Egypt, and the University of Chicago, where she is currently Professor of Modern Art History and a postdoctoral fellow.She is the author of The Gallery as Art Today (with Jessica Coon), to be published by Verso in 2017.Her work  	Unfixing Art: Modern Art, Gloriana, and Culture (2015) and co-editor of Dock Publishing/New Criterion, out now, of The Contemporary Condition: Art, Capital, and the End of the World, from Issue #1 of New Criterion, 2016.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is a writer and Curator for the New Contemporary Condition, a journal published every two years that brings together a range of cultural, curatorial and journalistic elements. Its theme this year is ‘culture warps our sense of time’. Culture Wars, co-</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art at San Francisco State University.She edited the online journal Stages and worked as a project leader for the online publication Stages. She is currently a project leader for the online publication Stages 2.0.Biennials have a habit of taking on a life of their own. In recent decades, the biennial has become something that is constantly (deeply) reimagined and revised. The general consensus seems to be that it is the curatorial and art institution that needs to be in the loop, since the biennial is the most widely distributed and representative of the art form. The biennial becomes what it is not – a transient cultural phenomenon that is eventually replaced by another art form. This is especially true of the increasing number of large-scale exhibitions and major curatorial initiatives. Art biennials are in a position to react to new curatorial initiatives and opportunities. This is due to the nature of the art form itself: its universality, its geographical spread, its penetration</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art at the University of California, Santa Barbara.She is the author of The Cultural Logic of Los Angeles (2012), which was a New York Times Best Seller and was translated into seven languages. Her artworks have been commissioned by the New York and Venice Biennials, and have been published in a number of biennials, including the Italian and the San Francisco.She has presented her art at the 17th Venice Biennale, the National Portrait Gallery of the United Kingdom, the American Museum of Modern Art, the Museum of Modern Art, the New Cultural Survey, the Fine Arts Museums of Berlin, and the London and New Economic Archive.She was a consultant for the documentary  	Zero Dark Thirty, which profiles American intelligence agency, the CIA, which engaged in torture and ill-treatment of detainees, as well as the journalist Mark Miodownik. She has written the foreword to the book  	Unravelled: The Human Cost of War, to</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in Las Vegas in 2017.  LATEXNINE is a digital artist and a co-founder of  	LATEXNINE, an interactive art and community multimedia project based in Oakland, California. She is a co-curator of the Venice Biennale and was previously curator of the Jewish Museum of Los Angeles and the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art.She has curated several exhibitions, including the Venice Biennale (2016), the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of contemporary art from the Venetian and Italian Museums, and the Israeli Museum of Modern Art's exhibition of Modern Art from the Tel Aviv Museum of Art.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the Village Voice, and the New Inquiry, amongst many other publications.She has taught at Brooklyn College of Art and the Graduate Center, University of California, Los Angeles, and NYU, and was a lecturer in art history and the modern history of art at the University of California, Santa Cruz.She is the recipient of several awards and mentions, including:Awards from the British Council, American Museum of Modern Art, the American Philosophical Society, and the British LibraryAllyson Guyton, Artist and Director of  	LATEXNINE Exhibition, Venice Biennale 2016, Venice, ItalyCuratorial Faculty of the American Museum of Modern Art, the British Library, 2014Curatorial Faculty of the British Library, US National Portrait Gallery, 2014Curatorial Faculty of the British Library, US Royal Academy of Arts, 2015Curatorial Faculty of the British Library, US National Portrait Gallery, 2015Curatorial Faculty of the British Library, US Royal Academy of Arts, 2015Curatorial Faculty of the British Library, US National Portrait Gallery, 2015Curatorial Faculty of the British Library, US National Portrait Gallery, 2015Awards from the British Council, American Museum of Modern Art, the British Library, 2014, 2015</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour
    <text>The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Age of Intangible Assets (MIT Press, 2016).Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThe author of both the LA Times bestselling memoirs LA (The Long Version) and the 2014 New York Times best-seller The Game Changer: Learning from LA (2007), Emily Pringle is the author of the new memoir LA: The Game Changer, to be published in Spring 2018 by Minerva. She is the host of the popular podcast LA Chronicles, and the co-host of the popular podcast Around the World with Emily Pringle (where she discusses contemporary and historical topics). In 2015, she served as the Special Advisor to the President of the United States for Emergency Operations Response (EORex), the White House's research arm, on the US response to the terror attack on the US diplomatic mission in Benghazi, Libya. She has written for The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New York Times, The New Republic, The</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour and the Politics of Injustice, co-authored with Ryan Avent and Richard Hewison, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2017.Download this article as PDFSue Bell YankSue Bell Yank is an artist, writer, educator and Research Chair in the Department of Visual Cultures &amp; Cultures of Publics at the University of Alberta, Canada. Her work has addressed the social, economic and political histories of tourism, culture and the post-colonial experience of culture in Canada. She has a particular interest in the social, political and cultural ramifications of historical voyages into North America, the Caribbean, and the Middle East. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Canadian Museum of Modern Art, Archives Canada, Thompson Rivers Art Gallery, Thunder Bay, Canada; Royal BC Museum, Vancouver, Canada; and New Museum, New York, USA; and her art has been exhibited at the Venice Biennale, New York, USA; the Whitney Museum of American Art, New York,</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in America 	.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor of English and Exhibition Studies at the Western Ontario College of Arts and Design, and holds the Canada Research Chair in English and Exhibition Studies. Her work has addressed the role of art in shaping social and political change, focusing on the role of art and artists in the history of Western societies from prehistory to the present. Her work has also addressed the connections between contemporary art and postcolonial/postcolonial studies, ethnography and popular culture. Her publications include essays in The New York Times, The New Republic, Cultural Critic and The Hollywood Reporter, as well as the book You've Seen the Signs: Race, Politics and Cultural Capital in Twentieth-Century America, published by Western Publishing Group.Her writing has also appeared in The New Yorker, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Times and The New York Times Critic. She is a past president of the American Association</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Age of Intangible Assets (Adams, Hamilton, &amp; Palmer, 2017). 	[iv] See my book The Marketplace of Intangible Assets: Money, Intangible Assets, and the Politics of Immobility for more on this. 	[v] See, for example, Susanne Kjellberg &amp; Christian Wohlgemuth, ‘On the use of value in appraisals: a case study of the art market’, in  	How Assets are Made (Eds.), Handbook of Value (Wiley-Blackwell, New York, 1988), p. 24. 	[vi] Cultural Capital (2015), p. 8. 	[vii] Monica Schipper, ‘Unfixing the Art Market’, in  	New York Times, 9 October 2016, http://www.nytimes.com/2016/10/09/us/politics/economy</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Twenty-First Century, University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 2013. 	[iv] See my book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Twenty-First Century, University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 2012. 	[v] See my book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Twenty-First Century, University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 2012. 	[vi] See my book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Twenty-First Century, University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 2012. 	[vii] See my book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Twenty-First Century, University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 2012. 	[viii] See my book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Twenty-</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in Rich Countries, by the Millennium Art Fund, New York, 2008.Download this article as PDFTim JeevesTim Jeeves is an independent writer, Curator of Transport and Culture at the Liverpool School of Arts, and co-curator of the GB's first and second Future City programmes. His work has addressed the social and political history of transport in several cities around the world, and the impact of economic growth, technological obsolescence and urban decay. His books include the US published Beyond the Art of Blurring Lines (2014), the UK-based environmental urbanist ‘Inhabitants’  (2015), and the 2015 UK book ‘Unfixed: Multidisciplinary Games for Urban Transformation’, based on his experiences as a Curator at the Liverpool John Moores Special Collections Library. He has written for the Guardian, The New York Times, The Atlantic and The Washington Post, among other publications.  Visit his website at timjeeves</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in America and Beyond, Palgrave, London, 2017. 	[iv] See also my new book The City of Refuge: On Resisting Neo-liberalism and Building Publics, Palgrave, London, 2017. 	[v] See my forthcoming book The City of Refuge: On Resisting Neo-liberalism and Building Publics, Palgrave, London, with Chris Wainwright, Blackwell, Oxford, forthcoming. 	[vi] See also my book The City of Refuge: On Resisting Neo-liberalism and Building Publics, Palgrave, London, 2017. 	[vii] See also my recent book The City of Refuge: On Resisting Neo-liberalism and Building Publics, Palgrave, London, 2017. 	[viii] See my book The City of Refuge, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 2016. 	[ix] See also my recent book The City of Refuge,</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flourishes in a Metropolis. 	[iv] See also my book The Cultural Barriers to Sustainable Development: Globalization, Capital and the Politics of Poor. 	[v] See also my book The City Trap, Basic, New York, 1996. 	[vi] See also my recent book The Participatory City, Basic, New York, 2008. 	[vii] See also my book The Participatory Society, Basic, New York, 2011. 	[viii] See also my book The City Trap, Basic, New York, 2008. 	[ix] See also my book The City Trap, Basic, New York, 2011. 	[x] See my book The City Trap, Basic, New York, 2012. 	[xi] See also my book The City Trap, Basic, New York, 2013. 	[xii] See my book The City</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Age of Intangible Assets.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleEmily Pringle is a London-based art and urbanist whose work has been exhibited in over twenty schools. She is a founding member of the Biennaleeers (England and Wales), an international network of collaborative art events, and co-curator of the forthcoming Oxford Union exhibition, with Alison Saunders. She has curated several exhibitions for the New Art Gallery, including Redefining Visceral Performance (2016), where she worked with Marieke Ruiz and others on a solo show about the relationship of art and urbanisation, and in 2017, the New Art Gallery invited her to join a curatorial team for a special exhibition of her work, The Biennial Generation: Anne Kølbæk Iversen, 2017. She has also curated the Liverpool Biennial, Anne Kølbæk Iversen, 2017.From the Post-Structuralist Condition to Now 	Since the 1970</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be at the Walsall Art Gallery, London, in September 2018. The Walsall Art Gallery is the only gallery in the UK to have hosted the 2017 Venice Biennale. The Biennale was supported by the UK’s Department for International Development (DFID), which runs a major international development programme. In 2017, DFID supported the construction of 'Champion 8', a £1.8 billion mixed-use development that will include a new stadium for Arsenal Football Club, a new masterplan for the area around the stadium, a new school for secondary school students and an expanded community centre. 	[i] Biennials have become a fixture of the biennale calendar, appearing in every edition since 1995.  	[ii] See  Biennale Calendar, International Publishers, New York, 2015. 	[iii] See also my recent book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Twenty-First Century, Columbia University Press, New York, 2016. 	[iv] See also my book The Cultural Barriers to Urban Transformation: Globalizing Urban Flour in the Twenty-First Century, Columbia University Press, New York, 2016. 	[v] See also my book The City in Crisis: Globalization and Its Aftermath, Palgrave Macmillan, New York, 2015. 	[vi] See also my book The City in Crisis: Globalization and Its Aftermath, Palgrave Macmillan, New York, 2015. 	[vii] See also my book The City in Crisis: Globalization and Its Aftermath, Palgrave Macmillan, New York, 2015. 	[viii] See also my book The City in Crisis: Globalization and Its Aftermath, Palgrave Macmillan, New York, 2015. 	[ix] See also my book The</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by
    <text>The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by Arjun Appadurai and Prem Krishnamurthy. See: http://www.appadurai.com/en/shop/home-design/1-2-arjun-appadurai/arjun-appadurai-instructors/learn-home-design-arjun-appadurai-instructors-home-design/home-design/home-design-home-design-arjun-appadurai-instructors-home-design/learn-home-design-home-design-arjun-appadurai/learn-home-design-home-design-arjun-appadurai-instructors-home-design/home-design-home-design-arjun-appadurai-instructors-home-design/learn-home-design-home-design-arjun-appadurai-instructors-home-design/learn-home-design-home-</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by H.E. W. Simons &amp; Co. as a way to confront the challenges facing the region. They were not opposed to the idea of the  	art department, but felt that the focus should have been on the city at this point in its development. 	[2] Arthur Joyner,  	Toronto: A Visual Novel (Cambridge: Polity, 1988), p. 3. 	[3] The sculpture is a mosaic of images, each representing a different chapter in the city’s chronicles. It was conceived as a ‘compendium of images from different places and times’. This could have been a book, a ‘database’ or an online resource. The key is in the title. The mosaic is a narrative fragment that speaks to the city’s episodic narrative, which draws together multiple images in an attempt to make a unified image. The word ‘till�</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by the Canadian Centre for Architecture's (CCA) New Economic Bridges program, which runs alongside the Canadian Centre for Innovation’s (CCI) new research and development divisions. The program’s funding comes from the Canada Council for the Innovative Cities, an independent federal government-funded agency.  	[2] Portland, USA: Trejago, 2014. Designed by Willene Schell, the architect’s conception of the waterfront as a series of islands in the middle of the river was inspired by the works of Scottish botanist Patrick Geddes.  	[3] New York Times, '50 Great Art Squares', 8 September 2014. Accessed 14 June 2016.[4] Toronto Star, '50 Great Art Squares', 8 September 2014. Accessed 14 June 2016.[5] Toronto Star, 8 September 2014. Accessed 14 June 2016.[6] Toronto Star, 8 September 2014. Accessed 14 June 2016</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by Grace Poe at the Urban Institute, New York, and commissioned by the City Council. It is a ‘vertical integration model’ that integrates a city’s infrastructure with grassroots arts and cultural organising. It involves not only arts professionals but also community organisers, grassroots organisations and educators working together to design, build and operate a ‘community college, high school or host of other educational and cultural infrastructure supporting the democratic process and socially engaged practices of the city’s urban future. 	[2] Waugh, Raymond. The Art of Not Being Governed: Participatory Public Art in an Apparition of Global Futures. New York: Marcel Dekker, 1995, p.8.Download this article as PDFRaymond James Walter is Professor of Architecture and Urban Studies at McGill University and holds the Canada Research Chair in Architecture and Urbanization at McGill University. His research interests include the built environment, urbanisation and management, the built environment and its politics, the</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by Arjun Appadurai and Prem Krishnamurthy. See: http://www.urbanformats.com/india/artes/um...[2] http://www.urbanformats.com/india/artes/um...[3] http://www.huffingtonpost.com/2013/06/08/pakistan-design-future-p...[4] http://www.dailymotion.com/video/x7f68f7af74437afbcf869a7bcf...[5] http://www.independent.co.uk/news/uk/science/...[6] http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/...[7] http://www.independent.co.uk/news/science/...[8] http://www.dailymail.co.uk/earth/earthnews/...[</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by Wadsworth &amp; Co. as part of the ‘Projections at the Château Tongue’ series in 1986. In these projects, Wadsworth worked with partners such as Meehan Reid, founder of Meehan Reid &amp; Associates; Sandy Harpe, of Black-E, Nuyumbalees Art Centre; Dmytro Baranov, of the arts organisation Rosie; Dmitriy Savrasov, co-founder of Rosie; Wallace Stevens, co-founder of Stevens Space; Dmytro Baranov, Russia; Nikolai Pashchinskiy, Russia; Vladimir Pavlov, Russia; Piotr Mazurek, Poland; Max Roser, US, Cuba; Leonid Sheremezh, Belarus; Boris Groys, Belgium; Ir</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by Welsh Streets and Associates, a not-for-profit cultural organisation based in Vancouver that is dedicated to the protection and enhancement of the historic character of the Welsh Streets and the area surrounding them. The Welsh Streets are among the most ‘endangered cities in North America’, and have been for over twenty years. 	[2] The idea of ‘enduring urban crises’ became popularised in the 1980s with the publication of Margaret Thatcher’s book, Coming to America: Britain, Communism and the English Crisis (1981). Thatcher writes: Every generation has to start somewhere, and history “plays itself out” again and again. But when the big crises happen, such as those affecting our own great cities, it’s worth remembering that they happened too. An example of this is the huge explosion in housing prices during the 1980s and early 1990s, which in some cases were so great that people had to be rescued from their</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by  	Rami Said and his team at Dubai-based arid-Doha Architecture Company. See www.arid-doha.com. Doha, Qatar: Rami Said Architectural Group. Accessed: December 2016. 	[2] Technical Report #2/2015-EC: &quot;Portraits of Portraits&quot; (Technical Report 2015), reproduced in  	Rami Said and co-workers at Qatar Foundation, 2015. [3] See also Rami Said, Portraits of Portraits: An Introduction (MIT/Institute of Contemporary Art, 2015). [4] Steve Gooch,  	Rethinking Architecture: Growth, Sanitation and the Politics of Remaking Urban Space (Chapel Hill, NC: University of North Carolina Press, 2003). [5] Michael Ames, The Collapse of Complex Cities (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2013), p. 11. [6] Ames</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by the Canadian Centre for Architecture Research, and the Université de Montreal.Download this article as PDFJeanne Heeswijk and Rob KlingenschmittJeanne Heeswijk is a practitioner in urban and regional studies, and holds a Bachelor of Urban Studies from the University of Alberta, specialization in spatial and design studies. Her dissertation examines the Carrefour de Montreal’s historic and ongoing urban transformation project, Plan Nord, which she calls ‘a war against the city’. She is the co-editor and co-founder of  The New Urban Frontier: Contemporaneity and Theory in a World City. She is the host of the weekly podcast Policy and The Geek, and the co-founder of the blog Participatory Urban Development. She has written for The New Republic, The New Inquiry, In These Times, Geopolitics, among many other publications.She has been a consultant for the military and intelligence agencies of the world. She lectures and writes</text>
    <text>The project is a speculation, but its preconditions are already there. The question becomes: what can be done with them? The answer is: of course, more needs to be done. What we do know is that in the area, at the moment of its greatest need, Canada is offering itself up as a model city. This is a historic and valuable role for Canada, and it remains to be seen whether the region can afford it. With the federal government threatening to pull the plug on the project, the region’s future looks bleak. But what are its priorities? The presentation by the architect was not a way to choose between good and bad art, or between capital and labour. Rather, it was an exploration of the contradictions and opportunities of a city that is trapped in a malaise of its own making. It’s a city that needs architects, and it’s a city that needs architects now more than ever.  	[1] The model was developed by the Foster &amp; Partners Agency, with the support of the Canada Foundation, and commissioned by the city. The architects themselves have a minority stake in the company. The proportions given are for reference only, and the outline may vary slightly.  [2] See www.designbylocation.com.au/english/industries/industry_research/fact_sheets/world_europe... [3] Department of International Development, The World Economy: The Role of City Pros, 2005.Download this article as PDFJordan CharitonJordi RodríguezJordi Rodríguez is Professor of English and Director of the Division of Cultural Studies and Media Studies at the University of Colorado, Boulder. His research interests include the social sciences, with a special focus on the social effects of globalisation. His publications include the popular books Autonomy, Identity, Geography and Reality: Migration, Capital and the Readiness for a New Economy (F. Int</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the
    <text>biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the city as a ‘site of constant upgrading’ that can further be described as modern. 	[1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/index.php?fuseaction=2&amp;ci=139&amp;art=2&amp;lang=en. 	[2] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com/index.php?fuseaction=2&amp;ci=139&amp;art=2&amp;lang=en. 	[3] See Richard Florida, ‘The Biennale and the Biennial’, Art &amp; Politics, Vol. 18, No. 1, Spring, 1988, p.281–309. 	[4] See Hugh Murphy, ‘The Biennale, Geography, and the Cultures of Art’, Art &amp; Cultural Studies, Vol. 38, No. 1, Spring, 1987, p.103. 	[5</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the city is not modern in its periphery.4 	Its current incarnation, the Venice Biennale, is a kind of ‘point’ in the city, presenting the city through a series of ‘points of entry’ into a single larger ‘city’. It began in 1974 as the Italian pavilion in the Venice Biennale, and expanded from there into the 1980 exhibition venue, the Giardini. In a project that gained momentum in the years that followed, the Biennale organised a number of cross-cultural acts, including a number of acts specifically for the Japanese pavilion, an ‘entertainment district’ in which ‘Japanese culture was a notable attraction.’5 In 1984, the Japanese pavilion was taken up by Cirque du Soleil, and in 1988 by Samsung Sanyo. In 1990, a production company for ‘Brazil’ introduced the world to WWE Superfly, who would go</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the city is not only modern but also a point of exit. The significance of this entry point, that is, the point at which culture (and especially art) leaves the city and enters into the modern world, has been an important area of contention between the biennale and the city. The biennale has consistently stressed how it is the duty of the city to present a ‘point of entry’ into the modern world – to present, that is, the cultural goods and trends of the city in a way that is consistent with the modern world as a modern world. This is true in Venice, in Alsace-Lorraine and in the Pyrenees – the Alsace region includes parts of France and Russia – but also in Basel, Berlin, and New York. In Venice, the point of departure is the Giardini – and, indeed, the entire Giardini – while in Alsace-Lorraine and the Pyrenees the</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the citizens of the city do not possess the ‘rational power’ necessary to effectively regulate itself. 	[1] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/index.php?fuseaction=art&amp;event=view&amp;section=20&amp;artid=1707&amp;artname=sydney-biennale-2015-art-full-pages]. 	[2] See http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/index.php?fuseaction=art&amp;event=view&amp;section=20&amp;artid=1709&amp;artname=sydney-biennale-2015-art-full-pages]. 	[3] See, for example, http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/index.php?fuseaction=art&amp;event=view&amp;section=20&amp;artid=1713&amp;</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the city as a ‘circulation’ is a ‘site of encounter’.1 	 In place of the usual three-year contracts with the biennale organisers, visitors to the Biennale are given the option of staying for a specified time in one of three ‘packages’ offered by the Biennale organisers: a ‘deluxe package’, a ‘basic package’ or a ‘sting pack’. The biennale organisers explain that this introductory offer is intended as a starting point for future packages, ‘delivering a unique experience’, at no additional cost than the standard packages, and that future packages can be tailored to individual travellers. 	The idea that one can choose to inhabit a site and be there for a specified time seems novel and perhaps a way to reorient the biennial visitor’s perception of the city. As the Biennale organisers explain, this is not the typical</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the city is not thus conceived in advance, but rather ‘in the process of being formed’.1 	In the twentieth century a biennale became increasingly important in North Africa and the Middle East, where it became the object of popular and regional ‘cultures’, ‘themes’, and ‘colours’, and a prominent site of identifications and traces of cultural activity. As a result, the twentieth  biennale was in a sense contemporary with the one hundredth anniversary of the foundation of the Biennale in Venice as a museum.2 	Within the biennale, the role of the artist is defined by the level of his or her celebrity, or ‘cult status’, which derives primarily from one of the engagements undertaken in the biennale. In the larger, formal sense, ‘the art’ is the object of the art’, whereas ‘the audience’ is</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the city does not necessarily need to be modernised. 	The Biennale has become a principal site for the financing, promotion and diffusion of various cultural practices worldwide, and has for decades been a major source of funding for various artworld projects. The themes and proposals of the present exhibition are intended to point to a future in which art and culture are actively supported, encouraged and entwined in a mutually reinforcing feedback loop. The exhibition is intended to point to ‘future’ through the present, and to do so through a series of surrogate cultural venues that attempt to anticipate the cultural landscapes of the present. ‘Centre’ is the operative word in this context. 	The first Venice Biennale was organised in 1888, and the following was the proposal that came out of it:  	[…] it would be a mistake to suppose that the present can dictate the future. A culture is a living organism that depends on the support of its historical institutions and the</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the city as a ‘complex’ is also a ‘place of encounter’ and ‘method’ for ‘researchers’ to exist in the city. It is a place where artists can ‘propose and plot new cities’, according to one description, ‘where cultures can’ coexist in peaceful co-existence’.1 	At the same time, the Biennale is a site of international tension, especially in the wake of the recent political violence in Italy and Greece. The recent presidential election in Italy threatens to upend a fragile socio-political equilibrium that the biennale has benefited from over decades, and the Greek crisis makes it increasingly difficult to bring any artists to the region due to a government clampdown on artistic activities. In response, Italian artists have been staging showstopping and pop-art versions of the biennale’s historical imprints in an attempt to offset the political and economic</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the city as a ‘circulation’ is a ‘species’ of multiplicity of radically different species. The term ‘biennale’ is frequently used in relation to the Venice Biennale, but while the history of the event is somewhat ambivalent, the present day significance of the term is quite different. While the historical meaning of the term is the same as it was in the 1920s and 1930s, the current use of the term in relation to the event largely depends on the particularised interests of a few institutionalised biennials (the Biennale of Sydney being an exception to this). The Biennale of Sydney, the largest and most prestigious of its kind, was founded in 1914 and is the only one left in Australia. Its success in generating internationally visible cultural capital and cash flow enabled it to commission commissioned works of architecture, design, animation and sculpture, as well as staging world-class exhibitions. Other important works included Roger et al.</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, from the 19th Venice Biennale to the present, in which artists from all over the world converge on one of the most iconic sites in the city: the Giardini and its streets. 	The Biennale as a Biennality 	The Biennale as a Biennality is a type of Cultural Tourism commissioned by the Italian Cultural Forum and organised by the DCCF. It aims to position the city as a cultural nexus through which a number of interrelated activities can be staged simultaneously. It is a frequent site of international celebrity-conversion, and the main base for the transnational transatlantic transindividuation of culture. It promotes a ‘peripheral’ link to the modernity that is often emphasized in the cultural discourse of the city – the modern city as modernity’ – while stressing the fact that this ‘centre’ is only a ‘point’ of entry into the city, and that the periphery is full of hidden contradictions and social ambiguities. 	In the 19th Venice Biennale, the ‘Bias Beppe Spada’ (a.k.a. ‘The Renaissance’) is the protagonist of the exhibition, and the Biennale itself the backdrop. In a planned, fully fledged cultural enterprise, his work represents the totality, while his ‘City of Lights’ ‘Base Camp’ – a sprawling ‘paradise’ – the entire site of the exhibition. The Biennale is a ‘transindividuation’ event that simultaneously inculcates a specific interpretation of history and geography, and positions contemporary art in relation to the history of cities. In this sense, it is the contemporary manifestation of Florentine modernism. 	The Biennale is structured around two main segments: the City of Lights and ‘Base Camp’ (the Italian flag</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist
    <text>biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist utopia is actually leading to a more fragmented and chaotic society with more unequal and unstable situations for many on the ground. Today, we’re witnessing the effects of this new ‘world order’ that is rapidly emerging. The post-WWII order that many of us imagined was here to stay is actually coming to define the very nature of our futures and the very nature of who we are as individuals and how we want to be governed. We need to find new and innovative ways of being in this world. This is why so many of us feel so passionately about the work we are doing in the community or even doing voluntary service work – even if it is subsistence-based or charity work – because we see ourselves as part of a community now, and see ourselves as part of a community future. We believe that our needs, desires and predicaments are with the community in which we live or work. We don’t see ourselves as individual artists or artists-in-wa</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist utopia – a.k.a. capitalism – has proved far more volatile and uneven, and far more characterised by multiple crises and conflicts. While there is much that could be done to create and encourage ‘transcendent forms of social life’, these have yet to materialise. The growing gulf between rich and poor, between those with access to resources and those without, between those with access to information and those without, between those with access to finance and those without, between those with access to energy and those without, between those with access to language and those without, between those with access to space and those without, etc. etc. etc. etc. etc. etc. There is much that could be said about these things in the present period – much that is still true even in the wake of everything that has been said and done. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring.</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist utopia is a far more insidious and widespread dynamic that has, until recently, been almost entirely ignored. Instead, the main thrust of new economic development has shifted towards the interests of national capital, primarily in the form of interests of interests of capital at international and local scales. This dynamic has been largely ignored in the description of the city, partly because it is considered to be politically unattractive and unreliable, partly because it is considered to be economically unviable and unreliable, and partly because it is considered to be politically inconvenient and unreliable.However, this description is almost entirely wrong. The reason why the city is almost entirely considered to be unviable in the current economic and political sense is that it is exposed to the elements that cause it to boom: the elements of the weather that cause floods and droughts, the elements of the tides that cause them to become increasingly aggressive, and the elements of the tides that cause them to become increasingly insubstantial. Therefore, the historical focus that</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist future for all humanity was averted by the massive, multi-billion-dollar social programmes and economic rebalancing acts that were necessary in order to accommodate and even harness the massive numbers now inhabiting cities across the globe. However, the social and ecological imbalances that emerged during the process of ‘postindustrial society’ are still being felt and canist-chase, whether we like it or not. The challenge now lies in continuing to infuse criticality and life-giving elements into the city in ways that are both structural and multi-generational. This is a multi-tiered game that requires all concerned to play their part. In order to win, the game has to be interesting, entertaining and transformational. The infrastructural renaissance that many predicted would happen in the ‘90s is here to stay. Whether the infrastructural renaissance will be ‘transformational’ remains to be seen, but it is certain that it will continue</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist society is being engineered by the state and its capitalist economy. The post-1989 globalisation is a ‘different kind of capitalism’ that has changed drastically from the one that started with the Bretton Woods system. The dominant forms of economic, political and social power are being weakened. The logic of global economic integration is being re-thought, and in many cases, radically altered. The shared but unequal forms of capitalism are being challenged not only by technological change but also by the forces that are now called ‘radical Islam’. Critical to this kind of challenge, of course, is a long-term view and long-term reflection. However, the tendencies shaping our contemporary global economic and social landscape are fundamentally set in motion. We are born into capitalist relations. Capitalism propels us into ever greater abundance, and in return we are given ever greater power. As a result, we are faced with ever greater political and social inequality. The post-WWII globalisation that many thought</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist future for all humanity – the social and cultural transformations that were to follow, and the ‘big brother’ narrative that would follow – never came to pass. Instead, the capitalist imperative to maximise profits and expand markets continues to lead to ever greater levels of poverty, conflict and alienation. Globalisation has produced mixed results. Some cities flourish, become fabulously wealthy, attract millions of tourists and so on. Other cities – including New York and London – crash and burn. Most of the people who lose their homes and property in the process, and so their jobs, move away or are forced to move to other cities or towns. The economic and social dislocation caused by such urban loss is immense. But the social costs tend to be more divisive. And so it is that in the present period, the question that remains is what can be done to address the social and spatial conditions that generate and foster this capitalism today.This is the subject of the present research project, Crisis in our City</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist society, or at the very least, a poorer one, is now being implemented in many of the world’s poorest countries. While there are undoubtedly voices of dissent within the global capitalist economy, most of us would agree that these voices are overridden by the ever-more-powerful logic of capitalism. Common to all of these conflicting narratives is the overriding reality that emerges from the totality of the given situation: that of ever-greater integration, globalisation and commerce. Yet questions of identity, belonging and community persist, particularly in the wake of the economic and financial crises that are now evident to all. The question of place, identity, identity is particularly relevant in the age of intranational migration, which has become increasingly important for the interests of several nations in the transnational capitalist economy. Indeed, much of the post-WWII growth for many in the West was based on the growth of a large trade surplus with low or negative interest rates, which allowed a large part of the</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist future for all humanity was actually quite liberating for a minority. The emergence of post-Fordist and post-autonomous regional centres around the world with their 'gods and queens’ of finance capital, media and auto manufacturing, accountants and law firms, political campaigns and PR firms – which have all but disappeared into the ground, replaced by new trade routes and codes – opens up vast new ways of life for people in the surrounding region. However, these developments also create opportunities for those who seek to break free and to seek alternative livelihoods. The post-Fordist and post-autonomous period in which we live is likely to remain characterised by periodic bouts of speculative capital flooding in and out of the region, fuelled by ever-flexible exchange between local and globalised forms of capital. The reason why the autonomous and autonomous periods in the region have tended to be relatively strong is that these were the periods when these forms of capital were most exposed to the vagaries of market forces</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist future for all humanity is here, and may very well be more propitious than many people imagined. But this does not negate the need for radical change and change must come from above. The future belongs to the generations who made and are making the cities, and not to the cities themselves.We need to develop longer-term strategies for the future cities of our cities and countryside. Building ressources for a city that is not just an economic engineering opportunity, but a source of creative power that supports a culture of culture as well as commerce, is an urgent task. The city is evolving at a phenomenal pace, but it is also undergoing a process of 'capital circulation' – capital circulation being the process of financing nascent industries of culture while leaving the infrastructure of city behind. The pace of cultural production and urban regeneration is outpacing the pace of regeneration, which is itself outpacing the infrastructure. This imbalance is creating new kinds of resistance and creating new kinds of conflicts. New kinds of urban forms are</text>
    <text>biennials past and present, about which little or nothing has been written yet, including stories from the present, for many reasons. There is much that could be said about this current period, which also includes the financial crisis and the associated political instability, economic repression, cultural marginalisation and impoverishment. However, to achieve lasting change, critical perspectives would have to be provided and encouraged in a way that is both systemic and enduring. This would necessitate a critical understanding of the present and future. For many in the centre, such a challenge is being made by those who seek to enfranchise and create 'their way of life' in this ‘postindustrial city’. A way of thinking about and acting on this change will only ever remain limited and fragmentary.In the present global economy, globalisation is a dynamic process that generates ever-greater market opportunities and deeper pockets for the super-rich. The post-WWII globalisation that many in the centre predicted would inevitably lead to a communist society – the ‘Great Transformation’ – did not come true, and modernity did not deliver communism, but there are signs that the contradictory tendencies of the past may have contributed to making the present possible. So there are signs that the contemporary predicament may have features that are ‘relevant’ to the emergent situation, but which are also potentially ephemeral and void of meaning. This is a problem for those who seek to enfranchise and create ‘their way of life’: a fiction of abundance, of course, but also of struggle and displacement and of conflict and anxiety. This is a crucial question for the future of our city and our species. The city is an indispensible site of exchange, communication and market place; but in a world increasingly defined by sensors and networks, the city is also a site of danger and conflict. The city is a site of habitation, and habitation is a powerful tool. The city is a site of survival</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting,
    <text>will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting, there’s a tension between the museum being where art can happen, and the museum being where art doesn’t happen. I would imagine that the museum would be quite unhappy if the art did. It’s a very interesting thing to have that exhibition as part of our research project at Tate Britain, because it marks the museum as a place where art is experienced in a particular way, and so that creates an experience of being in the museum that is very different to what you get from an exhibition or a private engagement.There’s another piece of the puzzle that we’re working on now, and it’s about the relationship between art and commerce. It’s a very interesting question, and I think that as we develop it more and more, the relationship between art and commerce will become more apparent. For example, the way that the relationship between art and photography is developing now, and is developing in a very complex and powerful way. Perhaps one</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting, the way in which the gallery has been transformed in relation to the new forms of artistic production that are emerging.I think the other thing is that the biennial has itself, since its starting in 1993, been part of the ever-present, almost daily narrative of the ever-greater metropolis. It’s a barometer, measuring – is it a skyscraper? A construction site? A transport hub? A media complex? A financial centre? A museum? A gallery? A plaza? A university? A square? A cathedral? A school? A stadium? A train station? A ferris wheel? A plane? A train station? A museum? A quarry? A factory? A slaughterhouse? A dockside restaurant? A furniture shop? A car wash? A car dealership? A hardware shop? A shoe shop? A magazine? A hardware shop? A storage room? A workshop? A loft? A patch room? A shelving shop? A frame shop</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting, this collective feeling that has a way of intervening in what’s normally perceived as a single space – where once there was only capitalism and the state – and influencing what’s perceived as the inevitable evolution of the society around them.I think that’s interesting in terms of what we don’t see coming or don’t want to see coming. I think that’s one of the beauties of the biennial form – it’s a space in which different perspectives can come together and are able to have that happen. And so I’m interested to see what the government does with the art it makes. I’m interested to know what that form looks like, because I don’t think I’ll ever understand how art is made and why it’s made. And so there is that sense of the impossible not necessarily happening, but how that happens. The new curator, whatever he or she may be,</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting, in the years since I started, to notice how many people refer to the art as commerce. I’d say the opposite: the art of making things happen in the world through art is commerce. It’s a different kind of commerce, and I think that in a certain kind of cultural revolution, commerce is something that happens organically.Not only is art made possible by the fact that the museum is a social institution, but the museum itself is a highly social institution too: by providing a platform on which artists can actually do interesting and creative things, art helps create a public space in which people can actually be in relationships with one another, which in turn helps promote social interactions. When the Tate Modern started, the question was, how do we make the art more accessible to people? And the answer was: we’ve done that by making it a platform for people to actually get on board and be in relationships with one another. So the introduction of a platform like that</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting, there’s a sense that the museum is a place where people can be made to feel like they’re part of that growing society, where art is actively produced and produced in a particular way. And I think that’s what happened with Art Basel, where the artists were asked to participate in what was essentially a service project, in that it was a way to engage with the city and to be made part of a cultural network. This was a very different model of engagement from the one that the biennial is undertaking, which is much more oriented towards providing a service. In the case of a biennial, the role is to actively create a social context in which art can be made and art can be shared, so the biennial does have that aspect of the city in mind. However, the real power of the biennial today is in its ability to create a specificised set of behaviours, which is very different from the original intentions of the biennial. The</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting, there’s some language here that might seem a bit simplistic and applied to cities and so on, but it’s clear that language has a huge effect on how we perceive the world. The fact that the biennial is now a significant part of the city, and the museum that’s there to take its place, and the city’s continued evolution as an entity – this is a strange turn of events. It’s as if the biennial has become the museum, and the museum has become a giant in the city. But it’s also as if the city has become the biennial – it’s become what it calls a ‘metropolitan centre’. And so the biennial is now both the museum and the museum cannot contain or contain the city. It’s the contradictory of the museum, which is there to be seen but can also, in the new administrative guise, be seen. And this is a dialect</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting, there’s this sense of the inevitable, the more we get bigger and more influential. And so I think the curatorial push is important. It’s that tipping point where something is said that isn’t supposed to be said. And so the more art there is to be curated, the less able we are to articulate our ideas and identify with the things around us. Sometimes that’s just by accident; it’s when we have no words.I asked the curator how he imagined the museum would operate in the new world. He said: ‘I’m thinking about the institution today: what kind of relationship would it be to be able to present a curated programme, and also to be able to move between different periods and themes? I think of the museum today more like a factory or a workshop: when you come to the museum, you’re there to be engaged, to be engaged with things, to learn about them.</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting, there’s a sense of the museum as an island in the sea – it’s not a perfect creation, and it’s becoming so.But I do admire the fact that the artist has decided to use the museum as a canvas to explore other aspects of his life: his past, present and future. I think that is a very powerful position to be in, because you can’t say, ‘I’m going to recreate myself here, but I’m going to look at other cultures, other ecosystems and different social formations and that creates a different kind of understanding of the past.’ I think that would be very exciting and different from the way in which the museum is organising itself, and so there’s that.I asked what the future might hold for the museum. He said: ‘It’s hard to say. I don’t think I can give you any predictions. But I can say this</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting, there’s a moment when you’re like ‘Whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa, whoa’ – that collective effect that’s quite powerful.Between then and now, there’s a moment when you’re like ‘What do we do with this mass of people?’And I think that moment – the one before that – there’s a question mark hanging over the question marks. Because I feel like there’s a way of how we might use this museum as a platform – use it as a platform in a way that allows you to actually be part of that history that was made, made possible by things like the Biennial and Tate Modern, and just to be able to feel like you’re actually part of that history that was made possible by art being produced and supported in this country. You’re able to feel like you’re part of it</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by the team’ of architects who worked with the artist, Richard Florida on the project. The exhibition will be ON STAGE! at the Tate Modern and will also be available online at Tate Britain.I asked the curator if he thought the idea of the museum as a place where art could actually happen would go down well in the new government. He said: ‘I’d like to think so. There’s a sense of the inevitable. We’re all part of the crowd that’s gathered to hear us say something that’s not supposed to be said. It’s a collective effect that’s quite powerful. And I think it’s a reflection of the times – we’re in a globalised, capitalist society. We’re part of the 1 per cent. We’re not there yet, but we’re making it there. And so it’s interesting, I suppose, that the invitation to the artist to lead a biennale in such a way is part of the job description that now calls for artists to be strategic planners. It’s part of what the biennial is about, and I think it’s part of what the curatorial role is about. It’s an essential part of what art does, and I think that which is most associated with it is the least able to absorb the shocks and surprises of a changing world.’The curator was referring to the emergent technologies of culture that circumscribe and constrain what can and cannot be said, and that shape what can and cannot be said. But I think that part of the job description is also about responding to those shocks and surprises, and making it work in a way that works for both of us.The other part of the job description is about making it seem as though what’s happening all around us is happening because people are communicating between</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the
    <text>will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the new look of the museum. Nevertheless, the new administration seems to have accepted the fact that the art center has to be able to function, and not only that its educational mission has to be maintained. So far, this has not been an issue at the KW, where visitors are able to explore the building and engage with the activities. With the new management, the building is being used as a training ground for staff to work in the administrative building, which is being converted into a residential complex. This is a game changing development, as it opens up a whole new set of possibilities for the borough, as well as for the artist(s) and organisation that is creating the artwork. The new administration seems to be open to new ideas and approaches, and this is one of the reasons why the borough is so excited about the potential of biennials as a venue for the production of knowledge. It has been a long time since the last biennial, and it is easy to forget how</text>
    <text>will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the idea of a ‘KW Cultural Center’. But the new administration also likes the idea of cultural capitalism, and so the new name is what we will keep. The problem with the old one is that it captured the imagination of the public, and so the new one will capture the imagination of the public again. And so the conflict between the public and the cultural capital will intensify, and so will the competition between the two. And so we will see artists chosen through a democratic process being asked to produce a project in the new name that is as effective as possible, while the administration works through a more restrictive one that is more focused on the arts and less concerned with the public. The challenges will be: how to engage the arts and culture at a fundamental level in a socially engaged way; how to create an experience that is valuable within the context of the new name; and how to build long-term relationships with local communities through what the administration calls ‘deepened cultural activities�</text>
    <text>will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the idea of a federally-funded cultural center in the borough. But the new administration also likes the idea of cultural tourism, and so the new name does not stand out too clearly.  The new Cultural Center will be run by the artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen and KWCA youth leader Ewa Haugen. The new name will mean a lot more to locals, and will be a bit harder for tourists to figure out (because of all the changes, but also because the buildings are being converted into apartments). But the new name will mean a lot more to tourists, and will mean a lot more to the arts community: tourists will know where to look.The Cultural Center will be located in the old Kølbæk Schule, which is no longer a primary cultural center for the area, and will be part of a new ‘cultural district’ initiative that will see the building occupied by artists and other groups</text>
    <text>will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the new shape of the cultural center. But the new guy seems to be getting on very well with the old guy, and the two are clearly pleased with each other’s work. Both agree that the center’s main role now is to offer exhibition space and a place for people to be together, rather than to offer any kind of artistic initiative.  	As a cultural geographer I’m interested in where the arts are located, and where the social dimensions of art are located. So when I came across Ovid’s Metamorphoses when looking for cultural resources in the borough, I immediately put together a list of the many cultural centers in the borough, and referenced the book when thinking about art and social practices. I found the following anecdote quite illustrative of the way that the Cultural Capital Fund views its work: One evening, while walking in the Borough [sic] End of the Williamsburg area, I happened to pass a stop sign. As I</text>
    <text>will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the idea of a joint Russian-Swiss museum. Nevertheless, the new administration seems to be moving towards a different kind of understanding of art and culture. In the borough of Mälvs, for example, the Russian and Swiss museums are being consolidated under one roof, and new environmental protection laws criminalizing nepotism are being drafted. It seems that the new cultural authorities do not see themselves as artists, but rather as curators, educators and administrators with a curatorial mandate to shape perceptions and forge relations with local stakeholders. The new curatorial approach may well be an expression of a desire to return to the kind of arts education that existed in the borough prior to the massive urban regeneration schemes.  A suggested curatorial structure for the development of knowledge is Guillermo Vitale (1894–1976), the son of an Italian and a Basque language teacher. Vitale produced a series of twelve books in his native Basque, which he translated to English, which included a </text>
    <text>will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the idea of a cultural center in the borough. However, the new administration has a different idea of what a cultural center should be: a place where artists can come, train, meet with staff, and so forth. The new administration’s idea of a cultural center is one where art is produced and enacted in ways that are not dictated by a particular administration, and so the new name may be a way to bring some elements of that new art back into the fold. The irony is that the administration that created the crisis of identity around art (in the 1990s and later on) is now trying to save it from itself by introducing a host of new curators and arts administrators into the fold.  The new administration’s cultural design team includes some of the same people who came out of the gate with the crisis of identity, including Bernard Hoffer, Peter McCaughey, and Elliott Dooley, who are all now in their mid-30s.</text>
    <text>will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the look of things, but the new guy seems to like the arts, and that’s all the changes that need to be made. The new guy needs to get on with the business of things, and I think that’s where things are at right now. The real work is yet to be done, but the changes that need to be made are already happening, and I’m certain that, as soon as the art center is up and running, the rest of the community is going to jump on board too. The new administration has certainly given the community a lot to think about, and I think that’s a good thing. The changes that need to be made, and the things that need to be changed, need to be worked through collectively, and that’s what we did at the Cultural Center, because we needed to work through these things as a unit, and so the name change didn’t make a lot of sense anymore, but</text>
    <text>will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the new shape of the cultural center. The new guy does not want a museum with a traditional role, and the museum is not a place to pretend like you’re not in charge. The new guy wants a museum that is an active participatory platform, and the cultural center has that role. But to make that happen, the new guy also needs a cultural foundation that will provide that. KW is already working with Dolphin Arts to create a new kind of cultural center that will actually be involved in the creation of the district, rather than inside the arts museum. This will mean providing arts education and activities in partnership with other partners, rather than just being an artist-run school with an artist’s studio. For Dolphin Arts, this means creating a programme of activities that meet the artist’s needs, rather than a static collection of objects that tell the artist’s story. The new cultural centre will be formally established as the K</text>
    <text>will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the new shape of the cultural center. But the new relationship between the arts and the city is different from that of partnership, which is often described as being between business and labour. The new form of cultural engagement between the arts and the city is one in which the arts are often seen as an asset rather than a liability.  The new form of cultural engagement between the arts and the city that is often described is that between artist-students and artist-teachers. I think that there are lessons here for other organisations too. I started my first art school in the Chisenhale School of the Arts, and it was a kind of a hybrid type of school. It offered a kind of academic education alongside a kind of cultural academic programme. Our curriculum included pieces from a range of different disciplines, including MFA's, but also pieces that came from the institutes and even fringe curatorship programmes. We</text>
    <text>will be curated in cooperation with KW Institute for Contemporary Art; the artists will collaborate with KW staff on research-based projects, while KW will establish an artist-run cultural center for students and professionals in the borough. The KW Cultural Center will be named after the artist who initiated the project, and the KW will be named after the borough. The artist(s) will be responsible for the content of the project and the content of the cultural center. The name change is a collaboration between myself and KW artist educator and director of KW Studies Anne Kølbæk Iversen. I used to run a cultural center in the borough called The Jakobs’ Museum, where art was often exhibited alongside Books of Consumption, a working-class arts and leisure center. The Jakobs’ Museum closed in 1995, and the arts were largely neglected until now. The change of name does not come without complications, and for sure the new administration does not like the new look of the place. But the administration seems to have a different attitude towards the new art center in the borough than the artists. It’s beginning to change, and the new administration is planning to invest in arts education and training in the borough. The cultural center will be a hub for activities including performances, meetings, events, and publications. It’s beginning to function like a curatorial enterprise. In the new urban landscape, a cultural center is the exception rather than the rule.  	The new administration seems to be moving away from the ghetto mentality that the borough had, and was a key contributor in fostering segregation. New Yorkers are becoming more educated about their urban environment, and the benefits and responsibilities of publics; the new administration needs to refresh its image in the eyes of the city’s residents and tourists if it is going to embark on any kind of sustained redevelopment. 	The new co-operative housing (which I co-founded)</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience.
    <text>present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience. It captures the interactive narrative as it is generated, and the narrators create a spatial and relational record of the project’s development. Their recording becomes a platform for sharing and commentating on the events. The digital recording becomes a platform for knowledge sharing and commentating. In this model, the audience returns time and again, and the creator or site’s stakeholders create a narrative out of assemblages of objects, phenomena, and data.[22] The space and time that is captured are claims on the site’s real estate. The EDL’s data-mining and video-recording practices allow the audience to assume identities, locations, places and become the narrative. This is done through objects, phenomena, and records – objects, phenomena, and records – that can be identified, measured, identified with, or inferred from. The most compelling narrative claims about the EDL that have been voiced include ‘That’s me, that’s me</text>
    <text>present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience. It captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It was designed to record and comment on the event, and to capture any new developments. The aim of the website was to record and comment on the ‘present and future of Birmingham’s infrastructure’. In the digital age of the ‘Internet Archive’ and the ‘Google Cloud’, this is an eventful time to be alive.The EDL’s interest in how infrastructure is produced and reproduced runs contrary to the prevailing consensus that places a premium on access to information and the exchange of ideas. The website is a living document that is constantly updating and adding to its record of relations between site visitors and the infrastructure it is designed to support. It draws on the site visitors to inform the site of its production and consumption. It is a place where people come to do things, exchange ideas and connect. In this way, it is both a</text>
    <text>present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience. The audience is a mix of participants in the project’s development team, as well as site visitors and community activists. It is an audience that has a direct and indirect relationship with their media environment. It is an audience that is able to articulate and take part in complex social, cultural and political change through direct action.‘InfrastructuresLive’ is a new media project that takes the audience at the edge of the project and takes them inside the project’s complex social dynamics. It leverages infrastructures theory to understand how cultural production can be dynamically promoted through the media of infrastructures, especially in the public sector, particularly in the context of the urban environment. The EDL hopes to one day establish an EDL Council, a board of representatives for the project. The Council will consist of representatives from the local area and the local area’s mainstream media, political and civic leaders, as well as academics, urbanists and urban researchers.</text>
    <text>present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience. The audience is an online community of participants in the project, and their hosts. It is a record of the site, the programming, the forums, the live programming, and of course the data feeds. The audience is a large and diverse group of users. It encompasses linguists, computer scientists, anthropologists, journalists, artists, policymakers, students and others with a range of expertise and perspectives. It is a record of a live programming event that engages with the contemporary infrastructures of the city and its inhabitants. It captures the dynamic relationship between the city and the internet, and the effect that the internet has on infrastructures and contemporary culture.  The site draws readers to a discussion on the topic, while the forum invites readers to engage in a public debate on the topic. The data feeds and recording mechanisms of the internet create multiple registers of engagement. ‘Active Link’ registers as a website when it delivers value to a site; it is a multimedia event when it</text>
    <text>present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience. The audience is the site owners, managing their interest from the site to the site. They control the discourse, and their access to the discourse is controlled by the authorities. In effect, the site owners and the site audiences are constrained by a single discourse, which in turn circulates in a specific form and function on a specific site. (JL)Eventual Exhibition and Communal Knowledge Barry Commoner &amp; Sarah Carter’s (2015) Communal Knowledge: The Exhibition as a Committed Documentary (2014) traces the life-cycle of the Liverpool Biennial as a series of interviews, observations and reflections, from its beginnings as a curatorial exercise to its present form as a site of ongoing work. In the process, she draws upon a range of curatorial practices, including documentation, archiving and documentation, to bring to life the complicated networks and forces that connect the Liverpool Biennial and the wider artworld. The event is an occasion to ask artist-centered questions of cur</text>
    <text>present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience. It captures the audience’s interaction with the site, its people, places and networks. It records any language, immediate, archival, and commentated memories of the site. It records the people who visit the site, and the networks they rely on. It records how people are drawn to the site, both by their networks and their networks’ connections. It records the politics of the site, and the site’s ability to hold together. 	The site’s audience can be divided into two broad categories: those who visit the site regularly, and those who stay home or move away. The former category is made up of visitors who come for the stories told by the Sherwood Forest Dwellers, and by the communities around the properties they occupy. The latter category is made up of locals, visitors and visitors from outside the area. Local people make up about half of the local population. They include tourists, locals, tourists from other parts of the world, people</text>
    <text>present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience. The audience is an ever-expanding constituency that is constantly seeking a comment or a remark. It is a constituency that is sensitive to the fact that the site understands it, and that the site can therefore expand its knowledge base. The audience is a user-base, and the site understands this fact. It knows which posts are relevant and which are not. It knows which posts are from the site and which are not. It knows which post is from the site and which are not. It knows which ‘topics’ are ‘worthy’ and which ones are ‘not worthy’. All of this is designed to map the audience’s knowledge onto an interface. The audience is a user-base, and the site understands this fact. It knows which posts are relevant and which are not. It knows which topics are worthy and which ones are ‘not worthy’. All of this is designed to map the audience’s knowledge onto an interface</text>
    <text>present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience. It captures not only the programming of the infrastructures live site, but also intervenes in the programmatic flow of the city and nation as a site for the construction of new infrastructures. The website is a microsite, embedded deep within the city’s infrastructure, accessible by a city’s network of streets, parks, tunnels, subways and elevated platforms. It captures the history of the project as it happens, from conception to construction, and any new developments that may arise from it. 	The website and podcast are rendered in HTML, which is a new programming model for the web that is both approachable and manipulable. It enables a multitude of possibilities for manipulation and exploitation. Indeed, the power of manipulation and the flexibility of the scripting language allow for the creation of interesting or bizarre experiences, ficticious scenarios or ‘living’ environments through the graphic manipulation of data. 	The 2014 Liverpool Biennial saw the establishment of a new</text>
    <text>present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience. It is a way to see how the two interact. In the event of a site closure, the site’s audience returns to the site, participates in the activities that are archived, creates a new audience through participation and creates a network of knowledge that is sustained through the interaction between the two. The interactive website and collaboration with the audience produced a series of site-specific activities that functioned as stand-ins for the closure of the site and the creation of a new city. These stand-ins for the closure of the site were intended to be temporary, appearing as a ‘temporary urban backdrop for a public event’ in a new guise. The interactive website continued to collect and analyze the site’s public and cultural landscape and its connections to the closure of the site and the creation of a new city. It became an essential part of the narrative of the event, a narrative that continued to be updated online. This critical website and the archives it produced allowed the public to</text>
    <text>present an online project that would ultimately result in the establishment of a new generation of designers and engineer’s through its publication, in turn, of the project’s findings and an analysis of how to creatively apply the knowledge gained. The EDL established an interactive website that provided a record of the project’s development, comments and suggestions on its design, analysis and implementation, as well as hosting a series of live webcasts throughout the year (accessed October 2018). The EDL website is hosted on a service called ‘InfrastructuresLive’ that captures the live programming, interactive tool and data feeds of the infrastructures programming and media communities. It provides a record of the project’s development, the live programming, interactive data feeds, product demonstrations and live webcasts. It was designed to record and comment on the events of the project, and to capture any new developments. This record is a set of relations between the site and the site’s audience. In   	programming terms, the audience is a set of people who come to the site to look at, sample or consume content. They are not there to learn, make friends or engage in any meaningful way with the site’s content. They are there to consume media, and especially to consume in an aesthetically pleasing way. So the audience is a data point and the site itself is a set of designed environments that continuously survey and survey the audience’s physical landscape in an attempt to figure out what they want to do with their time. 	The interactive website creates a simulacrum of the audience’s physical environment in an attempt to reflect the site’s own temporality. But in doing so, it also creates a simulacrum of temporality itself, in the form of a web site that continuously distorts the actuality in contradictory ways. The EDL’s interactive video website, for instance, exploits the fact that visitors to the site</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to change to respond to the demands of a curatorial state in the future.This all seems a long time ago now, but back then I was a curator and the kind of person who would have been interested in what was going on in the Gaza Strip. I was reading your book The Museum Problem and noticed something that you said that stuck with you. You said that the problem with the museum was that it was always present in some kind of framing. You had a point of view, but it was always filtered through other people’s perspectives. You see a museum and you see a factory or a school or a street or a flat but you don’t see a neighbourhood, a neighbourhood or a community. That is, the museum is always the last place you look. You can put a museum on the map and call it a neighbourhood but it’s still a museum. The kind of thinking that you had was very influential on what you did and what you believed. I</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to adapt to these new conditions.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in Exhibition Research and Aesthetic Theory at McGill University and holds the Canada Research Chair in Experimental Art and Exhibition Research. Her research interests include experimental art, experimental culture, and emerging art forms. Her publications include The Art Newspaper (with Jill Pagels), the award-winning catalogue of experimental art publications (with Jill Pagels), and the award-winning catalogue of contemporary art (with Jill Pagels and Elizabeth Povinelli). She is the editor of the online journal Stages (2013-16) and the journal Apperance (2016-present).In recent years she has been teaching exhibitions and conducting research into art, art-histories and art-institutions. She is currently Head of Research, Part 2 of the Art Newspaper and has her research interests focusing on the use of art as a political-ideological weapon in contemporary political struggles, especially in the context of experimental art.</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to change in order to accommodate the needs of the curatorial community in the 21st century.Thanks again, Joasia.DPS: Joasia, this is a question that came up during our working dinner this week: what does it mean to make a curated exhibition? I think that what we were trying to do was to create a system that supports a continuous exchange of knowledge, so that what we did at the festival was cumulative with other types of exhibitions and that the collection of artefacts we had available to us at the time we organised the festival would be able to be brought to life through this system. But I also think that the exhibitionary form needs to be reconceived in order to accommodate the needs of curatorial community in a contemporary and connected way.The main obstacle for me in my view is the prevailing notion that the curatorial is some kind of publicist or a museum administrator. I think that the curatorial is the frontline of power and that it’s really important for</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to undergo major changes in the coming decades, because it is becoming increasingly difficult to imagine a world without curatorial work.DDownload this article as PDF26 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for your exhibition-systems pioneer, DPW, which is developing a plan to bring you into a new kind of biennial experience in Liverpool.I</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to change as well.There are of course other forms of art today, and there are art and documentary art forms that exist today; but the form that I see emerging right now is the likely future form. And the way that this is occurring now is through the curatorial act as a specialist; as an enabler, a propulsive force, and as a convener of communities around art and culture. I think that the curatorial role today is more like a producer, and is more like a marketplace. It supplies the technology, the resources, the social networks, the cultural exchanges, the biennials and the megastructures that exist today, but it also provides the conditions that enable artists and curators to work on other forms of art and create new art forms tomorrow. And I see this in the form of biennials, megastructures and so on. The curatorial role today is an extraordinary, even disruptive force in shaping art and culture, but it is</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to change in order to support this new condition.The exhibitionary form has been around for a while now and I see many curators and art historians who are still involved in the art form today. And I see many of them who are remarkably apolitical. They may still think there are good reasons why the art form is important, noble and valuable. But I see many who are questioning the morality of the art form and its role in a capitalist society today.I think that there are also artists and curators who have grown up in this new medium and who know what they are doing is valuable and beautiful and have the potential to change the world. I remember, years ago, when I first started working at Tate, one of my first exhibitions was a solo show by two artists. And I remember one of the curators saying to the other: ‘You need to check out the exhibitionary form.’ And the other saying: ‘You need to check out social media.�</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to change in order to support the cultural life that we envision for ourselves and for our immediate communities.The exhibitionary form will have to undergo a radical shift if we are to have any chance of influencing it in interesting and creative ways. The evolution of the exhibitionary form will have to come from within, alongside other cultural forms, such as curatorial activities. The key is to find the right balance between the different forms of cultural reproduction, and between the needs of the producer and the needs of the consumer. The exhibitionary form will have to evolve in order to meet the needs of the diverse cultural groups that comprise the world we inhabit.The main challenges and opportunities for the anthropologist and museum professional in the twenty-first century are set out in the book The Anthropocene: Crisis, Triumph and the End of Oil (2014). The crisis of the petroleum-based economy that the fossil fuel generated on the planet presents us with is unprecedented. The scale of the problem is immense. The number of people</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to undergo fundamental changes in order to accommodate these new needs.This is the curatorial version of the ‘metainterface’ – the interface that is overproduced and consumes what little remains of the metainterface. The metainterface is what allows computers, cameras, tablets and other sensors to communicate with each other, yet it is also what limits this communication. It is this massive, ever-expanding interface that creates the illusion of transparency, but it is also what makes the metainterface possible. It is a device that can transmit data, yet it is also what enables the metainterface to be hacked – a hack into the data transmission process allows any app to be installed without user interaction. This sounds like an oxymoron, but it is the realisation of an industry problem.The metainterface is what allows the computer to do all this incredible, powerful thing that it does, yet it is also what makes the metainterface</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to change, and will have to change in order to accommodate and innovate in a different way, and thus it is important to take the time to put these different possibilities into practice.This is the curatorial role today. Its parameters are constantly changing, and I don’t think that the curator is immune to this. He has to be constantly adapting his act in order to account for the new requirements that he inherits. And I think that he also has to master the language of change. Because I think that he doesn’t have that luxury anymore.The fact that the biennale has had to change its format and has to account for these materials in different ways, while remaining static and unchallenging, is an artefact of the contemporary condition. There is no longer a museum-like setting that allows you to follow a curator’s narrative; there is no longer a permanent, fixed museum-like setting; the biennial is no longer the sum total of its</text>
    <text>The next Biennial will be held in late 2018. The curator, Joasia Krysa, intends to present a new narrative through the selected material from the exhibition. The exhibition will be based on the text of the selected materials and should be able to engage with and anticipate the present and future condition of the material. This should allow the audience to act as a catalyst for change through the use of language, events, places and social networks.The exhibition should be able to tell a story through the selected collection of artefacts. It should also be able to engage with and anticipate the condition of existence for the future generations of artists and designers. These are the challenges faced by a curatorial act in the 21st century. I think that the exhibition industry as a whole faces new kinds of problems. But I also think that the major problem of the contemporary condition is one of overproduction and that exhibitions in this medium have to change to meet the demands of the market. And I think that the exhibitionary form will have to change again to meet the demands of a post-industry society.Diageo Art Gallery, Cork, 5th Art + Biscuit Open Air, 2:00-4:00, 2018. Photo courtesy of Diageo.PreviousNextDiageo Art Gallery, Cork, 5th Art + Biscuit Open Air, 2:00-4:00, 2018. Photo courtesy of Diageo.Sven Spieker in his reflections on the influence of the Biennale on cultural practice makes an interesting comparison. He points out that, during the 1950s and 1960s, the biennale was a significant player in the city, regularly providing a significant presence in the art books of the city and prompting various cultural initiatives. But the influence of the biennale has become much more diffuse, occurring in smaller number of venues, often located further afield from the city. He also observes that the cultural organisations that used to support the biennale have since</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
