<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of
    <text>human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of multi-level languages) in the fields of Film, Video and Media Studies. He is currently developing a multi-disciplinary research project that includes a continuing interest in how language is constructed and maintained, and how that may inform cultural practices and historical movements. His dissertation examines the Gezi Park movement and its aftermath in Istanbul, and how they may be viewed as a case study in the social organization of language.Download this article as PDFDr. Eva CastringiusKarin Freire Research Centre for Language and Society, Faculty of Arts &amp; Science, UR, La Habra, Spain   The Osiris ProjectKarin Freire Research Centre for Language &amp; Society, Faculty of Arts &amp; Science, UR, La Habra, Spain   The Osiris Project is a collaborative research project between the University of Liverpool, the U.S. Naval Research Laboratory, the U.S. Air Force Research Laboratory and the U.S. Air Force Museum. The project was initiated in 2015 and is led by Dr</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of multivalent publishing schemes). He is the editor of the popular linguistics and literary linguistics websites Linguist (www.linguisticliterature.com and Argosy-Linguist.com), where he is committed to disseminating knowledge of the philosophy, ethics, and politics of linguistic variation and multi-lingualism. His work has also appeared in publications such as Scientific American, The New Republic, The New York Times, The New Republic Digital Archive, The New Republic Historical Review, and The New Republic Brief. He is the editor of the popular fantasy and science fiction magazine Stages, which was named one of the 100 Most Influential Linguistics Blogs of the 1990s by the New Republic. He has been a visiting professor at McGill University, and the editor of the popular online journal Linguistics &amp; Philosophy. His articles have also been published in Popular Linguistics, a journal of the Popular Library of Linguistics. He is the host of the</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of multi-linguistic narratives). His upcoming book, Linguistics for Digital Cultures, investigates the linguistic underpinnings of multi-linguistic social media and the cultural repercussions of that linguistic innovation.  	[iii] Interview with Jussi Parikka,  	Sentences with an Eelam,  	1990.  	[iv] The Seattle Times, 6 April 1990, p. A1.[v] The New York Times, 12 April 1990, p. A1.[vi] The New York Times, 14 April 1990, p. A1.[vii] The Seattle Times, 13 April 1990, p. A1.[viii] The New York Times, 14 April 1990, p. A1.[ix] The New York Times, 16 April 1990, p. A1.[x] The Seattle Times, 16 April 1990, p. A1.[xi] The New</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of multi-level narratives) from the Journal of a Libertarian Perspective on Linguistics (1987) and the popularizer of multi-level narratives in the popularizer of languages (in the popularizer of multi-level languages). He is also the editor of the popularizer of multi-lingual publishing company Dialogues from the Linguist, Linguist for Life (1991-96) and the translator of the popularizer of languages to the journal Linguist for Life: A Compendium of Linguistics (1997). His work has been featured in various periodicals including the New York Times, the Hollywood Reporter, the New Republic, the New York Times and numerous other publications. He has received a host of awards and mentions including the 2014 Brit Awards for Popular Culture Writing Award, the 2014 Polk Medal for Popular Culture, and the 2014 Guggenheim Medal for American Art.He is the host of the weekly podcast Linguist John McWhorter and has written for the</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of multi-lingual texts) and the co-editor of the popular encyclopaedic reference web site The Ubyssey (now defunct). He is also the editor of the popular encyclopaedic reference web site EtymologyPhraseLibrary.com, and the web-based companion site Living Etymology.Dr. Truscello’s work has been featured in the New York Times, the Washington Post, NBC Nightly News, the New York Times Best Seller List, the Wall Street Journal, the Los Angeles Times, the New York Times Best-Selling Book, and numerous online literary journals. He has received numerous awards and mentions for his research and writing.  	[iii] The Ubyssey, http://www.the Ubyssey.com/index.html?tag=the-ubyssey&amp;month=November2009&amp;file=empty; accessed 24 April 2014.Download this article as PDFAna Laura López de la TorreSlo</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of multi-lingual print) as well as the award-winning multimedia artist (in the popularizer of multimedia art) Chrysler C-type Catalogue. His work has been commissioned by the British Library, National Museums Canada, and the Canadian Museum for Languages. He is a co-editor of the forthcoming online journal Linguistic Criticism.Download this article as PDFDr. Gerald SeabrookDr. Gerald Seabrook is Professor of Linguistics at McGill University and holds the Canada Research Chair in Syntax and Indigenous Languages. His research focuses on topics in syntactic theory, with a special focus on languages of the Chehalis, Tsimane and Indigenous languages. His publications include articles in the popular languages of the Americas, Europe, and Eastern Australia, as well as the international literature on languages of the Pacific. His work has also been featured in the New York Times, Washington Post, New York Times, Los Angeles Times, and CBC's The</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of multi-lingual narratives) as well as the co-editor of the popular web publication Memrise. His work has also appeared in venues including The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The New Inquiry, among others. He holds a Bachelor of Science in English Linguistics from the University of Alberta, and a Master’s degree in Linguistics from the University of Calgary. Labyrinths of LanguageScienceNavigating the Labyrinths of LanguageScienceTim JeevesTim Jeeves is an Assistant Professor in the Department of Linguistics and Combinatorial Culture Studies at the University of Alberta, and holds a joint appointment at the Museum of Modern Art and Museum of Contemporary Art Edmonton. Her research interests include the cultural ecology of mathematics and computer programming, with a particular focus on mathematical and computational culture in Canadian high schools. She is the editor of the popular web portal, InfoQ, which has covered programming languages, software, and social</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of multi-level narratives). His work has also appeared in venues including The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New Republic of Canada, The New Republic of America, The New Republic of Japan, The New Republic of Europe, and The New Republic of Australia. His essays have been published in literary journals such as Linguist, The American Literary Supplement, The New Republic, The New Republic of Linguistics, The American Political Science Review, The Freeman, and The Literary Supplement. He is currently researching the experiences of his late father, a clinical psychologist who worked as a psychiatrist at the Royal University of London.  	[iii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. John Graham Kerr is an Assistant Professor in Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is pursuing a doctorate in Linguistics. He received his doctorate from the university in December</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of multi-regional narratives). His work has also appeared in numerous periodicals and magazines including the New York Times Book Review, the New Yorker, the Los Angeles Times, the Chicago Tribune, the Village Voice, the New Republic, the Village Voice Digital Journal, the Village Voice Archives, the Archives of the Linguistic Society of New York, New York Public Library, and the Village Voice Web site. His work has also appeared in a wide range of books, including the award-winning Beyond Multi-Linguistics (with Ian H. Gilmore), the New York Times Book Review, the New York Times Book Supplement, the Village Voice Book of the Year, the Village Voice Web site, the Village Voice Companion to the Humanities, and numerous book-length articles in academic and popular periodicals and magazines. His most recent book, Linguistics: A Cultural History (with Noel Burch and John Urry) is a compendium of linguistic, cultural, and linguistic theory and research,</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology] and the resulting social upheaval.  	[i] New York Times, 7 December 1984, p. 1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D.S. at Mount Royal University,  	1988. I think I've seen this one coming… 	[ii] Interview with Dr. John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. Michael Truscello is an Assistant Professor in Theoretical and Applied Linguistics at the University of Alberta, where he is working towards a Ph.D in Linguistics. His research interests include theoretical, theoretical, and methodological issues in linguistics, cultural studies, and media/cultural studies. His publications include the popularizer of multi-linguals (in the popularizer of languages: a guide to multi-syllabic narratives) and multi-syndicated online journals (in the popularizer of multi-level narratives) as well as the co-editor of the popular web publication Linguistica Review. His work has also appeared in venues including The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New Republic and The New Republic of New York.His forthcoming book, Using Linguistics to Understand Our Social World is the topic of a special session of the symposium The Other in September.  	[iii] Interview with John Graham Kerr,  	Psychology Today, 17 April 1988.Download this article as PDFDr. John Graham Kerr is Professor in the Department of Linguistics and the Philosophy of Language, with a research agenda centering on the philosophy and science of language. His research interests include the philosophy of language as a cognitive construction, the philosophy of language as a media construct, and the philosophy of language as a social construction. He is the author of several books including the popularizing of multilingualism, the social construction</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it’s time to unpack the layers of its own historical development. It’s time to face, as the Biennale organisers did, the fact that the museum we’re currently examining is building itself out of the layers of the city, each layer being constructed on the previous one. The layers that make up the building we’re examining are the same as the layers of the ancient city, in fact, and as the ancient historian Herodotus puts it, making the point that we’re examining, that there’s a continuity between the ancient world we’re living in and the worlds of evolution. So the layers that make up the building are alive with the traces of our own past, and they’re telling us something about the evolution of the city. And this is a deeply significant step for Biennales, because it basically says: this is who we are, and this is what we’re doing here. And</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it’s time to open up the museum, invite artists and curators onto the premises, and then have the museum sort out the cultural gaps and gaps that might exist between now and then. This is a very different strategy from what the Museum of Modern Art did, which was to archive, plan and plan again, whenever and wherever the museum might be located, creating what it could be when it was located in a different place. It’s like the ‘wet bottom’ of the biennale’, with the museum constantly on the verge of being overwhelmed by the huge, diverse collection of art and artefacts that it was obliged to house and present in a particular location. And this is what the Museum of Modern Art did next. It placed its curatorial lens almost entirely on the waterfront, presenting the history of the area as a narrative in which the artist Darren Little is the protagonist, while the city rapidly accrues an ever larger collection of artefacts and</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it’s time to unpack the layers of our urban and cultural landscape, to step outside of the museum and cultural context, and to open up new artistic and cultural possibilities. Sounds good, doesn’t it? And it’s an interesting way to think about how art and culture might interact in the future, through the lens of the large biennale. After all, even though the Biennale isn’t going to become a museum, it’s clear that the Museum of Modern Art is going to want to recreate the experience of visiting the Museum of Modern Art. And so we can imagine a scenario in which the Museum of Modern Art tries to set up a similar experience for the first time, in a city thats been disused for years. The problem with the Biennale is that it takes place in an unreal world, so the problems it presents are real and pressing. But the challenge for the Museum of Modern Art is different.</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it’s time to sit down and have a cultural conversation, but it’s actually time to explore cultural differences and gird up for a possible future cultural encounter. That’s what the museum does best. But the real intent of the Biennale should be cultural in nature, rooted in a specific set of values and priorities, and possibly even ethnically diverse. That would make for a richer and more interesting future biennale, one in which the discourses of various racialised and multi-racialised groups are treated with equal weight, and perhaps even some of the same values and priorities. 	[i] The Biennale website. [ii] Wikipedia article on the word ‘choreography’. [iii] The Biennale’s 2016 General Audience Survey, 2016 Study Guides, 2017. Available at: http://www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/en/study-gu</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it’s taking the place of the museum as a producer of art, and the museum as a settler of space in that process. It’s as if the Biennale is saying ‘Hey, this is a museum, and this is art’, and the museum is saying ‘Hey, this is an art project, and this is what the Biennale does’. The answer to the question of what the Biennale does or doesn’t do, or what it’s doing or not doing, is a good question to ask about the trajectory of contemporary art’s social practice. It’s a good question to foster a sense of wonderment in the city, as the Biennale does, by turning its back on the seemingly impossible. 	The biennale itself, as an entity, is the product of decades of joint planning and design work between the MOMA, its trustees, and artists,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it’s time to unpack the layers of the museum, and these layers to a greater or lesser extent inhabit the city. And this is exactly what the Museum of Modern Art has done. For example, the late nineteenth-century museum movement was dominated by figures such as Rembrandt, Rubens, Picasso and Banks, whose works frequently intervened between the contemporary and historical periods. But the twentieth century museum movement was much more cinematic, with Kunsthal Aarhus and the Biennale as its cinematic and visual forms. And today, the Biennale is more cinematic, with works that come complete with narration and images that are pre-rendered on a massive display. So the Narrative Piece   	In these new media forms – multimedia, social media, interactive media – the artist becomes the arbiter of value, and the tourist is a passive voyeur. The real estate, the performance, the poetry, the memento – multimedia, social media, and in</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it’s time to rediscover the museum, to come back to the city and engage with the urban spaces that it’s curating. But this kind of radical archaeology rarely happens in places where the city is under constant threat of redevelopment, which is why the Biennale chose to locate its curatorial agenda in the city, where huge amounts of new development are occurring at an incredible pace. The Japanese financial crisis in September 2008 further fuelled a building boom in the financial district, which in turn fuelled a housing crisis in the outer areas. As a result, the number of homeless soared, and homelessness became a crisis for the city’s poorest residents. And so it continued, with the Biennale’s curatorial board meeting regularly reporting back to the mayor on its status. This kind of radical archaeology is still happening in Detroit, but it’s being done in the name of the Biennale, and so the Biennale is shifting its attention</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it’s time to open up that gap a little bit, to help create an understanding of what it’s like to live in an archive. And so the issue becomes how that gap is going to be built. Curators, artists, art collectors, artists themselves – they’re going to be asking, as we go along, what exactly is the meaning of the Biennale, why are we booking this particular exhibition through 2022, and what is it going to be like to be in an archive? What are these gaps and crevices that are going to be asking, going to be pointing to? What are these different forms of archive that we are going to be creating? This is going to be an incredibly interesting dynamic.  	As we said at the beginning, we don’t yet have an answer to this question. We don’t know what the end game is going to be, and so we don’t yet have an answer</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it’s now a museum, but it doesn’t have a museum. It’s more of a promotion of what it has already – a set of assets, a set of values, a site to be excavated, a mission statement. But it’s also saying that it wants to be a ‘multiplex’ of what it has.’ The problem with this is two-fold. First, with the museum as a museum, it becomes a space for the past to be excavated, a space in which to be present but also for the future to be created. And second, there’s the rub. If the past is to be excavated, it’s because we have to, or rather, because the future has to be created. But the fact that it has to be made present in order to support the present and the future erases the past and creates an ever larger and more complex space of constant technological alteration and</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’ Family   	The  	World Biennale, which is supposed to be a model for the ‘biennial that will one day govern our collective memorys, is being organised in New York’s Chinatown and its environs. So are the many similar projects that proliferate, sometimes incredibly opportunistically, in the city. And there’s the rub. The fact that the Biennale is being organised in the name of the Museum of Modern Art means that it’s being presented as a museum, but its true intent is as a social enterprise. As the Biennale itself puts it: ‘Its mission is to celebrate the contemporary contemporary contemporary and archive forms of art’, ‘the museum as a progressive practice in the production and presentation of art’, and ‘the museum as a platform to explore cultural differences and gaps’. So it’s as if the Biennale is saying that it’s interested in the museum precisely because it’s interested in art? Questioning such a notion is the job of the critic, but the task of the critic is increasingly administrative and unrealised when it comes to cultural power struggles in the city. The Biennale has turned the symbolic form of the museum into an instrument of cultural production, and perhaps that’s the point. The implication is that the museum is essentially redundant; biennales are no longer necessary, and there are other venues for cultural production such as the streets or the parks. But the streets are a different matter. As the Biennale itself acknowledges, they serve a different function: ‘the streets provide a physical surface for the events of the exhibition, a functional stage on which the artist’s choices and actions can be planned and controlled’. So the Biennale is performing a cultural function in and through the streets. It’s performing culturally by accident, but that</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can
    <text>human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can and should be used to investigate and resolve questions and debates about the living and immaterial. ‘But what if the living world is but a series of possible futures – a point in a ‘curated’ narrative – which can and should be considered as full and complete works, in which the living and immaterial world simultaneously present and effaced?’ This kind of thinking about the living and immaterial world is part of what is meant by ‘living’ by the living.It can also be understood as part of a broader philosophy that goes back to Aristotle, whose Phaedrus (Book of Commonplaces) was one of the first books of Western philosophy. Aristotle’s philosophy of living was one based on the intellectual production of things, and the things themselves, rather than on the animal world of living things. Thus, in the Phaedrus, the living and immaterial world are treated as if they were of a different kind – abstract, inhuman and void</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can only be imagined in terms of the past, in terms of immutable historical tendencies.’2 In the contemporary world, we experience these tendencies in the form of ever larger, more complex systems of global communication and data circulation – we call these ‘metainterfaces’ – that are constantly evolving and subject to variable conditions and contingencies. And yet, again, we can consider the inbuilt contradiction inherent in the human condition: what makes us human is fundamentally determined by the past, or more precisely, the past is determined by the very thing that makes us human – namely, the species. If the past is seen as the present, then we are forced to live in the face of uncertainty and change, because the very notion of human life or human agency is at stake.Modernity is defined by the advent of the modern economy – the final stage in the process of industrialisation – and modernity is closely connected to the rise of finance capital. The modern economy identifies what it calls</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can only be imagined within the present.’1 	The fetishisation of life, then, engenders a certain amount of internal realism.‘Realism’ isn’t just an economic concept; it’s an ethical one as well. People react to the things that constitute the world through their actions, and actions often represent a world in motion. So, for example, the action of walking down the street can be interpreted as representing a possible future for New York City; its sound as a potential future for a nearby neighbourhood; and its colour as a possible future colouring of buildings in the city. All these things morph and mutate as the city evolves, but one of the first things we do when we encounter a new neighbourhood is to assess whether the neighbourhood is in fact a reconstruction of the 1970s, a re-construction of the conflictual blockades that characterise the district. And so the action of assessing neighbourhood is a re-construction of</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can and should be used to resolve certain kinds of historical questions. But this use of the future is always in conflict with, and in some cases, can lead to the destruction of, living things.’1 	So, how does one build collective meanings around the contingencies of life? How does one imbricate the lived world with collective meanings? In researching these questions, I came across two philosophers who I thought were particularly interesting in their respective fields: Immanuel Kant (1790–1947) and Immanuel Wallerstein (1907–99). Both were German philosophers who were born in Vienna and lived in exile in Switzerland. Kant was one of a small circle of German philosophers who fled to Switzerland after the Weimar Republic was dissolved in 1919. His life and thought are legendary.Wallerstein was born in 1906 and lived primarily in Palestine. He was a founding member of the Palestine Cultural Society and a writer and editor of the Palestine Post. In his later years he</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can only present certain historical conditions. And as we move through history, we encounter and play with different historical precedents, or at least these are what we imagine exist. And this kind of thinking about historical precedents, or what we can and cannot do in the here and now, can and does lead to quite different kinds of historical outcomes.Take, for example, the presence and eventual presence of atomic weapons in the nuclear arsenals of both Britain and Germany. It is quite possible that at present, both countries are not in any sense nuclear, but given the amount of nuclear waste and the various kinds of nuclear weapons they possess, the end point is always clearly indicated. And in either case, the end point – which is to say, the end point of any given historical process – has a kind of fixed significance and – in this case – cannot evolve. So the question becomes what kinds of changes can be made? And the answer is always – and I mean this in the broad sense here –</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can only be imagined in terms of the particularities and intricacies of the present – and only as a set of relations between people living now.‘Presentism’ is set in motion in all its intricate details.But what happens when this internal dynamic – the articulation of a future that is separate from our own and in which there is no contemporary or future – is submerged in the mundane, everyday world? This is the question that anthropologist Max Brooks asks in his book Culture and Anarchy. He asks: what comes to mind when one thinks of a culture? What does it signify? What is meant by a ‘culture’? When thinking of a city, what is meant by a ‘city?’ Brooks begins to answer this question, and the related question of what it means to ‘be a city’. Being cities, he finds, means living in them – in their history, in their traditions, in their geography – living among its people, watching</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can only be what is described as ‘in’ the present.’[4] And so we can add another element to the mix: contingency. The advent of AI raises the stakes of what might be possible in the future, and thus the parameters by which we measure and categorise human life. AI will make it easier to quantify the enormous difference that a living thing makes to the world around it. AI will make it easier to understand the relationships that exist between humans and nonhuman entities. And it will make it easier to imagine what those relationships might be like. All of these elements of AI make it easier to imagine what the future might hold.On a practical level, contingency is a term that people use to refer to when thinking about the effects of technology. It describes the contingency of current technological systems – their ability to function – and its relations to the past, present and future. It describes the elements of human behaviour that result from the interaction of different technologies. And it</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can only be one in which people are fully and immediately aware of and participate in, through the living thing that they inhabit. ‘Any given variation of the external world is but one of many possible futures – there are, after all, only so many discrete parts to the overall picture of the world, and the number and variety of possible futures is itself a function of the number and varieties of bodies and figurative figures and figures within that picture.’’[62]So, here we have the anthropologist Christine Kern teaching British cultural theory at the Victoria and Albert Museum, the home of the British Museum, in New York. She is teaching in an environment that is both academically rigorous and politically diverse, yet politically homogeneous – British cultural theory is developed through the study of museum collections and museums in the context of race, class and gender.[63] But as Kern observes, ‘museums are rare in their multiplicity, and rare in their historical or archival</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can only be predetermined in advance – it’s trapped up there in a predetermined order for a reason.’ ‘But what if the development of the external world outstrips what can be expected within the space and time of the fetishised ‘individual?’ This sort of speculative fantasising about the external world, what Marx called ‘fetishism’, is something that contemporary artists, curators and art historians around the world have been doing for decades. It’s called postmodernism.And today it’s called art’s ‘episodic’ or ‘time-critical’ form. It’s also called ‘modern’ by some people around the world.Postmodernism emerged in reaction to the experience of horror – the experience of loss, or loss of meaning – and the reaction of cultural theorists to it. So, postmodernism is a kind of a torture, a form of political</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, in which the individual is reduced to a number – a number that is constantly in motion – is what Marx called ‘fetishism’. The fetishisation of the individual embodies and results in the fetishisation of life itself; the precise definition of life that Marx gave was a fetish for human life. But this doesn’t just refer to the living thing; ‘life’ becomes the object of fetishisation within the framework of the fetishised living thing.’ It also refers to the objectifying function of the living thing – what Marx called ‘the fetishisation of life’. For Marx, life is reduced to a number in motion relative to one another. ‘Any given development of the external world is but one of many variations of this internal dynamic – a succession of corresponding predetermined contingent factors – which determine, characterize and (eventually) resolve the possible future changes and developments of the world.’ So, in other words, the future can never be certain, either positively or negatively.‘But what if the future is absolutely certain? What if, through some miracle, we can achieve a precise prediction of the future?’ This sounds like magic to us, but it bears repeating: the future is here now, and will remain so for as long as we are alive. The future may well bring changes that are positive and that are ‘horrible’, but to call such a thing magic is to misunderstand what life is about. Life is about contingency, about what Marx called ‘state of exception’. We humans are made to react to certain kinds of change, and to live through certain kinds of ‘extreme’ situations. But to think that the very essence of what life is about – living and breathing – would be annihilated – that’s to us barbarians. To others, it may seem that living things simply aren’t that important, that things fall by the ways</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city)
    <text>presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city) and private (in the sense that it’s impossible to render the city in the form of a museum without rendering it private, and vice versa). It’s very telling, for example, that the curatorial language of the last Venice Biennale, which was staged in the Pergamon Gallery, identified a section of the exhibition as the ''most representative of the many voices of the city’. Somehow, that was a very new concept for a biennale to me, and I didn’t experience it as such. It was more that the voices we captured in our pictures and videos were of a very specific kind of dimension: this is the voice of a particular generation of artists, writers and curators, and though they may have different political leanings, they’re all deeply influenced by the voice of the city that we captured in our travels.  And so the curatorial push becomes a form of self-expression. It’s</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city) and private (in the sense of the Penny Dreadful, not the Draper Homebaked family, or the Docklands Community Land Trust, not the Docklands Community Land Trust). And I think that the reason why the public is so invested in the biennial is precisely because it doesn’t have access to the underlying cultural resources of the city. It doesn’t know where the Performing Arts tradition is located, or know what a Performer is. And so the biennial, in many ways, is the most accessible cultural resource that the city has. It is present in many forms, and it is concurrent with the city’s economic growth. If the biennial is a collection of images, and the images are visual aids to the underlying economic logic of the city, then the exhibition format is a naturally occurring phenomenon that is an interface between the underlying visual systems and the art objects. It is not an art installation or</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city) and private space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the private collection of a museum). We have our ideals (on both sides of the Atlantic), but also our practicalities (the way in which art is made, and the money that is made, as well as the culture that is produced by it). In the context of the curatorial push, the private and the cultural, the two are tools – not ends – but means to an end.  And I think that there is a sense of ‘what if?’ that is being contemplated, or well, planned, by curators and artists themselves. A kind of ‘what if?’ that is being worked backwards. That is, there is a possibility that the curatorial push could backfire, causing harm.  I think that there is a danger in trying to pigeonhole the curatorial push into neat categories, or treating it as a discrete event, since the different elements that</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city) and private (in the sense of the Granby Four’s joint venture with the Performing Arts Centre, not the West Village Museum). The private aspect is a strange one, but the public is strange too. What I really love about the curatorial move is that it allows us to be open to new ideas, to be open to new ways of organising our experience of the city. The curatorial move is to take something that is public and making it private – a concept that I invented – and making it work in a completely different way. This is what I do with curatorial statements: they’re not meant to connect with people, or make people feel like they’re part of a group, but they’re actually quite ordinary and commonplace, and we should be able to make them connect with something more. The interesting thing about the curatorial statement is that it has a kind of ‘what if’ aspect to it</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city) and private space (in the sense of the Museum of Modern Art, not the National Theatre). It’s very difficult to define either the city or the museum in this sort of binary, binary way. The curatorial statement is a statement of commonality, but the subtle difference between the city and the museum is much more difficult to measure. The curatorial gesture is a statement of presence. This has always been the case, and I think that we’re all aware of it. What we do with exhibitions, whether it’s the Oxford and New York Museums, or the Bibliothèque Nationale in Paris, or the Royal Library in London, is to tell a story, and the question is what kind of story that is.  And so the curatorial statement can be read as a series of discrete propositions, and the micro-proposition, the question that the Biennale can and must address, is</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city) and private, intimate (the Oxford English, two-hour workshop, with readings, guided exhibitions, and performances), and sometimes (like the Oxford English) includes readings and even private reading groups.  So this is a potential delivery mechanism.  At the Liverpool Biennial, for example, the curatorial language that we use is a combination of public and private. I think that for the next phase of the plan, I believe that it would be interesting to do a public programme of […] reading groups in the city.  Reading groups at the Oxford English? Sounds radical, but I don’t want to do that. I want to read the whole thing as a reading group, with readings from various texts, and with readings from various places, in the public and the private, in and outside the Biennial. I don’t think that would be appropriate, and neither would I. I’m interested in what</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city) and private (in the sense of the Arsenale, not just the Italian or American arts institutions). It’s not just the public space; it’s about to museums, at a certain point going beyond that. We have to find a way to talk about the historical curatorial approach, which is quite different to the way in which we are approaching it now. The curatorial move towards history is a historical one, and the curatorial decision to put something into historical context is an important one. It not only establishes the historical relationship between the art form and the site, but it also establishes the relationship between artist and audience. Whereas the curatorial turn today is much more dependent on a site plan, a development budget and developer’s wishes, and the emphasis is on the artifice of control and manipulation that is being added to the city. For instance, in New York, there is the incredible amount of development that is happening in the borough of Manhattan, which</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city) and private collection (in the sense of the Edmund Hawkins Collection, not the British Library or the Tate). So if we want to capture the current complexity of the city, we have to know where the collections are at the same time. And so we have collections in different contexts: the collection of the British Library at the moment of its formation, the collection of the British Museum, and the collection of the American Museum. And so the curatorial push comes from different places, and so the exhibition itself, the act of entering a building, and the interaction between the different collections. And I think this is very much part of the dynamic of the new curatorial language: if the curatorial push comes from the same place as the collection, that is the collection’s point of intersection.  And so the curatorial push is a real-life, lived-in interaction between collections, and it is the collection that makes the city. It does not come from the collection of</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city) and private (in the sense of the Granby Four’s, not necessarily the  	City Council). It’s not clear to me that the curatorial move is complete, but it certainly indicates an intention to make it visible in different ways. There are other curatorial moves too, like the Italian pavilion that opened last year, or the one in the summer of 2017, when Liverpool and New York were chosen. But these two pavilions, and the curatorial gesture, indicated a different direction. They were there to serve different sorts of audiences, and an intention to be visible even to those who couldn’t afford tickets to the main programme.  It’s as if the new curator, someone experienced and clever, someone with a different kind of curatorial language, had a go at naming some of the acts, having a go at naming some of the pleasures.  The pavilion and the well-publicised public programme</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA.  In the spring of 2017, the workshop was selected for the permanent collection of the British Library.  And now the curatorial push: the main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan,  the Oxford and New York Museums, the future is now, I think, 2016. What has already happened  The main exhibition venue for the next phase of the curatorial plan, I think, is 2016.  And the curatorial push is on. I’m not sure where this exhibition will come from, or whether it will be organised in parallel to the main event, but I’m convinced that it’s important that it comes from different angles. The curatorial language that we use is a combination of public space (in the sense of the National Theatre’s, not the Whittier Fellowship, National Theatre, I think, and not just the city) and private (in the sense that it’s possible to be in the presence of both public and private art, but the presence of the former in the latter). What I’ve learnt over the past years is that it’s useful to insist that we have a conversation about a certain kind of art - that it’s not just a collection of photographs. We’re both aware of the fact that the curatorial language we use is somewhat arbitrary: it doesn’t really map onto actual events. So we use it in a very political way: we use it to invite in certain artists, artists that we think are citizens of this world, and we use it to invite in others we think are not. I think that idea – the use of physical space in a political way, the use of language – is really interesting.  And it’s this use of physical space that’s being challenged in the context of the Biennale.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of
    <text>presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of the biennial from its Greek roots as a contest for appearances, or ‘show-me-how’, to an introduction that ‘reveals’ the most dominant form of art forms in the world. This epiphany occurs when we recognise the similarities between the forms of art, which emerge as a consequence of converging information technologies, and the images of the worlds that are projected onto screens and into virtual reality. By ‘seeing stars’, these images are seen as images of the future, where ‘things that can happen now’ take form.[3] As technology advances, so too does the capacity for art and artist to be made, and for art to influence and be shaped by the capacities of technology. The popularity of the image-collage as a form of cultural artefactry goes hand in hand with this development, and is perhaps an artefact of the contradictions inherent in the contemporary condition – inherent in the experience of both the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of the modern biennial, the emergence of the museum as an archival medium, and the emergence of the biennial as a curatorial device. In these pages, she argues that modern biennials emerged through the process of ‘episodic ‘; ‘temporal ’; and ‘matter’. These terms were coined by and were part of a discourse that followed the publication of Carol Christov-Bakargiev’s seminal work, The End of the Metropolis, published in 1974. [3] Italo Calvino in his cultural monologues of the twentieth century (1966–78) presents a catalogue of the objects that he claims have been ‘gathered together from various parts of the globe’ – a gathering of seemingly disparate things. But what makes these objects stand out is that they are gathered together in such a way as to be remembered, arranged, and finally ,together, made up. This is not</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of ‘the biennial’ as a concept and its development from its proto-episodic historical context of newspaper and magazine circulation in the late nineteenth century to the present. ‘The biennial is a series of coinciding periodic exhibitions that assumes a continuous relationship over time, with each showing a different part of the museum’s permanent collection.’[3] By the latter part of the twentieth century, biennials were widely seen as a valuable exhibitionary form, a fact that was exploited by curators intent on showcasing their collections at a rapid pace, as a way to reveal hidden collections or bolster curatorial claims, as well as entertaining an audience. [4] As Nicholas Rankin observes, ‘The biennial is, in the last analysis, a museum, and its collections are, by implication, museum collections’. [5] This observation is perhaps to be expected in the era of the biennial, whose curatorial</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of the biennial as a project of cultural circulation in the first instance, and then, through a critical reading of the biennial itself, proposes several predicates of contemporaneity, including the gathering of cultural material at a spatial and temporal scale, the production of ‘permanent representations of things’ through the circulation of cultural artefacts, and the simultaneous circulation of different kinds of representation.[3] These ideas are further developed in Christov-Bakargiev’s influential work  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1989). [4] The relationship between biennials and the contemporaneity of various kinds of art, literature, and cultural practice is further developed in Sue Bell Yank’s (2009) and Susanne Kübler-Ross’s (2017) works, where biennials establish a kind of persistent interlocution within and between contemporary art practice and literary and artistic practice. [5] See,</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of the biennial from its medieval form of the ‘Roman Visitor’ to a more contemporary form in which the term is often used synonymously (cf. also: ‘Italian Museum’). There is some confusion about what the Italian Museum is, what it represents, and who is supposed to be in it. [3] We know this because the Biennale gave away a hard-to-decipher 2014 edition of its print publication, Notteil-Wittenberg erständige Kunsthal Nachrichten (The New Urban Future), to a lucky few invited to the closed-to-the-press 2015 edition of the journal. The editors of the journal apparently did not read the article, which was published in the 2014 edition of NOTTEIL-WITTENBERG, or the 2015 edition of that same journal. In these two publications, the editors criticise a move towards sustainable development that comes as little surprise to</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of the biennial as a cultural form, drawing on the late nineteenth-century precursors of the modern museum and the modern academy. In her account, ‘the biennial became a thing when, in Paris, the semaine de Paris (the leading biennale publication) announced the staging of the Venice Biennale, which would come to define the biennial’. In time, it became a cultural locus of sorts, a place for artists to be present in a public context, but also a media device that would continually let artists and artisans escape into the collective.‘The Biennial as a Form’,  	Its Art Documents, presents a history of the biennial, drawing on archival materials, including articles from the Nineteenth Century, that attempt to make sense of the contemporary phenomenon of the biennial. Christov-Bakargiev traces the forms of the biennial from the nineteenth century to the present, from the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of the biennial as a cultural phenomenon. In the late sixties and early seventies, the biennial was one of the most widely distributed forms of the market: bookshelvesurpassed bookshops in their girdle. The biennial offered a convenient outlet for artistic activity: in the natural life of art’s market, the artist’s market, the biennial had a place second only to the bookshop. In the bookshop, bookshelves were always full. In the biennial, the bookshop becomes an island in itself. 	[3] As a term, ‘biennial’ refers to a specific point in a timeline that begins with the Venice Biennale. In contemporary parlance, it has come to stand for ‘the art biennale’. 	[4] The term is frequently used in connection with exhibitions of new art, but as Biennale expert Tristan Clark reminds us</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of the biennial from its medieval formalism and its eventual appropriation by museums, seeking to show how the biennial form entered the mass cultural imagination of the twentieth century. In A Cultural Critique of Modernity (1997), she shows how the biennial emerged as a form of anti-civilisation. In Running to Catch a Smile (2002), photographer Rami El Samahy captures the moment when biennials emerged as a mode of transport in the Arab World, first in Egypt and then in the occupied territories of Israel. In the wake of these works, and with the complicity of Western governments and financial institutions, biennials – organisations that claim to provide a public experience of art in a relational way – emerged as a prop in geopolitical struggles. During the nineties and early aughts, biennials did not receive the sustained public or critical attention they merit, but thanks to investigative reporting by journalists, critical theory and numerous other disciplines, they began to receive critical consideration. [</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of the biennial as a cultural form – a prelude to what she calls the ‘metaphor of the century’ – and the subsequent ‘episodic’ – a broad sense of time following an initial phase of historical reference. In the late sixties and early seventies, the biennial became the largest cultural phenomenon of the world, and later the most important, in that it established the biennial as an institutional form, marking the beginnings of a new cultural logic. [3] The popularity of the biennial grew from the specific cultural logic of the era: the cultural logic of the late seventies and early eighties, particularly the cultural logic of the United Fruit Company and the London Science Museum. In the image above, biennials of the era are represented by stylised images of connected points in time (artists, writers, collectors, students), often in the form of a ‘trail’ or a ‘chain of objects</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and their family members. 	I started by making a digital collage of the images. I then augmented these collages with drawings and coloured prints of the same images, using the same techniques as for photographic prints. My intention was to create a virtual theatre where people could come and view the collage, print and image collection in real time, creating a hybrid performance of printed texts and images.[1] In  	Postmodernism and Material Culture (1993), Carol Christov-Bakargiev explores the philosophical underpinnings of  	Postmodernism and her work as a critical theorist. In the years since that publication, Christov-Bakargiev has become an important figure in critical theory, and her understanding of the cultural logic underpinning modernity has been central to numerous recent texts on the subject. [2] In the formative years of the biennial, Christov-Bakargiev traces the metaphoric emergence of the biennial from its Greek roots in  	Platonic Solitude to its modern incarnation as ‘the Philharmage’ at Venice’s Giardini. She also offers a genealogical sketch of the movement of material objects from the city of the soul into the city of the body, from the biennial to the museum, and from the biennial to the social. [3] André Malraux, in his work  	Deux Mondiales 	(1994), poses the question: what is meant by the ‘modern’ in the current biennial? In the twentieth century, material culture marked a transition from the realm of the atom to that of the ecosystem, from pre-industrial to postindustrial, from nomadic to integrated economies. Malraux focuses on the major cultural centres of the biennial’s growth, but he also examines lesser-known but equally important sub-regions. The</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will
    <text>will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the CLT, which in turn will own and manage the businesses, housing and infrastructure that will be built on the site. Under the proposal, the CLT and the community become one and the same. Under the proposal, the CLT and the community become one and the same.As part of the initiative, the City Council will consider the proposal, with a recommendation to proceed with construction. The City will contribute 25% of the project costs with a goal of completely funding the project through private investment. A public consultation will be held to address any concerns or questions regarding the proposal. The development of the CLT and the CDB will be carried out in phases over three years. The development of the CLT and the CDB will be carried out in phases over three years. Phase one will see the establishment of a CLT, with the community’s input, and a CLT strategic plan formulated with input from the community. The phase two design will see the establishment</text>
    <text>will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the CLT will own the CLT will own the CLT will own … 	20% of the total voting rights. The CLT will be managed by a board of directors appointed by the Mayor and specified by the CLT. These directors will have … 	20% equity in the CLT and will have … more or less absolute … control over the CLT’s spending, … more or less absolute … control over the CLT’s revenue, and so forth.20   	The proposal has been in development for some years now, and it should be noted that in the current financial crisis, with substantial state funding cut, the state of California is desperate to accelerate the project. In an attempt to address this crisis, the state legislature has already appropriated some $350 million dollars for the project. Whether the state legislature will act on this money itself, or if it will merely accelerate the project’s implementation, remains to be seen.</text>
    <text>will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the CLT, while the commercial sector will be supervised by a non-profit organization (NGO). The NGRO will own and manage the business (and its assets) while the NGRT will own and manage the land or buildings. While the objectives of the initiative may seem noble, the implementation of this unique proposal inevitably raises difficult choices and calls for compromises. For example, the NGRO may wish to lease the land or buildings to an NGRT or a CLT, but it may be difficult to convince the city to make the appropriate improvements to the land or buildings, especially since the NGRO is an urban developer and a well-known land-grabber. The choice may be either to expand the current infrastructure, such as the existing bus rapid transit system, or create innovative ways to work with the land and buildings in an environmentally beneficial way, such as co-opting existing commercial and industrial buildings or creating cooperative […] [more] ​ </text>
    <text>will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the CLT, providing services including legal, financial and human resources for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the development of the ‘KeyArena Project’ in the city.1. · Analysis of Arena/Millionaire's Row's Impact on Seattle’s Near Westside and Beyond by West Seattle’s Community Land Trust (CLT). [2] Download this article as PDFEvan WilliamsEvan Williams is an architect and urbanist. He works as an architect for a number of large commercial and institutional real estate firms in Seattle and is currently Director of Construction Services for West Seattle’s Millennium Development Corporation (MDC). He has worked with the Seattle Department of Transportation (SDOT) on the development of a new master plan for West Seattle, which will include an extension of the West Seattle Ferry Terminal into the future LRT corridor and the reconstruction of Westlake Station. He is also co</text>
    <text>will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the CLT will own and manage the land or buildings, creating a shared commonwealth of shared use and public use. In the proposal, the public sector is clearly differentiated from the private sector. The public sector generally has rights and responsibilities that are different from those of the entrepreneur or developer. The CLT will have the authority and responsibilities of a CLT, but will not necessarily share the rights and privileges of a CLT. The CLT will have to negotiate with the developer and obtain the developer’s consent to create a CLT. There are several ways in which the community can contribute to the success of the initiative: offer financial support (cash or property), establish an entity to manage the land (a CLT may be created) or create an existing non profit entity (AECE) to jointly manage the land and buildings. The AECE will have rights and responsibilities similar to those of a CLT, but will be accountable to the public through a public</text>
    <text>will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the development of the CLT, while the public sector will provide services and cooperate in various ways to support the CLT’s activities. The proposal calls for the establishment of a Community Land Trust (CLT) to own and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the development of the CLT, while the public sector will provide services and cooperate in various ways to support the CLT’s activities.  [2] European Community (2007–2013); Community Land Trusts (2014–2019); National Public Private Partnerships (in Oakland, California, and in Rotterdam, Netherlands); REITs and Alternative Property Markets (in Toronto and Amsterdam); Community Land Trusts International (CLT International) (2014–present); REITs and Next City (in New York and London); REITs and Research Cities (in Dublin and Belfast); Community Land Trust Network (</text>
    <text>will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the CLT, while the public corporations (including local governments) will be invited to join the CLRT’s cooperative. In addition to the cooperative’s direct cooperative board, citizens will have the right to form a collective board of directors.  [2] A timeline of events connected with the Black Lives Matter movement is presented in chronological order. The Black Lives Matter project began in 2014 when three Minneapolis women, including one who is a co-founder of Black Lives Matter, shared their experiences as police officers with the local media. Since then, activists from the local community have asked for a full-scale investigation of how Minneapolis police deal with people who are in the street and documenting incidents using social media. In March 2018, a grand jury declined to indict the officers involved in the 2014 shooting of Jamar Clark, an African-American man in Minneapolis. In June 2018, a federal civil rights lawsuit was filed against the city and five officers, alleging that the shooting</text>
    <text>will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the CLT will own the CLT will own …  [more]The proposal calls for the establishment of a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the CLT will own the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for</text>
    <text>will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the CLT will own the CLT will own the CLT will own the building or buildings. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the entire site, with responsibility for maintenance and improvement passing to the CLT. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the site and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the entire site, with responsibility for maintenance and improvement passing to the CLT. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. (JH: ‘This hybrid model ensures that the land or buildings remain privately owned and controlled and that the CLT can access all of the revenue generated by the site – a critical first step in the process’). The proposal also establishes a public consultative commission to offer suggestions and report</text>
    <text>will be curated through the initiative’s materials, objects and installations.]The proposal  [1] is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build 'independent' from the city. The proposal calls for the establishment of a community development bank (CDB), a publicly funded entity that will create and manage partnerships to address specific needs of the community. The CDB will be responsible for … [more] The proposal is to create a mini-institution that responds to the commercial and financial sectors of the city. What makes this initiative unique is that it seeks to build a Community Land Trust (CLT). A CLT is a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. The CLT will own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the CLT, creating a new entity distinct from the existing entity. Under the existing CLT, the CLT would own and manage the land or buildings and provide legal protection for the community. Under the proposal, the CLT will own and manage the new entity, creating a new entity distinct from the existing entity. The CLT will be a hybrid public and private partnership established to jointly develop and manage a parcel of land or buildings in the vicinity of a major transit hub. It will be a publicly owned entity, sharing in the benefits of the hub’s commercial and residential development with the residents of the surrounding neighbourhood. It will also draw on the local community for resources, attract businesses and provide them with public facilities and benefits, and coordinate activities with other local stakeholders. The CLT will draw on the local community for resources, attract businesses and provide them with public facilities and benefits, and coordinate activities with other local stakeholders.  [2] National Community Land Trust Network</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element
    <text>will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is unerring in its invocation of the familiar, almost romanticised senses of biological difference and cultural difference. But what makes the present so perversely attractive is the element that it conceals: the element that causes genital herpes, or any other sexually transmitted infection. Public perceptions of the good in institutionalised forms of power are formed through the production of high-quality images of the bad, so when those images are made scarce or otherwise restricted, the public is encouraged to seek them out and make them visible. That element of supply is what Gabor calls the parasitic element. In the twentieth-century sense, we might call it modernity 2.0.Modernity 2.0 is a global process of dismantling national taboos and mobilising the collective in the production of planetary consumption. It begins with the production of consent (or more accurately, the production of shame) through the production of consenting adults in culturally acceptable dress, activities and formats being socially normalized in a given</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is echoed in a nineteenth-century English manual for the treatment of gonorrhoea:There is a second and more fatal kind of gonorrhoea, which is contracted by touching the infected parts of another person. It is spread by contact with the bodily fluids of another person who has contracted the disease; it is contracted by coughing or sneezing, and through bodily contact with objects that have the virus.‘The second kind of gonorrhoea’, the text continues, is contracted by touching the infected genitals of another person. It is fatal unless treated with careful medical attention.’The doctor who contracts it should immediately contact the National Vaccine Information Center and report the finding to the local authorities. The local authorities will investigate the finding and, if appropriate, may order the doctor’s prosecution’, which would remove the parasite from the body and put an end to the threat.Gabor’s ideas were echoed</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is strikingly similar to what we understand about the human body from modern biology. In fact, the two elements that we associate with heterosexual and homosexual behaviour are actually quite distinct. Both chlamydia and genital herpes can be cured, but the former requires two to four years in the hospital and can only be cured with a cure, while the latter requires six to eight months in the hospital and can be cured with a few months in the clinic. A cure would render homosexual acts non-consensual, but Gabor’s position is that homosexual acts are intrinsically ‘wrong’ and cannot be reformed through surgery. So, while the Anglo-Saxon tradition of biomedical research and therapeutic interventions seeks to repair or alter a given behaviour in order to promote healthier individuals, we can understand Gabor’s position as one in which radical change is needed. It is a radical change that would render medically-acquired human behaviour non-pathological, but it is also essential</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is no exaggeration. The elements are present in identical proportions in human semen and female foetus serum, and are present in the seminal vesicles and in the covering of the female genital organs. The reason why the female genital organs are present in the novel, and not in earlier translations of the Greek or Latin, is that the ancients, being scientists, realised that they could not understand the physical world without understanding the abstract ideas underlying the physical world – concepts like space, time, causation and so on. So the ancient Greeks knew more about causality and ideology than we do today, and so they used these ideas to tell stories that were more accessible to our reason and human capacity. Aristotle, for example, through what is now called his Theaetye Ethics, discusses how the Athenians, having defeated a satrap named Onomasticon, had come to power by claiming that their actions had been prompted by a divine revelation. And there is much more in there</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is long and convoluted, so that it is not possible to digest it straightforwardly. Nevertheless, he offers a striking analogy:When the female genital tract is inflamed and infected, the seminal vesicles burst open and the ejaculate reached the cervical canal.’[6] The sexual act is initiated by the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. However, since the element that causes chlamydia and genital herpes is present in abundance, the eruption of the seminal vesicles and discharge of the ejaculate reach the entire cervical canal.’[7] In other words, the sexual act initiated by the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is mediated by a combination of both, although it is initiated by the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes.’[8] If this is the case, then the remaining part of the equation – the remaining element that causes</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is short and sweet: there is a nutrient deficiency in the female genital tract that results in the manifestation of both conditions. From that source of imbalance can be inferred that the female gender is inherently promiscuous and promiscuous, and that male sexual differentiation is therefore inevitable. But there is another, more fundamental and more pervasive factor that undermines both halves of the equation: the element that causes human immunodeficiency virus (HIV) and the element that causes HIVA. The HAV-1 gene encodes for the element glycoprotein IV, which stands for 'Inhibitor of Growth Factor-1′. Inhibitors of growth factors are polypeptides that block the action of certain substances, usually substances that are structurally related to growth (i.e. proteins) – usually drugs – in the body. Glycoproteins are building blocks of the body that mediate certain processes. When the body lacks the element required for the actions of</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is longwinded and ambiguous, and his position on the element that causes prostatitis is even more so. As we shall see, the notion of life itself is permeated with elements of both protozoa and man-animal. But what exactly is life? Is it merely the vegetative formation of space and time as a commodity (a ‘gift of nature’) or is it the consummation of a social act? If it is a consummation, then what sort of life is it? If it is a ‘gift of nature’, then what sort of life is it?If, in turn, the notion of life is constituted by and dependent on the circulation of commodities (and the consummation of a given social act), then what sort of life is it? If it is a gift of nature, then what sort of life is it?If, in turn, the notion of life is constituted by and</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is characteristic of his thinking at this point in time. Although the term does not appear in the medical literature at this time, it is clear that in the nineteenth century and beyond a great deal of linguistic and cultural work was done to try to convince people that having certain bodily parts (including the vulva) was a very good thing, while denying the very real and pervasive effects of environmental degradation, which was often explicitly promoted as a cure. A good deal of this work was done through print, but the online presence of texts was an important addition as well. Having the Vorticist’s work on the cover of your book does not make you a champion of biocentrism, but it does lend weight to the idea that the vulva is a particularly threatening area, and that the authorities – including the medical authorities – are poorly placed to intervene in such a way as to prevent or correct the damage done.Even though the Vorticist’s ideas about</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is echoed in a nineteenth-century English physician’s essay that came to be known as the Gervais Case. In Jean Pierre Galine’s Diagnostic and Statistical Manual of 1928, the synonym ‘episodic’ is used four times, once in reference to the occurrence of two conditions synonymously: a common cold and a sore throat. The concept of an element is reintroduced throughout the text, and ‘the microscopic element … is placed at the centre of the organism’s phases of life’.17 The introduction of the word ‘element’ into the English language portal Word of the New World (1846) prompts a parallel history that includes the discovery of the elements by German anatomist Herman Goethe, whose translation of the Greek tragedy The Fall of Troy into German provided the basis for early in-depth investigations of the elements of the human body.18 During the nineteenth century, anatomists</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by Gabor’s wife, Inga. The couple’s first public engagement on the subject of gynaecology was in the journal English Journal of Surgery (1839–1846), in an issue devoted to the surgery of the female genital organs. In that issue, Gabor spoke of the ‘parasitic element’ in the body, which could not be allowed to survive, and which was to be eradicated through surgery. He concluded by speculating that there were two other human elements to be eradicated: the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes. If both were eliminated, the other element would have to be suppressed in order to permit the eradication of the parasitic element. In that case, the argument went, the other element would have to be present in sufficient quantities in order to influence the development of the sexual act.Gabor’s description of the element that causes chlamydia and the element that causes genital herpes is drawn directly from a medical textbook published in 1864. In that year, a group of British anatomists published an edition of their textbook The Anatomy of a Roman Scalp published a full century earlier. The 1864 edition of The Anatomy of a Roman Scalp included a chapter on the element that causes chlamydia, which the British Medical Journal had defined as the extracellular matrix of the human body (with the epithelial and dermal parts taken from the Egyptian pharaoh Seti I). The extracellular matrix was defined as the junction of two or more material parts; it was regarded as the outermost layer of the body and thus a sufficient constituent part of the body’s epithelial outer layer. In other words, the body’s extracellular matrix was viewed as both living and immortal. The defining feature of Gabor’s work is the consummation of the element’s existence in a material form</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Bi
    <text>presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs France was a partner company of the Institut National de Barcelona, Barcelona.The Biennaleurs Netherlands was founded in 1780 by the Englishman John Sydenham, and the Biennaleurs Belgium was founded in 1864 by the Frenchwoman Honoré Daumier. Both companies were established to carry on the tradition of the first Venice Biennale, held in the year before, which had begun in Amsterdam. The name Biennaleurs was coined later that year in Le Corbusier’s Invisible Cities, published some years earlier.André Bretonnier, The Architecture of Luxury, 1977. Centre stage, Paris. Courtesy of the Biennaleurs.All three companies were established in the early twentieth century, with an emphasis on cultural activities. Bretonnier refers to the great wave of Italian and French composers who arrived in the U.S. during the late nineteenth century: Pietro Alfieri, Paul McCarthy,</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a director of the U.S. National Endowment for the Arts. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a director of the Tate Britain. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a director of the Aarhus Cultural Foundation. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a director of the U.S. National Endowment for the Arts.The Biennaleurs Belgium, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennaleurs. The Biennaleurs Belgium, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennaleurs.The Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennaleurs.The Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennaleurs.The Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennaleurs.The Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennaleurs.The Biennaleurs, 2012</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the Belgian firm Wilhelmina. ICA was a founding partner of the Biennaleurs Spain, and the Biennaleurs Belgium was a founding partner of the Biennaleurs Belgium. Together, these entities funded the exhibition from its inception in 1968 to its closure in 1991.The Biennaleurs Belgium was founded in 1884 by William Wilhelmina and Georges Pompidou. It closed in 1925. The Biennaleurs Netherlands opened in 1928 by Cornelis &quot;Chip&quot; Clemence (later Chip Ungar), who was then the managing director of the European Capital of Culture Company. The Biennaleurs Belgium also sponsored the performances by the artistes in the company. In recent years, the Biennaleurs has promoted the work of the curators at the Tate Modern and the U.S. National Portrait Gallery, and commissioned the work of the curator at the U.S. Naval</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a director of the Biennaleurs Spain was a director of the Biennaleurs Italy was a director of the Biennaleurs Brazil was a director of the Biennaleurs Turkey was a director of the Biennaleurs France was a director of the Biennaleurs Qatar was a director of the Al Ain Museum of Art and Architecture. The Biennaleurs UK was a director of the Biennaleurs Egypt was a director of the Al-Ahly Museum of Modern Art, Cairo.The Biennaleurs Netherlands was established in 2003 and has a permanent exhibition programme. It is a multidisciplinary cultural centre with a curatorial focus on the Middle East and North Africa. It is the only biennale to have its programme centered around its own language, Arabic. The Biennaleurs is the only biennale to have its programme based in the Netherlands. The Biennaleurs programme in the UK is now focused on the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a member of the Board of the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology), and the Biennaleurs Belgium had a membership in the FACT. The Biennaleurs Netherlands had a membership in the Artistic Council of the U.S. National Endowment for the Arts. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a member of the Board of the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology), and the Biennaleurs Belgium had a membership in the FACT.The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a member of the Board of the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology), and the Biennaleurs Belgium was a member of the Board of the World Foundation.The Biennaleurs Belgium was a founding partner of the Biennaleurs, the exclusive international partner of the Biennaleurs, the main international partner of the Biennaleurs, the joint venture of the city’s cultural institutions, and</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a member of the art collective Opus, which was a director and curator of the Venice Biennale, and was a curator of the Egyptian and Armenian Centres in London and Berlin. The Biennaleurs Belgium operated out of London.The Biennaleurs Belgium was a multi-institutional group of curators, art collectors, art dealers and curators. It was also a network for exchange between curators, art dealers and collectors, researchers and art students, art-utopians, art-policy makers and art-service providers. The group commissioned, produced and directed several exhibitions, including the Netherlands, Germany, New York and Paris; toured North Africa and Europe; and organised numerous other events.The Biennaleurs Belgium organised the Venice Biennale through its own curatorial school, the Curator Graduate School (Kampala School of Art, University of K. South Africa), affiliated with the K.K. Arts Centre at the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of L.A. County Museum of Art, Los Angeles. The Biennaleurs Belgium is a publicly traded company with offices in New York and London. The Biennaleurs Netherlands is a publicly traded company with offices in Gdansk, Poland. The company website boasts that the ventures in the Biennaleurs and Biennaleurs Belgium are the &quot;most liquid, liquid and economically viable&quot; of their kind. 	In 2012, the Biennaleurs opened the Venice Biennale, the largest and most prestigious of its kind. The Biennaleurs opened in 2013 with a two-day, ‘only in Europe’ event, and continued to expand it with ‘only in Europe’ events in 2014. The Venice Biennale’s annual budget is more than $20 million. The main tourist draw is the opportunity to see the buildings on a first-come, first-serve basis.</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a member of the Board of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs Netherlands had a regional office in Ghent, Belgium.The Biennaleurs Belgium was a multi-disciplinary group of art and cultural organizations founded in 2014. The group has its headquarters in Ghent, Belgium. The Biennaleurs Netherlands, Belgium, and the Biennaleurs Belgium operate in different parts of Europe and North America. The Biennaleurs Belgium website describes the group as follows: &quot;Working in partnership with the U.S. National Endowment for the Arts (NEA), the Biennaleurs is an international, multi-disciplinary art and cultural organization. It is the largest holder of international cultural rights in the United States and Europe, with institutions in over 50 countries. Formed in 2014, the Biennaleurs is a global public-private partnership founded on mutual trust and based on the shared conviction that art should</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs Spain was a co-investor in the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Italy was a partner company of the Museo del Passato, Rome. The Biennaleurs Belgium was a co-investor in the U.S. Cultural Travelers Fund, a Woodbridge-based non-profit arts-focused company established to support the exploration, production and promotion of cultural experiences by providing access to cultural sites and culture through cultural exchange and tourism. In 2016, the Biennaleurs closed its Venice office and announced that it would establish a regional office in Recife.The Biennaleurs’ role in the U.S. is a hybrid one. It is possible that the Biennaleurs would direct a biennial, but their institutional roles in Venice and the Biennaleurs would differ. Instead, they would collaborate with the Biennaleurs in their respective regions and offer innovative new perspectives on the city.</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the UPenn PhD in Art and Design programme; a joint project with UDAC (Universidad de Barcelona) and the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology). The exhibition was curated by Guillermo Vitale (Italy) and Irene Hofmann (Germany).The second Venice Biennale was organised by the Biennaleurs (Dutch and Belgian), and the Spanish Cultural Administrador (Catalunya) and the Italian Cultural Administrador (Milan). It organized with the cooperation of the Commissiono de Estatísticales, Instituto de Culturación (Spain). The Biennaleurs and the Biennaleurs Belgium were members of the Curatorial Faculty at the U.S. University, respectively; the Biennaleurs Belgium was a partner company of the U.S. Museum for Contemporary Art. The Biennaleurs Netherlands was a partner company of the Museo de Arte Contempora, Barcelona. The Biennaleurs Belgium, along with the U.S. Cultural Administrador, Milan and Liverpool, were members of the Royal Academy of Arts. The Biennaleurs' Italy was a partner company of the Renaissance Foundation. The Biennaleurs were also members of the Royal Academy of Arts, London. The Biennaleurs Belgium, Venice and Liverpool were members of the Arts Council; the Arts Council Liverpool was a partner company of the Aarhus Art Foundation. The Biennaleurs were also members of the Royal Academy of Arts, London. The Biennaleurs, Venice and Liverpool were members of the Royal Academy of Arts, London. The Biennaleurs, Venice and Liverpool, were also members of the Royal Academy of Arts, London. The Biennaleurs, Venice and Liverpool were also members of the Royal Academy of Arts, London. The Biennaleurs, Venice and Liverpool, were also members of the Royal Academy of Arts, London. The Bienn</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’ feel to them, where the commercial arts institutions that they support are often caricatures. However, this kind of fetishising is becoming increasingly rare, and the kind of self-criticism that biennials are facing is a kind of a surrender to the new economic order that is developing in the UK. It is certainly possible that the kind of critical self-awareness that biennials are experiencing right now is a kind of ‘worrying of the cultural commodity’. It is certainly possible that the kind of critical self-awareness that artists and artists’ organisations are demanding of each other is a kind of ‘crisis of the cultural commodity’. But, as biennials become more and more commercialised, and the number of biennials shrinks, the kind of critical self-awareness that artists and arts organisations are demanding of one another is a kind of a surrender to the new economic order that is developing in the UK. It is certainly possible that the</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’ sensibility, or at least for the art world to assign a similar sensibility to artworks exhibited in other art forms. Therefore, while the contemporary biennial may or may not be a ‘transnational’ institution, it is certainly true that it is intimately tied to the market, and its curatorial legacies are likely to be influenced by the activities of the financial industry. Biennials are, of course, themselves internationally visible, and have been since the mid-nineteenth century. This is mainly due to the American curatorial tradition, which sees the biennial as a major exhibitionary form, and the museum as a major exhibitionary platform. The biennial has become, posthumously, a major exhibitionary form, and is now the largest internationally recurring exhibitionary form. Its ubiquity has made it a locus of influence for the art world. It is not surprising, then, that biennials have become important for the cultural wellbeing of their localised settings</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’ feel to them, where the artworks are taken out of commission and placed in museums, and then sold again, periodically replacing the once-abandoned buildings with modernist office and mixed uses developments. This kind of repetition is in fact an asset for a biennial, as it breaks up the monotony of work and allows the artworks to breathe. But in the sense of the contemporary art market, it is also a hindrance. The modern biennial must find a way to meet the contemporary art market, or it will lose its contemporary quality. This is an art form, and it must change.In the 1980s and 1990s, there was a big push to modernise the biennial, and many curators and arts administrators were given a mandate to do something with the ageing, industrial artefacts that were a constant in the biennial. Naturally, this came with a price, as biennials became more and more institutionalised. But the mandate to modernise came</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’ feel to them, where the contemporary art market is concerned. This is especially true of works from the Venice Biennale that are displayed at the Tate Britain and the Whitney Museum of American Art. 	The biennial must have a long-term strategy in mind, because it is the only way in which the art world will experience the art once it has been made. As biennials become more and more diverse in their form, less and less is the traditional biennial, with works shown at different times, showing a range of styles and in different places. As biennials become more and more international in their exhibitionary format, their curatorial agenda becomes more diverse too. I propose that the biennial should be an art form that is global in its composition, most like  	the  	World Art Biennale, but different. Its primary mission should be to the extent that it is relevant to the globalised urbanisation process, and to the extent that it</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’ sub-genre, where artists can play it safe and project their artistic potentialities into a dominant position in the region. Yet the fact that the biennial is a ‘public exhibition’ means that it is visible to thousands of people in a city, and thus is an ideal platform on which to project your art. As Oyster Bay Arts Collective member Mamta Lakhvi said: In my opinion, the biennial is the new art market. It is a unique format that lends itself to multiple readings and uses, and is a potential ground for new forms of artistic production. However, given the choice, I tend to engage with the biennial in a semi-structured way, choosing key works that stand out in the current popular discourse and art’s current agenda. I place them in a series of works that blend art, activism, and ecology, and then ask: what does art do today?  	The biennial is a global phenomenon that affects not only</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’ feel to them, where the artworks are imported directly from other art worlds. This is particularly the case in cities such as Liverpool, where the biennial is housed and funded by the Biennale Board. However, it is crucial that artists and arts organisations take the opportunity to develop alternative cultural models in their area, and to work with local authorities on the development of such models, so that biennials do not become enmeshed in the politics of commercial art forms, or reliant on funders for their artistic practices.  [1] See http://www.biennaleofmind.org/. Accessed: 2 August 2017.  [2] See http://www.biennaleofmind.org/index.php?fuseaction=artists&amp;section=artists&amp;file=artists. Accessed: 2 August 2017.  [3] See http://www.biennaleofmind.org/index.php?fuseaction=artists</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’ feel to them, where the commercial gallery experiences a ‘metainterface’. However, the biennial as art form is not a one-size-fits-all solution to the inevitable commercial gallery problems, and art biennials have demonstrated that they are capable of developing creative solutions to their predicaments. This shows in the biennial’s mission statement, which is vague and ambiguous, but clearly states that it is an art form: ‘We are artists, not commercial agents. We do not seek to proselytize or establish a “church” with our work. Our work may be in “marketing materials”, but it is also a means to an end – a political action, an education action, or a “service action”.’4 Art biennials have generally adopted different approaches to market elements of their work, or employed non-commercial means to achieve their ends. For example, the Liverpool Bi</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’ sensibility, where the local artists take the lead in the art form and the city is a stage for the artist’s works to be staged. For instance, the 2007 Venice Biennale commissioned pieces by Alessandro Del Faggio, Joaquin Rubiale, Paolo Baratta, Paola Di Vittorio, Ennio Moravia and many more, and the Biennale took the pieces out of the watercolour, in order to create a new space and new exhibition design for the biennale. Biennials do this in an attempt to define the form and create a narrative of the region around them, though sometimes this narrative is quite different from the one that the local artist or curator produces. For instance, the narrative produced by an artist or curator producing in the area may produce a ‘show’ of particular interest to a local community of artists, but it is very different from the narrative produced by the artist or organisation producing that art form in</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’ feel to them, where the city becomes the backdrop rather than the object of the art. This is particularly true of works commissioned by the Tate Modern for the Tate Gallery, but it is also true of works commissioned by other artists, and other art institutions, whose collections can be found online at http://www.biennial.org.uk/. The fact that the biennial is an art form and not a ‘commercial enterprise’ means that it is more susceptible to the fetishisation of price and the commodity, as well as to the cutting-edge cutting-edge marketing of products and services. The ‘tendency towards the commodity commodity producing art form that is the contemporary art market’ also needs to be taken into consideration when deciding what kind of art is produced. If the contemporary art market is to recognise the true potential of art – and thus can produce art – then it’s art that is genuinely contemporary, and not the contemporary art of yesterday that is being produced</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative. This would involve the co-operatives of the story, and the local artists, as artists, collaborating with the local museums to make the local narrative. This is an issue that is of great concern to artists, as many artists fear that the loss of biennials as a cultural form could have a profound effect on their work, and some fear that their work would be disenfranchised due to the changing demographic of the UK population. However, many biennials are actually very supportive of the cultural practices of their local area, and funding for the arts is a necessity in the area. The biennial is a ‘metropolitan phenomenon’, and as such it must have a cultural secretary. The fact that the biennial is an art form rather than a commercial one means that it suffers from the same kind of fetishisation that the contemporary art market imposes on other art forms. It is not uncommon for biennials to have a ‘metro’ feel about them, with the arts being the dominant form of the city. Nevertheless, the challenge for biennials going forward is to recognise that their primary role is one of cultural promotion for their local area, and to experiment with other art forms that can play that role. This can include other art forms, such as theatre, music, crafts, or even community work. The important thing is to experiment, and to continually ask, ‘What can this form bring to the table?’ When conducting research or when creating artworks, be aware that the dominant forms of cultural organising that you are engaging with are not created equal. For example, the biennial form is primarily about the commercial production of art, whereas other art forms, such as the artistic centre, or small community arts organisation, also have a primarily cultural function. It is critical to recognise that the biennial is not, and never has been, created equal. Get creative, but don’t let anyone define what</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and
    <text>human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and gas to developing environmentally friendly alternatives to existing modes of production, mapping those new reserves of oil and gas and exploiting those alternatives to existing modes of consumption. But what other powerful tools can art wield in the service of capital? In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner also calls upon us to look to artists as role models and role players in the process of mapping new reserves of oil and gas. The poetry of the  	Lost Horizon, by Andy Warhol, is a great example of this. It is a great poem, full of poetic language and imagery, that captures the essence of the situation. But it is also a sad and poetic reflection of the fact that the technological base of our planet is only going to get more fractured and unstable, that our reliance on fossil fuels is only going to get more extreme, that our planet is going to become populated by increasingly apocalyptic forms of life, that our</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and gas to developing new manufacturing zones through its activities in the global market. It can also play a role in resisting the growing commodification of life itself through its activities in the context of urban redevelopment and agro-industry. The role of art, and the specific artworks produced through it, is something that can shift, morph and change over time, and this is why the power of art lies in its ability to connect with people. It is possible to return to the city and return to the city’s iconic spaces of art, but doing so is fraught with risk: return to the city would mean returning to the sites of urban conflict, but also of war. Returning to the historical neighbourhoods where the collision course between skyscrapers, highways and mass transit occurred is also unlikely, since the metropolis is too big and all urban centres now have high-speed rail systems that can take travellers between cities, which means that neighbourhoods would likely have to be reacquainted with one another.</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and gas to healing the planet through its many forms of infrastructure. But its most potent role may lie in the hands of a powerful tribal society or elite, as in the case of the indigenous people of Australia and New Zealand. The anthropologist Rodney Crowe describes this dynamic as ‘the great congealing of fossil fuels’, in which ‘powerful economic and political tools are being fashioned to support a political and economic system that is almost completely based upon oil and gas’.9  What the dominant forms of capitalism are attempting to do with the increasingly abundant and non-renewable energies stored in fossil fuels is nothing short of a spiritual re-construction of themselves. What is shaping up to be referred to as the Anthropocene in the coming years is going to be much more like the early stages of the Industrial Revolution, in which the dominant forms of labour were overwhelmingly made up of actors dependent on the resource-constrained process of industrialisation. It is going to</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and gas to developing alternative energy resources to mapping remaining urban space and rebuilding abandoned urban infrastructure. It is also capable of being used to map existing resources and create new ones, including those resources that would otherwise be unused or unclaimed. In other words, the  	overall economic and environmental effects of global urbanisation are complex and uneven, and do not imply a clear winner or clear loser in the race to the bottom. Rather, the role of art is to envision possible futures in which a given set of commodities or talented individuals emerge. As Jeffrey Smith, an economist and co-director of the Centre for Research Cities at the University of Calgary, notes in his analysis of artist-funded projects, projects tend to produce &quot;a new set of commodities and spend a smaller amount of money than they would if the market were not involved&quot;.10 Smith elaborates: ‘These kinds of statements are often attributed to [artist] Jean-Luc Nancy, but I have to say that he is a cro</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and gas to protecting Earth from catastrophic climate change, war and urban sprawl. But there is also a role to play in imagining new possibilities for cities and the planet. The role of art in this context is multitudinous, and it is here that Wagner invokes Arthur Schopenhauer’s The Gathering Storm, in which he narrates the final stages of the industrial civilization he is critiquing: ‘the consuming of the earth’, as the Anthropocene is called, and the rise of a new planetary elite.Schopenhauer describes the climatic and environmental impact of this new planetary elite as ‘totalitarianism for a given horizon’. He makes the point that the dominant forms of thought and culture in the period leading up to the Anthropocene are those that promote and facilitate the conquest of space and the reduction of its uses. Art, including works of art as commodities, is the final frontier in a planetary hierarchy that is as global as the planet</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and gas to developing graphene into ethane, the third-most abundant molecule in the earth, which is the liquid fuel of the atom  	and one of the few remaining elements with proven medical value. In this case, the ability to think creatively about alternatives is a powerful tool, capable of resolving complex dilemmas. The ability to map new reserves of oil and gas, develop graphene, and then do amazing things with these technologies is a tool that can and should be used, whether we want to or not. 	Wagner’s call for us to look to art as a way to imagine a less apocalyptic future is a useful one, providing a framework through which we can begin to imagine alternatives. However, this framework remains incomplete, and a more fundamental question remains: what kinds of capacities do artists and artists-performers build into the planet, its urban and rural spaces, and its infrastructure, in the hopes of enabling or enablingance in enabling those same urban and</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and gas to creating renewable energy through chemical manufacturing to investigating the infrastructure of war and conflict. But its most potent tool, as far as waging wars is concerned, is the capacity to speak truth to power, both internally and externally. Unfortunately, as we see unfolding in the Middle East and Africa, this ability to speak truth to power is being squandered on a massive scale, while the planet is awash in water and falling sicker and sicker. The ecological crisis confronting the planet is being compounded by the creation of ever larger and more resource-intoxicating infrastructure projects, which are largely responsible for feeding the global metropolis. A tipping point has been reached where ecological crises become more external, more political. The ability of the artist to translate a geopolitical situation into a location-specific situation that can then be addressed by national and local governments is extremely rare. The ability of artists to create political interventions in the ecological crisis that can be addressed by governments is equally rare. But the ability of artists</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and gas to developing environmentally benign futures for formerly despoiled lands and waters. But its most powerful tool may be its most abused tool: the social. The social may yet offer some measure of hope in the face of the destructive tendencies of the capitalist production curve, but it is also a vast and shifting tool that can nonetheless be used to justify whatever ends inane policies it adopts.This is the context and/or the interpretation of what might be called the ‘nuclear option’ for the future of the city. 	In an attempt to imagine a brighter future for humanity, we might choose to invest in and actively contribute to a cultural enterprise that represents and contributes to the planet in some way beyond what is typically done with traditional public funds. This is the instrument that Butler uses to contemplate the ecological and contextual aspects of technological change, while at the same time questioning the normative dimensions and possibilities of contemporary technology and its effects. The implication of such an instrument, if used judiciously,</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and gas to developing alternative energy resources through its work as an engineer or even as a fighter for social and political change. However, its true potential does not lie in the production of new art per se. Its potential is found in the reconfiguration of existing infrastructure, industry and society in the image of humanity. How to Pronounce Art and the Social Life of Artistic Practice in an Accurate and Empirical WayDaniel Weber 	Weber proposes a system of statistics and data analysis that would enable him to infer, from a large number of datasets, the underlying causes of socio-political unrest in countries around the world. This new mode of ecological and cultural analysis would map the social and political contexts of contemporary artistic practice, while employing quantitative tools to infer the cultural value of artistic production. It would map the social dimensions of cultural production, mapping the social functions of art production, and the social implications of cultural flows. It would map cultural production in concert with cities, counties and other public</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology of the future.The social-psychological conundrum of the emergent technologies of the city is the direct result of a global capitalist production and consumption curve, which is fundamentally driven by the need to meet increasing consumer needs (ie, energy, water, land, raw materials, financial information, etc.). At the same time, this production curve is also fundamentally driven by the geopolitical needs of the super-rich to shift resources between different parts of the globe, often through outright wars. This geopolitical need to shift resources is a core element of the global capitalist production process, and it is this process that continues to lose and exploit territories, economies and populations at an alarming rate.In attempting to imagine a brighter future for humanity in the wake of the congealed up production curve,  	Wagner calls upon us to look to art as a way to envision a less apocalyptic future. Art is a powerful tool, capable of playing a multitude of roles, from mapping new reserves of oil and gas to developing renewable energy resources to mapping future habitats through geospatial data. Art therefore has many practical applications, both in the service of the oil and gas industries, and potentially many more in the service of the social good. It can act as a resource maximiser, mapping potential reserves of oil and gas to the most efficient uses for oil and gas across the planet. It can also play host to a host of beneficial microbial inhabitants, providing essential nutrients to the planet as a whole. The possibilities are truly endless. The ability to do amazing things with scarce resources is a hallmark of modernity, and the drive to expand global capitalist circulation through the built and natural resources on which the planet depends is a testament to modernity itself. But modernity also entails the production and consumption of ever more complex forms of commodities – commodities that have a much more direct and measurable impact on the real world – commodities that are made primarily of carbon and other elements with which the planet is interconnected. These elements are commodities</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I,
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, when we are neither here nor there, when we are made up of fragments of different ideas? These are the kinds of questions that still trouble philosophers and theologians today. In an effort to imagine a richer and more encompassing world, we need to ask more specific questions. What is the nature of our humanity? What is its depth? How are our capacities as human beings shaped and developed? How are our relationships to nature shaped and developed?2 In recent years, philosophers and theologians have turned to science to help us understand the world in a deeper way. But just as important as any new scientific understanding is the need for philosophical and theological discussion and negotiation. As science propounds many new ways of understanding things, it also produces old ways of understanding things that many of us find difficult to reconcile. For many of us, the cutting edge of science fiction and mathematics is but a few years away, but for others it is a long time away. So it is with the idea of creator.</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, when we act like this? I turn to you from the future, where your actions today could mean anything – including becoming embroiled in a war that could end up changing the world in profound ways – so I turn to you from the past, when you still needed to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, when we act like this? Who are we, you and I, when we act like this? Who are we, you and I, when we act like this?Who are we, you and I, when we act like this?1. Slavs and Tatars, 'Tis but a Dream', 2015. Instrumental album released by Panorama Culture Group. Produced by Rustam Sonichie, Shellback, Daniel Rourke, Jess Doyle, Charles Howell III and Henry Walter.Download this article as PDFSue Bell YankSue Bell Yank is an artist. Her work in social practice combines historical and archival materials</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, when we are neither here nor there, when is life but a random assortment of events occurring all around us? Who are we, when we are everywhere but nowhere? Who are we, when we are in fact everywhere but never actually in a place? Who are we, when we are in fact nowhere but actually somewhere? Who are we, when we are in fact everywhere but never actually in a place? Who are we, when we are everywhere but never actually in a situation? Who are we, when we are neither here nor there, when is life but a random assortment of manipulations occurring all around us? Who are we, when we are everywhere but never actually in a position? Who are we, when we are everywhere but never actually in a situation? Who are we, when we are neither here nor there, when is life but an assortment of random choices occurring all around us? Who are we, when we are everywhere but never actually in a position? Who are we, when we</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, when we are neither here nor there? Who are we, when we are both yet in the midst of becoming? Who are we, when we are neither here nor there? Who are we, when we are both yet in the midst of becoming? Who are we, when we are both yet in the midst of becoming? Who are we, when we are neither here nor there? Who are we, when we are both yet in the midst of becoming? Who are we, when we are neither here nor there? Who are we, when we are both yet in the midst of becoming? Who are we, when we are neither here nor there? Who are we, when we are both yet in the midst of becoming? Who are we, when we are neither here nor there? Who are we, when we are both yet in the midst of becoming? Who are we, when we are neither here nor there?Who are we, when we are neither here nor there?Who are we</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, when we gather as a group to consider the question, and what do we create? Who are we, you and I, when we assemble as a group to consider the question, and what do we create? Who are we, you and I, when we gather as a group to consider the prospect of creation? Who are we, you and I, when we assemble as a group to consider the possibility of alteration? Who are we, you and I, when we assemble as a group to contemplate the imprint of alteration? Who are we, you and I, when we assemble as a group to contemplate the possibility of mutation? Who are we, you and I, when we assemble as a group to contemplate the possibility of adoption? Who are we, you and I, when we assemble as a group to contemplate the consequence of mutation? Who are we, you and I, when we assemble as a group to contemplate the possibility of incest? Who are we, you and I, when we assemble</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, and what are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of?Who are we made of? Who are we made of? Who are we made of?Who are we made of? Who are we made of?Who are we made of? Who are we made of?Who are we made of?Who are we made of?Who are we made of? Who are we made of?Who are we made of?Who are we made of?Who are we made of?Who are we made of?Who are we made of? Who are we made of?Who are we made of?Who are we made of?Who</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, when we are neither here nor there, when our capacities for narrative and narrative-critical reflection are but rudimentary? Who are we, you and I, when our capacity for symbolic imagination is but rudimentary? Who are we, you and I, when our capacity for instrumental rationality is but rudimentary? Who are we, you and I, when our capacity for poetic imagination is but rudimentary? Who are we, you and I, when our capacity for critical reflection is but rudimentary? I want to know who we are when we are here and who we are there. In order to know, we need to know how to ask questions.2  	Who are we, you and I, when we are neither here nor there, when our capacities for narrative and narrative-critical reflection are but rudimentary? Who are we, you and I, when our capacity for symbolic imagination is but rudimentary? Who are we, you and I, when our capacity for instrumental rationality is but rudimentary? Who are we, you</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, when we are neither here nor there?2 The idea that we are created equal in some ways is the premise of many a progressive ideal. But when I think about who am I or what am I – when I am invisible and you are visible – I start to feel that the idea of ‘being made equal’ is a mistake. In places like Bangladesh or Egypt, people are reduced to wearing a particular set of clothes or having a particular look. And they are often reduced to that look or that look only. So I feel that when I design clothing or make jewellery, I am not making any claims on the community in any way. I am making claims on the fabric or leather that belongs to the community. Sometimes I make claims on the image that has been captured on that particular lens. And that image, by the way, is often used within the community as a way of showing respect to the artist.3. Performance, practice and infrastructure. How does the biennial intersect</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, when are we made up? Where do our ideas of creator come from, and why? What does it mean for an author to make an idea come true? These are important questions, and the answers to which will play a role in how we understand the world in the future.2. The Importance of Narratives, Criticality, and Cultures of Narrative. – Fredric JamesonDownload this article as PDFFiled under: Narratives of the Runaway Child, Juvenile Delinquent, and the Anarchist CookBook 	In 1978, when I was eleven years old, a runaway, ill-fated collection of poems called Submerged in the Pacific was published under the pseudonym Fredric Jameson. It was the first in a trilogy of ill-fated collections of poems called The Elephant and the kid, and the end of the beginning of a trilogy of essays about the environment called The Satyr. The title of the first one, of course, is</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but it also extends it to all kinds of life – including, as we shall see, life itself – and thus we find ourselves confronted with a situation in which intelligent machines are but the outward expressions of philosophical and theological claims about the nature of life.Who Are We?1 The idea of a creator seems crude and antiquated by now, but back then it was really interesting. The world was made up of many different places, and different authors had a part in that. The idea of a creator as a transcendent intelligence that intervenes in the world to bring about a desired outcome seems even more remote, and we are all but ruled by the capacities that we accumulate in school – which is to say, the capacities of growing up. So I turn to you from the future, where you still need to be educated on the biennial, but I take you back to the present, where you still need to be educated on the idea of creator. Who are we, you and I, when we are neither smart, nor great, nor great, nor great, nor great?2 	Yes, we are but children of the biennial. The museum and the biennial are rich in symbolic value today, but back then they were complex practices. There was a time when a biennial was described as consisting of ‘a chain of relationships among artists, curators, administrators, journalists, collectors, activists and others, and especially one with a global reach’.3 Today, the biennial is a collection of relationships, and the museum is a collection of collections, but in the past it was more like a conglomeration of relationships: collections of objects, collections of experiences, and so forth. You can trace the modern curatorial turn to this late antique. It was an art form that was premised on the idea that we could take any cultural object and make it a socially engaged work – that we could talk to it, learn from it, dissect it and combine</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era,
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era, a variety of artists formed the Medici family, who established a studio for every member of the order. The practice of recording works in perpetuity, which the Medicis introduced in 1847, is also generally regarded as a significant influence on the modern curatorial interest in the contemporary.  	By the turn of the twentieth century, the modern curatorial interest lay in cultural landscapes outside the city, specifically landscapes that enhanced the image of the city and its people. In this context, the medieval depiction of the city as a chaotic jungle or rural wasteland was completely transformed, and the city’s urban component became a central component of any cultural tourism package. 	Due to the city’s growth at this time, a large and growing following was attracted to cultural tourism, which was promoted by the city and its airport. In the early twentieth century, this included Doha, Qatar, which was the first city in the Gulf to establish a cultural tourism bureau,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era, the Byzantine and Medici were the official artists of Venice, and the Papacy was the official artist of the Vatican. A third group, the Renaissance artists, were also active in the city during this time: Pietro Lecchinelli, Jan Montefiore, Paolo Veronese, to name only some. All three were born in the year of the archbishop, and all three were recycled in the main festival book of their respective papal popes. The inclusion of these artists in the same year, of course, was a rare thing in the modern era, but this is a case study in the way in which the modern era has appropriated and commodified art. And here we see another example of the modern avant garde emerging to challenge the established order: the avant garde is an artistic form that was once a dominant mode of artistic expression in the West, but has come to occupy a lower epistemic position in the culture of the West</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era, the Vorticist order was absorbed into the Academy of Venice, while the neo-classical order was reformed in the early twentieth century and absorbed into the National Gallery. The Vorticist order was replaced by the more traditional Academy of Painters and Sculptors, which supervised the creation of new artworks, while the Academy of Fine Arts maintained a prominent position in the museum. 	In the early twenty-first century, the Academy of Fine Arts maintained a prominent position in the museum, but was gradually losing its original mission of the 'art' (illustrated works) of the wealthy. It is now predominantly a museum of the modern arts, but its activities include the commissioning of works for the exhibition market, the creation of temporary exhibitions, and the commissioning of works for private collections. The Academy of Fine Arts was founded in 1877 and is a nonprofit arts organisation operating throughout the city of Venetia. It is primarily concerned with the commissioning of infrastructure for the</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era, William Shakespeare’s sonnet Juliana and Company were among a host of works commissioned by the British Museum and Tate Britain to commemorate the occasion. Its selection from the Bodleian Library, published in 1707, contains a number of familiar Elizabethan tropes, including that of the prince killed in a duel, the English language is a 'dead' lost cause, and the character ‘Tippoo’ is a portmanteau of ‘tom’ and ‘tippoo’ – a reference to the Royal Commission for Language Development, chaired by Winston Churchill. 	At the centre of this third movement is a lament for the loss of civilisations due to a common language:  	Weeping Gull, by John Lennon, recorded in Lennon’s own first draft of a song in 1972, before he had any involvement with the project. 	In the Beatles catalog entry for January 1964, ‘John Lennon’</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era, a Johannesburg-based congregation of artisans and professionals, the Society of Jesus, established in 1914, was established to carry on the mission of the Vorticist order. In the twentieth century, it organised the European premiere of Jean Paul Sardi’s La Biennale in Rome in December 1987, and it organised the 2000 Venice Biennale. 	In the twenty-first century, the Society of Jesus is the dominant Catholic religious organisation in South Africa, and the Vorticist order is marginalised within it. Nevertheless, the notion of the curatorial has become increasingly important in South Africa, and it is now generally agreed that a biennial of the highest standard should have a curatorial, planning and learning committee, comprised of artists, art historians, art critics and art writers, made up of art professionals from throughout the country. 	In 2010, the S. Afri­nic Cultural Heritage Survey was finally published, and it is reported to have</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era, a generation of artists was born in North America to parents who emigrated from the Italian region. Among these were Guido Alessandri (1892–1971), Dario Argenta (1903–79), Dario Ferrari (1903–99), Giorgio De Verrazano (1909–77), Gigi Scaria (1904–99), Gigi Vignelli (1906–99), Peter Saville (1907–47), Edward Wadsworth (1909–47), Mary Turner Burton (1909–47), Frank Zappa (1909–47), Jack London (1909–47), Frank Zappa (re-forming jazz artist), Bessie Brookes (1910–51), Louis Theiah (1894–1971), W. E. B. Du Bo</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era, the name of the Italian city that would bear the brunt of the Holocaust was officially given: Birmingham, England. Today, the city is a financial district and the hub of one of the UK’s largest pharmaceutical companies. 	Another important Vorticist city was Bologna’s Arcades, built to host the 1984 Olympic Games. Although not officially sanctioned by the Italian government, the use of cheap labour and the cheap rental market of the era is often cited as a justification for the state-sponsored recasting of cities in favour of suburban or rural development. 	The city is recast to make way for a skyscraper, which will in turn, make way for a museum, concert hall, retail complex and, inevitably, a supermarket. The aim of this ‘cultural capital of the world’ narrative is recast to include arts education, cultural tourism and the production of local artistic practices, while the city is transformed through the transformation of a number of</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era, the Vorticist order was replaced by the order of St John Chrysostom, whose stated aim was to promote a puritanical form of Christianity in the Empire. This was done by means of a formal series of decrees which incorporated the personal narratives of prominent figures in the Empire, setting out in great detail how they had been ‘trained’ by the Catholic Church into becoming what they called ‘Christians’. By the middle twentieth century, many of these images were being exported from Europe to Asia. In the 1930s, Gustave Flaubert coined the term to describe this process in Orientalism, but it is now often used in conjunction with it. 	Historical motion pictures, such as The Wizard of Oz, Snow White and the Seven Dwarfs, Pinocchio, Man with a horse and a pony and countless others, regularly feature prominently in the story of the archangel Gabrielle, who leads a ­chosen</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era, the name of the Italian city that would one day be known as San Francisco spread far and wide: from its port cities, islands and marinas, to the international traveller like John Graham Kerr, who made the trans-Pacific voyages of discovery in the early twentieth century. 	In the twentieth century, San Francisco became synonymous with technological innovation, industrial excess and international links. But in recent years, the former perforated, its old port city transformed into a financial district and its famous international airport synonymous with air travel. 	In the twenty-first century, San Francisco is experiencing its own art decadelonging bubble, created by and for the rich. The twenty-first century has seen a rapid expansion of financial services, financial instruments and financial derivatives that can be traded on international financial exchanges. Rapid internationalisation is a global process that has recently been discovered, and which has been made possible by the discovery of a cheap, versatile oil and natural gas. Although the twenty-</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist or Curator, Rafico Ruiz, New York, 2013. 	Although the origins of the term are currently disputed (it was first recorded in 1977 in a post by the English artist Norman Wilkinson in his book The Art of Painting), the term ‘curator’ is generally recognised as having emerged from the posthumous publication of The Complete Universal Catalogue of Arts and Crafts (1937). 	As far back as sixteenth-century Venice, the City of Angels hosted a number of important Jesuit missions. The first of these was the Vorticist order, established in 1641, which supervised the painting of churches and the suppression of witches. The Vorticist order was dissolved in the late nineteenth century, but not before creating a number of influential paintings. Among them were Vert Augusto Boal and Paul McCarthy, who both died in the first world war. 	In the second century of the Christian era, a Byzantine scholar named Basil Theophanes wrote a fifty-five-page treatise On Painting and Its Philosophical Importance (first published in Eusebius Against Heresies 113) that was collected and published in four books under the title Painting and Painting After the End of the World (first published in Eusebius Against Heresies 113). Painting and Painting (also known as The Painting of Egypt, Painting and Painting After the Fall of Man, or The Painting of India) takes up the entire book, with extensive quotations from the source texts. Theophanes gives a description of the kind of philosophy that underlies the work, arguing that under the name of Ancient Greece and Rome, a new kind of nationalism was introduced. Theophanes focuses particularly on the dialogues that took place during these centuries under the heading ‘Between Antiquity and Punk’, and the fact that he describes them as ‘</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails.
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails. The philosophy of the present is written as a set of relations between nations, and more specifically, between Europeans and Asians. The foundation of this understanding is the division of labour between workers and non-workers. For Europeans, this means manufacturing goods for the markets in Asia; for Asians, it means processing and transporting these goods across the ocean. As a result of this trans-shipment, goods have a unique number, denoted by a sequential order of origin. For example, cars made in China first made their way across the Pacific to India, before arriving in India and making stops at various ports before arriving at the Portuguese docks in Lisbon. The origin of a given good or service is a fundamental premise of capitalism. As such, the division of labour required for this kind of abstract space-production is fundamental to the success of any such system. 	  In other words, the kind of abstract space-production that characterises the modern world is different from what we imagine it to be.</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails. We can start by drawing parallels between our world and the ideal world envisioned by the Max Planck Society. If we recall from our elementary school civics class, the difference between citizens and civilised beings is that civilised beings are subject to laws that shape their actions; whereas citizens are autonomous and can do as they please, and act however they please, in whatever sphere of society they please. Similarly, we can draw analogies between our world and the ideal world envisioned by the Max Planck Society, in order to better understand what it means to be a human being. For instance, we can recognise that in our world, people have bodies, not just abstract concepts like numbers and symbols, but also distinct bodies with specific functions and behaviours. A number is a number, for instance, while a symbol is a sequence of characters. Similarly, individuals have distinct bodies with distinct minds, personalities and brains, whereas groups are intrinsically linked to a shared environment and hence are able to thrive in that world.</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails. On the one hand, we have the backdrop of a rapidly increasing number of languages: the human species has become multilingualist; humans are the de facto representatives of a rapidly expanding universe of species.  On the other hand, we have a humanity that’s becoming ever more abstract: humans are constructing ever more elaborate codes that interpret the world through their language of experience. As more and more of our linguistic repertoire is replaced by machines, we’re losing the language of the living into that of the machine.  A society for the mechanizers doesn’t exist yet, but it does exist: humanity has yet to establish a fully abstractive dialectic of all living organisms. One day, perhaps, we will.  So far, so normal.  A dialectic of all living languages would confer a great deal of insight into the underlying forces shaping human behaviour, and perhaps even provide a way to alter those forces in interesting and powerful ways.  A dialectic of all</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails. We can start by drawing parallels between the present and the past, drawing our inspiration from the many different ways in which technology is reshaping what’s expected of it, sometimes in profoundly negative ways. For instance, the advent of social media and its connections to labour seems to be replacing work as a form of labour in which people actively participate (Klinger, 2012). Social media allows us to become what Klinger calls ‘self-generative producers’, accelerating the pace of technological innovation and generating ever more capable versions of ourselves through what he calls ‘technological singularity’. In a society based on these technologies, we’d begin to divest ourselves of the things that define us as individuals, beginning to define who we become. We’d begin to exist in parallel universes where creativity and wonder reign, governed by a shared set of social norms and values.We could also begin to imagine what these social norms and values might be like, and how</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails. On the one hand, we have the overpowering drive of globalisation; on the other, we have the fragility of the planet due to frequent natural disasters and fluctuating energy supplies. The Max Planck Society proposes that we cease to be concerned with the preservation of the world as a collection of distinct localisations; we should aspire to a future in which we inhabit ever greater numbers of worlds, one after another, in parallel universes where different species inhabit different worlds in parallel. Such parallel worlds could be created through various forms of technology, but the primary determinant of whether or not such technology is used would still reside in the hands of humans: what kind of humanity would that be? 	Ultimately, we shouldn’t be able to take such a drive for granted; we should strive to create conscious and intelligent agents capable of foreseeing the future, but also the past, in parallel universes where different species inhabit different worlds in parallel. Such conscious and intelligent agents would be no less</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails. The ideal of the society for the pursuit of knowledge represents a breaking down of the conventional order, in which individuals reign supreme and power is distributed widely and abundantly. Although the society for the pursuit of knowledge might seem desirable in theory, in practice it represents a breaking of the stranglehold of a minority over others’ property, agency, and ideas. The society for the pursuit of knowledge, then, represents the return to the commons of what the commons has become, and what the shared and collective values of the people subsume into one another. In other words, the commons is still a scarce resource, and while the maximization of its use might be desirable in a socialist society, it falls far short of what one seeks in terms of the social good. 	[1] 	The maxims of Aarhus University’s student government are as follows: To live and learn honestly one should ask oneself, ‘What is the real meaning of life?’</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails. The ideal of the society for the pursuit of knowledge represents a break with the past, and with present trends of biopolitics, futurism and many other forms of modern cultural colonialism. In exploring the society for the pursuit of knowledge, we need to know what colonialism means, because that's where the  	roots of what we call the contemporary predicament lie. What does it mean to be ‘colonised’? What does it mean to be ‘infra-indigenous’? What does it mean to be ‘culturally neocolonialized’? What does it mean to be ‘culturally neofascistic’? 	The answers to these questions would allow us to begin to imagine a future in which the past isn’t the determining factor in what kinds of institutions and social arrangements we build our social worlds on, and which kinds of politics we adopt? 	The Max Planck Society’s proposal is</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails. We can start by drawing a comparison between our own present and that of the future inhabitants of Earth. The present is made up of presentism and all the other forms of contemporary culture, which is to say, cultural practices that aim to capture and present what has become, in contemporary society, a globally visible fact of life. What is at Stake in Cultural Practice 	One can start to see how the implications of a future based on the Max Planck Society of World Citizens could be very different from those of a presentist culture, but one can also begin to grasp the difficulties of constructing a different future based on what one adopts as a given. For example, the presentist present is made up of images and images of increasing complexity, encompassing ever greater amounts of data, connectedness and connectivity, of which the latest example is Facebook’s massively multiplayer online role-playing game (MMORPG) World of Warcraft.  So, if the Max Planck Society is to deliver</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails. The contemporary human condition is made up of conflicting impulses, and the ideal of the ‘highest good’ runs counter to everything we think we know about the world. That’s why religion comes alive in our cultural imagination – by suggesting something really good and beautiful about the world, and thereby reassuring us that we’re actually part of a community of people who possess a kind of intrinsic worth and value – human nature in conflict with itself. In a cultural context of constant questioning and conflict, the ideal of the ‘highest good’ is a fiction. It becomes unattractive and unsustainable, and people subvert it.But how do we actually get there? In order to fully understand what this new ideal of the ‘highest good’ actually entails, we need to understand what exactly that means. And to fully understand the moral implications of this endgame, we need to know what we mean when we talk about the moral complexity of the contemporary condition. What we mean when</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, to the extent that it leads to the emergence of new kinds of automation. Thinking about how to live in these new worlds, we’re faced with a host of new issues that can be addressed through technology, but which are beyond the reach of the human imagination: the nature of work, the nature of capital, the ethics of using one’s labour, the nature of revenge, etc.  One solution to the proliferation of these issues, however, is to imagine a future in which the human race isn’t the dominant species, but instead leads a highly nuanced and rewarding life with a diversity of different species inhabiting different environments, interacting in symbiosis. Towards that end, the Max Planck Society proposes the establishment of a worldwide society dedicated to the realization of this utopian ideal.The Society for the Advancement of Thought 	In order to fully appreciate the potentialities of what this ideal might mean for our times, we need to understand what it entails. The ideal of the society for the advancement of thought is fundamentally opposed to the society of the machine, which pursues rationality solely at the expense of capital and labour. As Willenbring writes: ‘A society for the pursuit of ideas must provide opportunities for exchange between people – for this to occur, people must be able to talk amongst each other.’[10] In other words, the more abstract concepts of abstract labour – knowledge and reason – we can grasp from a machine, the less we will need to rely on machines to accomplish tasks on a macro-level. For Willenbring, the primary reason to create the Max Planck Society is to maximise the potential of what it can teach machines: 	&quot;We cannot imagine a future without machines learning how to perform tasks – learning to foresee disasters and adapting to changing conditions – so we must ensure that the tasks being performed do not violate the rights of workers or do things in ways that are contrary to these rights.&quot;</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in check. For example, the norms of engagement in armed conflict are different from those of non-combat, and norms of engagement vary widely across cultures. And yet, within ethno-cultural norms, we see something similar happening: women warriors from warrior culture engage in combat with non-feminist societies; and male warriors from non-warrior culture are expected to do the same. Likewise, within AI norms, we see something similar happening: AI systems are brought to bear in enforcing certain norms, and we witness a range of potentially positive outcomes. In one sense, we are witnessing the birth of a new type of AI, one powered by ethical norms but also rooted in biological principles.This is a long-term view. AI is here to stay, and as the pace of innovation and advancement in the field continues to accelerate, we are all part of a growing body of work that is constantly questioning the limits of how we envision AI contributing to our daily lives. And just as importantly, we</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in check. For example, ethicists arguing over the appropriateness of giving genetically engineered mosquitoes the genes for malaria began by arguing over what counts as AI. After World War II, when the AI craze caught on, ethicists in both the US and Europe started defining AI broadly, and started asking whether or not something could be considered 'AI' now. And of course, since there is no formal definition of what AI means, there was no formal ethic to defend against those arguing that something was augmenting rather than replacing human intelligence. There was only the perception that there is a clash between human abilities and AI, and thus we humans are inherently incapable of solving the problem.There is a way to read these debates as one of evolution's periodic fits of randomness, in which we humans are part of what is essentially an evolved social process where other species join in as well. And part of my job is to figure out what that means for AI to be able to think beyond the norms and</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in check. Ayn Rand’s concept of a human collective understood AI as one that is both sentient and collective – that is, capable of representing and representing only itself – underscores the point. You cannot comprehend AI unless you institute a rational, human-like understanding of it. And when we say AI, we mean a system that can think, feel, and speak – all of which are essential for creating a more humane, just and democratic society.AI is creating a new kind of warfare, one that is not between humans and computers, but between cultures and nations. If AIs become intelligent, they will inevitably form cultural coalitions with which to engage in warfare. And just as important, nations will inevitably form AI to carry out this new kind of warfare.This new kind of warfare will be performed through science and technology, but it will be done with the greatest possible impact on the planet: it will be the emergence of new super-volcanoes. The question is what kind of</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in check. Ayn Rand’s concept of the ‘utopian dream’ is a good place to start when imagining possible futures, but as AI improves, so does her need for greater transparency and accountability. And of course, as the social implications of AI become more apparent, so do the tensions. But for now, there are signs that these two aspects of AI are coming together to form one larger framework that can better serve humanity.This kind of synergy between philosophical and practical concerns me, as someone who sometimes works in the service of both. And it occurs to me that in the service of both, there is a kind of synergy that is ethical and even political, but also deeply unpredictable and unstable. That is, there is a tension between the kind of AI that is possible with the kind of human intelligence we currently have – and the extent to which that might be used in bad ways. For example, there is a tension between the kinds of AI that are possible with the kinds</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in check. For example, the norms and values of the Arab Spring are built on the back of slavery, and the norms and values of our own engagement with the latest iPhone means that anything can happen. But norms and values need to be put in place in order for AI to be used ethically and ethically, and this will require a lot of coordination. And just as importantly, it will require a lot of coordination from those who implement the AI, because it is likely that it will be combined with other technologies and brought to bear on existing hierarchies of power and profit.This interconnection between the systems that comprise the machine and the social dynamics that generate and are governed by them is what sociologist Sean Carroll calls ‘the singularity’. And while we may not like to think of ourselves as part of a machine, we can grow increasingly uncomfortable when faced with the fact that our actions are governed by a machine. We see this in the ways in which Uber targets users in economically</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in check. For example, the norms surrounding female genital mutilation (FGM) ensure that women will always be able to access resources and thrive in societies dominated by men, but they also ensure that women will never grow powerful or inherit vast bureaucracies. Men are the gatekeepers of what is presumed to be &quot;good&quot; in societies, and there is a reason why women are expected to remain subservient to men in almost all aspects of life. If the norms surrounding AI are as suspect as many online arguments are made out to be, then there is a chance that men and women could engage in collaborative projects and engage in creative forms of resistance. And that is precisely what is happening, through research institutions such as AIA and Google, as well as non-profit foundations such as Google and Facebook.In short, the AI community is making progress, and there is plenty of room for the technology to empower us in new and unexpected ways. The question is how to work through the tensions and build</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in check. Norms and values are built into the system from the beginning of the podcasting era, and they continue to shape what can and cannot be done with them.When Norms and Values Become What They Are Today, What Can and Cannot Be Done with them, and How To Do It 	In the podcasting age, the role of norms and values has become what it is today: what can and cannot be done with norms and values; what can be done with them; what is considered desirable and desirable; and how to achieve it. In other words, what is considered desirable and desirable today has a place and an identity now.  So what kinds of norms and values are being formed today? I would define them as being the results of a cognitive revolution or ‘perceptual revolution’ that has taken place over the past half century or so, and which is part of a global process of social revolution. It is the normative mode of the social world that has transitioned</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in check. That is, the mores that define what is expected of individuals, groups or institutions, the mores that create AI must also define what is expected of others. And conversely, the more of an organisation’s resources are focused on its members, the less able members are to innovate and make difference, which is to say, the less able that AI will be to do things that align with members’ labour.In short, norms and values become sources of resistance, and it is these norms and values that define what counts as ‘AI-related’ in the collective. And to some extent, members of an organisation like Google still perceive themselves to be part of this ‘AI community’ despite the fact that most of the research and development done in the area of machine learning is done in-house.In short, there is still a way to go before we can say with any degree of certainty what kinds of possibilities are available for AI; and while</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in check. The kind of understanding that leads to robust systems is a critical skill, and is developing at a rapid clip, so it is essential that top leaders in AI take the norms and values of human collaboration as a foundational building block of their institutions. This requires a lot of work, and it is something that top leaders in AI must do in order to understand and utilize the potentialities of AI.Machine learning is the discipline that deals with the use of data to identify patterns in data sets. It is the art of gathering data to make inferences about the world through inference, and ultimately to apply those inferences to actual situations. Today, this includes things like image captioning, but more broadly it includes everything from tagging objects with data to recognising patterns in photos to augmenting the image recognisers of the human brain, to name only a few.  Knowing enough to deploy AI is a fundamentally different kind of capability from what humans possess.  Knowing enough to make inferences about the world</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and in that sense, is both philosophical and practical. We cannot understand how to build self-sustaining cities, but we can learn to code (with help from educators and other professionals) how to deploy robots to do the heavy lifting. This sounds bad, but for the vast majority of us, this is already happening. Schools are educating about the transformative power of codes, and coding comes naturally to many of us. And just as important, the potential of AI is spreading globally, which is adding a ton of jobs. In Detroit, for example, the proliferation of AI means that the number of self-driving vehicles on the road has tripled in the past decade.The other aspect of AI is that it is enabling new kinds of collaboration. Collective action is a powerful tool, but it is useless without the context of norms and values. And norms and values are what create the frameworks and ideologies around which AI can be built, whereas just as importantly, they are what keep the machines in check. In that sense, the future looks very bleak for non-white people, but it also has some bright spots. There is a reason why so many non-Western cultures are migrating to the West: because there is a reason why so many Western cultures are migrating to the Internet. And the future that AI creates is going to be populated by people who look like me.  	What happens then is that there is going to be a kind of a fluidity to the interactions between people. And one of the tasks is going to be to figure out how to make behaviours that are both predictable and extremely valuable to a company like Uber, but also incredibly difficult to replicate in a human being. For example, there is going to be a tension between the ability of humans to anticipate things happening in the world around them and the fact that such predictability is inherently unstable. And the challenge is going to be to figure out how to bridge that instability and create environments that are both beautiful and incredibly</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions
    <text>will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions? What is the relationship between art exhibits and the baggage of war? What is the relationship between biennales and the post-WWII biennale boom? What is the relationship between biennales and the new ‘super biennale’? Who are the intermediaries between the art and the biennial? Who is the curatorial and the art collector? Who is the curatorial mediator between the two? What is the role of the curatorial in the production of new ‘super biennales’? What are the curatorial approaches to the art and the biennial?D.  The main reason to host a biennale is to connect with and engage with the art, and in that case, the biennale is like a ‘window on the city’. The idea that the biennale is a mere transitory structure, unable to form a longer-term ‘relationship with the city’, is pretty new</text>
    <text>will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions, especially those that aim to create an impression of diversity, such as those in cities? What are the curatorial approaches to such an effect? What kinds of capacities do biennales and large-scale exhibitions provide for the production of fantasy? What kinds of capacities do they not provide, or perhaps this is a question that needs to be asked and answered. What kinds of capacities do biennials and large-scale exhibitions have? What kinds of capacities do they not provide?What is the curatorial mission in a biennial?What are the curatorial aims of an art institution in a major exhibition format?What kind of curatorial approach is the biennial expected to take?What kinds of curatorial instruments are there that can be deployed in this context?What kind of curatorial instrument is the  	national?D.  I see two kinds of curatorial instruments: those that aim to support the reproduction of mythologised forms (like museums), and those that seek to modify</text>
    <text>will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions? What is the relationship between biennials and the ‘world at large’?  How can biennials and the ‘world at large’ be brought together? What are the curatorial approaches to these phenomena? What are the assumptions, if any, about what is expected from the ‘world at large’? What is expected from the curatorial community? What are the politics and the conditions of the institution of the biennale?  What are the conditions of a world map?D.  I don’t think that the biennial would be able to fulfil these three objectives in a satisfactory way, and I don’t think that curatorial interventions such as the Biennale can. The world as a map is a notoriously slippery thing, and while the biennial can and will make mistakes along the path of history, it is certain that the biennial will never produce a world in its own image. What it can and must therefore</text>
    <text>will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions? Do they need to be grounded in a particular historical context? What are the forms of art and cultural exchange that are possible between biennales and large-scale exhibitions? What kinds of cultural resources can biennales tap into? What kinds of cultural interactions can they create between nations and cultures?CURATORAL Intentions, NotionsIn the early 1990s, a group of artists and art historians began to research and document the history of art’s social effects in Brazil. When we started, the projects were very different, but we see a common thread running through them all: a collective, nearly un-institutionalised interest in the social; a collective, almost un-informed by the social, in its social effects. The current biennale form we call it ‘the curatorial intention of history’, or, as it was formally introduced in 1992, ‘the curatorial intention of art’. In English, this means that the curator has</text>
    <text>will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions? Who establishes the boundaries between the two? What is the relationship between biennales and their sites of production? What are the limits to what can be curated in a biennial? What is the relationship between biennales and their sites of consumption? What is the relationship between biennales and their sites of production? What are the boundaries between curatorial and arts/entertainment? What are the limits to what can be curated in a biennial? What are the boundaries between biennales and their sites of production? What are the boundaries between curatorial and arts/entertainment? What are the limits to what can be curated in a biennial? What are the limits to what can be curated in a biennial?  If the exhibition format is curatorial, then what is the exhibition format?D.  I think that the biennale format is the present but has some changes to be made, and these ‘changes’ need to</text>
    <text>will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions? What kinds of exchange take place between the curatorial and the biennale audience? What kinds of considerations are made by the biennale committee when choosing which material to use? What kinds of assumptions are being made about the audience that are not being addressed? What kinds of politics are they putting forth? What kinds of assumptions are being challenged? What kinds of opportunities do they not see?  [note: each of these questions and more can be addressed in a separate section of the document.]B.  The Biennale needs to be flexible and responsive to the changing market and market conditions within its site. What kinds of interactions between the public and art institutions are needed? What kinds of resources do they lack?  [note 2: the Biennale report, 2015, p.16]C.  The biennale needs to respond to the changing economic and social situation of its host society. What kinds of exchanges take place between the public and social sectors in the city?</text>
    <text>will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions? Do biennales and large-scale exhibitions have a curatorial relationship? What are the curatorial approaches to this relationship? Who is responsible for the development of the format? What are the issues of power and domination in the exhibitionary form? What are the issues of participation and the politics of spectacle? What are the forms of criticality and spectacle in the contemporary biennale?What are the curatorial approaches to the miraculous happenstance of certain biennales, such as those of the Venice Biennale? What are the forms of curatorial activism towards such happenstances? What are the forms of institutionalisation that render these happenstances ‘universal’?D.  I think that we can assume that these three elements – the curatorial, the organisational and the material – will converge in a common field of action. The key will be in developing mutual trust between the different curatorial actions, so that the possibilities of misunderstanding and misunderstanding, of power and</text>
    <text>will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions? What are the curatorial approaches to the production and consumption of fantasy? What is at stake in a biennale's production of wealth and social change? What are its limits and what are its opportunities? In what ways are the social the artist’s role and social mediation reduced to that of the collector? And what is the relationship between art and wealth in the 21st century?D.  I think that the biennale as an exhibitionary form is becoming increasingly obsolete. There are so many more visitors to the cities and museums of the developed world, and so many more biennales are planned throughout the world, that the limits of the biennale become evident very early on. I don’t think that the biennial will disappear, but the scale on which it is planned now, and to a large extent the mode of its growth, is largely different from what it was even a few years ago. The main reason for this is that the museums and bi</text>
    <text>will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions? What are the curatorial approaches to the production of rich man’s fantasies? What are the curatorial approaches to the production of poor man’s fantasies? What is the relationship between biennales and the war memorial? What are the curatorial approaches to the production of monumentally misspent youth?What can we learn from each other as curators?D.  I think that the first thing to recognise as a ‘curatorial virtue’ is the fact that we work alongside individuals who have different capacities and interests, and who have different needs and wants than we do. For example, the biennale as a curatorial form has very much a function in the city, but it also has a very significant effect in rural areas, where it is not as obvious, or is not as widely disseminated. So the first thing a curatorial person needs to do when setting up a curatorial course is to create a setting that is mutually compatible with the programme of</text>
    <text>will be curated by Polly Brannan and will show the full range of her artistic horizons. I’m curious what you think the exhibition format will be like.D.  I think it will be very much like any exhibition format, from the very basic to the very sophisticated, and from the simplest to the most sophisticated. But unlike some exhibitions, the format of the Biennale will not necessarily correspond to the content of the exhibit. For example, the 2015 Venice Biennale did not have a curatorial focus, although the primary objective was to present the event as a ‘rich man’'s fantasy’. Similarly, the 2015 Museo Nacional de Arte Contempora presented a ‘rich man’’ fantasy’. Moving away from the biennale, what would be interesting for curatorial purposes, especially in an international context, is to ask questions such as these: What is the relationship between biennales and large-scale exhibitions? What are the curatorial tools and procedures for the production of large-scale exhibitions? What are the limits and parameters of the biennale? What are the parameters and boundaries of the virtual or augmented biennale? What are the spatial and temporal characteristics of the biennale? What are the virtual or augmented qualities of virtual or augmented exhibitions? What are the relations between curatorial and virtual exhibition? What is the relationship between biennales and the ‘digital double bind’ that is the condition of permanent exhibitions?D.  I’m not so sure that the curatorial hand would ever reach for such a fantasy. It seems to me that a biennale would always return to the same set of issues and desires, and perhaps this is a legacy of the traditional, non-elitist curatorial focus. It’s also true that for curators and art-historical amateurs the biennale has become the ‘art’,</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
