<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was also narrated by the historian and art critic David Hetherington, who has a new book forthcoming from Verso Books on the topic Future City. The exhibition was designed to be accessible to a general visitor to the country, but also to a visitor who has a cultural or historical interest in the region but isn’t interested in architecture. This visitor group was sought to explore the history of design in the region, and to find a place in the exhibition that suited their interests and style. For this, a diverse group of artists, from different places in the world, were invited to develop a project that reflected the cultural, historical or geographical history of the region in a way that is accessible to all. The project was then voted on by the artists and their team at Doha-based team Delphine Atangana &amp; Ahmed Awad, who selected six projects from the curatorial wish-list. The other projects were: DIY (digital natives of the Arab World), a research</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was curated as a joint venture between the two institutions, and the subjects appeared in both institutions’ museums. ‘A History of Umm al-Hiran’ is the subject of a new book by the curator, Joasia Krysa, entitled The House That Javed Jordan Built. Weale and Reed, who were also the curators of the 2014 and 2016 Venice Biennale curatorial plans, were part of a team that designed the exhibition.Krysa takes us from the city of her birth, the city with which she identifies, ‘the city that never sleeps’, to the city that is currently drafting a new government and economy – a city that will undoubtedly see a host of inward migrations as a result of the ongoing economic crisis – which is the second most populous city in the Arab peninsula. ‘Umm al-Hiran’ is a city on the edge of a vast desert, surrounded by hostile waters and populated mostly by nom</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was designed with the Manchester Museum and the Universities of Liverpool and Liverpool as the subject matter experts in their respective countries. The project was also designed by the firm Waverley &amp; Weale, based in Liverpool. The exhibition was presented at the Museum of Modern Art, London, and the Universities of Liverpool and Liverpool, Manchester, UK. The firm provides a range of historic and contemporary restoration and design services to heritage sites, as well as major museum exhibitions. Their first project for the Liverpool Biennial was commissioned by the city’s Museum of Modern Art, which is part of the Museums Commission, the national museum organisation. The project was to restore the facade of the defunct British Museum, which was gutted by a fire in 2014. The restoration project began in earnest in 2017, and we saw significant progress in 2017: the building was handed back to the city council, who are now running a public tender for a new use for the buildings, which should see the former behemoth transformed into a</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was conceived to document the history and contemporary development of design in Tunisia and Jordan, using modern and postmodern forms of art, architecture and heritage as materials for analysis and critique. The exhibition was curated with the assistance of the award-winning design studio ARRIV (Architecture Interactive Research Unit), London, UK. After being selected for the commission, the projects were developed into interactive experiences using ARRIV’s 3D Model maker, Create 3D, and ARRIV’s Narrative tool, Narrative 3D, which allowed viewers to become part of a design process through which ideas, designs and materials were gathered and gathered into one place. The project culminated in a major exhibition at the British Museum, New York, USA, in 2017. 	I was invited to design an experience for the Liverpool Biennial 2018 that would bring together the places I grew up, the city I now call home, and the places I expect to be visiting in five years' time.</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was designed to bring together a wealth of archival materials, digitised materials and archival images from the commission’s research, archiving and archival departments, as well as providing a rich resource of archival design, textile production and design, furniture making, architecture and interior decoration materials from the region. All of these elements were part of a larger project that Weale &amp; Reed developed in cooperation with The Museum of Modern Art, London. The project, which was partially funded by the Arts Council, was designed to bring together material from the varied archives of the museum, including archival photography, sound recordings, documents, drawings, photographic negatives, structural drawings and much more. The material was selected on the basis of its accessibility, historical value and incorporation into the wider context of the museum collection. Despite this broad range of subject matter, the material was carefully selected to be of interest to a number of distinct design sub-disciplines. The commission asked participants to select materials that would contribute to</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was designed with a conceptual design workshop at the Museum of Modern Art, London, in mind, and the design and planning process at Manchester University, Manchester, UK, in mind. The idea was to instigate a conversation about where and how design came from, and how it impacted on the world we live in, with the Museum of Modern Art in London and Manchester University in Manchester, UK. The exhibition was also designed to get people talking about design through what’s called a ‘context lock’ — a notion that’s often associated with synchronic historical periods, but is far more descriptive of the kind of design that’s being done in the world right now. This idea is that every object that comes into being has been architected in exactly the same way, with exactly the same intentions and properties, with absolute control over its shape and configuration. And so in that way, every design that’s being made today is structurally the same — even the</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was a response to the crisis of documentation that was threatening to swallow up the museum, and by doing so, the university. So it was a kind of ‘big picture’ that was showing in many places, and it was showing us things that our small commission might not. The real innovation of the exhibition was the way in which it was organized, and the way in which it was curated. The way in which it was organized was through a process called ‘curatorial rumination’. In the words of the historian Graham Smith, who edited the Manchester City Council's 2004 guide to urban exploration, this was a situation in which ‘the city’ was seen by the museum as an ongoing, evolving work of art that had to be continuously photographed and recorded (with electronic or analog photography, of course). The present, present and future were seen as possibilities for the city’s future, and the curatorial rumination process was used to generate and narrate this</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was also presented in conjunction with the 70th Venice Biennale, but we think it’s a good idea to explain how the project came about in the context of and in relation to the biennale itself. The idea was that the exhibition, which was conceived as a ‘life-sized’ version of the building in question, would sit alongside the historical works on a large, permanent, public display. The commissioning began in earnest in earnest in Liverpool, with visits to sites in Anfield and to a local bakery where the biennale was tentatively scheduled to be held on October 17th. The bakery itself had been approached by the Biennale about holding the exhibition alongside the bakery’s bakery, but the Biennale didn’t see it that way. It seemed to us that this was an odd approach, like trying to use a public museum to tell a private story. The approach we took was to ask, how can we tell a story in</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was also co-curated by the Museum of Modern Art, London, and the Manchester University Art Gallery. It opened on 11 October 2016. It was a rare and very welcome change from the usual student-led curatorial agenda of this exhibition, which was getting very boring. The young curators had a field day finding something to interest the young and empty galleries. It was as if there were underground art galleries here. The only people who weren’t invited to this exhibition were the curators from the exhibition, and they were all granted VIP access. So, there were young curators, art fans, art writers from all over the world, and a few people from the art dealer lobby. These people sought out the rare artworks, and bought them, or found them in specialist art markets. It was a rare opportunity to see some of the art being made now in places like Liverpool and Manchester. And it was a rare opportunity to see some of the art being made in the past</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Co-Operative Team}, with installation by Navid Handelsman, opened as part of the Biennale in Lisbon in 2016. In this exhibition, the curators chose six of their nine budget-supported projects to be exhibited in a retrospective in the city in 2018. Design Histories: Tunisia and Jordan By Peter OsborneThere are many different kinds of design. With the exception of the extraordinary, high-profile pieces, including some that are in museums for a reason, most of us don’t really know what we’re doing when we do design work. Inspired by the work of the American design firm Gibson, Weale and Reed, the British architectural historian Peter Weale established a special commission, funded by the Arts Council and Manchester University, to investigate the country’s architectural histories and the role of design in contemporary society. The commission was a collaboration between the Museum of Modern Art, London, and Manchester University, Manchester, UK. This exhibition was also co-curated by the Museum of Modern Art’s Kristin Forbes and Petra Kepschko, with the support of the Arts Council and the Kew Gardens, London, UK. The exhibition itself was curated by Geoffrey Pullum, Curator for the British Museum, New York, USA; Judy Wood, Curator for the British Museum, London, UK; and Meera Sethi, Curator for the British Museum, New York, USA. Together, they explored the ways in which architectural histories, curatorial and archival research could be used to tell stories and connect diverse communities in a way that is both powerful and simultaneously accessible. Their project was part of the exhibition The Architecture of Cities: War and Peace, presented by the British Antarctic Survey at the British Museum, London, UK, and part of the exhibition The Architecture of Neglected Cities, presented by the New York Public Library, New York, USA. Together, they were part of the curatorial team for</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital
    <text>accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital media.Art is made public through what is, in effect, what the biennial is: the art is made visible through what it represents. In this sense, it uses its inherent unpredictability to its advantage. And given the unpredictable nature of the art world, it is also said to profit from art, especially when it is made visible through an art institution. In The Artist, Judith Butler describes how the sudden proliferation of visual artworks and image macros in the 1990s prompted artists to create worlds that were neither static nor predetermined, but could be created with just about anything. Such is the inherent unpredictability of the art world. It is easy to get swept away by the randomness of it all, to lose track of time, and perhaps all of this is unavoidable, but what is particularly remarkable about the biennial is the way in which it is capable of awakening us, making us something other than mediators of it. It makes us artists, curators, artists’ assistants,</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital media.8 In this analysis, the public realm is a virtual annex of the museum, something that the museum patron can cart around in any direction, and the media that is the interface between the physical and digital worlds. Media such as the mobile phone, the blog, the social network, the DVD, the games consoles, the magazines, the streams, the DVDs, the photos, the videos, the instant messaging services, the blogs, the forums, the social events, the shopping networks, the forums, the forums, the forums, the social networking services, and so forth. And, as I said, the public realm is an idealised way of bringing together disparate elements, drawing people together, and thereby creating a shared space. But it is also possible to create a ‘public realm’ in the shape of a museum, a kind of urban playground in which visitors can walk through freely without having to ask anyone to do anything in return. Such a realm could draw visitors away from</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital media. The intention was to do this, in part, to make the art public domain so that it could again be ‘collected and utilized’ by artists, curators, art writers and other stakeholders. But there was a problem with the idea of public realm, a problem with the idea of public space. The concept of public space itself, like so many other elements of the urbanisation agenda, is being systematically erased. Any notion of public space is being increasingly transformed, not by those with a political, economic or social agenda, but by those with no political, economic or social agenda at all. One might even agree that the biennial is part of a much broader trend of diminished cultural power in urban environments. But there is a way of saying what the role of art institutions is in the public sphere, and what the public realm is becoming. That was one of the aims of the Bristol Biennial.  The second was to create a public realm around the city, by</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital media. As a curatorial exercise, the biennial is an art project that begins with a bang and builds up from there. Curators and art writers are among those who find themselves thrust into the middle of what is often described as ‘the biennial question’. As one curator put it to me, the ‘biennial question’ is: ‘How can art be made in the present, today?’ If the answer is ‘today’ and not ‘later’ then the ‘biennial question’ should be: ‘How can art be made in the future, in radically new ways?’ The answer to this question tends to be a resounding yes. This is perhaps why biennials often declare their intentions to be works in progress, a process whereby ‘revealing more and exploring more’ may be done in the museum or gallery. In other words, they’re there to be encountered,</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital media. But this is the fantasy of power projection, the work of an organisation that needs to be continually replenished in order to survive and offer the fiction of permanence to an ever-expanding audience. It does not seem to me that the biennial has any such power. The biennial can and should occupy a specific position in the art world, and it is this ‘position’ that biennials like to claim, but it is not necessarily the ‘position’ that generates the art world’. I think that the real power of the biennial is that which comes from within, and so it’s this constant need to be seen to be what it actually is: what it claims to be.  At a deeper level, biennials are about the spectacle of art being made elsewhere in the world, in locations and settings that are not necessarily located in a particular city. They are about the difference between the superficial and the deep representations of art</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital media. This mirrors something else that biennials do: they produce what they call a publishing of the unseen, but which is in fact an accentuation of the visible. If you’re looking for an example of how the biennial can and should engage with and contribute to the art world’s life, you’ll find many contemporary artist’s exhibitions and biennials doing exactly that.But if you want to know whether what we as artists do produces or contributes to the world around us, and how we live our lives, you need to know what the biennial does and does not. And you need to know what it means to make art. In order to know whether what the biennial does or does not is meaningful to us, or to other artists, you need to know what art means. I believe that what the Biennial has done since its inception in 1988 has, through its complexity, generated or created many lives and many ideas about art and</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital media and social media. This is a public realm, not an art world; it’s what the marchers on the Mall in DC managed to do on the first day of the Biennale; it’s what the 4th generation of Irish immigrants did with their five acres in the city; it’s what the residents of Lower Manhattan tried to do with a block party in Greenwich Village; it’s what the residents of Richmond, British Columbia, tried to do with a mini-constitution; it’s what the residents of Minneapolis tried to do with a city council retreat in the summer of 2009; it’s what the residents of Venice, Italy, tried to do with an independent district council in 2009; it’s what the residents of Lahore, Pakistan, tried to do with a parallel, not-for-profit, not-for-profit organisation; it’s what the residents of Tianjin, China, tried</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital media and social media. This public realm concept is similar to that of the city, but it does have one crucial difference – in the digital age it is possible to ‘pin’ things to a computer and render them invisible, to render ‘real-time’ and so on.1  This sounds trivial, but tracing the power of the biennial in the social and cultural imagination can be seen as a project that could potentially end up bringing down powerful institutions – or at least, things that people create with their own brains.  In the end, of course, it is the artists, the curators, the art writers, the administrators of art sites, the PR departments of museums and so forth who exert significant influence over what is or is not considered aesthetically significant within the visual arts.  Art is often seen as a necessary evil that is often over-emphasised, but the other important art-making activities – such as poetry, painting and gathering – are</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital media. The very notion that art can be produced by a public audience – or that it could be something else entirely – was a turning point in my thinking. 	Artworks created using the Biennial as a platform will be commissioned and supported by the Biennial with materials and strategies designed to work with the public realm envisaged by the biennial. The biennial will place the audience at the centre of its creation, and through engagement with that audience, as well as facilitating the dispersal and movement of artworks across the geographically diverse site. The audience will be the instigators of their own creation and will be the media through which the arts will be made manifest. This is a very powerful combination. 	In the words of the biennial itself, ‘the audience is the future’. And it is this very idea of the audience that we must consider when considering new media, big data and new art forms. The audience is the future because it is the platform on which</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the museums and cultural organisations that were instrumental in putting on the festival. The intention was to show how art is made by people, and how this is realized through the use of tools and techniques that were created or adapted by these organisations. Later, I asked my wife what she thought of when she’d seen what the makers of the devices we’ve made could do with the art that was being generated by the biennial. She suggested that perhaps the real power of the biennial is that it causes such a strong reaction in the art world that it produces results that are unexpected and unexpected ones. Perhaps we can see the power of the biennial in the attempt to create what it calls a ‘public realm’ by mobilising artists, curators, artists’ unions, art writers, artists’ assistants and so forth to collate and analyse what has, in the words of the biennial itself, been ‘rendered invisible’ by the proliferation of digital media. While there is certainly power in gathering this data and bringing it to bear on a biennial event, there is also a danger that such a public realm could be taken over by those with a political agenda or powerful economic instruments such as those described in the 2005 book   The Art of Not Being Governed, by the same title author.10. The biennial as a curatorial tool. The biennial has become an instrument through which the social and political meaning of art is actively generated and negotiated. It is continuously (re)negotiated in relation to the curatorial and art school ‘primary and secondary’, as it were. The art biennial has, since its advent in 1991, been organised by and for the elite. It is impossible to underestimate the role of the art biennial in the neoliberal transformation of contemporary art’s social contexts and social relations, and the consequent social tensions that flow from it. The significance of the biennial as a cur</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities
    <text>accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities on the Prairies fuelled the expansion of the railway network, which in turn fed the growth of the city's post office, hotels and other commercial centres. The growth of the urban post was fuelled by the growth of the ‘mile post’ – the new economy of letters – and the associated rise in post office volume that accompanied it. The post office was a strategic innovation that expanded rapidly during the twentieth century, but its future appears to have been heavily influenced by the interests of the financial sector, which viewed technological innovation as a potential way to enrich themselves at the expense of society. It is not clear that the financial services industry was particularly interested in infrastructure or transit in the way that the Railway Club was, and the post office was less clear about what kinds of socio-political impact it might have. But the fact that it operated largely as an independent organisation with a clear, strategic interest in the technology it was developing seems to have played a role in its success. The post office was a</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities to travel by rail was driving up the price of rail passes, and the demand for more capacity to cater to growing passenger populations was growing. The demand for more cars also meant adding ever more freight cars to the network, which in turn meant adding ever more cars to the roads. A shortage of road space meant unbridged stretches of the Trans Canada Highway, and the Junction at Spruce Grove became a ghost town during rush hour. In an attempt to combat this growing congestion, the Railway Club embarked on a scheme of over-the-air (OTA) updates of the Trans Canada Highway network that allowed commuters to access the newly upgraded route via their cars. The aim of these updates was to repair or replace worn down or destroyed vehicles, and to add new tunnels and bridges. The Club’s financial backer in Vancouver at this time was the Canada Lands Company (CLC), a land-grant corporation established in 1897 by the Canadian government to develop large tracts of land under the Crown for</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities to carry them meant that the railway needed new ways of supporting the growing membership, and the Railway Club was born. The club’s first convention was held in Liverpool's Victoria County Hall on November 20, 1888, and the first issue of the magazine was published on December 8, 1889. The second and third editions followed in early 1900. The magazine was founded in 1901 by Norman Mailer and it carried articles on everything from photography to wildlife and the homeless. The first issue of the journal was published on October 26, 1902. The first issue of the magazine was distributed free of charge to members via post. By the end of that year, the magazine had over 800 covers and over 1,000 illustrations. The cover image is a stock image from the cover of the first issue. The back cover image is a photograph of a livery horseÂ chosen by the editor to advertise a train. The image is a stock photo from the cover of the second issue. The journal continued to be published</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities to travel further afield also fuelled the growth of the club, which continued to be a regular visitor to the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway platforms in the early 1900s. During this decade, the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway was absorbed into the Canadian Pacific Railway, and the Railway Club became a subsidiary company of the new Canadian National Railway (CNR). The aim of the new company was to expand the network it already had built, creating a chain of interconnected passenger and freight railways linking Vancouver to Montreal. The Railway Club responded by creating a subsidiary company, the Northern Access Railway Company (N.A.R.C.), to expand the network even further: ‘N.A.R.C. is a non-profit public limited partnership established to build, maintain and operate the next generation of intermodal transit facilities in Canada’s North Atlantic Sector.’ The new company also set up a subsidiary, the Northern Access Rail Company (N.A.R.C.). During</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities to accommodate them was fuelling a city’s rapid population growth, which was also feeding into the growth of a suburban railway industry. The rise of the suburban railway coincided with a decrease in the size of the city, which meant that the railway stations that were once bustling with passengers were now serving as ground-floor offices, or more accurately, bedrooms for workers. The number of commuters in the late nineteenth century was much less than the number who commute to and from work in this city today, but they certainly increased their numbers on a regular basis. The population density in the city at the turn of the twentieth century was approximately 130,000 souls per square kilometre. By 1960, however, this had dropped to approximately 80,000 souls per square kilometre. The rapid growth of the metros during the decade was also feeding into the growth of the metropolis, which in turn was feeding into the metropolis-building boom that would give way to a citywide halt to urban growth in</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities to travel further afield fuelled a rapid expansion of passenger and freight service along the CPR’s lines, which in turn, sent the railway scrambling. In an attempt to address the increasing speed of transit, the Railway Club established a subsidiary company, the Northern Pacific Railway (NPR), established in 1889 and renamed the 1890 Montreal Exposition in honour of the Canadian Pacific War hero Captain John Kerr. The aim of the exposition was to display the latest in steam-driven engineering and related technology, while showcasing the advantages of the new railway over all other modes of transport. The NPR’s president, William Cooper, considered the exposition a major step in the advancement of his nascent railway company. ‘The first International Exhibition of Canada took place in Ottawa in 1887, and William Cooper, the company president, noted that while the technology of automobiles ‘was not advanced to such a pitch as to enable rapid transit of large masses’, the importance of the exposition remained the same.</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities on the post was increasing, and technological innovation was clearly not a primary consideration in the club’s decision-making. At a conference in 1889, representatives of the Canadian Pacific Railway (CPR) expressed interest in opening a second station in Vancouver, but the Federal government’s post was firmly established in place and the project was effectively quixotic. And yet another reason to celebrate the inevitable.Download this article as PDFEmily PringlePhotograph courtesy of Emily PringlePhotograph courtesy of National Film and Archive ServicePhotograph courtesy of National Film and Archive ServicePhotograph courtesy of National Film and Archive ServiceEmily Pringle is a photographer and writer whose work has been exhibited at the Venice Biennale, South as a State of Mind, the New York and New York Gallery, and the National Film and Archive Service. Her photographs have been featured in cultural publications including the New York Times, the New Yorker, the Washington Post, the Los Angeles Times, the Village Voice,</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities fuelled an expansion of passenger services, but the rapid growth of population density during this time also put a great strain on the already limited water and food resources of the region. As the city grew larger, the Club began to struggle with the strain on its limited infrastructure. In 1890, for example, overcrowding threatened the vital water source of the YMCA – which was already suffering from desalination problems – when the YMCA was forced to close a spring that provided drinking water for much of the campus. The Club was forced to close a second spring shortly afterwards due to overcrowding. Despite these difficulties, the Club continued to expand its services to the local population, and even to visitors during the Depression years. At one point, the Club even offered free housing to struggling professionals attempting to access the Club’s lucrative real estate market.At the same time, the Club was becoming increasingly aware that its non-profit status was not 100% secure, and that political forces were actively trying</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities to handle them led to the development of counter-systems that combined the railway company’s control over the terrain with that of the non-profit, creating a new paradigm of ownership and control. 	[1] National Post, November 18, 1888, p. A1.Download this article as PDFMark MiodownikMark Miodownik is an artist, writer, educator and researcher. His research focuses on the social and political history of post-Impact Technology (near-ultra-modernism, cybernetics and agro-industrial society), and the social implications of biotechnology and autonomous technology. His publications include numerous essay collections and more recently, the collection of essays ‘On Mutant Life’ published in New Media Ecology. His writing has also been featured in the New York Times, Washington Post, Los Angeles Times, New Republic, New Scientist, Wired Magazine, and others. His new book, Devoid of Identity: Race, Identity</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the Federated Clubs. All rights reserved, reproduced with kind permission of the writer(s).The Railway Club was founded in 1887 and its mission statement read as follows: ‘To support and encourage the railway in its various operations’. The Railway Club was a non-profit organisation established in 1887 and carried out primarily as a postal service for letters to the board of the Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway: ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ is the oldest non-proprietary railway in Canada, and ‘Liverpool &amp; North Atlantic Railway’ was the first non-commercial railway in Canada. The Railway Club’s early investments were in the construction of new tracks and tunnels, and the modernization of existing ones. By the end of the decade, however, the club was operating in a precarious financial situation and struggling with a maintenance backlog that sometimes forced it to close tunnels and bridges over its opposition to mechanising infrastructure. The demand for faster trains and better facilities to carry them meant that the railway needed new ways of funding and supporting its operations. The Railway Club, as a vertically integrated organisation, had access to both public and private funds, so a public offering to the railroads was an option. The club’s initial public offering was ungenerous: investors lost money on the stock, and most of the profit went to shareholders. The loss of revenue streams was a by-product of the industry standardising on rapid transit as the solution to a transit problem that could not be sustained with existing infrastructure. So the club’s early capital projects were transit only in name only. But transit only goes so far, and in the late 1880s, the advent of electric transit meant that the railway could begin to offer longer-term service to communities along the route of the newly electrified lines. So the Railway Club became transit-oriented and transitioned into a non-profit public organisation, fully committed to supporting a growing network of transit along the routes</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience.
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience. Discoveries and achievements in the Biennial’s archive The Biennial is a rare example of an institution that has survived both the economic and the social catastrophe that characterises contemporary art today. Its business plan, developed over the past twenty years, has been a combination of public relations (its main form of work since the Biennale in 1992), institutional capital (its main form of art since the 1990s, and its ongoing work even after), and creative perforations (the art world’s particular form of art, which the Biennial has frequently repeated over the years). Its current financial situation is questionable, and its future seems equally uncertain. Nevertheless, the Biennial remains a centre of activity for art and visual culture in the city, and has been for some time. Its current capacity to engage with the city and its diverse cultures is an artifact of its status as an institution within the tourism industry. Its ability to create genuinely local experiences of being in the city is another</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience.He was also the curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2013, and curated the entry for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2016. He curated the entry for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2017, and curated the entry for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2019. He is the curator of the forthcoming The Polyphony of Images: Art, Architecture, and the Making of the Twentieth-Century Venetian City. He curated the entry for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2021, and curated the entry for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2024. I spoke to him by phone from New York.You both work for the Biennale. What role do you see arts and culture playing in the twenty-first century? Hayden: I think that there’s a kind of physical manifestation of the ‘present’: the fact that we’re both working in the same city, in the same city</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience. He curated the 2013 Sussex International Film Festival, where he collaborated with Jon Millard on the exhibition, and the 2014 Venice Biennale, where he worked alongside Carol Emshwiller and Lightroom Museum for a second year. He curated the 2015 Venice Biennale, where he worked alongside Carol Emshwiller and Lightroom Museum for a third year in the historic space of the Giardini. He was a curator for the 2016 Singapore International Film Festival, where he collaborated with Carol Emshwiller and Lightroom Museum for a second year in the Giardini. He was a curator for the 2017 Mexico City Biennale, where he collaborated with Carol Emshwiller and Lightroom Museum for a second year in the Giardini. He curated the 2018 Venice Biennale, where he collaborated with Carol Emshwiller and Lightroom Museum for a third year in the historic space of the Giardini. He was a curator for the 2018 Songdo International Film</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience. Interview with Hayden Christensen 	[1] Pablo Neruda, ‘On Communal Knowledge and Necessary Actions’,  	Interstellaria del Passato, ed. Rafael Cardoso, Ch. 12, Triennale of Venice, 2012, p.103. [2] The Biennale also commissioned a number of new works by local artists, including new work by Rafael Cardoso, Colline Thomas, Rebecca Harpe, and many others. See:  http://www.bbc.com/news/uk-england-liverpool-24666941. [3] The Biennale website now includes a wider section on www.biennale.org. [4] The Biennale press release announcing the closure of the Tadros Fund was issued on 13 April 2017. [5] Sven Spieker and Christian Körner, ‘On the Cinema Monograph</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience. Tom is a member of the executive committee of the Transplant International Forum and was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2014. He curated the 2014 Venice Biennale, which was part of the '16 core' and part of a '17' series of exhibitions. He curated the 2015 Venice Biennale, part of the '15 core' series and part of the '16 core' series. He curated the 2016 Venice Biennale, part of the “'17' core'” series and part of the “'18'” core'” series of exhibitions.He is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His previous projects include Surplus-Books (2015), a new exhibition format for unused, historic and battered media from around the world, and the book series Stored Sentences (2016–17), on the archive and their connections to the present. He was a curator for the San Francisco–based</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience. He is the author of  	Contemporary Art and  	Postmodern Art: Contemporaneity, celebrity and contemporaneity in critical theory. The current project is his latest book, Basecamp: Urban Alternatives to Campus Life. Tom is a regular contributor to the online magazine, The New Inquiry, and the online journal, PLATEAU, where he has written extensively on a range of social, urban and ecological topics. He is the curator of the English language version of  	Postmodern Art: Contemporaneity, celebrity and contemporaneity in critical theory. The current project is his latest book, Basecamp: Urban Alternatives to Campus Life. 	[1] Taken from the October 2013 issue of Basecamp, Issue #2, with contributions from Sue Bell Yank, Louise Hui and many others.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor of English and Department Chair of the Department of</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience.Interior of the Alon Foundation Building, Alon-Georges St, Alon, Greece. Collection Georges St. © Alon Georges St. / Alon Georges St. All rights reserved, DACS 2015.PreviousNextInterior of the Alon Foundation Building, Alon-Georges St, Alon, Greece. Collection Georges St. © Alon Georges St. / Alon Georges St. All rights reserved, DACS 2015.Alon Georges St. in Alon, Greece. The Greek Theatre - Alon Georges Stearns. Photo: Tom Vandeputte.PreviousNextInterior of the Alon Foundation Building, Alon Georges Stearns, Alon, Greece. Collection Georges Stearns. Photo: Tom Vandeputte.The Alon Foundation Building, Alon Georges Stearns, Alon, Greece. Photo courtesy of the Alon Foundation.PreviousNext</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2014, and curated the US entry for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2016. He curated the Venice Biennale that followed in 2018, and curated the Venice Biennale that followed in 2020. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2025, and curated the 2018 and US entries in the Venice Biennale that followed in 2030. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in Twenty-First Century that followed in Fourteen Curators. He curated the Venice Biennale that followed in Three Musketeers that followed in Fourteen Curators. He curated the Venice Biennale that followed in Twenty-First Century that followed in Twenty-First Century that followed in Fourteen Curators. He curated the 2018 and US entries in the Venice Biennale that followed in Twenty-First Century that followed in Twenty-First Century that followed in Fourteen Curators. As</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience. He curated the 2012 Venice Biennale, where the 12-site biennale took place, and the 2013 Venice Biennale that followed in 2014. He curated the 2015 Venice Biennale, where the international audience was invited to participate in a virtual exhibition of the same name. He has written for this publication, including for the Illustrated London News, the Daily Mail, The New York Times and The Telegraph. He is the recipient of numerous awards and mentions, including the 2012 British Museum Record Prize for Creative Media, the 2013 John Moores Journalism Prize for Journalism at the University of Glasgow, the 2013 Guggenheim Prize for Documentary Writing, and the 2013 Guggenheim Prize for Documentary Writing. He was shortlisted for the 17th Oxford Documentary Film Festival, the 2014 John Lennon Biennial, the 2014 John Lennon &amp; Yoko Ono Lennon: Lennon, John and Yoko Ono, Lennon, John: A Portrait, 1987, and the</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, co-curated by Hayden and Tom Vandeputte, won't happen. Undoing the damage doesn't sit well with some in the arts community, who see parallels between the relocation of the Biennial and the mass exhibition industry that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s. In a move that many see as undemocratic, the Biennial has been attempting to reestablish its relationship to the city in recent years. In an attempt to restore some of that historical intimacy, the Biennial has commissioned a series of new works to be displayed in the main exhibition venue, as well as online at the biennial. Tom Vandeputte is the curator of the English language online at the Biennial. His latest project,  	Spaces of the Suburbs, was one of the most exhibited in the Venice Biennale. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2012, and has extensive documentary and photographic archival and contemporary art experience. He curated the 2013 New Media biennale,  	Postmodern Venice, and the 2014 British postmodernist retrospective,  	Postmodern Venice Redevelopment. He curated the 2015 New Media biennale,  	Postmodern Venice, and the 2016 British postmodernist retrospective,  	Postmodern Venice. He is the curator of the upcoming 5th Annual Venice Biennale, to open in 2017. He has curated the  	14th Annual of the ARTnews/Bienal de São Paulo, and the 11th Annual of the Neue Zu?rich Biennale, to open in 2018. He curated the 2016 Italian pavilion,  	Postmodern Venice, and the 2017 Hungarian pavilion,  	Postmodern Venice Redevelopment. He was a curator for the Venice Biennale that followed in 2017, and curated the 2018 German pavilion,  	</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �
    <text>accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �sit, ‘pick flowers, ‘talk birds, ‘take pictures, and so forth’ – part of a broader public-goods sectoral restructuring is part of a wider ‘public realm strategy’.3 	Such is the  	logic of the ‘public realm’. 	But the ‘public’ has two  	different kinds of people. There are the arrogant, obviously aware of their privileged position, who think, rightly, that they own the public realm and that everyone else has to submit to their will. There are the rest of us, ‘commoners’ who are ‘fair game’ for their superior ideas and behaviour. 	There is a difference, then, between the kind of person who thinks he owns the public realm and the kind who actually does. The former kind is arrogant and entitled; the latter is patient, thoughtful and humble.  	An example of</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �and ‘think freely’ – but more of the delightful, but less of the inhabitable. Cultural tourism is part of what Norman Green calls ‘the metropolis’ that is increasingly mediated through data (emphasis added): transformed into physical locations and commodities (location, accommodation, food, water, etc.), but more of the transformed into virtual locations of data capture and delivery.3   	Similarly, the metropolis is part of a globalized globalized economy that increasingly depends on data (production, distribution, consumption, etc.), but more of the inhabitable: cities with their parks, their factories, their traffic jams, etc. – are subject to the technologies of photography and maps, but more of the ‘natural’ infrastructures that arise from the land and urban infrastructures that migrate there (traffic, electricity, water, gas).  	So, too, is the metropolis transformed by the exchange of images (photography has</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �and ‘talk, ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, ‘and ‘talk’ – but also with art’s natural ability to engender collective action. 	The public realm provides us with images and a landscape for thought, but it does not envision, articulate or represent the concrete possibilities of a future that is fully attainable only for a few fortunate souls with access to a place like Manhattan. That realm is the realm of the celebrity, of course; but it is also the realm of the islander who happens to be visiting ‘the island’. And that is the point: that is, the island is the realm of the celebrity and the metropolis, but it is also the realm of the islander who happens to be a celebrity. 	The main reason why celebrities visit the island is to be celebrated – to sell products, to shoot movies or to perform in festivals. But ‘the island’ is</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �and ‘ambulate’ freely – but which is also a highly profitable for capital to inhabit in its current form, especially given the island’s precarious condition. The reclamation of the natural spaces and natural settings of the island as part of a larger ‘public realm’ project is part of a wider ‘public imagination’ project that seeks to replace the lost time and labour with more profitable images of the island in perpetuity. And these images are often apocalyptic. The image of the bulldozer and the demon is often a prop in the service of a capitalist enterprise. 	In recent years, however, a ‘public realm’ has emerged on the other side of the globe, where the image of the islander is regularly juxtaposed with images of fantastical creatures, exotic landscapes and exotic cultures. Here, the image of the islander is often juxtaposed with images of fantastical creatures, exotic cultures and exotic labour. 	In  	</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �and ‘ambulate’ – partaken in by art and culture, partaken in by architecture and partaken in by every form of media imaginable. The public realm of the island is to a large extent comprised of the media of today, but through a process of accretions, and these media are to a growing extent online. 	A public realm is one in which images and images matter, and images matter in a way that is uncorrelated with the accessibility of images, or, well, images. In other words, it is ephemeral, subject to the conditions of its accessibility, and capable of surviving in its place, even though it is not present or present at any moment. 	So we can say that today’s images are of cities only insofar as they are images of cities, but this is only possible because of the inaccessibility of the island’s cities to the modes of mobility and mobility accrual of today’</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �and ‘dig our own holes’ – partaken by nature in perpetuity. This is part of what Lecrae calls ‘the metainterface’, a name given to the speculative, real-estate-backed derivative forms of colonialism and neocolonialism that seek to capitalize on the openness and otherings of the natural spaces and the landscape in an image that stands for nothing and signifies a lot. It is a proto-policymaking project that seeks to replace the image of the natural ‘public realm’ with that of the urbanized citizen.  	The metainterface is a global phenomenon that is deeply related to the rise of neoliberalism, but is also intimately linked to the movements of ecological destruction that it purveyes. It emerges as a consequence of the logic of capitalist globalization, the very economic logic that Lecrae describes as being at odds with the dignity of the natural world. It is to a large</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �daydream, ‘ambulate’ and ‘agitate’ – but which is also a site of active, sometimes creative, play. Play that can ‘overlap’ with the active, sometimes creative, sometimes destructive dynamic of the built environment.  	As a playground for children, the built public realm is a good thing. It offers places where people gather to connect, exchange, exchange, travel, eat, sleep and breathe. It is a setting in which people can ‘agitate’ – consciously or unconsciously people often exaggerate the benefits of such spaces to generate buzz and attract investors, as when images of fast-food outlets line the trolley tracks outside the Harbourfront Station. It is a ‘public space’ that people can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, ‘daydream’ and ‘ambulate’ within. It is a space for ‘rhythmic patterns’</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �daydream, ‘ambulate and ‘consume nature’ – the public realm of the built environment is to some extent a re-constituted image of the island. It is a space in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, ‘daydream, ‘ambulate and ‘consume nature’, in the language of the built environment. It is a ‘public realm’ where we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, ‘daydream, ‘ambulate and ‘consume nature’. But more and more we are left to contemplate the landscape, and the walk, and the swish, and the loll, and the shimmy, and the shimmy, and the shimmy, and the shimmy, and the shimmy, and the shimmy, and the shimmy, and the shim</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �and ‘talk’ without getting pooped on’ by cars, trucks, buildings and other infrastructure. Architecture is a much more natural way to inhabit the natural spaces of the island, while also serving as a buffer between the highly visible islands and the increasingly threatened ‘public realm’. The ‘public’ is displaced from the island’ by the development of a metropolis on the one hand, and the increasingly visible ‘public realm’ on the other. How to Think About the Recent Crisis of the Island Chronicle David Harvey,  	Talking Point: ‘The Island’ (2014), part of a series of six essays in the October 2014 issue of the journal (published monthly by the Pacific Science and Film Society), frames the recent crisis of the Hawaiian Islander, Hilo Nui, as a symptom of a broader problem: gentrification. Harvey narrates the encroachments of development on the island’s natural resources, the</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of these commercial real-estate investors, who – as we shall see – use their investment to alter the character of the island in their image-conscious city. 	But the commercial interests that profit from the image of the island outweigh the social needs of the islanders in the making of its future. The commercial imperative to produce images of the island in order to boost stock prices and the value of the share capital of the built environment is at odds with the social imperative to inhabit the island in perpetuity. The reclamation of the island as a ‘public domain’ is part of a wider ‘public realm’ project that seeks to liberate not only images, but also language, concepts and concepts – including images of oneself – from the public realm of development.2 	So, too, with the public realm – which is to say, the island’s natural spaces and landscape in which we can ‘walk, ‘swim, ‘sleep, �and ‘talk shop’ – part of a global capitalist circulation. As a landscape that rises and falls with the flow of capitalist circulation, the island is a landscape for the occupying classes, but it is primarily a landscape for tourists and mainland tourists (including me) to inhabit. Its character is its ability to capture our attention and keep us on our toes. 	Such is the  	narrative of growth. As we saw, it is not just the aesthetic of the islander’s ascent – in the book I narrate the part that happens inside the islander – but the underlying political and economic dynamics of the ‘public realm’. And although the image of the islander – who I identify as a narrator because I inhabit the island – may capture our attention, this does not necessarily map onto a future with or without the islander. The image of the islander that emerges from the images that we take of the islander comes from a minority</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So
    <text>should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So, the challenge for the future urban planner is this: how do we enable culture to coexist with the city in ways that are not necessarily ideologically opposed to what the city is trying to do? 	In a perfect world, the answer to this question would be a comprehensive housing programme for everyone, but right now, especially in the US, we’re not that lucky. The financial incentives for urban growth in much of the country are very strong, and cultural institutions that provide a safe haven for artists and their ideas to develop quickly find themselves embroiled in battles over building height restrictions or access to funds that could really help the city. 	Another challenge for the future urban planner is what to do with all the art that’s produced in an area. As a starting point, consider an area with an area of strong art culture, where people tend to gather around galleries, museums, and the arts produced in that area. The challenge is to decide what to do with the art that</text>
    <text>should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So, although the aim of a community art institution might be to provide a home for people to live together and make art, it is also about supporting an institution’s mission in a way that is mutually beneficial to both. The mission of a community land trust is about creating and sustaining a community of people who share the land and the responsibility for producing and using the land, while the mission of a community land trust is about creating and sustaining a community of people who share the values and beliefs of the community. As such, the two missions are not mutually exclusive, and whilst the mission of the Community Land Trustees Association might have been to create an institution to do creative things in the city, its primary role was to ensure that the values and beliefs of the community were incorporated into the institution’s mission statement. 	Similarly, although the mission of a community art institution might be to provide a place for people to live together and make art, its primary role was about creating an environment</text>
    <text>should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So, there was a shift in attitude, and a shift in control. The shift was: towards the arts institution, towards people who could build long-term relationships with the land, towards those who could think beyond the immediate community use-case. 	However, the shift also caused some fundamental organisational changes – which are still needed for such a to fully engage the community. The main thing is to understand that the control that people have over their community is much more powerful than the art institutions realise. The question is: how do we empower communities to take over their own organisations? In the 1980s, people were more open to the idea of alternative art forms, but now institutions realise that they are much more valuable when they are in co-responsibility for generating wealth, rather than being in the hands of the people. 	So, the question becomes: how do we create partnerships with communities to allow people to take over an organisation? There are a number of approaches that have been tried</text>
    <text>should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So, in other words, a community garden could become a hybrid farm, supporting the arts institution in the process, while at the same time encouraging independent development – supporting artists in the process, but also supporting the community as a whole. 	But what is the alternative to a hybrid farm? What is the organic or ‘natural?’ model of community gardening? In my view, the alternative to hybrid farming is horizontal farming. Horizontal farming is the act of growing crops alongside animals, usually plants, rather than following the traditional path of rooted animals (including humans) in an attempted to replicate the act of farming. For example, the Growing Presence organic farm I started growing carrots alongside beetles and pollen, lamburge, ferns, sheep and goose, as well as other insects and worms, radishes, squash and okra, tomato-juice plants, cabbages and onions,</text>
    <text>should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So, the mission of a community land trust, or CLT, should be informed by the objectives of a local government, or more specifically, the priorities of a local government at the time. It is not enough to say that the Community Land Trustees at the San Francisco Art Institute (SFMI), who were elected in 1999, ‘reached a consensus’ regarding the direction of the institution. It is imperative that the objectives of the CLT be responsive to the purposes of the SFMI at the time and remain responsive to those purposes in the future. The term ‘community land trust’ has become synonymous with the term ‘public domain’, but this is not necessarily true. The public domain includes both private and public domain land. If the public domain includes both public and private domain land, then the public domain includes only what the public desires, which often times includes things that are not meant to be shared or distributed. In other words, the public has a clear</text>
    <text>should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So, the mission of a community land trust is to support the artist’s mission, but in a non-institutional way). 	In this model, the community is not the administrator of the trust (it is instead a patron), but the land trust is an entity that supports the artist’s mission through services and instruments that are institutionalised and power-sharing based on patronage. In this model, the community has the capacity to determine what the trust should be doing, and to levy a fee (which would fund the trust, in perpetuity) to enable that determination. 	However, in most models, the community is not so empowered; institutional resources and their trustees are vested with broad, political-ideological, and economic-institutional power. In most models, the community is left to make such determinates, but in reality there is no such thing as a ‘community land trust’ in the US, nor anywhere else in the world. The US</text>
    <text>should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So, the mission of a community land trust is to provide a home for people to live together, nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together. Yet another example of cultural capture, perhaps more iconic than the Getty Museum or the Global Art Initiative. 	Once again, cultural theorists and artists’ unions can help us understand the logic of  	taking culture as a commodity and placing it at the service of the collective. 	The logic of cultural capture is simple: if its mission is to provide a home for people to live together, then why put up with the mundanity of overcrowding, homelessness, poverty, alienation and alienation of all kinds? Why not just create artist-owned co-operatives and give them a try? Why not just  	start a community land trust and see what happens? Why not just  	start a Community Land Trust and see what happens? Why not just call it a Community Land Trust and</text>
    <text>should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So, the mission of a community art institution should be directed not just to the institution itself, but to the wider community. I believe that Community Arts is at the centre of this new progressive turn in community engagement, and that the mission of a community arts institution should be directed towards the very thing that was historically at odds with the social organisation: building socially for people to live together in harmony. 	However, this new radical veneer does not cover everything that is socially engaged with, nor is it complete to all engagement. 	For instance, as the mission of a community arts institution evolves, so does the need for a social secretary, and the social secretary has to be creative and flexible to meet the changing circumstances. So, while the mission of a community arts institution may shift to be more about promoting communal wellbeing, or just about providing a social interaction toolkit, the social secretary has other priorities. So, the social secretary has other priorities, and these</text>
    <text>should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So, the objective of a community garden should be compatible with the objectives of an institution, but distinct from the institutionalised aims of producing organic produce or building self-sustaining hydrogen fuel cells.  	To be eligible for funding from the Community Land Trust Fund, a community’s land use plan (LULU) must: 1. be collaborative and 2. address a set of priorities specific to the locality. A community’s land use plan can come from anywhere; it is just that it cannot be an institution or a charter member of an institution. Moreover, the LULU cannot legislate or create an ‘institution’ – a new private company or a new government agency would be far too powerful and far too entrenched in local government, both culturally and geographically, for that to be possible. 	Instead, a community’s land use plan should harness local resources to support a wide range of community-owned and -managed activities, including but</text>
    <text>should be curated by, and open to, local residents and artists’ communities’ participation. Community gardens are a natural extension of such a programme. Nevertheless, it would be foolish to assume that the aim of a local community garden would be to provide a home for everyone – indeed, this is what happened with the failed California 360 plan, which was predicated on the idea that a community would control the direction of a local art institution. Rather, the mission of a local community garden should be to provide a home for people to live together, to nurture community life, and to create an environment in which people can do things together – things that are not necessarily the things intended for the institution or the community to endorse or believe are appropriate. After the failed California 360, the city of San Francisco started a community land trust, which became a hybrid farm – housing the arts institution and its staff, developing a sustainable green space for community use, and supporting the artistic enterprise through a small fee.  	So, there was a conflict between the organic and the industrial into which the city’s Community Land Trusts were placed. Art’s mission is to produce art, and the city’s Community Land Trusts were seen as a way of financing the work. The conflict between the two functions – to produce and fund art – is often talked about, but rarely resolved. This is an art project, and art’s place is in the context of a social and political struggle. 	When the San Francisco Art Biennale was first proposed in 1999, a proposal to establish a permanent exhibition hall in the city centre, with a mandate to show contemporary and recent work from the biennale, was made in front of a group of community groups that had actively petitioned to have the hall changed to a place where they could live and work freely. The petitioners included local residents and artists, as well as a coalition of community leaders, community organisations and foundations. The Bi</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation,
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation, and while the concept may be traced back to the 1930s, its geographical spread and periodic appearance in different locales across the world today is a development largely caused by the anthropogenic global urbanisation project.  The first biennial in North America was in 1994, and the first in Europe in 1995.  The adoption of biennials as curating tools, and their increasing global spread, has come at a cost. The globalisation of art’s social impacts, and the increasing decentralisation of power and resources in the context of postindustrial landscapes, has placed curators in situations of increasing political and economic dependence on the city in which they operate. They are the enforcers of a new curatorial style influencing art’s social and economic trajectory, and this in turn has resulted in a massive increase in administrative costs. ‘Unique opportunities for ‘curatorial impact’ emerged during the 1990s and 2000s, and the Biennial fee has played a large part</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation, and while the significance of the past 20th century is often cited, it is often forgotten that the first biennials were created in the US in the aftermath of the second world war, and continue to be so to this day.  The term ‘biennial’ had been used by artists and arts organisations in the decades immediately after the war, but with the economic crash of 2008, the biennial entered the domain of the bankruptcy court, and quickly went from strength to strength. It is true that the biennial has traditionally had a very important role at the Venice Biennale, as a venue for shows of various kinds, and a significant exhibition of contemporary art in the main exhibition hall. But its true strength has always been its capacity to create a buzz, to introduce something new and different into the mix, and to offer a glimmer of hope to a city on the edge of a financial abyss. It is this glimmer of hope, this façade of civility</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation, and the concept as an exhibitionary form is much older than that. Its emergence in the 1990s coincided with the acceleration of new globalised information technologies, and the emergence of large art fairs that sponsored a proliferation of art-historical items, a proliferation of art-networks and a proliferation of art-exhibitions.  [1] See www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/for-students/how-to-get-involved/how-to-get-involved/ [2] See www.biennaleofsydney.com.au/for-students/how-to-get-involved/how-to-get-involved/how-to-get-involved/how-to-get-involved/how-to-get-involved/how-to-get-involved/how-to-get-involved/how-to-get-involved/how-to-get-</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation, and although the early history of the term is documented in numerous books and encyclopedias, the core concept and practice of the biennial is relatively new.  The Biennial was conceived by the Arts Council of Canada and the Museum of Contemporary Art in cooperation, and its first public exhibition was in Toronto (the Museum of Contemporary Art’s first public exhibition).  A second public exhibition, ‘The Contemporary Condition’, was held in June 2018 at the Museum of Modern Art and it was described by curator Peter Osborne as follows:  It is a question that has dogged Canadian art historians: What happens when contemporary art per se perishes? And what does it mean to perish? The current state of our cultural landscape, its cyclical character, and the fact that it is impossible to define or rank contemporary art merely by reference to art displayed in museums, stalls, and on the frontiers of contemporary art per se – all of this precludes a simple, direct and unified</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation, and while the significance of the art fair as a localised event can be traced to the mid-1990s, the significance of the art fair as a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial is much less clear.  A more precise definition of ‘the art fair’ would need to be developed, but there are various ways to think about the phenomenon, from its emergence as an art form in the US to the current wave of the biennial, which begins in 2017 in Paris and will run through October ‘Holidrama’ in Ankara.5  Biennials have always been important to contemporary art, and they continue to be so today, especially in the biennials of the world’s major cities. The importance of the art fair as a localised event cannot be understated. It marks the emergence of a new art form, it spreads the cultural weight of the local community, and it binds the artist</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation, and while the major biennials of the 1980s and 1990s may be credited with inspiring other artists to enter artist-centered artworlds, the importance of the Biennial in creating this present may be overstated. The Biennial fee itself may have been an initial epiphany for some artists, who were faced with the prospect of never being able to show their work in a major art museum again, or being forced to leave a biennial behind them when it closed. These artists may have felt that their work was not seen the way it was due to a lack of resources, but it is important to note that most artists of the time would have considered themselves artists first and foremost, and would have understood the cultural and economic power of their work. Biennials and the art market The biennial has come a long way since its beginnings in Venice in the late nineteenth century, and while the importance of the art museum remains as significant as ever, the biennial has come a long way</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation, and while the specific definition of a biennial may vary from venue to venue, the overall point is that the same principles and values govern both. The important point is that the biennial has a localised effect and that it is this localised impact that shapes the cultural landscape of the city. In the traditional sense, a biennial is an event that occurs in a city over and above other events, but in the modern sense, a biennial is a curated cultural exchange occurring between artists and audiences in a city. ‘Art’ and ‘content’ in the traditional biennial sense are closely related terms, and the biennial may be similarly tied to the art fair and the art market. In other words, the traditional biennial form may be seen as constituting a kind of content-producing function that is complementary to and dependent on the development and popularity of other elements within the exhibitionary complex. Biennials have become more and more of a production and consumption function within</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation, and much of the art featured in these exhibitions was produced prior to this. To date, there has been no major revision of the Biennial registration, exhibition schedule or content, and the artworks often stray into other media, often misrepresenting the intent or characters of the artists. It is important to note that in the early years of the biennial, artists and curators often collaborated constructively with local authorities to create a new art exhibition, an event to mark a milestone in the history of the local community, or just to have a good time. This approach to contemporary art was often influenced by the local community, and in some cases, the local authority contributed financially for the art.  One can argue that as the biennial has become more and more of a spectacle, the community art movement has decayed into obscurity, but this is largely due to the power of the biennial as a cultural currency and cultural locus of influence. In the past five years alone, the Biennial has</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation, and while the important role that art plays in generating wealth and social mobility may be crucial for our contemporary culture, it is clear that the social functions of art today are different from many artists realise.  The US cultural landscape is changing, and within it as well. The art market is shifting, and growing increasingly competitive, and ‘art in the social’ is a commodity that is increasingly difficult to identify and define. Art is no longer valued for its social value, but for its artistic ability to generate social impact. Socially engaged art may be more accessible to audiences in areas affected by the crisis of social impact, but this is not the case today. Social impact is more often cited as a reason to engage us in socially engaged art, and the impact of this is evident in the biennial gross receipts. The economic impact of art has become increasingly apparent in the biennial gross receipts, which are a reflection of the financial viability of art per se. The impact of the crisis of social</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial meant that the art fair would move to October, but that the biennial would continue to be October, with its own agenda and content.  The issues of community, cultural and urban regeneration being raised at the council level were used as a way to bring artists together to work on a parallel basis.  The council also funded a series of community initiatives through the Biennial fee, which allowed artists and community organisers to develop skills and tools to engage local communities more effectively.  This approach was not based on a religious or community focus, but on skills development and capacity building. Arts funding has always been a limited resource, and the biennial has been an important event for the local community, both financially and culturally. Biennials have become ever more prominent in the history books, and the term ‘biennial’ is frequently used to refer to a globally distributed exhibition of new art created in cooperation with or in partnership with a biennial. However, biennial is a relatively recent creation, and the first biennials were:  biennials are episodic exhibitions that occur later in the calendar year, and  biennials are ‘art episodes’ that occur in seasonal terms (e.g., the Venice Biennale rolls from June to September). Art’s first episodic show, the Mémoires de l’artiste on the Champs-Elysees, was created in Paris in 18 Bernard Nassau s, L’apparence de l’artiste, Paris, 18 prix (1801–1804). Art and artist Henri Bergson made several more episodic and ‘temporal’ shows during this period, such as the École Polytechnique départ à l’Art et l’Architecture on the Champs-Elysees, Paris, 1846; the École Polytechnique, Paris, 1847; the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery of energy, but he concluded that ‘the most fundamental concepts are concepts of energy’.[2] And from there, the article concludes with a description of the concept itself, concluding with a mathematical formula that characterises the amount of energy contained in a barrel of oil or the amount of energy produced by burning coal or oil shale. 	[3] An example is given of a thermosetting unit of oil equivalent (WE), denoted as a molecule  	Eq. of which 100 parts are  	hydrocarbons and which is classified as a fossil energy resource by the EOG. In the context of alternative energy, this unit is understood as equivalent to  	2,000,000 liters of regular gasoline, or approximately one million US gallons. The formula itself is a mapping of physical spaces and phenomena – locating where, how, and by whom – into a hierarchy of values or hierarchies of use. It is a mapping of</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery of the world, but he concluded that the ineradicable is energy, and metaphysically speaking, that is all there is. This conclusion is consistent with the ineradicable being energy contained in and accessible to matter.’[4] In fact, Schrödinger’s equation gives the mass of ineradicable energy (i.e. that which remains after the ineradicable destruction of matter) a form of mathematical certainty, a kind of structure that supports the possibility of a future beyond the here and now. And from that equation, we can derive the structure of a future in which ineradicable forms of matter will no longer be possible. This structure is a kind of prison, or perhaps a utopia. It is, in the words of Max Horkheimer, ‘a kind of interior jungle of stability, security and predictability, a house divided against itself’. The internal logic of the future is structured</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery of what an Ineradicable Mystery.2 Nadine Attewell, ‘Dazzle: The New Economy of Media Art’, in The New Economy of Media Art, ed. Stefan Collini (New York: Routledge, 2002), p. 7.3 Michael Ames, ‘The Hive Mind: The Modern Challenge to Entanglement’, in Cognitive Science (New York: Oxford University Press, 2005), p. 541.4 John McWhorter, ‘On Fractal Forms of Knowledge: The Fallacy of Reading Complex Information into Summaries’, in Thinking Inquiry: Essays on Multiverses and Fractals (Durham: Duke University Press, 1995), p. 221.5 Thérèse Coffr, ‘The Hive Mind: Understanding Computation’, in Cognitive Science (New York: Oxford University Press, 2005), p. 547.6 Thériault</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery of energy, but he did know that to understand it fully one would have to understand mathematics. ,3Diesel, the Phase Transition Process and the Massive Electrolyte System presents an ideal setting for the analysis of idealised knowledge, since it is based on a universally applicable set of physical and biological principles. ,4Ethan et al., ‘On the notion of ineradicable Memory: new perspectives on bioelectrifying the physical and redefining the  	Alternative Energy Model’, in Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 103, 13, 1975, p. 1029.Download this article as PDFEthan A. Andresen, The Ethical Energizer: Why We Should All Be Energizers (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2008), p. 40.Download this article as PDFEthan A. Andresen, The Ethical Energizer</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery of energy, but he soon came up with a set of paradoxical yet powerful definitions that bear his name today:  	Definition of Life, I, pg. 17. 	[2] John A. Church and Neil J. White, ‘On the use of probability and statistics to understand the behavior of natural resources’,  	Wallace E. Harpe, ed., Resource Economies: An Introduction to Resource Metabolism, Prentice Hall, New York, 1990, p.111. 	[3] The term  	Alternative Energy was coined by the American Petroleum Institute (API) in 1972 and continues to be used by the petroleum industry to describe new types of petroleum derived from renewable resources. See API Publications, Inc., 2016.  	[4] The Utilitarians were a working group of researchers from Yale University formed in 1972 to address the environmental and social issues of the day. See API Publications, Inc</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery of energy, but he concluded that ‘nothing can be accepted as final, immutable, or unchangeable, save through the creative and efficient use of knowledge’.[4] And from that conclusion, the equations and calculus that underlie the kinetic, chemical and nuclear processes that underlie all forms of material production – including those that underlie the production of diamonds – are of course but playthings of constant change and change, of ever-changing realisations and counter-turns. And from that, we can infer that the conceptualisation of ‘final, immutable, or unchangeable’ is itself a plaything of constant change and change, a product of knowledge-production and constant new infrastructures being put in place, and that ‘potential ends justifying means’ are all around us in all our activities. 	[5] And from that conclusion, we can infer that the desire for a ‘final, immutable or un</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery of energy, but he concluded that ‘nothing can be done to explain it – not even to create an elaborate theoretical construct to try – not even to conceive of such a thing.’[4] And from the same issue of Physics Today, published in 1953, a version of the same article is quoted in the journal article: ‘Schrodinger thought he knew what to do with the newly discovered resource: give it up whenever it fails to deliver what it purported to produce.’[5] Consequently, ‘a general approach to ineradicable mysteries’ is given in the scientific literature to all phenomena that have a foreseeable future, while theoretical and mathematical models are avoided. 	[6] This is consistent with the idea that theory and mathematics should be avoided in ineradicable ways, since they tend to predict what may or may not happen, and with the widespread acceptance of scientific realism in contemporary culture, it is also consistent</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery of the apparent randomness and randomness’ associated with the properties of the new types of petroleum. , wherein he posits that the world is governed by things called equations of nature. , wherein he describes how an equation, or a collection of things, is able to solve a problem when coupled with another concept called a ‘time equation’. (b) Consequences of Economic Behavioral Modification in Publics with Disabilities. 	[2] See, for instance, Thomas Waugh, A Politically Interactive Media Environment: The Rise and Fall of Creative Strategies (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1998).[3] See Thomas Waugh, Media Considered: Performance, Performance Theory, and Media Studies (Durham: Duke University Press, 1991), and my interview in collaboration with Matthew Arnold on the show, The Writers Studio.Download this article as PDFMatthew ArnoldIn his new book Critical Issues in Media Studies,</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery of space, and no one is more aware of its malleability than is Samuel Johnson, the British explorer and poet, who wrote: ‘The first mariner appropriates the idea of the ineradicable to find a way of appropriation of the idea of the immutable’.[6] And from Johnson’s mariner’s bible – a work that Johnson translated and published in 1845 – the journal article continues: ‘the first to write … is a writer who intends to bind himself forever to the spot where his ancestors once sat, or at least to that part of the ocean on which his ancestors once sat’.[7] And from that work, with its reference to ‘the first mariner appropriates the idea of the ineradicable’ and its parallel ‘way of appropriation’, Johnson’s mariner locates his search for ineradicable space in the second ‘book’ –</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system that is capable of detecting and measuring quantities of a substance with unprecedented specificity. 	[1] The term  	Alternative Energy refers to renewable and 'green' energy resources that promote the maximisation of both the quantity and quality of material resources. From its first definition in the journal of the American Petroleum Institute (1937), in a footnote, the footnote becomes more specific: 	&quot;Any resource can be considered an Alternative Energy (see §7 of this issue).’[2] And from that footnote, the journal article continues: &quot;Each alternative energy source has a distinct scientific name and is distinguished on the basis of its properties – a point of similarity between the name and the resource.’[3] And from the American Petroleum Institute, in its chapter on 'Technology and Value', the journal article continues: ‘[T]heoretical physicist] Werner[1] Schrödinger could not begin to define the ineradicable mystery of the intangible, intangible being. Even less could he have imagined the pernicious effects of a perceived inability to think clearly, when applied to the public’s discourse on energy as a whole.’[4] And from that chapter, the journal article continues: &quot;It is important to emphasize that the notion of a “energy sink” does not imply a physical limitation to resources; rather, the loss of mass as a result of depletion is invariably interpreted as a limitation to the extent that the capacity to sustain life is limited.’[5] And from that, the journal article continues: &quot;It is now generally accepted that the last ice age began approximately 11,500 years ago, with the appearance of a new species of rodent-like reptile on the rocks of Antarctica.’[6] And from that, with the fossil-fuel era ending some seven-hundred million years ago, and the emergence of renewable energies culminating some eight</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be
    <text>should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be thinking about, and which are just as present and timely today as they were in the past. I would classify them as ‘present-criticality’. These are the practices of art as social events, and they’re happening now, even though they’re happening thousands of years in the future. I think that there’s a way of our thinking about what these past practices may be like, and how they may be constituting ‘the urban space of the future’.These are the kinds of questions that are constantly cropping up in the city: what does it mean when we say that a certain neighbourhood is the future capital of Canada? When we talk about the ‘present’, we often mean the past – the humanity that we’re creating, the social forms that we’re creating, the impacts that we’re having now, and what’s happening to it. And so, we’ve</text>
    <text>should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be thinking about. There’s the past when people worked not for the money in their pockets but for the future, the future when people started to draw power from the future, the past when there’s no dictator but rather a people’s governor, and the future when there’s no foreign enemy but rather a shared set of ideologies and practices. What we learn in art is that there’s a difference between what we can and cannot do with the art object that we acquire, and what we do with it. We can shift the shape of time, and sometimes that’s OK. But there are limits to what we can accomplish with art objects. How we use art objects in certain contexts is part of what we can do with them, and part of what we don’t do with them. And part of what we don’t do with them is subject them to the kinds of political, economic and cultural changes that affect all of us</text>
    <text>should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be thinking about as part of the future. One such practice is what Richard Southern calls ‘technological pastiche’: the past in the service of the present. In other words, it’s the role of art institutions to offer and enable infrastructure for the future, while at the same time resisting becoming passive or complicit in the neoliberal transformation of infrastructure. The Museum of Modern Art in New York has done exactly that, creating a series of interactive maps that let visitors ‘stack’ and ‘pull’ elements from different past periods into a new technological present. The stacks and pulls of different past practices are, in effect, different forms of the same technology now running through the city. The point of these maps is to tell stories through pictures. The story of New York City in the digital age is one of rapid change, but they’re telling a story through pictures. What Southern calls ‘technological pastiche’ is the future we should be imagining,</text>
    <text>should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be thinking about, and these are particular to New York City and particular to the cultural life that is generated by it. For example, what is it that the Museum of Modern Art did in the early twentieth century? What is it that the Museum of Modern Art did in the late nineteenth century? What are its present cultural forms? These are questions that we need to be thinking about in the present, especially as we attempt to imagine what the future might bring.Another example is the museum that was once the home of the Black Arts movement: The Black and Tarrytown Art Museums. The Black Arts movement emerged in the late nineteenth century and centered on the art of Black immigrant groups who were often artists themselves, migrating from the industrial port cities in the southern half of the United States such as New York and Philadelphia. The aim of the movement was to document their cultural heritage through artworks produced in and for the communities they were sent to. In the twentieth century, the term appeared synonymously</text>
    <text>should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be drawing on too – looking at the structure and practices of curatorial curating today, in relation to past curating, for example. And these are practices such as the making of performance works, documentation of a performance, or the making of an archive.These past practices – the making of artefacts, the making of performance works, and the making of an archive – are the site of what Julian Barnes refers to as ‘the great metainterface-change’. He describes this as the historical and quasi-biennial metainterface, which is reshaping its own form and everyday contents. It’s a metainterface in which art, performance, and artefacts are placed in relation to one another, strategically and repeatedly, and in an ever-shifting series of relations. And this is what we mean when we talk about the past, or about the metainterface: the past is here in the present in a constantly shifting and changing way</text>
    <text>should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be bringing into the present – practices that are contemporaneous with the events that we think of as being in the present – practices that are based on a specific historical moment or dimension. For example, ‘black and white photography’ might be considered to be one such practice, but it’s also photography first and black and white photography second. It’s taking pictures in broad daylight, but it’s also taking pictures in dark places, taking pictures in public places, taking pictures from above and taking pictures of landscapes. Black and white photography is a past practice, but it’s one that we can and should be bringing into the present through a specific historical moment or dimension.‘Postmodern’ is a descriptor that bestows meaning on events that are happening now; it is a descriptor that is often misused and misconstrued. But postmodernism is a critically significant and long-term orientation for contemporary art and creative activity, and it is one that</text>
    <text>should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be thinking about, and these are the kinds of thinking that happen in the world of art. Some of these other past practices are quite salient today, and they include: conspicuous consumption, financial inaccessibility, gentrification, celebrity culture, and curatorial turn around-indulgence. But there are also practices that are much less visible but have a huge impact on our lives, and that is what we’re trying to capture and institutionalise: the practices that create and are built on the backs of migrant labour, the curatorial turn around indulgence, and the curatorial race.The curatorial turn around indulgence: the race to the bottomThis is the race to the bottom, as it is called. It is very important for us to understand this in order to address the systemic issues that we face as artists and creators in the city today. Many of our fellow artists, curators and art professionals who move to the city move to do so on the understanding that they</text>
    <text>should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be thinking about as well. There’s the past of theatre, for example. There’s the past of photography. There’s the past of publishing. There’s the past of street life – be it street life in the olden days of Manhattan or the new urban life we’re born into – and there’s the past of houses. There’s the past of schools. There’s the past of farms. There’s the past of cemeteries. There’s the past of abandoned housing. There’s the past of the Big Left.Then there’s the past of technology, which is the past of the technologies that create and foster life, and which we can all become enmeshed in. What does it mean for a technology to be ‘in the abstract’? I don’t know what you’re saying, but I don’t get</text>
    <text>should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be thinking about, and these are practices that come into being when we think about the future. For example, there are practices like ‘muralism’, which are actually practices that emerged in the wake of the art-historical-materialist turn in the late twentieth century, and which are part of what the poet Maya Angelou would call a ‘different kind of memory’. And there are new kinds of art that emerge from the shifting of time, like graffiti, which is now largely a response to the historical and ephemeral nature of urban life, but which can be seen as a new kind of art form that emerges when we think about the future. Finally, there are ‘past practices’ that we can and should be thinking about today, in the present and in the future, in order to create new kinds of art from the past. This last kind of art is what Maya Angelou would call a ‘radical present’, and it</text>
    <text>should be curated and founded by and with the artists’ collective] The Museum of Modern Art, New York, in the early twentieth century, which is more or less the equivalent of what we’re doing now. It’s a museum of production, innovation and achievement. In the museum, the collection is assembled from objects that have, in the past, been of a particular kind: semi-active art objects, objects that have had a significant impact on the artworld in the past, and artefacts from the past that are now either destroyed or in the process of being destroyed. This is an evolving collection, and as we go on, new kinds of art may be added to it.What do we mean when we talk about the past? When we think about art in the city, we usually think of the past as part of the present, with the present as an ephemeral shifting and shifting of places and times. But there are other past practices that we can and should be looking at, and they include things like food and beverage collections, old-fashioned art fairs, and the collection of forgotten artists and artists who used to come to the exhibitions we’re highlighting today.All these practices have something in common, in my view: they’re collections of different kinds of art, of art from different places and with different kinds of practices. But they also have some features in common, and this is where collections get interesting. I think collections draw us into them, they create a certain kind of immersion, engender a certain kind of connection, and so on. The interesting thing about biennial collections is that they typically contain something new, or at least something that we haven’t seen before. And this is happening with the New Museum collection, which is being curated now; it was on display for a week in New York and London, and now it’s back in New York. The collection as a whole is a collection of ideas</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mis
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mismanaged. The mismanagement of coastal sediments has been a problem since the late nineteenth century, but until recently the scientific and technical focus was directed towards developing alternative, less destructive, and more controllable ways to handle the debris. A new generation of oceanographers is uncovering the historical record, coming to grips with the fact that the original purpose of the ocean was to a large extent environmental in character, and that the environmental problems of the past were largely political in character. A new generation of oceanographers is uncovering the historical record, coming to grips with the fact that overfishing is a global problem. This is the view of leading experts in the field, including the chairpersons of the MBL, as well as eminent biophysicists, including Myron at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology and Joasia Atangana at Queen’s University in Kingston, Canada. This is the view of leading experts in the field, including the chairpersons of the MBL</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mislabelled as fish. These studies, together with the growing body of scientific and academic literature documenting the hazards of overfishing, has made it increasingly difficult to define the precise term 'overfishing' in response to the local impact on marine environments and human society. Nevertheless, the MBL is an essential component of any scientific investigation of overfishing and is expected to continue to provide the framework for the continued development of research-based knowledge about overfishing.The MBL emerged as a response to a need for a permanent, publicly accessible, and transparent laboratory for the creation, measurement and manipulation of matter in the coastal environment. It provided a location for the theoretical and computational modelling of coastal and marine resources as well as for the production and dissemination of informatics publications on these resources. The laboratory became a platform for the future of engineering and scientific research in the form of interactive multimedia simulations and publications. These can be seen as complementing the journal and its extensive editorial content, which is dominated</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mismanaged. Their research revealed that up to 10 percent of the catch may have been released back into the sea, where it meets with various forms of life that can further be labelled as ‘endangered’. This mismatch between the demands of commercial and scientific fisheries seems inevitable given the rapid advances in technology and commerce. But the MBL’s focus on the problem allowed scientists to devise a targeted response. A team led by Elizabeth Daly, a biologist by training, worked with fishermen to develop a prototype for a ‘smart catch bag’ that incorporates sensors that monitor the health of the ecosystem in real time. This technology enabled the scientists to monitor large numbers of planktonic and cyborg planktonic and cyborg algal communities, as well as the genetic activity of larger predatory fish. A total of ten samples were collected from each of the ten sites, providing data on the populations of over 1,000 species. Eight of these were from China; the remaining eight from the</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mislabelled as farmed Atlantic salmon. A 2008 study led by researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology focused on the effects of overfishing on a specific species: monk seal, in particular. It concluded that the overfishing of monk seals was a leading cause of mortality among marine mammals.Over the past decades, the scientific and regulatory communities have been quick to respond to the needs of the urban poor. The need for new ways to detect and address overfishing has intensified, and the MBL was created as a central place to coordinate efforts to detect and mitigate overfishing. It is now led by a director who is appointed by the president, and who is also a scientist or engineer. There is now a Research Triangle, created as part of the National Laboratory, which is responsible for spearphishing – the art of creating fake monikers to boost the numbers of endangered species – and the development of market research that can be used to monitor and assess the progress of overfishing.</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mislabelled as fish. Around the world, commercial fisheries continue to dominate. The MBL was founded in Baltimore in 1903 and its director was William H. Burtynsky, a former Air Force lieutenant general and a founding member of the Stone Aerospace Company. At the time, Burtynsky was the United States representative to the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change.Burtynsky’s interest in space exploration and globalisation were twofold. The first was technological: the exploration of outer space and the possibility of space colonization. The second was environmental: the development of environmentally conscious industrial and commercial operations. The MBL was created as a division of Burtynsky’s company, Burtynsky Space Company, to address the latter concern. The company was chartered as a non-profit corporation and its board was composed of representatives from many fields of endeavor. The corporation was divided into sub-divisions with specific tasks assigned to each. The first was focused</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mislabelled as fish food. As a result, local fishermen tend to catch more of what they think they know how to fish. In a recent survey of more than 2,000 local fishermen in Denmark, over half said they believed in superstition. For them, fishing for hard-to-define things like mythical creatures or mythical fish was a form of &quot;devotion&quot; that required a supernatural intervention. This seems utterly ridiculous to me, and flies in the face of decades of scientific and archaeological evidence that reveals that overfishing is a huge environmental and socio-economic problem. More to the point, it shows no sign of improving.As a scientist and academician, I come prepared to engage with scepticism. I am not sure that I am qualified to speak on behalf of the sea, nor am I sure that I have the authority to judge what is or isn’t possible. But I do feel that I have a responsibility to speak the truth to a very powerful place, to</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mislabelled as fish by fisheries authorities. In these surveys, overfishing is often cited as a cultural phenomenon rather than an economic one. Whether the failure to see the signs of overfishing and to respond with effective countermeasures is due to a failure to analyse the issue holistically as a complex set of interacting factors, or whether the failure to see these complex, but well understood, causes lies at the level of the species and its ecosystem. Overfishing is a problem that society as a whole, and particularly governments, do not yet understand. This is evident in the failure to act on overfishing in East Anglia despite the overwhelming scientific and regulatory evidence. 	[i] See, for example, Richard Florida and Christian Körner, eds.,  	The Science of Not-So-Big Agriculture: Fauna, Fauna, and the Philosophy of Nature (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2016). 	[ii] Ibid. 	[</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mislabelled as &quot;archipelago&quot; or &quot;subsidence&quot; due to overfishing.[1]In researching the effects of overfishing on an international scale, it became evident that the only organisms with which to work were those with which the multinational corporations that control the oceans today – Japan and South Korea being the most prominent examples – were most comfortable. These transnational corporations control virtually everything that moves in the seas, and thus every plankton, every feather, every fish, every mollusk, every tiny speck of plankton – including invertebrates such as tiny crustaceans and tiny mollusks – that are caught, nets and trawlers take their cues from them, and products derived from them. The only way to reliably monitor and manipulate such transient phenomena as planktonic life is to rely on proprietary, high-tech instruments that constantly monitor and record the movements of organisms at the molecular level, but which also constantly monitor and record the movements of larger</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mislabelled as fish. Only a small percentage of the catch actually made it to the East Coast. In these instances, the mislabelling can be attributed to institutional racism and industrialisation in the United Kingdom. In the event that the effects of climate change become evident, it is predicted that up to ninety percent of the Earth’s catch could end up in the seas. This risk has become particularly acute in the past decade because of unregulated fishing. Seafood prices have skyrocketed, making it ever more difficult to turn a profit in a market dominated by a few large companies. Many species of fish are over-valued, and the value of their catch has little bearing in determining the value of the fishery. A 2015 study by scientists at the University of East Anglia, however, suggested that the value of a catch today could be much greater if fisheries management were properly targeted. They defined a fishery as a ‘systemically managed domain of interactions between humans and non-human animals</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring, controlling and mapping of marine life, and in particular, the ability to monitor the movements of large numbers of plankton, which are the primary constituents of the coastal sediments.A first step in this direction is the establishment of a Marine Biological Laboratory (MBL) in 1971. This was a response to the failure to develop an effective countermeasure to the effects of overfishing, which was primarily attributed to climate change. In the intervening twenty years, several innovations have been made in the laboratory, most notably the developments in biomolecular biology and computational biology that allow the rapid and precise measurement and manipulation of matter. There is increasing evidence that overfishing is a global problem. In 1990, for example, a United Nations panel of experts on fisheries concluded that overfishing was a global problem with worldwide implications. More recently, a survey conducted by scientists at the University of East Anglia revealed that up to 90 percent of the catch in East Anglia may have been mislabeled as fish by fishermen. Around the world, fishermen are employing innovative tactics to thwart detection, including the employment of specialized underwater vehicles (UUVs), which disguise vast quantities of fish in highly mobile, misleap-forming sediments. In the coming years, researchers at the MBL and elsewhere may attempt to develop more environmentally responsive fishing strategies.One of the many exciting aspects of the new marine sciences is the development of technologies to monitor, control and map the movements of large numbers of creatures at once. This is particularly true for creatures like whales and dolphins, which are highly variable in their behaviours and require constant verification in real-time via satellite or other platforms. A prime example of this kind of platform is the submarine, which uses sophisticated sonar to map the depths and locations of the ocean floor, using data from its excavators and other instruments to detect and map small creatures (including whales and seals) at depths of up to 300 m. In the coming years, researchers at the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water and sewage systems. The ‘Indian Ocean island of Laos’ forms the basis for a future ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ that would include infrastructure on an island scale, covering an area the size of Great Britain. The Indo-Pacific Rim is divided into three ‘Greater Mekong Regions’ that are supported by the Indian Ocean island of Sa to a lesser extent by Cambodia. The Indo-Pacific Rim covers an area the size of Turkey. The Indo-Pacific consists of five coastal islands: Taiwan, Hong Kong and Macau. The Indo-Chinese ‘land bridge’ links the island of Sa to the mainland, while the island of Macau links the mainland to the island of Macau. ‘The land bridge’ is an important water and wastewater conveyor belt in the Indo-Pacific that supplies water to the region. It is also an important point of entry and exits into the region, where it is possible to cross over to the island</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water systems. Roads connect the three zones, while rail and road systems connect the major inland cities. In the case of the Indo-Mekong and Indo-China regions, the infrastructures of the cities function as transalpine highways for the transport of goods and people. In the case of the Indo-Pacific Rim region, the infrastructures of the metropolis – which are the result of the ‘collective brain’ – function as transalpine highways for the transport of goods and people. In both the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ and the ‘Indo-Pacific Rim’ regions, infrastructural growth is promoted through the ‘absorption’ of water’, which is subdivided into ‘slurry’ and ‘matter’ of various types and sizes. The slurry is then processed for various products, which include textiles, footwear, vehicles, packaging materials, pharmaceuticals, consumer</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water systems. Roads enable movement between the various zones, while rail and road systems transport passengers and goods throughout the system. Water holds large amounts of water in the form of salts and organic compounds, which enable transport across the vast distances of the basin. The three-tiered socio-political structure of the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is contrasted by the ‘Urban Edge’ – high-density, mixed-use districts that are the direct result of the ‘Urban Return’ (TR) programme, promoted by the state of Singapore. The TR programme’s stated objective is to ‘rebuild “imperiled” neighbourhoods with a positive mix of residential, retail and public spaces through a cooperative […] cooperative’.[14] 	In her book [PDF - 851 KB] Tokyo Critic (1997), Agrawal Mitra makes the same point in relation to Singapore’s ‘Urban Return’ programme: ‘</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water systems. While the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ has its own in-depth description, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim ‘regions’ have somewhat different renderings and figurative expressions of urban infrastructure. While the Indo-China is characterised by its ‘Great Wall’ and ‘Little Pearl’ rivers, the Pacific Rim ‘urban regions’ feature ‘Kampala’ and ‘Kampala’ national parks, where large numbers of people live in neat, well-maintained and walkable subdivision. The ‘City of Runaways’ is also frequently mentioned as a possible future site for a future ‘regional capital’. 	The term ‘regional’ is frequently used in connection with places and communities located in other countries. In the case of the ‘Great Mekong Valley’, the term is used to refer to ‘a complex</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water systems. Roads form the basis of regional transport networks and connect different areas. The development of new rail networks along the Indian and Pacific Ocean borders forms part of the Indian Ocean Coastal Plus (IOC+) project, which is a tertiary project of the UK’s National Grid Developments Group (NGDG). The project is managed by NGRG in cooperation with the UK’s Department for International Development (DfID). 	The article proposes three possible future growth trajectories for the Indo-Pacific and Indo-Chinese cities of the future to be based on three main factors: (1) the reduction in dependence on oil; (2) the expansion of information technology; and (3) the reduction in urbanisation potentials due to better mobility, including car sharing and drone commuting. The article does not specify which of these factors should be addressed and what form their implementation should take. That would be a valuable and unique position for an article such as this to have.</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water and sewer systems. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are governed by regional governments. The three ‘Greater Mekong Temples’ are located in the Indo-Mekong Zone 1, which covers an area of over 1,600 square kilometres. The three temples are currently occupied by international visitors. Surface World (2013) imagines a future in which ‘tripartite institutions representing a range of disciplines, led by the World Bank, sit down to discuss ways to work together to address the challenges of the Greater Mekong Valley, from development to migration and refugees’.[14] 	The article’s acknowledgement of the ‘difficulties of the region’ is part of a rhetorical exercise. In the context of the global urbanisation process, the authors’ deliberate non-representational ‘city’</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water systems. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by city-states. ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is a useful classification for the article, since it offers a framework for thinking about the ‘urban transition’ that may be desirable in the future, but it is also a framework for considering the different forms of infrastructure that may be built upon the back of urban growth. The article calls for ‘deep decarbonisation’ of the ‘base elements’ of the ‘city’, and for the establishment of ‘indigenous ‘regimes of production and consumption’ in the region. The article does not propose a ‘replacement for’ in the region, since there is no discernable role for the state in the region today. Rather, the ‘city’ becomes an</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water systems. Roads connect the three ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ zones. Infrastructure provides both physical and virtual support to ‘high-performance urban clusters’.[14] Surface World (2013) builds on this idea of ‘high performance’, proposing a new ‘science and technology’ complex in each zone that supports ‘high-value‐added [WSC] projects at multiple scales of scale, with an emphasis on scale-producing ‘high performance coal and gas terminals, manufacturing plants, and […] real estate investment trusts [HRTs] in the region around port cities’. The infrastructure ‘systems design, construction, and […] management […] typically employed in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ are located in the port cities of Minger, Lopburi and Bitburg. The HSR is a prime location for the ‘development and […] operations of these ‘high performance’ clusters, with a mix</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water systems. The ‘Indian cities’ that make up the bulk of the ‘system’ make their presence felt in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The ‘Indian cities’ form a transnational complex that operates according to the laws of the region, addressing issues of poverty, urbanisation and development in a manner that is both inclusive and nationalistic. The region is divided into three ‘regionals’ and ‘littoral cities’. ‘Littoral’ cities are those that are vulnerable to the effects of climate change and inundation, but which have not built ‘climate-effective adaptation plans’ or incorporated ‘smart strategies’ into their development processes. They are typically located in the south and east and contribute to the discharge of one of the greatest sources of freshwater in the world: the Yangtze River. ‘Climate-smart cities’ are those that incorporate both mitigation and adaptation strategies</text>
    <text>possibility of developing an experimental system for monitoring global sea-level rise and its impacts on coastal cities.[12] 	In an assessment of the risks and benefits of different modes of travel in the 21st century, a different approach was taken with regard to urbanisation and travel in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’. The article, entitled ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, in the book [PDF - 8 KB] Surface World (2013), considered the past in favour of the future in an attempt to create an ‘infrastructure for a new kind of urbanity’.[13] The article proposes a ‘city for tomorrow’ based on the logic of ‘global ecology’. The ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ is divided into three zones – Indo-Mekong, the Indo-China and the Indo-Pacific Rim – which are managed by regional governments. The three zones are characterised by different levels of infrastructure: roads, rail networks and water systems. The Indo-Mekong Zone (1949-2001) is the most developed with a metro system, international airports and a border with Laos. The area encompassed in the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’ comprises much of the national airline ‘London Heathrow Airport’ and is also the international financial centre for trans-shipping from the UK to Asia. The Indo-China and Indo-Pacific Rim Zones (1949-2001) are the third and final chapters in the ‘Surface World’ series. In the ‘Greater Mekong Valley’, the metro and airports are gone, but the city remains an important source of daily commerce, with over one million cars crossing the Tsetse River every day.[14] 	In the ‘Greater Mekong River Valley’, the metro and airports no longer dominate the landscape, but rather form part of a larger ‘urban-delineation network�</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with renegotiated relationships with various stakeholders in the city and internationally, and a dearth of local interest in the form. All of these changes, according to Graham, are the direct result of the in-depth, long-term research activities of MFA students over the past decade, both as artists and curators, who, through collaborative projects, created ‘representations of the city that are as real as possible’. 	[i] Graham, Sarah. ‘10 Curating Tasks for a Future City’, 2016, accessed October 2018.  [ii] Granick, Thomas. ‘On the Use of Surplus in Art’, 1925, in Proceedings of the Eighth International Surplus Art Congress, London, 29 September–12 October, pp. 119–28, accessed October 2018.  [iii] Granick, Thomas. ‘On the Use of Surplus in Art’, 1926, in Proceedings of</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with its current focus shifting towards socially engaged art practices and its future possibilities. 	[i] Oliver Wendell Holmes, The Art of Not Being Governed, Harper &amp; Row, New York, 1975. p.30.  [ii] Ray Bradbury, Cybernetics: A Modern Science of Being, McGraw-Hill, New York, 1976, p.9.  [iii] William Burston, The Art of Living, McGraw-Hill, New York, 1976, p.91.  [iv] Ray Bradbury, Fahrenheit 451, Marvelous Clouds, Random House, New York, 1982, p.9.  [v] Malachi Deena and Kevin Warwick Hoyne, eds., Life and Culture: Essays on the Uses of Books, Film, Music, and Architecture, McGraw-Hill, New York, 2011, p.95.  [vi] Curtis Christov-Trot</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with the number of sites reaching over 6,000.2  The exhibition will be created with software that analyzes artworks by curators, artists, experimental groups and museums and produces a report summarizing the state of the art in the city at a given time. It will offer a snapshot of the city, but it will also tell the story in a number of engravings, short stories and poems, collages, mementos and sculptures. The artworks will be arranged according to various themes or priorities, including the past, present and future of art in the city. Each site will have a different role to play in the exhibition, with interiors and texts that comment on the different dimensions of the city. All the curators at the Biennale have master’s’idebar degrees in art history or urban studies from the London School of Art, or equivalent training, and many have PhDs in the subject. The curators at the Venice Biennale have both</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with more and more art being made outside of its walls.1  In the past, the mode of the biennial was characterised by the annual production of more than one kind of artworks, with works appearing in many different ways. The importance of biennials as curatorial investments in the way in which they operate today is underscored by the fact that the biennial itself often exhibits a number of different kinds of artworks in various kinds of media. I say ‘generally speaking’ because there are many kinds of biennials. But the kind of biennial that interests me is the kind that exhibits in its title, celebrates in a particular way (the word is a bit clunky), and, above all, makes money.2  If the title of this book is a bit clunky, it is because, while it is true that the first edition of the Biennial was only ever a diary, and the text is a bit bare-bones, the</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with artists increasingly opting to produce works in smaller venues and with smaller curators, which reduces the museum-based form to one in which the artist’s work can have a more prominent presence.1  In other words, the exhibitionary form – and the curatorial hand in which it takes place – is an evolving, dynamic and variable kind of tool.  	Looking backwards, we can infer that the biennial was always going to be a temporary, transitory kind of place, and that the exhibitionary form would be a part of that very plane of constant, transient change. But looking forwards, we can infer that the biennial will always occupy a unique place in the city, and that the art will always be on the other side of the temporal threshold, at a slightly later and later date. 	So the interesting thing about the biennial is that it exists in a temporal situation that is still very much in the present, but is also aware of the temporal situation</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with some artists refusing to make exhibitions there because of its high production costs (both financially and art-historically). 	As a museum, Liverpool Biennial seeks to represent and act as a point of entry into the city, using the museum as a platform to expose different aspects of the city that are often under-reported or under-under-utilised. The exhibition is made up of many different points of entry into the city, from the domestic (the exhibition space) to the urban (the museum), with brief statements from various fieldworkers about the city. The main objective of the exhibition is to expose ‘the city as a place where art can happen’. More specifically, the exhibition is made up of three parts: the first part is devoted to the activities of art school teachers and staff; the second part is a ‘shopping’ section dedicated to local art dealers and art performance organisations; and the third part is a ‘museum’ section that documents</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with the number of artists currently living and working in the city declining, though the biennial may still exhibit an occasional art that reflects the city’s socio-politically dynamic. 	[i] Gareth White, The Art of Not Being Governed: The Political Basis of Biennials, Princeton Architectural Review, Vol. 114, No. 2, 2010, p.335.  [ii] Gareth White, The Art of Not Being Governed: The Political Basis of Biennials, Princeton Architectural Review, Vol. 114, No. 2, 2010, p.335. [iii] John Urry, ‘Economic Hubris and the Reality Check of Containerization’,  	Postmodern Culture 11:3 (November/December, 2012), pp.339–45. [iv] Urry, op. cit., p.339. [v] James Howard Kunstler, ‘In</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with its main role to act as a curatorial appointment. All of these changes make it easy to see the impact that the biennial can and should play in shifting the balance of power and wealth in the city, whether that shift is towards art as objects of exchange or in support of a social infrastructure supporting culture as a political-ideological position.In these ways, biennials provide a double-edged sword: they can function as repositories of historical knowledge, but also as the sites of the latest in a long line of political and social experiments that – if not properly addressed and addressed in– actively shape and constrain the future possibilities and possibilities of art making and culture. The unique feature of the biennial is that it can render long-standing themes and practices of art and art-making obsolete, creating a ‘regeneration’ around a particular art form or art-object. Shakespeare’s ‘King Henry VI’ features this process in the nineteenth-century form</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with artists more and more preferring to produce works in-gallery and showing works that are constructed of materials or buildings of some sort.  [Note by the author: the word used here is generic, but the idea of location and the idea of staging of events in and through a biennial have also gained in force in the past few years.]  [1] The exhibition was curated by Tito Villalobos, and featured a selection from the collection of the Museo de Arte Contempora (National Museum of Arterial Research and Technology, Ciudadana de California). The museum was the venue for the project’s public launch, and the blogger ‘Satyajit Roy’ organized a number of live performances, both in the museum, in the street and in the exhibition space. Both the museum and the audience were present in the exhibition. ‘The Biennial Condition’ was displayed as a number of different sub-exhibitions. The exhibition</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, which was originally set to open in June 2018, will now be held in November 2019. As the name suggests, the exhibition will be based around a single location – a museum rather than a collection – and the various ways in which art is made, reproduced and celebrated in the city. The exhibition will be the product of a shared process of what MFA student Sarah Graham calls ‘biennialism’ – or, in other words, a biennial as a concept today, encompassing a number of different modes of art making. The main differences between the way in which art is produced in and through a biennial today and in the past are as follows: the biennial is no longer the dominant art form producing large numbers of artists annually, and the number of artists producing in the city is growing; the biennial is no longer the art institution of last resort, but is now the venue of last resort; and finally, the biennial itself has entered a transition phase, with projects having ceased to be considered for consideration. All of these changes, and many more that we may enumerate, can be found in the book Stages of Utopia: Biennials and the End of an Era,2 (Oxford University Press, 2016).3 	The exhibition format and the way in which it is generated is deeply related to the city’s current economic and urban condition. 	The biennial is a ‘once in a generation’ artform, and its reproduction and current condition is indicative of a more globalised, complex and dispersed form of art production that is becoming increasingly difficult to define and quantify. It is now possible to identify a succession of biennials – a global art-historical pattern that began in the 1990s with the release of the Venice Biennale and has continued to this day with the institution of the Venice Biennale – with the same artist, theme or theme being exhibited in different biennials around the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month, from September to April, and document the tour through drawings, text and drawings, collage and still photographs. The annotations will appear in the book as a chapter titled ‘Annotations’ and in the companion publication ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ (2016).  [1] The Anfield Home Tour, (2016), 53. [2] Interview with Andy Warhol, The New York Times: 1925, 25 November, 1999. [3] Storage of Human Anatomy (1926), Vol. I, p. 359. [4] William Harvey, The Anatomy of a Plague (1899), Vol. I, p. 463. [5] J.R. McNeill, An Introduction to Zoology (1940), Vol. II, p. 447. [6] William Harvey, The Anatomy of a Plague (1899), Vol. I, p. 447. [7</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month.   Nasdag (2015): The Anfield Home Tour is the subject of a project that I co-direct with Wendy Harpe, funded by the Arts Council and The Bluecoat. The project examines the housing crisis in the area through personal stories of two local residents, as well as art projects that address the issue through music, light and organisation. I am the artist. The plan is to produce three CDs of the tour, each based around a different aspect of the housing crisis. The first CD, entitled ‘Stories from the Anfield Home Tour’ gathers together previously selected stories from the tour, as well as music, poetry, political statements and photographs from the area. The project is intended as a one-day biennial event, with occasional stopovers in Liverpool. The project will have a public function in Anfield at a later date. The CDs will include music, lyrics and images from the original stories, as well as new compositions and lyric videos. The</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month, from October to April, and document the tour on my blog. The annotation sees into the distance the history of the area – the houses that were once occupied by the bakery and the building that was once the dance hall. The annotation is a place where the story is told through visualisations and poetry. The annotation is a place where voices from the past are told together with the voice of the future. The annotation is a point of intersection. It is a boundary, and it is a place where stories collide.The Anfield Home Tour marks ten years since the last edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and ten years since the last time an annotation was made. Ten years on from the last time an annotation was made, how have the stories of the area come back to haunt us? We tell them in this text, from the archives of the 1996 Biennial, as told by artist Lawrence Abu Hamdan, and the voices of the residents who formed the core of the original 1996 Biennial.Law</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month, from September to April. I am interested in the history of the area – the houses that were built on the old Royal Docks site, the closed bakery, the abandoned cinema. I visit the area because I believe that the history of the area – the houses, the closed bakery, the abandoned cinema – is important for understanding the present. I visit because I believe that there is a potential for change within the area.I visit the cinema again and again because I believe that – like the theatre – cinema – it provides a setting that is rich with meaning. Meaning is made real, tangible and can be experienced. Through the cinema, we learn about the processes that create meaning, and through the history of the area – which is closely tied to the processes – we learn about the ways in which the cinema can be an obstacle in changing the world.In The Anfield Home Tour, I refer to three films that were made in the area around the time that the tour was staged:Ingmar Berg</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month, from October to January, and document the tour’s development, preparation and abandonment at the same time. The annotations take the place of the actual photographs, piecing together over years of planning, research and abandonment. They feature characters from the area, from the local farmers and traders to the council, developers and tourists. They discuss the condition of the neighbourhood, its history and present, and the role of artists, historians and other publics in the regeneration of the site. In the case of a city, the annotations could function as a register of interests, drawing together different registers of knowledge and providing a mapping of the site as a site of activity.  References  Liverpool Biennial,  	The Anfield Home Tour (2015). ​http://www.biennial.com/en/events/archive/download/archive/2015/new.html#.UXfDzdGVzdF._3 Up  (2015). ​http://www</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month, from October to December, and document the tour in my new book,  	The Anfield Home Tour: Art, Community and Place in the City of Dreams. The book is a ‘snap’shot’ of the tour, documenting its evolution through local and national media, during the past year and into the next. 9 July 2016................................................................ The Anfield Home Tour team 	At the end of 2016, we launched the second stage of the Anfield Home Tour, in which the identity of the neighborhood around Anfield HQ/the Anfield/Brick was revisited in the form of a series of questions and answers. The introduction of the new questions and answers came as a surprise to many people, but the answers, presented in chronological order, reveal a past that can be traced to the 1990s: how the neighbourhood came to be named; the role of the local government in creating and sustaining the project; the history of the local arts community in keeping the neighbourhood alive; and the</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month, and document the tours ‘in-depth’ in my book,  	Inside the Anfield Home Tour. I also interview the local residents and groups that work in and around Anfield, and the city itself.  The Anfield Home Tour (2015), Liverpool Biennial, http://www.the-arnoldemboss.com/wp-content/uploads/2014/07/Inside-the-Anfield-Home-Tours-in-History.pdf (accessed September 2018). 	So why then, when the Biennial began, did the Home Tour decrease in popularity? My personal take is that the increase in access to and immersion in the local arts scene in the past few years coincided with the decrease in relevance of the Biennial to the local arts scene. In the early years, the Biennial was an institution that people could point to and identify with; as the art and culture they were exposed to. As the art and culture around the biennial</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month. The Anfield Home Tour (2015) marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month.  Preeana Reddy,  	The Anfield Home Tour (2015), Liverpool, UK. Image courtesy of the artist.  Preeana Reddy,  	The Anfield Home Tour (2015), Liverpool, UK. Image courtesy of the artist.   LIVERPOOL, UK - JUNE 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool, June 2017The Anfield Home Tour Liverpool</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month, from August to October, and document the tour in my book  	The Anfield Home Tour: Liverpool Biennial, Liverpool Biennial, 2015. I photograph the houses that the community has created around the tour, and make architectural renderings and illustrations as part of the project ‘The Anfield Home Tour Project’ organised by Bluecoat and Liverpool Biennial. I hope to one day build a community of artists’ homes around the tour, and make works with that community.  Annex 1: The Home Tour Project 	The Home Tour Project is a biennial that documents the lives and work of the community that has incorporated new housing into their community. I was born and raised in the Welsh Streets area of Toxteth, and moved to Anfield when I was five. My work began when I was five, when my mother would invite me to a local primary school arts and crafts day. There were a few older artists there too, but I was the only child. The rest</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s College&quot; that has been established in partnership with the Liverpool Biennial. The mission of the College is to promote and facilitate an understanding of the diverse arts practices of the local area through educational activities, research and reporting.  In order to achieve this, the College relies on the support of a range of arts organisations, including the arts council (with funding from the Arts Council, 2012–2015); the Bluecoat (with funding from the Arts Council, 2014–16); the BIM (Bluecoat Instrument for Monitoring Arts Practices, Bluecoat, 2014); the Liverpool Biennial (2015); the Open School East (2012); Future City (2013); Icon (2014); the Liverpool Biennial Trust; and Welsh Streets Association.  Annotation (2015): ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ marks the tenth edition of the Anfield Home Tour, and the first time that the tour has been staged in the historic venue. I visit the place once a month. My aim is to introduce the story of Homebaked and the cultural practices of the area.  My tour group travels to Anfield from Liverpool, Glasgow, Dundee, Glasgow, Welsh Streets and onto to Anfield. We meet people from the area, see the bakery, Brick Lane Bakery, the community and play a game called ‘The Anfield Home Tour’ where residents take turns listing off the different homes in Brick Lane. After the tour, we meet people from the county and the local authorities who will explain the plans for the area. I try to explain the politics of the area, the fact that the bakery is a site of political activity and the fact that the bakery is a site of illegal dumping of council property. The area has a long history of resistance to the way in which the bakery is run. The politics of the area are complicated. We learn about the challenges of running a bakery in Anfield, including</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and co-founder of the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, a national art and cultural organisation. He has curated numerous exhibitions including the Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, the 2018 Venice Biennale, and the 2018 Museo do Vittorio Emanuele. He is the curator-at-large for the forthcoming Architecture of the Not-So-Future: Towards a Museum-Centre in the Not-So-Future (2018) and the project MAP, which will investigate the future of historic architecture in an expanded European context. He is the editor-at-large of New Art &amp; Architecture, a journal of architecture and design published jointly by Stratazen and KW. His architecture projects have included the ancient walled city of São Paulo, the Great Wall of China (2014), Japan’s Akasaka Katmai,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and co-director of the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale. His work has been commissioned by, and has been presented by, several public and private organisations including: Osservatore Romano, Rafico Rucci, Giorgio De Beaufort, Enrico Lazzarato, Dario Portoghesi, Giuseppe Raposo, Joana Dey, Frank Giacomo, Benito Quinquela, Eduardo Giacomo, Joana Baptista Martins, Moishe Postone, Paolo Portoghesi, Peter Varga, Eduard Steyerl, Bruno Latoury, Gianni Modolo, Manoli Leckey, Emmanuelle Leckey, Suzanne Lacy, John Akomfrah or just people. He was a co-curator of</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and co-founder of the Italian pavilion in the Venice Biennale. He curated the 14th Istanbul Biennale, the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the first Italian pavilion in Alaska with ART James Ivory, DCU’s Center for Art, Media and Politics, Anchorage, Alaska. He has curated the Venice Biennale, Milan Biennale, New York Biennale, Istanbul Biennale, and SITE Santa Fe Biennale. His periodic exhibitions include the Architecture of Silence: Israel, Palestine, and Architecture (2014), Anachronism: Overcoming a Name (2015) and Next Architecture: US and International Architecture (2016). He has lectured at a number of architecture schools and is currently working as an adjunct professor at Arizona State University. His work often addresses the political and social dimensions of urban and regional development, and the cultural and political concomitant thereof. He has co-written the</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and co-founder of Papas, a cultural organisation focused on the protection and promotion of the native wildlife of the Ganges Delta region. He has curated the Venice Biennale, the 11th Beppe Grillo curated by Grillo in Sopravisions Pontificia and the Venice Biennale, and the biennale of the Austrian pavilion in Athens, Greece. He is a co-founder of the New Frontiers Foundation, a non-profit cultural organisation based in New York City that develops culturally responsive local and regional public programmes. He has also curated the 15th Italian pavilion and the Venice Biennale, as well as the 17th Beppe Grillo curated by Grillo in Sopravisions Pontificia.Art and culture in crisis: from Greece to TurkeyIntroduction: Greece and Turkey  [1] In the summer of 2014, a group of artists, curators, researchers and writers from across</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and co-founder of the online public art portal Nasser Rabbati. He has curated numerous exhibitions globally including the 6th Rome Biennale (2016), the 12th Sydney Biennale (2015), the 13th Istanbul Biennale (2015), the 15th Venice Biennale (2015), the 16th New York Biennale (2016), the 17th Seoul Biennale (2017), the 18th Kampala Biennale (2018) and the 20th Baku and Davos Biennale (2019). He was a curator for the Greek and Armenian pavilions at the 2014 Venice Biennale, and was a co-founder of the Greek Cultural Centre at the University of Illinois, which is dedicated to the study and exhibition of contemporary art from the two largest remaining Middle Eastern countries. He was also a curator for the 2009 New York Biennale and the 2010 Berliner Kurzweilai – Show</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and publisher of the weekly art and architecture newspaper, Assemble’s fourth issue, which was recently shortlisted for the Arsenale du Vin, France. Papas has been a curator for the LA-area branch of the  National Gallery and the Palestine Museum, and curated the US branch of the Temple at BYU, and the Lebanese branch of the Gulf and California branches of the National Art Gallery. He curated the Venice Biennale, Venice (Italy), and Venice (US) at the M.I.T. Pollock, James Howard Kunstler, Lincoln Center, New York, USA, and was a curator for the New York Museum of Art’s &quot;Performativity&quot; programme, which recorded the work of local artists, including Mouawadir Khalili and Ameen Ebadi. The Palestine Museum’s exhibition Palestine: Statelessness at Tate Britain and the move to the</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and co-founder of the New Frontiers Foundation, an international non-profit cultural organisation based in London. His books include the Non-Place: Non-Place, Non-Knowledge (2014) and the upcoming Non-Place: Strategies for Securing Future Contents of Text, 2015. He has written for the New York Times, Wall Street Journal, Wall Street·E, New York Daily News, the Guardian, CBC, and CBC Radio. He is a regular lecturer at Wichita College of Art and Design.OUP DeSOUX POLLONIER: What is the significance of the fact that you live above ground?SKILLED:  It’s a point of departure, a point of entry into a city that’s built on top of us. I’m not trying to state what the significance of that point of entry is. It’s more that I’m interested in the ways in which we create spaces</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and co-founder of the Fifth Art Film &amp; TV Festival, a collective, which together oversee the Italian pavilion in Venice, and are responsible for the Italian pavilion in the US, both located in the city. He has curated several exhibitions in Italy, including: the 14th Rome Biennale (2018), the Italy &amp; Venice - Meet the Artists (2018), the Venice Biennale, the Italy &amp; Philadelphia - Meet the Artists (2018), the Venice Biennale, the Italy &amp; Washington DC - Meet the Artists (2018), the Venice Biennale, the USA (2017), and the Venice Biennale, the UK (2017). He has curated the Venice International Film &amp; Television Festival (2006-08), the Italy - Meet the Artists (2010), the Venice International Film &amp; Television Festival, Italy (2010), the Venice Biennale, the USA (2017), and the Venice Architecture Biennale, Italy (2018).He was a curator for the 14th edition</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and co-founder of the forthcoming New Frontiers Foundation, a curatorial initiative focused on the Arab World. He has presented the 10th Istanbul Biennale and the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and was a curator for the Venice and Italian pavilions in the New Frontiers Program, a curatorial experiment at the core of the Biennale. He has curated the 1st Mehrwander Plan International Art Biennale, Istanbul, Turkey.He has also curated the 1st MEHRWIG International Biennale, L.A. to Chicago, USA, and was a curatorial advisor for the UK’s International Biennale Network, 2016. He has co-curated the Venice Biennale for the US pavilion, and was a curatorial advisor for the Venice and Italian pavilions in the US pavilion. He is a member of the Curator Council and the advisory board for the 20th Istanbul</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist, Not a Governmental Agency&quot; (2014), and Occupy Cairo (2014). His work in the public domain includes the Carrot Cake Project (2011-2015), the Egyptian Bookshelf Project (2010-2011), as well as the sculpture and installation Towards A Poor Egypt, 2014 by MOHAMMED ABD el-Basat and the public programme of the New Frontiers Foundation, 2015-16 by Nasser Rabbati.He has spoken at Venice Biennale, the Venice Architecture Biennale, the 2015 Bilderberg Network conference, the 16th Istanbul Biennale, and was a curator at the 2009 Rome Biennale. He was a curator for the Italian pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and the Italian pavilion in the US pavilion at the Venice Biennale. Papas is a curator and founder of Papas Antenna, a local art and cultural organisation, and a curator and curator at the Egyptian and Tunisian pavilions of the US pavilion at the 2013 GLAAD/SABCAL event, and was a curator at the 15th Istanbul Biennale. He has been a curator for the Egyptian and Tunisian pavilions at the Venice Biennale, and the US pavilion in the Tunisian pavilion. He is the author of From Cairo To Venice: Art, Architecture, Consensus (2015) and The Art of Not Being Governed: US Urban Development Priorities in a World Fractured into Subjects (2015). He is a Fellow of the American Museum of Naturalists and has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, and the Guardian. He is a recipient of the 2016 National Book Foundation Award for Social Criticism and a 2017 Guggenheim Fellow. He is the recipient of the 2017 Wilson Kerr Prize for Social Thought from the American Museum of Naturalists.Art has always been a prominent part of his identity.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York
    <text>should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1976, p.10.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a writer, curator, and founding director of the Heidelberg Gallery, New York City. She is the recipient of numerous awards and has curated numerous exhibitions including the 2014 Venice Biennale, the 2016 Whitney Biennale, the 2017 John Lennon Biennale, the 2017 Sarah Lowy Humanitarian Prize, and the 2018 Philip E Agre Humanitarian of the Year Shortlist. She has written for the New York Times, The New Republic, The New Republic Digital, and The New Republic Online, among others. She is the editor-in-chief of Digital Shortages, a digital literary journal published by the New Press Syndicate. She is a member of the board of the New York-based digital poetry collective, Digital Shortages.Gabriela Rendon is the editor-in-chief of Digital Shortages, a digital literary journal published by the New Press Syndicate</text>
    <text>should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1988, p.211.Download this article as PDFHeininger, J. (2016) 	The Art of Not Being Governed: Reflections on the Art of Not Being Governed, 2016. Installation, Brisbane. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextHeininger, J. (2016) 	The Art of Not Being Governed, 2016. Installation, Brisbane. Photo: Tom Lox. 	The Art of Not Being Governed, 2016. Installation, Brisbane. Photo: Tom Lox. 	The Art of Not Being Governed, 2016. Installation, Brisbane. Photo: Tom Lox. 	[2] John Berger, 	The Politics of Media/Rethinking U.S. Media, 1994, p.5.Download this article as PDFHeininger, J. (2016) 	The Politics of Media/Rethinking U.S. Media, 1994, p.6.[3</text>
    <text>should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 2004, and Bernard J. Heim, ed., The Contemporary Condition: Art, Criticism, and the Representations of Value, MIT Press, Cambridge, 2004. 	[2] Stuart Moulthroup,  	Fast Fact: Identifying Literary and Documentary Genres From Quarter Century to Twentieth Century, Duke University Press, Durham, 1998. 	[3] See: David Himmelstein, ed.,  	A Short Introduction to Documentary, CD-ROM, and Print, SUNY Press, Albany, 2003, p.20. 	[4] The following sample essay, from an unpublished essay entitled  	The Twenty-First Century Documentary, was first published in The New Inquiry, Issue 2, 2000, pp.75–81. (originally published in 2000 in response to the name of the artist who was to be considered for the posthumous Academy Award, but now</text>
    <text>should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1995, p. 17–26.Download this article as PDFHeinz SprachHeinz Sprach is Professor in Geographical Disciplines and Director of the Geographical Studies Program at the New School for Social Research in New York University. His publications include the collections The New Museum (2003), Maps (2006), and the forthcoming book Series C: Geographies of Art and Politics of Antiquity (2015). His essays include the essays collections The New Republic (2008) and The New Inquiry (2009). He has written for the New York Times, The New Republic, The New Republic (London), The New Republic (New York), The New Republic (Jerusalem) and The New Republic (Tokyo). He is part of the Editorial Writing Team for the forthcoming book of essays from the year 2000 on the Geographies of Our Time, the roots of postmodernism, and an answer to Richard Florida’s &quot;Where are the Origins of Our Ideas of Geography?&quot;</text>
    <text>should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1978, p. 3-39.Download this article as PDFJeff McMahanJesse Helmer and Amber Dean 	1 What makes a community a community is different from what makes a community a city or a community of people who happen to share a history or a place of habitation? For example, in the nineteenth century the nineteenth-century community was the urban community, but in the twentieth century it was the rural community, and in the twenty-first century it is the combination of both. Isolated incidents are common, but when they happen in and on a community level they often unfold due to the actions of individuals with a wide range of skills and competencies. In the nineteenth century the artists, writers, artists' families and other community members who produced and curated art during the Victorian era were largely excluded from participation in the artworld. In the twentieth century and beyond the participation of such communities was largely restricted to artists and a small elite. Even then, the participation of</text>
    <text>should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1980, p. 603. [2] David Heinemeier Hansson,  	Self- Criticism, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1982, p. 270. [3] Katharine Graham Pratt,  	Thinking Animals, New York University Press, New York, 1985, p. 139. [4] Katharine Graham Pratt,  	Thinking Animals, New York University Press, New York, 1985, p. 40. [5] Heinemeier Hansson, ‘The Creative Class’, in  	Thinking Animals, p. 40. [6] Thomas Merton,  	The Collected Essays of Thomas Merton, Vol. 2,  	Heinemeier Hansson,  	Heinemeier Haus, New York, 1980, p. 6. [7] Heinemeier Hansson, �</text>
    <text>should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1974, p. 20.  [2] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1974, p. 23.  [3] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1974, p. 23.  [4] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1976, p. 35.  [5] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1981, p. 4.  [6] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1983, p. 4.  [7] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary</text>
    <text>should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1980, p. 11.Download this article as PDFHeinz GrundmannHeinz Grundmann is an artist, writer, educator and the Chairperson of the Board of Governors of the Kübler-Ross Gallery, Berlin, Germany. He has curated over 50 exhibitions worldwide, including at Venice, New York and Berlin. He has received a host of accolades and has written several books on art and culture. His latest work, ‘Art as Public Practice’, was published by New Art Press, New York, 2016.The Crisis of the CityHeinz Grundmann is a writer and curator. His work has addressed a wide range of topics including the economic, political and social crises of the city. Recent books include: (1) The Society of the Spectacle (2013), (2) The Society of the Spectacle: Social Criticism and Modern Production (2014), (3) Modern Portraits: Essays on Photography and Art's</text>
    <text>should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1980, p.41.Download this article as PDFHeinz Gruen and Christoph BuchelHeinz Gruen and Christoph Buchel are Professor of Contemporary Art History and Director of the Centre for Art, Culture, and Politics of Modernity at the Max Planck Institute for Art, Culture and Politics in Berlin. They are co-curators of the upcoming Venice Biennale, and part of the curatorial team for the forthcoming Liverpool Biennale. They are co-curators of the upcoming 13th Kampala Art Biennale, and part of the curatorial team for the forthcoming 14th Kampala Art Biennale. They have co-curated the 13th Kampala Art Biennale, and part of the curatorial team for the forthcoming 14th Kampala Art Biennale. They were part of the curatorial team for the exhibition Constructing a Future for Ugandan Children, as well</text>
    <text>should be curated’s removal from its site. It is a question that, I believe, has relevance for us today. We need to be able to identify and identify with the places we are living today. This is how we acquire knowledge, how we acquire values and behaviours. We cannot acquire knowledge and morals in the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. That is, we cannot acquire morals and values through collections of historic photographs. Nor can we acquire morals and values through the same way that we acquire knowledge and knowledge. The ability to read between the lines, to discern what is being done in a given community today is fundamentally different from the ability to discern values and knowledge through a set of photographs. Yet we can all agree that it is vitally important to protect and preserve the historical and maritime heritage of our region at the same time. Do we? 	[1] See Bernard J. Heim, ed., Current Art and Contemporary Criticism, The New School Library, New York, 1988, p.20.Download this article as PDFHeinz GrundmannHeinz Grundmann is an artist. His practice is as curatorial for museums, galleries, archives and zoos as it is for education institutions, and he is currently Head of the Research Department at the Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology in Berlin. His work has been featured in numerous books, magazines and newspapers worldwide, as well as numerous reference works. His most recent work Animal Manor was commissioned by Liverpool Biennial 2015 and will be on view at Tate Gallery from November 2015. Anticipated Opening: 12 July 2016.Location: Berlin, Germany. Exhibition catalogue. Photo courtesy of Frieze.PreviousNextHeinz GrundmannHeinz Grundmann is an artist. His practice is as curatorial for museums, galleries, archives and zoos as it is for education institutions, and he is currently Head of the Research Department at the Max Planck Institute for</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
