<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.
    <text>will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.Download this article as PDFMatthew StokesMatthew Stokes is an artist. His work in the public sphere has been focused on the economic in the aftermath of neoliberalism, and the ecological in the aftermath of biennials and major exhibitions of new media. He is the Curator of Art and Leadership for the Public Programme of the Southwark Arts Forum, Southwark Arts Council, New Media Museum and Southwark Arts Forum, and he is currently Senior Curator at Tate Britain where he oversees the gallery programme. His latest project, New Media Monuments: Work and Life in the Context of Video, was recently presented by Tate Britain and Salford Museum of Art, and is the subject of a new book due to be published in 2017. Notes from the  	Future City 	Future City is a curatorial exercise in the social, cultural and political significance of new media technologies in contemporary society. It was originally designed and produced as part of the Turner Prize programme in September 2016</text>
    <text>will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.Download this article as PDFFrammeier &amp; Mandelstam Gallery, 2017. Photo by Carrie JohnstonPreviousNextFrammeier &amp; Mandelstam Gallery, 2017. Photo by Carrie JohnstonThe Flemish Painting Prize is a multi-award-winning, US-based, non-profit organisation established in 1994. It is a not-for-profit organisation, and its mission is to create opportunities for the sharing and exchange of artistic and creative processes through collaborative, artist-led projects in areas of the world where they are predominant. The Flemish Painting Prize was the inspiration for the exhibition at the Tate Modern, which opened in 2015. It was also the inspiration for the Centre piece, a multi-award-winning multi-sites project that opened in 2016. The Flemish Painting Prize was established in 1994 and is an international organisation with branches in Belgium, the Netherlands, Luxemburg and Berlin. It is a member of the Organisation for Transformative</text>
    <text>will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.Download this article as PDFMatthew StokesMatthew Stokes is Professor in the Department of Communication Studies and the Arts in the Graduate School of Arts and Sciences at McGill University. His research interests include the social construction of spatial forms and the media (particularly social media), the infrastructure of art, and the social consequences of intensive forms of simulation. His publications include the forthcoming book, Spatial Form: On the Metainterface of the Digital Metainterface (2017), which takes spatial forms into account in the construction of web services;  The Metainterface Archive: An Anthology of Illustrative Software (2018) for the book, which makes geographical infrastructures and their infrastructures of data an integral part of web infrastructures and their socio-politically reactive consequences; and most recently,  The Metainterface Project: A Cultural Contemporaneity (2017) for the book, which offers a unified front for the advancement of spatial and object</text>
    <text>will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.Download this article as PDFMatthew StokesMatthew Stokes is an artist. His work in the public arena has tended to respond to the contemporary condition through forms of protest, often relating to the economic. His installation, ‘Rip it up, Burn it down’ at the Manchester Museum, for example, was a response to the economic crash of 2008. His installation for the Liverpool Biennial, ‘You Say You Want a Revolution’, was also a response to the economic meltdown of 2008, but in a much more restrained way. It was also a response to the legacy of colonialism and slavery, and the legacy of oppression and conflict still lingers in many parts of the world. He has been called upon to be presentÂ at an ‘imminent’ gathering of leading artists and thinkers from across the globe to discuss the state of art and contemporary art in the world as a whole. To date, his installation at the Manchester Museum and his presentation at the Liverpool Bi</text>
    <text>will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.Download this article as PDFMatthew StokesMatthew Stokes is an artist. His practice involves historical and contemporary artworks that address the effects of modernism and urbanisation. His projects have been featured in the New York Times, the Wall Street Journal, the New Yorker, the Village Voice, and numerous other publications. He is the recipient of two 2014 Ig Nobel Prizes and was a finalist for the 2016 Tony and Cherie Blair Diversity Prize. He is the Senior Editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages, and the publisher of the online art journal at Stages (London and New York) Limited. His work for the New York Times includes articles on the Bluecoat, Wall Street Journal, the New Yorker, New York Magazine, Stages (London and New York), and many others.He is the Senior Editor of the online art journal Stages, and the publisher of the online art journal at Stages (London and New York) Limited. His work for the New</text>
    <text>will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.Download this article as PDFMatthew StokesMatthew Stokes is an artist and researcher who specialises in the contemporary world of art, visual culture, and is the Director of the Centre for Contemporary Art Studies at the University of Alberta. His research examines the historical and current conditions of art and stimulates discussion through discussions with artists, curators, critics, and students. His work has been exhibited in over twenty-five countries and has received an international audience. He has written for the Toronto Star, The New York Times, The New Republic, The New York Review of Books, The Nation, The Wall Street Journal, The Nation, The New Republic, The Hollywood Reporter, The Village Voice, The Village Voice, The Village Voice, The Village Voice, The Village Voice, The Village Voice, The Village Voice, The Village Voice, The Village Voice, The Village Voice, The Nation, The New York Times, The Washington Post and The Village Voice. He has been a presenter of CBC's The Current</text>
    <text>will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.Download this article as PDFMatthew StokesMatthew Stokes is an artist. His practice is collaborative, incorporating public and collective open-to-interpretation, art as a social practice, and materials that are both tangible (he has used them in ways that are ethical, political and economical) and intangible (material and malleable). In addition to founding the Bluecoat, he is the Director of Leeds Gallery Tract Society and a past president of the Board of the European Communities Trust. He is the author of From Counterculture to Cyberculture (2013 and forthcoming). His work with the Counter Culture tour organisation Auspicious Minds explored the relationship between the technological and the cultural in ways that are as plausible and as destabilising as his earlier work exploring the political and economic conditions of urban and rural life. His work is currently being commissioned by and part of the Curatorial team for the New Art project, and is due to be exhibited in the spring 2018 Biennale of Sydney at</text>
    <text>will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.Download this article as PDFMatthew StokesMatthew Stokes is Associate Professor in the Department of Communication Studies at the Winchester School of Art and the Graduate Center, the City University of New York, where he also holds the Donald E. Kolbe Chair in Art History and is the author of Contemporary Art: Issues of Identity in an Uncertain Post-Post-Industrial Society (2017). His work has addressed contemporary social and political issues including the impact of deindustrialisation, the politics of the homeless and the incarceration of activists, and he has received a regular stream of critical feedback from readers and peers, many of which have commented on the same sections of his book as they have on his other work. He is the co-editor of the forthcoming Issues of Identity in an Uncertain Post-Industrial Society (2018) which will be published later this year. contemporary art as a production of precariousnessMatthew Stokes’ work often addresses the conditions of modern art production</text>
    <text>will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.  [2] The question of whether the use of language is a construct or an artefact of the modern language is arguably one of the most pervasive in the ‘modern’. See  Pascual-Leone &amp; Coel, Elements of Modern Spanish Writing, pp. 69–83; Sánchez-Altamura, Linguistics: Language as a Social Form (Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1983), p. 138.  [3] The geographer Tim Cresswell analyses the role of the urban in a multi-sited metropolis, from the 1980 Venice Biennale to the present-day Abu Dhabi. He finds that cities today play a pivotal role in supporting a multi-tiered economy, fostering social mobility and ensuring a healthy environment – all tasks that are sufficiently capable of being performed by any number of autonomous agents. Unfortunately, the human settlement in the city is spread over large areas and located in close proximity</text>
    <text>will be curated by Matt Stokes and Vanessa Boni, and will be exhibited at the Bluecoat Gallery, London, and at the Bluecoat, Leeds, in early 2017. www.bluecoat.co.uk/gallery/2018/exhibition/art/214957.html 	[1] The Bluecoat was founded in 1887 and was one of the first art galleries in Leeds. It was, however, not the first or even the main art gallery in Leeds, and it is not likely to be the last. See, for example, the Los Angeles and New York Philharmonic, whose galleries in the city followed soon after. See also Matthew Stokes and Vanessa Boni, ‘On the Modern Condition: Art's Role in Recent Trends’, in, Nadine Attewell, ed., Recent Developments in Art and Art’s Social Context (New York: New York University Press, 2016), pp. 57–74.Download this article as PDFMatthew StokesMatthew Stokes is an artist, writer and Professor in the Department of the Arts, Media and Society at the University of Oxford, where he is also Professor in the Art and Communications Department. His latest book is What is Contemporary Art? (2017), which addresses the role artists play in contemporary cultural formations. In addition to his regular columns in The Guardian (UK), The Observer (UK), and The New York Times (US), he is an adjunct curator at the Tate Modern where he works alongside his wife, Zoya, who is the assistant curator. In 2015 they opened the multi-disciplinary Gallery Assemble in Athens, Greece, where they present a series of projects from 2007–2013 including installation and reading groups exploring the history, art and practices of the Greek Theater and Underground, as well as a reading group exploring the work of Art and Architecture underground. They are currently conducting a series of fieldwork projects in Cyprus, Israel and the West Bank. In</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas
    <text>archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas and culture, often in a form that is static and unchanging. It is the contemporary simulacrum of a givenity. And although the biennial has clearly emerged as a dominant exhibitionary form in the last twenty years, it is worth recalling that the biennial was largely invented in 1966 by George Singer, a biographer of Paul Newman, who wrote the book ‘Gentlemen’ in 1966. Singer, a biographer, used the phrase ‘biennial’ to describe a collection that was episodic, curatorial and textual, and which followed a strict theme. And ‘biennial’ as an adjective was here first coined in the second half of the twentieth century.Beginning of the End of the BiennialIn 1966, my then-fiancé, the artistes Ross had, with their venues in the Prado Museum and Tate Modern, and their growing list of writers, curators, collectors and activists, embarked on a series of series of visits</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas and narratives, and its materiality tends to be contested. It is a very particular kind of cultural capital to be made in the biennial, and the materiality of this is what makes it contemporary, whatever the other. But the biennial is a building block of a city, and its use today necessarily entails a certain amount of cultural capital too. The biennial is a building block of a city, but it does not itself represent the city; rather, it represents a particular kind of real estate, or ‘place-making potentiality’ that the city (in or through which it is constructed) has retained through diligent management over decades. The real estate is always in transition, and yet its very contemporary character – in its ability to generate new artworks, to be lived in contemporaneity with contemporary artworks, to be manufactured and resold – is what makes it a cultural capital. The ability of biennials to foster new artworks and render existing art obsolete is</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas and narratives, expressed in a form that is specific to the site, often expressed through a place (often a city) as a whole. It is a temporal feature, one that is constantly on the lookout for its host, and which seeks to establish an international reputation by being present in a local context. It is a place of encounter, not necessarily an establishment place, but one that seeks to foster a relationship through exchange and knowledge. As a visitor to any city museum, or even a local museum, will tell you, a ‘biennial’ is more a collection of collections, a monument to a given collection. And while today's biennials may include collections from many localities, today's biennials are usually collections from a particular city (or cities, or regions), and the collection as a whole is usually a collection of collections from that city. And so the theme of the biennial is always going to be ‘international’, although the ‘international</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas and narratives, often repeated over and over again, which are often presented as the sole correct or representative form of contemporary art. It is a place where different interpretations or representations of the same idea can be found, or invented, depending on one’s point of view. And while the biennial may or may not include the idea or story that is presented as its primary point of view, it is certain that it will always contain some element or other that is presented in an ideological or political light. In this sense, the term ‘biennial’ encompasses not only the collection of objects in a museum, archive or collection, but also includes cultural institutions such as museums, archives, archives, archives, and the like. Biennials have become so embedded in our cultural landscape that we rarely get to see them in art forms, and rarely get to do something with them. But every now and then a museum or a large archive or collection of cultural institutions decides to host a biennial</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas and projectivities; its materiality is a result of the complex processes of cultural capital accumulation that gradually transform what is or can be called the ‘biennial’ into the ‘cultural institution’. The accumulation of cultural capital, in turn, creates material forms that are both stable (i.e. non-contemporaneous) and fluid (i.e. subject to change, constantly shifting and mobile). And so, too, do the political and material forms of cultural capital. One result of this process is that biennials are no longer the sole sites of exhibition and extra-art venue, and that many other exhibitionary forms, including those in their historical hey-days, now exist and are quite visible. But they are by no means the main or even most prominent form of exhibitionary form in the contemporary world. We also live in a world in which the social is increasingly subordinate to the economising economic. We live in a world in which bienn</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas, practices, or collections; it is also a set of relations. The word ‘biennial’ has been co-invented, which means that ideas, practices or collections are/were prevalent in ideas, beliefs, or in the actual world at a particular moment in time. So the biennial is a double-edged sword. It can mean power (in that it permits and even endorses an interpretation of a given idea, practice, or collection) and material comfort (in that it provides and supports the essential infrastructure of the biennial, its promotional apparatus and its institutional forms of expression).The biennial has come to represent, as David Hockney (the Biennial Artist) puts it, ‘the ultimate expression of the power of the biennial to create and maintain cultural capital’. This is at odds with the unstated assumption of much of the value in the concept – perhaps, in the history of the biennial, the ultimate expression of this assumption</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas and images, often in a public forum, often on a global scale. Its social functions derive from the fact that it is the international marketplace of ideas, so its funding comes from a capitalising capitalist public. It is a cultural singularity in its own right, and yet it must also contend with the fact that it is structurally interwoven with its urban and regionalised clientèle, often operating at the level of a city or region. It is this dynamic that the biennial must constantly be on the lookout for, or else fall victim to. The biennial is a global phenomenon, but it is itself a domestic one, with its particularity confined to its home turf. It is only at this international level that its potential can be realised, and only at these international levels can it conduct significant socio-politically relevant research. The main reason why the biennial remains so deeply embedded in our cities is precisely because it can, and will always, find a home. It is</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas, which are then regularly modified, supplemented or abandoned in response to changing circumstances. It is a cultural institution, and while it may convey these ideas in a number of other ways (including physically), precisely because it is a cultural institution, and especially because it is regularly shown in a designated cultural centre, then it is still only a ‘fixed point of view’ in a particular cultural neighbourhood. It is on this latter account that the biennial is most susceptible to the pressures of capital accumulation. It is commonplace for biennials to be informed or even instigated by the Museum of Modern Art, whose curatorial arm, the museum, is frequently accused of being antiquated or antiquated-looking (a charge it strenuously denies).Other art forms have their festivals of their own, and many cultural institutions, including the museum, have their own festivals, but they are usually seen as supplemental, supplemental or ‘celebrity’-supporting in that they are events that draw</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas and issues, and for the subsequent re-presentation or reiteration of those ideas and issues at various scales or forms. It is, in other words, not a site or sites for the expression or discussion of a particular historical event or set of ideas; nor is it a place for the recovery of cultural practices or practices. Rather, it is a place where a cultural authority or set of ideas is said to be reigning or existing. This last quality is an essential to the biennial as we understand it today, and it is what makes it different from other cultural apparatuses. A museum, a.k.a. a cultural locus of power, a.k.a. a museum of ideas, holds a particular linguistic and taxonomic quality that is both authoritative and subversive of change. It is both a static building block – a kind of core building of the contemporary culture – and a site of constant shifting and emerging (forming, that is, not currently in existence) that</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, in particular, which is perennially at odds with the contemporaneous materiality of work, activity and circulation in modern city. The so-called ‘biennial boom’ of the 1990s ushered in a number of new breed of biennials, which appealed to a more urban centre’s accommodation to visitors from that era. Biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, regularly cited as a pre-requisite for a city’s future cultural institutions. But in the 1990s, the biennial boom was accompanied by a crash, which for many reasons – deeply felt, protracted and often violent – almost wiped out the cultural institutions that we now call the biennial. And while the biennial has largely recovered from these traumas, their political and material characteristics are still to be found in contemporary art forms, especially in the forms that we now associate with the contemporary. The biennial is a venue for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas and, in contemporary art terms, a set of practices. As the number and variety of exhibition space multiplied, so did the number of participants in a biennial exhibition. And as a curatorial exercise, exhibitions are a place for the presentation of a fixed or growing set of ideas, usually those shared by many visitors to the same site, and are thus a place for the presentation of a changing set of global ideals. They are a particular form of cultural artefact, elevated to a special status in a city, a past that is somehow remembered but not actually present in the present.They were, however, always at odds with each other, and as a curatorial exercise, occasionally provoked fierce rivalries (Venice Portobello, Tijuana Five’s ‘Cuba’s Little Trees’ exhibition in 1992, for starters). And while they might be local in their conception and implementation, biennials have become cultural institutions in their own right, with a distinctive cur</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011
    <text>an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011–present)Future City teamNassim TalebSofia MillánOsip MandelstamCollection: Futura, 2010. Branch: CA1604202, ca. 8 x 6.5 in wove, fiber, paper, wood, metal, wax, clay and rubber, lot # G-06-03025Collection: Futura, 2010. Branch: CA1604202, ca. 8 x 6.5 in wove, fiber, paper, wood, metal, wax, clay and rubber, lot # G-06-03025, auction # F-06-03025. © Sofia MillánAll rights reserved, DACS 2015.Sofia MillánCarrot CakeRecipes by the Homebaked ChefsPreviousNextCarrot CakeIngredients 230g peeled and finely grated Carrots900g peeled and grated Root Ginger300g peeled and grated Onion200g peeled and grated Ginger Root400g</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011-ongoing)Presentation as part of the 3rd Burnley Biennial, 2018. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextArt (2011-ongoing)Presentation as part of the 3rd Burnley Biennial, 2018. Photo: Tom Lox.'Tis the season to be merry, to share, to exchange, to meet, to be merry, to be merry.  - William Shakespeare, King Henry VI Author's Preface, King Henry VI, 1523, Shakespeare and Company, Tudor, Shakespeare and Company, London, 2015.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJenny Gleadhill is a writer and performer best known for her work at the Liverpool Biennial, where she performed The Three Musketeers, and in the Tate Modern, where she explored the role of the gun in the Napoleonic wars. In 2015, she produced and co-commissioned The Two Towers, a performative ‘recap</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011-present) - Documenta 13, Istanbul, Turkey; Welsh Streets Arts Festival, Liverpool, England; Manchester Artspace, Manchester, England; Jussi ParikkaURI: Your project with Documenta 13 was inspired by the example of the Romanian artist Caracal, who has a new exhibition scheduled to open in Istanbul. Documenta 13 is her large-scale, three-month exploration of identity and public space set in Istanbul. Documenta 13 is also her new project with Welsh Streets Arts Festival Liverpool, which brings together Welsh Streets, Documenta 13 and FACT, and documents the experiences and works of each organisation in a public space context. For the Liverpool Biennial, you established a project within Documenta 13 with Caracal, whose name comes from the 13th edition of the Biennale, and whose works are named after the 13th edition of the Biennale itself. What brought you to Documenta 13 and to Welsh Streets?</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011-ongoing)CuratorialI was born and raised in India, but raised in the US as well. I started when I was seven years old making figures and street art in my bedroom. I started painting when I was nine and have been doing it ever since. It’s a very traditional Indian painting technique with bright colours and abstract patterns. I started out with landscapes and over the years I have added buildings, animals, historical figures and now this one is a sculpture of a woman. She is shrouded in mystery, but the more I look at her the more I want to know what she is wearing and why. When I get really excited about something I will make a sculpture out of the imagery. This is a hybrid technique that I use with great artistic freedom: sculpture, painting, narrative. When I first started it was just for show and museum purposes. Later on I started thinking about making things that people would want to come see and that also engage with. I started thinking about</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011-ongoing)Part One: The Rediscovery of Art’s PastNYT Picker (2011-ongoing)Art (2011-ongoing)Part Two: The Politics of the Real in Art's RetrospectiveNYT Picker (2011-ongoing)Art (2011-ongoing)Part Three: The Politics of Access in Art's RetrospectiveNYT Picker (2011-ongoing)Art (2011-ongoing)Part Four: Access to Experience in RetrospectiveNYT Picker (2011-ongoing)Art (2011-ongoing)Part Five: Art and the Politics of Access in the 21st CenturyNYT Picker (2011-ongoing)Art (2011-ongoing)Part Six: From Access to Strategy: World War ZNYT Picker (2011-ongoing)Art (2012-ongoing)Part Seven: From Strategy to Survival: The Art of Post-Traumatic Stress DisorderNYT Picker</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011–present)PreviousNextArt (2011–present)Jonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artspace, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...HomebakedCommunity ArtProject (2011–present)Homebaked is a project formed in 2008 by Leeds Artspace, Leeds School of Art, The Black-E, Deena Chalabi and others based in and around the city. The goal of the</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011-2018)Curatorial IntentionsPreviousNextArt (2011-2018)Jonathan CraryA collection of objects was donated by the family of Ronnie O'Rourke, who was murdered in the Syrian city of Homs in 2008. The collection came to my attention whilst researching the uprising in Bahrain against the monarchy, which is currently embroiled in a political crisis. Although there is no evidence of any direct involvement from the UK or US government, the inclusion of this collection in the exhibition reflects the warped political mindset of the dominant culture in that country. The institutionalised division between 'us' and 'them' that characterises the lived experience of being Black, Muslim or Arab in Bahrain is reproduced in the media, academia, law and in many other public spaces and institutions. The collection thus represents a snapshot in time, a way to imagine things differently. It was designed with this in mind. Building Blocks for Biennials in Future City (Part 1)PreviousNextBuilding Blocks for Biennials in</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011-ongoing)I started out by asking whether there had been any unexpected changes in the way that art and education interact in the UK in the past ten years. The short answer to that question is yes. I’ve heard some people say that the increase in state arts funding for UK cities has had an effect on art education, but I think that claim is just as fallacious as the claim that the quality of art education has increased in the UK. The real funding boost for arts education in the UK has come from outside the institution, and it’s this interconnection that I wanted to explore.  ART (2011-ongoing)In 2011, the Biennial format was formally re-organized into the new  	Academia 3. I thought it would be interesting to explore this structure in relation to the history of art and education in the UK, and the US.  ART (2011-ongoing)In 2011, the Biennial format was formally re</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011-) as Media (2011)Jonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is based on the relationship between art and education and how education can work with art, organisations and individuals. He has exhibited widely including at The American Museum of Natural History, Venice, Venice Biennale, New York Museum of Art, Venice, and various other venues. He has written for The New York Times, The New Yorker, The New Republic, The New York Times Digital Archive, The New York Times Digital Archive, The New Republic Digital Archive, The New York Times Digital Archive, and The New York Times Digital Archive. He was a judge on the newscast shows 'The Voice of the City', hosted by The Today Show and The Morning Report, and has lectured on art, cities and education. He was instrumental in getting the hugely popular Instagram platform launched in China and has written for The New York Times Digital Archive, The New Yorker, The New Republic, The New York Times</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation, which opened as part of its `Digital Muralistas: Mobile Muralists from Iran’s First Gulf War Museums. The exhibition was curated by Qomayb Artusdaghi and Farshid Javed.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJonathan Crary is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education and how education can work in a collaborative and equitable way with art, organisations and individuals. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artsapce, Yorkshire Artspace, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He has been a judge at the Black-E, Black-E, Black-E, a local arts venue in Lewisham, and was a judge at the 2012 London Arts Festival. He is currently a judge at the 4th Oxford and Southwark Arts Venue, and the 2012 Oxford and Southwark Arts Cymrui... read more...Art (2011-2016)PreviousNextArt (2011-2016)Jussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an artist. His work in education is centred on the relationship between art and education. His project 'Where are You Right Now?' utilises social media to engage with the question, where one lives, and how one is affected by change. His work has been commissioned by Leeds Artspace, Yorkshire Artspace, Black-E, and the Arts Council of Great Britain. He also co-directs the online arts and social practice website www.thesocialusefront.com.au/2015/ours-universities-in-the-re-public-... read more...Dolphin Contemporary Art Gallery Liverpool, June 2017PreviousNextDolphin Contemporary Art Gallery Liverpool, June 2017Dolphin Contemporary Art Gallery Liverpool, June 2017I came to Liverpool as a Fulbright scholar in 2016, intending to study the art of transport and urbanisation from a feminist perspective.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial website, https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [6] Whitney Biennial website, https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [7] Whitney Biennial website, https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [8] Whitney Biennial website, https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [9] See, for example, https://www.academia.org/1702/the-white-board-computer-</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [6] Whitney Biennial website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [7] Ibid. See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018).[8] Whitney Biennial website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [9] Whitney Biennial website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial website, https://www.whitney.org/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [6] Whitney Biennial press release, https://www.whitney.org/press-releases/whitney-biennial-2015-summary.html (accessed January 2018). [7] Whitney Biennial website, https://www.whitney.org/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [8] Whitney Biennial press release, https://www.whitney.org/press-releases/whitney-biennial-2015-summary.html (accessed January 2018). [9] See also Phil Agre, The Art of Not Being Governed: The Socially Responsible Art of Autonomy, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2005</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed March 2018). [6] Whitney Biennial website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed July 2018). [7] Whitney Biennial website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed November 2018). [8] Whitney Biennial website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed March 2019). [9] Whitney Biennial website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial’s website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [6] Whitney Biennial’s website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [7] Whitney Biennial’s website, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [8] Whitney Biennial, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [9] Whitney Biennial, The Whitney Biennial Trust, http://www.whitney.com</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial, Whitney Center, 2014. Installation view at the Whitney Museum of American Art. Photo courtesy of the Whitney Museum of American Art. [6] See also Whitney Museum of American Art, http://www.whitney.org/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=Whitney_Collection_2015_e_0608_summary (accessed June 2018). [7] Whitney Biennial, Whitney Center, 2014. Installation view at the Whitney Museum of American Art. Photo courtesy of the Whitney Museum of American Art. [8] Whitney, Whitney Biennial, 2014. Final project report. Photo courtesy of the Whitney Museum of American Art. [9] See also Whitney, http://www.whitney.org/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=Whitney_Collection_2015_e_0</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [6] Whitney Biennial, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [7] Whitney Biennial, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [8] Whitney Biennial, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [9] Whitney Biennial, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial, San Francisco (2015). Retrieved February 2018. [6] See also, e.g., Tom Jewett, ‘The Whitworth File: A Personal Narrative of Two Visits to the Museum’, in The Whitworth File: A Personal Narrative of Two Visits to the Museum, ed. Stefan Collini and Tom Jewett, Manchester University Press, Manchester, 1986, p. 82. [7] See also, e.g., Tom Jewett, ‘The Whitworth File: A Personal Narrative of Two Visits to the Museum’, in The Whitworth File: A Personal Narrative of Two Visits to the Museum, ed. Stefan Collini and Tom Jewett, Manchester University Press, Manchester, 1986, p. 83. [8] Jewett, op. cit., p. 83. [9] See, for example, Collini and Collini, Manchester University Press, Manchester, 1986, p. 78.</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial is the latest iteration of a tradition that began in 1994 with the original Sydney, Australia, biennale. The Whitney Biennial 2018 was curated as a present in the H. Lee and Jacob Lund Pavilion at the San Francisco Museum of Modern Art. The other previous instalments have been presented in front of a live audience in New York and Los Angeles, respectively.Yvonne Rainer, The Americas of the Future: Art from Globalization, 1995–1999, UC Hastings Center, Vancouver, Canada, 1999. Photograph courtesy of the UC Hastings Center Archive. [6] See Colin Ward, ‘On Immersive Painting’, in, Visual Culturistics, Issue 7, June, 1999, p.141. [7] Ward, ‘On Immersive Painting’, was a contemporary artist who specialized in the use of virtual media to engage with the 'real-life' experience of cultural consumption. He was the co-founder of Brave Collective, a global</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be held at the Bienal de São Paulo, Brazil, in October 2017.  [1] See http://www.whitney.com/en/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2014/exhibition/index.html (accessed June 2018). [2] See also http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [3] See the first page of the catalogue, http://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collections/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [4] See also https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [5] Whitney Biennial website, https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [6] Whitney Biennial press release, https://www.whiteney.com/press-releases/whitney-2018-summary-summary.html?format=summary&amp;month=novac&amp;day=novac&amp;year=2018 (accessed September 2018). [7] Whitney Biennial website, https://www.whitney.com/en/exhibitions/whitney-collection/2015/exhibition/index.html (accessed January 2018). [8] Whitney Biennial press release, https://www.whiteney.com/press-release/whitney-20150724-summary.html?format=release&amp;month=novac&amp;day=novac&amp;year=2015&amp;subscription=first (accessed September</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer a new way of looking at art and the contemporary condition of everyday life. Drawing directly on their experiences during The Resident, they reveal a cultural history that is complex, contradictory and ultimately satisfying. The Contemporary Condition will be published as a book series in June 2019.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition, offer a new way of looking at art and the contemporary condition of everyday life. Drawing directly on their experiences during The Resident, they reveal a cultural history that is complex, contradictory and ultimately satisfying. The Contemporary Condition will be published as a book series in June 2019.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition, offer a new way of looking at art and the contemporary condition of everyday life. Drawing directly on their experiences during The Resident,</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer a fresh and provocative perspective on the contemporary condition. In their view, the contemporary contemporary condition – a.k.a. the era of the Internet, Instagram and Facebook ­– offers us no fixed understanding of continuity or contemporaneity, and so we need to invent our own understanding of the temporal complexity that characterises the contemporary temporal complexity paradigm.To do so, the artists and curators in The Contemporary Condition build their account on a narrative of events, places and things that happened in the last century. They foreground the cultural transformation that resulted from reading the works of a range of artists and thinkers, including Jean Paul Sartre, Max Horkheimer, Herman Goring, Irving Kristol and Suzanne Lacy, as well as biennials, documenta and lithographs. They then foreground the role of the historian, presenting a survey of the leading figures – thinkers such as Sartre, Kristol and Lacy ­– in constructing and narrating the understanding of the twentieth and</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer a fresh and provocative approach to the politics, ideologies and cultural practices of late imperial transformation and contemporary globalism. Drawing upon extensive archival research, the two scholars bring together archival sources, political science, archival diaries, art, photography, texts, and archival documents to decipher the many layers and creases of contemporary culture, urbanisation and flux. Whether researching the social, economic and spatial conditions of modernity in the aftermath of major social and political upheavals, or investigating the contemporaneous political and ecological conditions that followed from the industrial revolution, the two authors uncover contradictions and similarities, but also the distinctive and persistent features of contemporary culture and urbanisation. Drawing upon their expertise as art historians and imaging professionals, they also uncover a neglected and destabilising infrastructure of ideas, practices, ideologies, and practices that is both cultural and political in the making, but which – despite its seemingly powerful array of words – is quite hard to figure out.This is the second part of a two</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer a fresh perspective on a particular style of cultural theorization. Drawing upon a rich body of research, their book documents the experiences and practices of their generation of artists, collectors and writers during the period from 2010–2016. Their book, published in the United Kingdom and America, and internationally distributed in the United States and Germany, is the result of a year-long collaborative process that culminated in March 2019 with the United States.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna Best's 'The Contemporary Condition'John Urry‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’. is a collection of short essays that capture the spirit, the everyday life and the culture of the late antique and early modern world in a single sitting. Drawing upon a rich body of research, the essays lay out the neurobiological, sociocultural and political factors that contribute to the contemporary condition. While the essays do not attempt to present a unified</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer a fresh and provocative interpretation of the ancient world’s classical cultures in which modernity was born. Drawing upon their own experiences as artists and historians, they reimagine the ancient world through the power of art, culture, and urbanization. Drawing on a year of research into the archives of ancient civilizations in the developing world, they produce a rich body of text that constitutes a new understanding of cultural practices, practices, and places of human social history that will challenge the prevailing narratives and paradigms of modernity. In the process, they risk becoming not only the forgotten but also the victors in a cultural power struggle that could alter how we understand the future.Modernity, Culture, and Art 	The Contemporary Condition, Chapter 2: Culture and Capital Culture and Capital: The Rise of Global Cultures 	In this chapter, Anna and her team of artists, curators, journalists, and historians trace the forces shaping and enabling culture today. They draw upon a rich body of text</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer a fresh and provocative interpretation of the concept of contemporaneity. In their words, ‘Contemporaneity’ is a time-critical concept that, at a fundamental level, is tied to the structure of the modern world.’ Through a collection of curatorial actions and project proposals, they demonstrate that the contemporary condition is deeply embedded in the contemporary form of cultural production.Contemporaneity is a concept that has been around for a while, but rarely gives full or meaningful expression to the spatial relations among artists, curators, collectors, collectors, critics and others with an interest in art and culture. The relationship between the artist and collector is conspicuous, but the collections agent is often invisible, except as a data point or a prop in a larger production. Contemporaneity, then, is a concept that is often under-explored or misunderstood. It is a term that is frequently used synonymously, but rarely truly understood. Drawing upon her work</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer a fresh and provocative interpretation of the concept of contemporaneity. Utilizing archival materials, including diaries, correspondence, artwork, travel and documents, the artists reconstruct the social and political contexts of the early modern period in Greece, Italy and Egypt. These texts provide a new paradigm for our understanding of the contemporaneity that seeks to grapple with the persistent and deeply embedded ideas of national belonging, cultural difference, the modernising influence of modernism and the politics of difference. The artists argue that the present we inhabit is an artifact of the past; that, rather, it is the ongoing and compressed condition of contemporaneity. They use these terms to reflect on ideas of contemporaneity in an age of globalised information technologies, material abundance and ecological crises. The book is the product of a year-long, multi-disciplinary research project that sought to understand how art and artists are positioned in time and across cultures. It sought to understand how art is produced in conditions of material abundance</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer a fresh and provocative alternative to the tired and often simplistic contemporary contemporary art-history narratives of art and culture. Drawing from their curatorial training at the Victoria and Albert Museum, Liverpool, and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, Anna and her team embark on a critical look at the way we understand contemporaneity, imagining what it means to be contemporaneous with art today. What is contemporary in these terms, according to their thinking, is necessarily global and ephemeral, and events such as the Brexit vote and American presidential election result, and the war in Ukraine, are only part of a globally distributed and mediated picture of contemporaneity. Contemporary art today is globalised; and art’s global reach is the direct result of the development of ever more intricate and interconnected information technologies, which make it easier and more economical to travel to many places in the world.  	[2] Thoreau, ‘Essays on the nature of contemporaneity�</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer an alternative understanding of the contemporary condition through the structure of a biennial, rather than the static variety of an art gallery, museum or collection. Drawing on her own unique perspective and expertise, Anna examines the cultural and economic factors that contributed to the construction of modern museum-going experiences, particularly in the form of dense, suburbanized, and urban museums. Through a combination of ethnographic, archival, and historical research, she seeks to identify critical precursors of the present in the city and rural areas, and throughout the world. Drawing upon a unique combination of languages, she explores the history of photography, video and film, as well as the social, political and legal conditions that simultaneously constituted and created the contemporary condition. Her research takes multiple forms: historical, qualitative, quantitative, and narrative, as well as curatorial, educational and archival. The book is divided into four sections: The Contemporary Condition, The Gallery and the Public, The Public Gallery and the Gallery of Art, and</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial, curated by MOCAD resident artistes Anna Best and Angie Johnson, will open in December 2018. Anna and Angie will lead a team of artists, curators, journalists and researchers as they investigate the biennial as a continuous cultural practice. This will be their most extensive research to date, but it will also reveal surprising continuities and divisions within and between art, biennials and the contemporary artworld. The two-day event, curated by Anna and Angie Johnson, will take place December 9–11, 2018.  [1]   John Urry, ‘On the nature of contemporaneity: a reading of Late Greek and Roman cultural theory’, in Modern Cultural Theory, Vol. 32, No. 2 (January, 2014), p.335.Download this article as PDFAngie Johnson and Anna BestAnna Best and her team of artists, curators, journalists and historians, in their new book The Contemporary Condition (2018), offer a fresh and provocative approach to the complexities and differences of our contemporary cultural situation. In their view, much of what we take for granted as contemporary – the ‘culture industry’ – constitutes a deeply flawed representation of the actual conditions of existence of people and places on a global scale. The book is divided into four sections covering the social, economic and political dimensions of contemporary life, and their relationship to ideas of contemporaneity. Chapter 1 focuses on the social. It begins with an introduction to the concept of contemporary culture. The social is a concept with an assumed shared origin – and hence a shared vocabulary – that exists in all contemporary languages, and therefore all human languages can be considered to be contemporary. Yet the social is also an idea with a number of contested origins. Most contemporary social ideas are conceived as fundamentally or primarily related to the interests of multinational corporations and their boards of directors. The social is more easily conceived as the idea that arises from a given set of circumstances and is therefore more</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media
    <text>archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media. In other words, the biennial was often seen as a vehicle through which the politics of culture were brought into being.    	In recent decades, when biennials have become more prominent, it is often as a side-effect of other trends in urban development, such as the expansion of tourism, the expansion of international conventions, and the democratisation of media culture industries. The biennial becomes the main exhibitionary form in cities in large amounts of both developed and developing nations, and attracts large audiences from all over the world. 	Art and cultural tourism account for over 20% of all tourist spending in South Korea, Japan, and other major tourist destinations.2  And though in recent years the cultural tourism sector has started to experience its share of turbulence and cutbacks, it is important to stress that these are only the sectors with which the biennials are directly connected. The social and cultural tourism generated by the biennial has to negotiate a wider market dominated by</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media. As a result, it is easy to see how the biennial has come to render marginalised and oppressed communities the property of large corporations and the dominant forms of society. 	Since the mid-1990s, the biennial has increasingly been seen as a last resort, a relatively unstable venue that must be decisively terminated in order to permit new opportunities to be unearthed. Although it is true that in recent biennials the termination of profits has come before the imperative necessity of providing publics – a process that has been going on for decades now – there is reason to believe that the biennial may yet form part of a larger overture, if it ceases to be concerned with profit itself and instead adopts the role of the mediator of its own possibilities. 	In my opinion, the time has come to redefine the biennial as a last resort, to abandon its fixation on the capitalist profitability of art and culture, and to act in favour of the publics, especially those</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media.  	The biennial format has varied greatly over time, but generally speaking, the artistically ambitious organisation seeking to produce a ‘significant cultural impact’ in the city has sought to engage with the city during a post-production stage. Art institutions, including those established in the UK, have historically been interested in the creation of a cultural identity around a specific artist or artist, and the development of a relationship with the city through programming, particularly programmes oriented towards reproducing contemporary art worldwide. 	The Biennale as a Form,  	W. Maurizio Lazzarato, (Image courtesy of the Biennale). In the 1980s and 1990s, artists and artists’ organisations began to develop innovative ways of framing the interaction between art and community, between community and art institutions, and between community and the biennial itself. These new forms of engagement often sought to decipher the language of participation and discovery, asking: how can art be produced in</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media.  	The contemporary biennial is an event that can be seen as both a response to and a complication of the crisis of poverty. It is a ‘big-picture’ event with a ‘stern’ face, addressing a much broader public. 	Its popularity comes as no surprise to those who have studied, experienced, or followed art’s social dynamics. 	Its ubiquity as an exhibition attraction, and its organisational abilities in the face of state repression, has come at a cost. In the 1990s, the art fair was fundamentally undermined by the emergence of the ‘Curatorial Centric Development [CCDD] movement’, which sought to establish a single global benchmark for aestheticisation and cultural capital.2  The biennale has its own set of discursively-generated contemporary ethical questions, including as it does the contemporary ethical quandary: is art itself a ‘capitalist cultural production?’?</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media.  	Further readings 	Brent Bellamy, The Cultural Logic of U.S. Economic Development (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2011), p. 3. 	Peter Lawrence,  	Money, Power and the Politics of Cultures (Cambridge: The MIT Press, 1992), p. 23. 	Stella Quines,  	The Rise of the Cultures of Commerce (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2012), p. 34. 	Robert H MacDonald, ‘Cultures of Capital: Modern Art and International Finance as Transnational Fuglaciators’,  	Towards a Theory of International Finance (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1972), p. 3. 	Robert H MacDonald, ‘The End of Cultures’,  	Towards a Theory of Intangible Assets (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1983), p. 3. 	</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media.  	The purchase of cultural commodities is a function of numerous social and economic factors, which are beyond the scope of this article. Nevertheless, the increasing commodification of images of art and images of art’s audience via social media and the in-store display of contemporary artworks, is a recurring theme of the biennial calendar. 	In 1983, the Venice Biennale commissioned Peter Schjeldahl to develop a plan for the archival and ethnographic study of the city, surrounding peninsula and Venice. Schjeldahl developed the plan for the first time in 1987, during the construction of The Empire State Building.2  The plan, a revised and enlarged version of which was presented as the basis for the planned ethnographic survey of the peninsula and Venice in 1992, was published in 1993 and remains the basis for an ongoing commissioning process today. 	Schjeldahl followed up his ethnographic survey in 1994 with a survey of the region�</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media and technology. The biennial became something that people could point to and identify with, rather than something that is inherently contingent on the historical moment. 	So, we can add another element to the mix: the proliferation of biennials has led to a proliferation of biennials themselves, which have become ever more sophisticated, diversified and opulent in their formative experiences, and continue to add to the collections they uncover. 	And this brings us to our present and future predicament. The biennial has become something that is categorised by quite rigid criteria. It is no longer able to unfold in a traditional way as a curatorial statement, or in the form of a traditional art gallery. Biennials now also exhibit a growing literature of self-branding and are part of a larger ephemeral media-production complex that includes biennial exhibitions and the development of a curatorialal vocabulary. So a biennial can no longer be seen as something that is constitutive of</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media.  	Fast-food restaurants, music festivals, art galleries and museums, which once housed projects that enquired into the social implications of art and aesthetics, are now devices through which people are recruited and equipped for the work that they do not yet possess the skills for. The construction of ever larger and more diverse collections and exhibitions, and the continual circulation of these collections and exhibitions, is now seen as a necessity in an increasingly stratified society. The biennial may be seen as a fixed form, and its growth as the necessary next step in its social reproduction. But just as biennials have expanded in size and range over the years, their geographical locations have also diversified. 	The Los Angeles Basin is a region in which the cultural life takes place, meets the demands of a globalised urbanisation, and is all but colonised. It is an area with an estimated 11 million residents but also a significant number of tourists, many of whom come to the area to see</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media.   5  This is a compendium of ten of these media technologies (film, television, computer, books, DVDs, billboards, street art, street performers and social media) and their functions in the urbanisation of the US.   6  Not all biennials are created equal. The early twentieth-century biennale was a rare exception to this rule, in that it was possible to identify a particular biennale by a curatorial choice. The support of a national art gallery or a museum organisation was critical to staging a biennale, whereas the support of a biennial that is self-sustaining and produces its own revenue stream was much less so. Nevertheless, the ten biennials listed here represent the leading biennalists today, and their decisions to catalogue and present a particular event reflect the priorities of the art market today. The ten listed biennials comprise a field of work that was once considered ‘exclusive’</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which is today often seen as a response to the financial crisis, is now frequently seen as a response to the city’s crisis of poverty. In the 1980s and 1990s, biennials were initially instigated by a broad range of community and progressive organisations, including the Black International Aid Society, founded in 1980, and Black Panther Party, founded in 1991. Black Panther Party was a local offshoot of the Black International League for People of Colour (BLOC) and fought for the liberation of African-American people from colonialism and neo-colonialism. The Black Panther Party was banned by the state in 1986, but its ideas and programmes were incorporated into the national Democratic Party platform in 1992.1  The adoption of neoliberalism and the attendant production of surplus space brought about changes in the way in which people viewed art and culture, which in turn led to an increase in the value of art, which in turn increased the purchasing power of people with access to increasingly sophisticated media.  	In the years that followed, the artistic and cultural peripheries of the city experienced a glut of cultural products that could be snapped up quickly by investors and financial institutions, which led to a transient boom-bust cycle of artistic activity in the city.  	But the biennale didn’t become popular in the city due to a transient artistic boom; it was much more of a reaction to the city’s crisis of poverty, which it both symbolises and actually undertakes. The biennale, by contrast, is a great venue for reflecting on the past, which inevitably brings with it a concomitant of feelings of loss and anger.  	The biennial form entered into vogue during the 1990s and early 2000s, when the biennial itself and its collections of artefacts became hugely popular. The art market was flooded with these collections, which became collector's commodities. Art biennials became so popular that collections were identified</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/en/) or the figures in J.M. Coetzee’s The Fountainhead (1970), there is a familiar, yet shifting, character based on the exploration of the natural world. 	In the case of a biennial, however, the interpretive, material, and political dimensions of the art market are explicitly differentiated through the commissioned work, the researcher’s role, and the outlet for her/his research through publications, lectures, and events. Biodiversity,  	and art events are expressions of the socio-cultural forces shaping contemporary art forms, and their institutionalization is a global process. The biennial is not just an exhibitionary form; it is a geopolitical form, with real-life, concrete social consequences. It is a form of cultural exchange mediated through the material and imaginary resources of art. When all art forms are taken into consideration, it is a form of cultural consumption that is not just a form of consumption, but relies on</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/english/news/2017/exhibition/art-biennales-2018), we can see that this is a media-making mission. The museum is the primary site of stage, and the art world is the backdrop. But the media can also be employed to create a more expansive perception of the world around us, one in which we actually inhabit.Where does this model of the media-maker come from? When did the biennial first come to England? Is it really the Englishman who first Protestantised the art world or is it the Dutchman who is the first to adopt the Protestant faith? When did the biennale first come to America? Is it really the Dutchman who conceived and first implemented the art fair, or is it the American, who came first? When did the biennale first come to Paris? Is it really the American, who sits on the board of trustees, or is it the Russian, who chairs the advisory board? When did the bi</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/en/artnews/20170420_full-page-painting.html), a narrative element is added, often subtly.  The painting is a ‘biennial’ in the strictest meaning of the word. It is not a museum piece, nor is it a performance piece, nor is it a product of a curatorial or art-historical approach. It is a work of art, and as such it deserves to be understood in the strictest sense of the word.In the case of the M/M, the narrative element is added by the curator and her team to tell the story of the art, in a strict and sometimes contradictory sense. The artist is not there to tell the artist’s story, but to tell the story of the art, and the curatorial team here is no exception. The M/M project is not there to score artistic points, or to create a buzz or any other form of extraneous behaviour, but to tell</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/en/m/biennial/), the relationship is figurative as well as literal. When M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/en/m/biennial/) first launched, the mission statement read: ‘We are here to stay’. The nature of this ‘we’, or the biennial, as a structured organisation demands a continuing definition. The biennial as a cultural form is likely to be around for some time to come, but the mission statement (along with the  	biennial commissioning committee’s reports and other documents) remains the guiding light of the art world’s perception of the art form. This figurative writing is a powerful tool, and one that can exert a powerful influence on an artist’s work. It is used by some within the art world to delegitimise the work of others, to establish an authoritative voice within the art sector. It is not always</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/au/m/m-art/biennale/biennale.html), the association is that of a pilgrimage, and the object of the itinerary is a kind of sacrament. In this sense, the biennial is both a temporal phenomenon and a religious one. Yet the biennial, like any other art form, is also a social phenomenon. It is a social enterprise, but it is socially mediated: the art is produced, and the art conveys, and the art is shared. The art market, by and large, does not see art as a commodity, but as an asset, a gift, a resource, an asset that can be used to further the social mission of the cultural centre. And this is why the  	art market, as we move into the new media of digital distribution and ubiquitous access, is able to sustain the art condition in a way that cannot be replicated in the physical market. The market cannot create a biennial, but it can</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/public-art-series/biennials-in-pictures/) or the artwork of Sonia Diaz (http://www.sonia-diaz.com/home-art/201703305173.html), journalists often employ other language than literary to describe events in a cultural sense. Words and actions that are clearly understood are used to describe an event as it occurs, and ‘big picture’ is often used to describe the cultural landscape as a whole. Such figurative uses of ‘big picture’ are common in artworks, but journalism or serious cultural reporting is a completely different beast. Public art is often criticised for being too abstract, and ‘deep dive’ journalism more specifically, does not take into account of the complexity of the projects being made, or the human impact that cultural production can have. Journalists, on the other hand, often get a raw deal because they are ambitious and take the project on faith that</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/m/mmedia/index.html?), then the biennial is a ‘glimmer of hope’ in the darkening of a future that seems bleak by design. When used as a journalistically oriented sense, as in art books and magazine feature articles, the biennial becomes a call to action. Its publication, and consequent traffic, is a reductive end in itself, but its humanizing effect is cumulative and global.If we take the example of Venice, and its environs, then the ‘biennial boom’ might be seen as a precursory to the present, and the post-biennial phase as a phase in which art will be made and consumed in ever greater numbers. By the same token, the ‘episodic’ and ‘triennial’ might be seen as a prescriptive and ‘monumental’ form of art will be made in ever smaller numbers. This is the logic</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/en), the figurative language of the situation is used:  	the biennial is a ‘temporal ordering system’ that operates ‘out of time’, operating between past and future. 	The anthropologist Peter Osborne proposes a more precise definition of the biennial in his book  	The Anthropology of Entertainment: A Documentary History of the Art World 	. 	[i] He defines the institution ‘as a non-commercial, community-based multi-use cultural resource created and directed by and through an individual or small group of individuals, often through informal and networked means’ (p.6).  	[ii] He defines the non-commercial cultural resource thus:  	a set of skills, knowledge, resources, or knowledge that are useful in a specific context and may be shared between individuals or may be customised and made appropriate for use in a particular context. 	[iii] </text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/au/m/m/M?lang=en), the figurative language of the art market, the news media, and biennials,  the reference is to events occurring both within and without the art market. 	As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a literal sense, as in the work of a real-life artist, reporter, or editor, the answer is a simple: yes, I do believe that I can call a biennial what it is, and I’m doing exactly that. 	This is the literal translation of a tweet by journalist Yvonne García of El País (http://www.elpais.com/yvonne/essays/364/el-bulawebsite-201112091419.html),</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data, and the associated access to the art market, which in turn feeds into the art market. The point of view of the artist who commissioned the data is the point of view of the art market.Â Understanding this data is a journalist’s media-making mission statement: to find and deliver the news that will generate interest, and perhaps change minds.Here, then, we can move from the   	analysis of the art market to the more fundamental mission of journalism. Journalism is an art form, and journalists dedicate a significant amount of time to learning the intricacies of this craft. The journalism of the biennial is no exception. As the biennial matures, and the journalist’s writing becomes longer and more complex, she/he must constantly renegotiate the meaning of the word biennial. When the term biennial is used in a figurative sense, as in the work of M/M (http://www.imprimerie.com/2012/art/1/biennale-in-pictures-from-the-future), the situation is even more complex: the biennial as an entity, with its own set of relations to the world, is subject to the world as a commodity, and its stories may no longer be told. The circulation of such stories does not necessarily result in their telling; nor does the fact that artists are now commissioned to regularly produce and co-author a ‘biennial journal’ (though this is a crucial change from the earlier practice of artists writing articles on a regular basis). Rather, the journal serves to define the way in which the artist’s/designer’s relationship to the art market can be negotiated. The journal may not always be forthcoming, nor always be positive, but it is a record, and the artist/designer’s engagement with the art market is a story told by the artist/designer in the journal.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York
    <text>will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times (New York), The Washington Post (Washington), and The New Republic. She is co-editor of the upcoming nonfiction book Images from the Future: Essays from the Archive of Photography (2015). Towards A Future In which Art and Culture Take RootPatrick JoyceMeehan Crist is the Curator of Art Activities at the Allen Gallery, London, and also the Curator of Cultural Futures at the Allen Gallery, New York. His research interests include the curatorial, the visual arts, and the history of science and technology. He has written for the New York Times, The New Yorker, The New Republic, The New York Herald Tribune, and The New York Sun. He is the host of the Chasing Unruffled podcast.Towards A Future In which Art and Culture Take RootPatrick JoyceMeehan Crist is the Curator of Art Activities at the Allen Gallery, London, and also the Curator of Cultural Futures at the Allen Gallery New</text>
    <text>will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, The Washington Post, London and New York World Reports, among others. She is currently editor of the online journal Stages.Her book Stages: Photography, State, Economy is published by Illustrated London News and it includes a chapter on the production of photographic negatives. Stages was co-curated by Rebecca Stott and Joasia Krysa.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is the Curator for the Rome Biennale 2017. She co-curated the exhibition with Paola Marrati and Giorgio Bitarossi. She is also a co-curator of the Liverpool Biennale 2017. She curated the Venice Biennale 2015, which was co-curated by Paola Marrati and Giorgio Bitarossi, and was a part of the curatorial team for the 2016 Venice Biennale. She co-curated the Venice Biennale 2016, which was co-curated</text>
    <text>will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Sun, The New York Daily Post, The New York Public Theater, The New York Public Library, The New York Public Theatre Review, The New York Public Theatre Archive, The New York Public Theater Archive, The New York Public Theater Archive, The New York Public Theatre Archive, The New York Public Theatre Review, The New York Public Theatre Archive, The New York Public Theatre Archive, The New York Public Theatre, The New York Public Theatre, The New York Public Theater, The New York Public Theatre Review, The New York Public Theatre Review, The New York Public Theatre Archive, and The New York Public Theatre. She has edited the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Sun, The New York Public Theater, The New Republic, The New York Public Theatre, The New Republic, The New Republic, and The New York Public Theatre. She has also edited the New York Public</text>
    <text>will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, The Washington Post and The New Republic, among others. She has a particular interest in the history of visual arts production in America.Samantha JonesSamantha Jones is a New Zealand-born curator living in London. She is currently Director of Exhibition Research Lab at the Allen and Lowndes Humanities Archive and is the Curator of Public Programs at the Allen and Lowndes Art Gallery. She has a particular interest in the history of visual arts production in Britain and is currently researching the 1980s Biennale of Sydney.She is the host of the weekly public programme The Vintage Beat, which she co-chairs, and was a curator at the Autumn/Winter 2006 and 2008 Liverpool Biennale curatorial projects. She has a particular interest in the role of artists in the production of histories, particularly in the production of ‘positive’ images through the arts. She is currently researching the 1980s Biennale of Sydney, the Australian branch of the Venice Bi</text>
    <text>will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, The New Republic, The Nation and The Washington Post, among other publications.Her book The Muse is a chronological survey of all the artworks she has photographed, annotated and published since 2011, collectively titled A Portrait of Meehan Crist. It is the result of a collaboration between the two of them and was published by Verso in 2015.Her writing has been featured in the New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The Nation, The New York Times, The New York Times Magazine, The New York Times Higher Critic, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic, The New Republic,</text>
    <text>will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The New Inquiry Magazine, The New Inquiry Radio, and The New Inquiry Web site. She is currently Curator of Public Art at the New York Public Library and co-curator of The Other Gallery, New York, USA. Her artworks have been commissioned by the New York Public Library, the North Atlantic Regional Gallery (Jersey City Region), and the North Shore Regional Gallery (Vancouver). Her books include the illustrated guide to Public Art, forthcoming from McGraw-Hill, New York, USA, and the online publication Public Art: Art from Secrecy (1998). She has served on the boards of various arts organizations, and was a recipient of multiple honours and awards.She lives in Brooklyn, New York.Biennials, Biennials in Context, 2011. Photo courtesy of the artist and LACMA.PreviousNextBiennials, Biennials in Context, 2011. Photo courtesy of the artist and LAC</text>
    <text>will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, Newsweek and The Washington Post.She is currently Associate Curator for the forthcoming Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities and Arts: A City's Theatre, and has written for the BBC News Magazine, The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry and The Observer.Biennials and the MuseumTowards a Community of Arts,Part TwoMeehan CristMeehan Crist is the Curator for the Community Arts Residency Program at the Brooklyn Museum. She has curated several exhibitions including the Brooklyn Museum/Vanguard of Art, the New Individualist Museum and the artist-in-residence post at the Brooklyn Museum. She is the author of The Community Arts Reader, published by Hodder and Stoughton.Biennials and the MuseumTowards a Community of Arts,Part ThreeMeehan CristThis is the third in a series of reports into the curatorial thinking behind the Biennale. The first two, in 2015 and 2017, looked</text>
    <text>will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, The Washington Post and The New Republic, among others. Her work has been commissioned by the New York Museum of Art, New York Graphic Society, and the Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive.She is currently a curator at the Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive, where she is currently completing a two-year project on the workshop of art, design and architecture for the Biennale. She has also curated the Allen &amp; Lowndes Cultural Trail, 2016 - Present at the Allen &amp; Lowndes Art &amp; Design Biennale, 2017, and curated the Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive, 2016 - Present at the Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive, 2016. She served as a curatorial adviser for the Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive, 2016 - Present at the Allen &amp; Lowndes Art &amp; Design Biennale, 2017, and the Allen &amp; Lowndes Cultural Trail, 2016 - Present at the Allen &amp; Lowndes</text>
    <text>will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, The Guardian, The New York Times Digital Archive, The New York Public Library, and The New York Public Library Digital Archive. She has also written for The New York Times, The New York Times Digital Archive, and The New York Public Library Digital Archive.She is the Curator of Visual Art at the Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive, and was previously Curator of Public Practice at the Allen &amp; Lowndes Art Archive. She is currently Associate Professor of Art Education at Chapman University, where she is developing an interdisciplinary art-history and photography-episodic series entitled The New Frontier. She has been an advisor for the 2014 Bogota Biennale, and curated the 2014 Istanbul Biennale, as well as a co-curator of the upcoming 15th Istanbul Biennale, to be held in autumn 2015.Her publications include the illustrated guide to contemporary art from “The New York Times”, published in Vintage in 2014; The</text>
    <text>will be curated by Allen and his team of senior curators, including Sally Tallant, Oona Hutchinson and Ruth Hunt.The exhibition will show work from the Allen Collection as part of the exhibition on the history of art from 1850 to the present. The exhibition will also show work from the Allen Gallery since the early 1990s, and features from the Allen Humanities Branch, including works by participants in the 1984 Venice Biennale.More information and to book a seat please see our Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive page.Download this article as PDFMeehan CristMeehan Crist is a writer, curator, educator and producer with a particular interest in the history of photography and the visual arts, particularly with respect to the production of historical photographic negatives. Her work has been shown in numerous venues including Venice (Italy), Bern (Switzerland), Künstlerhaus (Switzerland), Sydney (Australia), and Istanbul (Turkey). She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, The New Republic, The Colbert Report, The New Yorker, The New York Public Library, The New York Public Theater, The New York Public Theatre/Sternberg Arts Productions, The New York Public Theater/Union Stage, and The New York Public Theater/Union Stage. She has been a Curator at the British Museum, the Victoria and Albert Museum, and the Stages, London; a Visiting Professor at the University of Chicago; and a professor at McGill University, the University of Alberta, and Simon Fraser University, where she directed the documentary film The Pots Project (2015). She is currently the executive director of the Allen &amp; Lowndes Humanities Archive, a research and visual arts centre in Oldham, UK. She has written for the Illustrated London News, The New York Times, The New Republic, The Colbert Report, The New Yorker, The New York Public Library, The New York Public Theater, The New York Public Theatre/Sternberg Arts Productions,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale
    <text>will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.The Biennale Archive is a non-profit organisation founded in London in 2014 to bring together the curatorial thinking behind the Biennale, and the wider arts and cultural ecosystem through a shared archive. The Biennale Archive is a hub for the curatorial thinking behind the Biennale, producing and curating content across a broad range of sites in and around the city, with a particular focus on the monuments and sites associated with the 1915–1921 Gezi Park movement. Our content strategy includes producing, curating, hosting, and presenting exhibitions, public programming, writing for the site, and research. The Biennale Archive is a record of the development of ideas, processes, and identities that shape cultural practice and is the clearest articulation of that in one place. 	The Biennale Archive is a record of the development of ideas, processes, and identities that shape cultural practice and is the clearest</text>
    <text>will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the</text>
    <text>will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the</text>
    <text>will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.The Biennale Archive, the most current inventory of artworks and objects held in the Art Context Centre, is a London-based non-profit organisation established in 2004. The Biennale is a global art event with a history that encompasses three continents and twenty-six countries. The Biennale is the single largest purchaser of art and design in the world and is responsible for generating wealth, social impact and creating new ways of being in art. The Biennale, its partners, staff and volunteers work tirelessly around the world to bring art together in new forms and engaging practices. The annual event is curated by Michael Ames, Trevor Mills and Olu Oguibe</text>
    <text>will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the</text>
    <text>will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Bienn</text>
    <text>will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2017. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2018. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Join the Conversation!   Get our newsletter Subscribe TTYTTYTTYTTYTTYTTYTTYTTYTTYTTYTTYTTYTTYTTYTIF0  (212) 548-5300  (voice)  Subscribe to the Email List Get the latest from Usher &amp; The Weeknd, including episode access, by subscribing through Usher &amp; The Weeknd on  Facebook , Twitter  and Instagram  (email</text>
    <text>will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.The Biennale as Cultural Exchange In my conversation with Samantha Jones at Liverpool John Moores University, the conversation shifts from the biennale as a cultural phenomenon, to the much more practical question of what it would take to support a biennale as an art form, beyond the biennale itself. Jones makes some interesting points about the relationship between biennials and art forms: biennial as a cultural form is itself a product of the past, and art forms, including art itself, move towards a future with or without the presence of biennials. The biennial form, she argues, is an artefact of the age of the artist, and the art form, while exhibiting its traces, is itself a product of the age of the biennale. If biennials are absorbed into the broader art exhibitioning industry, they lose some of their power as curators and artists, and</text>
    <text>will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2016. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2017. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2017. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2017. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2018. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Subscribe to The Local Homebaked Newsletter Get the latest news, events and offers from the Biennale as PDFDelivering fresh and original local knowledge to your inbox, every Tuesday.The Biennale is an international, multi-day, three-day art and design event, organised by the Leverhulme Trust and NOMAD (North London Museum of Art). Each year, over 1,000 artists, curators, designers and architects from all over the world converge on the heart of</text>
    <text>will be curated by Deena Chalabi and Frank Langfitt) in partnership with the Leverhulme Trust. Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.PreviousNextLos Angeles Biennale, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2011. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2012. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2013. Photo courtesy of the Biennale Archive.Los Angeles Biennale, 2014. Photo courtesy of the Bienn</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to
    <text>vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to Perth or Darwin to do post-production, and so on. These were the days before satellite imagery, so the imagery we linked to our cities was of much lower resolution. But the links between the art gallery and the telco were undeniable. And so it was that the politics of the artist’s gallery came to dominate the politics of the NBN.  	When the NBN was first conceived, the notion of the ‘utopian artist’ was used to describe those who could benefit from the technological advancements that would result from the network being built. The implication was that these people were in effect technological slaves to the interests of the network, dependent on the providers of the networks they were connected to.  	In the early days of the NBN, the aspirations of the network architects were pure opportunism. There was a clear ideological difference between the artists who wanted to use the infrastructure to make art connections and the people who wanted to use it to deliver fibre optic cables. And</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to the NT DoT ‘main office’ in Canmore or to the regional art centers in the Gold Coast or elsewhere in the state? And the art galleries would convene in Canmore to welcome the artists and give them space and encouragement to explore the region? There were a few sad cases where artists were sent to prison for non-conforming to the art gallery conventions, but generally speaking, the arts were highly valued in the NT. And so the NBN was a radical innovation that I applaud in many ways, and I fear for the way in which it is being absorbed into our lives. The loss of painting is a loss that we do not yet know how to grapple with, and the loss of music is a loss that we do not yet know how to fight. The politics of culture are fluid and multi-layered, and new modes of understanding are constantly being invented. But the fluidity of the cultural norms that are constantly challenged – and remain vulnerable – is part of what</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to Perth or Darwin for their residencies, and the feeling was that these places were this distant third party to the other. Now that distance is what defines us. It defines what we can expect from them. It defines how we feel about them when we don’t know what we can expect from them. And so the relationship between the gallery and the territory has radically changed. The gallery becomes the outpost of a multi-national corporation, while the territory, as a quasi-public holding company, constitutes a significant portion of the corporation’s revenue.1  The idea that a local community could dictate how a publicly traded company performing commercially in the metropolitan centres would operate within the territory has also created perverse incentives for corporations to seek out economic opportunities within the territory. For example, the Barnett Shale gas field in the north, which would see British Columbia join the rest of the country in tapping into, or at least sharing in the extraction of, the shale gas, has already attracted investors</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to places such as Rotch’s, the Perth and Geelong Art Gallerys, and even the now-defunct Woodhouse gallery in Toowoomba, where Aboriginal artists were trained by the NT DoT. These local government galleries were places where the politics of Aboriginalness were not central, but the importance of making art with Aboriginal people was. And as a result, artist-run galleries such as these were often quite visionary. These were the galleries where artists actually felt like they could happen, and where politics were not a factor. Many Aboriginal and Torres Strait Islander artists would later work in galleries, as an outlet for their creativity and political involvement.These days, it’s rare for an artist to be trained by a local gallery; although I suppose in the past when the art was displayed in a predominantly Aboriginal community setting, such as at the Royal College of Art, the art would have been viewed as heretical and repugnant. And although there are good</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to the regional centres for regional government engagement, participation and grants. The art world was much more welcoming of this kind of infrastructure. It was seen as a technological innovation, a way to connect with artists’ audiences beyond the geographical borders. More important for the cultural tourism industry was the emergence of a regional arts and culture marketing agency, which could then connect with relevant government departments and engagement agencies. Creativeism, the idea that ideas could be exchanged and that cultures could be formed, began to be championed. Creativeism was exported to other parts of the world and internationally, and now other forms of cultural tourism are being developed in regions where the idea of the ‘Creative Class’ was particularly helpful. Creativeism gave voice to a large and diverse group of people to be attracted to a shared set of values and aspirations, and it did so through acts of agency. ‘Culture tourism’ is an important economic driver for the biennale. It generates significant cash flows for the bi</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to the regional centres where the art was produced, and right across the board, including for works by the NT DoT, such as Aboriginal Arts and Cultural Institutions Tasmania (AA12) and the University of Technology (2Up, 2Down, 1971); the Arts Council of Australia (ACAA), Western Australia (AW) (1952) and the Northern Territory Arts Council (N.T.A. Arts Council, 1953); the Northern Territory Art Gallery (N.T.A.A.G.C.), Darwin (1972) and the NT. Art Gallery of New South Wales (1994). 	When I started work on the NT.T.A.G.C, the aim was to do things through the galleries that they trusted to stock their community arts programs. But what I found very interesting and dynamic was the way that artists, curators and artisans started to cluster around the galleries, and began to dialogue with the other, more institutionalised, arts sector.</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to Perth for installation or commissioning. Local artists would lead the way in what would become a very important phase in the development of the art world in the NT. Later on, when the biennale came to a closing, local organisers would often form collaborative partnerships with other art institutions in the city, such as the Art Alliance and the Northern Territory Art Gallery.These days, the only places you'd find such collaboration are in the art compendiums or in the local art press, where the goals and aspirations of the artist are regularly aggregated and reported on as a 'community property' or a ‘wonder project’. As a result, the conversation often seems to center on the modes of participation – activism, art as political action, etc. – but little mentions of the actual work or art being done. That’s changing. There’s a movement underway now, and it’s not activism, it’s called repurposing. See:</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to the Northern Territory where the art was done by locals on a part-time basis. It was a massive, national art school. And yet the NCT would often refer to itself as a ‘northern university’. I think it was a double-binding thing: on the one hand, the Northern Territory Government was very interested in distancing itself from the institution, but at the same time the NCT was trying to incorporate the art school back into the institution’s curriculum. In other words, the institution was trying to engage with the community through a period of intensive engagement, but the NCT was also looking for ways to incorporate the art into the institution’s operations. NCT regional director general, Maureen Doyle Scott said at the time: ‘The art school is the smallest and most embedded part of the institution, and so is the bulk of the research and development that goes on behind the scenes.’[13] This is incredibly prescient coming from the</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to the coast for the festivities, and the major art institutions – ­– ­– ­– were quite literally the only ones with training programs in the NT. But what are the social consequences of this? I think that what’s happening is that there is no such thing as a ‘natural’ population; there is an ‘inherent’ surplus of resources, both physical and cultural. And so the DoT is telling artists: look, this is what you do. This is the economy of narcissism. This is the economy of collectivism. And it’s not just DoT programs: the art world is responding to this neo-liberal ideology, and to a post-industrial economy, by offering incentives to localities to boost tourism, to create ‘high-quality’ cultural environments, to invest in art and education systems, to adopt ‘creative practices’ and to adopt ‘holistic management’ – things that are not</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data processing. It’s hard to believe how much of what we think we know about the NBN is actually just old, tired, water-cooler talk. And yet the NBN has become so embedded in our lives that it’s hard to even notice. Do you remember the days when your local art gallery was the place to be for post-production, post-commissioning activities? When you could actually go and visit the galleries? When you could actually visit the place where the artwork is made? When you could actually visit the art school where the artist is educated? When you could actually actually visit the artist’s school? When you could actually actually visit the museum? When you could actually visit the local town hall and the Northern Territory Government? When every government department was a local government? When the NT DoT was just a postal service? I remember vividly the days when it was common for artists to be trained by the local art galleries, and then fly out to Perth or Darwin to do post-production and post-commissioning work? When the art centres were municipally funded, and the art was generally produced at a lower standard? I can still see examples of some of the artwork I produced during this time, such as the Aboriginal Women’s Resource Centre, which was exhibited in the local newspapers, and the occasional installation in schools. Many Aboriginal artists were artists themselves, and many of those who worked with us were artists themselves. The key was that we all saw the common aim, which was to have a positive impact on the community through what we did together.  	There were of course also religious people who were involved too, and they were doing their bit in the broader cultural game, but at the time we were creating a more integrative model, one that involved not only artists and art institutions, but also community organisers, schools, churches, heritage organisations and much more. The model that we developed was a natural extension of what</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be
    <text>vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be an island. The city becomes an island when it is reduced to a mode of exchange; it ceases to be a place. The role of the artist becomes to construct the city in such a way as to sustain the very existence of the city as a place, while simultaneously challenging the city’s capacity to support the artist’s work.  In short, the role of the artist is to produce what the city provides, while simultaneously challenging the capacity of the city to support the artist’s work.  This is the  	differentiating factor that Søren Kierkegaard refers to. Kierkegaard is one of the thinkers who proposed that ‘nothing is more repugnant to the fabric of modern society than a society which appropriates and destroys the natural world’. He is perhaps the one to have articulated the idea in the first place, perhaps having been inspired by the ecological theory of Kewpie Kardec.  He is perhaps the one</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be an island. The city is an island in itself, and so the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has, and to let the citizens decide how those resources are used. This may include actions that are ‘negative’ but are also positive, such as activism. The city has the capacity to intervene and shape ideas and perceptions, but it does not necessarily need to. The city is an island in itself, and so the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has, and to let the citizens decide how those resources are used. This may include actions that are ‘negative’ but are also positive, such as activism. The city has the capacity to intervene and shape ideas and perceptions, but it does not necessarily need to. The city is an island in itself, and so the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has, and to let the citizens decide how those resources are used. This may include actions that are �</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be your own island. The city is a capital for the city’s decline, and the role of the artist is to deliver capital to the city’s decline. We need your help to create an atmosphere in which the artist can work in the city, and so the question becomes how to build on the strengths of the artist’s existing portfolio and to expand the portfolio. The city does this through a variety of mechanisms, but its primary objective is to finance the city’s future use of art materials and to ensure that the city’s artworlds remain attractive to tourists. The city thus creates a market for tourism, and so this is part of the equation that the city seeks to cultivate and foster a mutually beneficial relationship with the artist. In other words, the city seeks to exploit artists’ labour in an exploitative way. The city thus creates a working class of artists who are obliged to become tourists, and this is why so many of them leave the</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be an island. The city is an island in a sea of its citizens, and so the role of the artist is to deliver whatever resources are there, in whatever quantity or form, to knit the city together. This may include actions that are conscious or unconscious, fictional or actual, but it’s always the latter. The city is a complex ecosystem with many interrelated nodes and branches, and so its production of its own products and services is often quite unconscious. The city does make conscious decisions, and these may be quite strategic, but they are often not based on rational criteria. For instance, the financial crisis brought down financial services giant Bear Stearns, which in turn brought down auto parts makers, which in turn brought down other parts of the economy, which in turn brought down housing prices, which in turn brought down many other parts of the economy, which in turn reduced employment opportunities and made it harder to get work. All these phenomena were caused by overproduction in the auto and</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be an island. The city has to begin to negotiate its own resources. For many years, the city did this by proposing things to the artists, organising them into artist-performances, and encouraging them to go further out into the city than the city normally would. But this approach was exploitative: the city provided the infrastructure, the financial lifeline, the culture, the playground, the river, etc. So the art world had to find a way to intervene constructively, even if this meant engaging the city in small-scale projects that contributed to the construction of the infrastructure, but which nevertheless constrained the city’s ability to inhabit the island effectively. So the biennial format was invented, and now every major one of the world’s major art museums has a biennial in some capacity. The importance of this has not lost on city officials and cultural planners, who continue to tell city councils and city councils of the need to preserve the integrity of the city and its assets</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be your own. The role of the artist is to expand the city’s infrastructure to meet the needs of the citizens, and so the city becomes an additional stage on which the citizens can expand their perceptions and alter those perceptions and actions as much as possible.  In the case of the Occupy movement, this has meant finding creative ways to engage people’s sense of place, and making things happen in the city that are not necessarily desirable or successful, but which can be beneficial to the city as a whole. For example, the city has resources that it does not necessarily need, and so it might make sense to provide free or cheap housing to people who contribute to the city’s coffers, but it is important that these funds be used responsibly. In the case of a major city decline, this means making things safer for working-class and poorer residents, but it also means devoting resources to supporting cultural institutions that help the wealthy and privileged blend in more. The role of the</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be an island. The city must make choices, and so the artist has an opportunity to intervene in the city’s decisions, its very nature as an administrative operation. The city has the capacity to shape its perceptions, but the artist has to exert creative control over the city’s creation. 	 Art has many other modes of expression besides what is intended for the purposes of institutional consumption. It can be political, it can be literal, and it can be quite insidious. The practice of aquatic painting, for example, emerged as a direct result of the financial crisis and its concomitant rise in social costs. The art world did not invent art as a political tool. But it certainly can. 	The art world has its share of critics, and while their critical views of the world are often misguided, much of what they publish is valuable or perfectly valid, and valuable or perfectly valid observations. The critical eye that looks to a world beyond the site where things happen,</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be an island. The city needs to ask, and then tailor its own response. The city needs to know how it is being populated, and so it does this through measuring, mapping and survey work. It does this by collecting and aggregating data, and so it collects what it can from a variety of sources, including but not limited to, the Port of Toronto, Statistics Canada, local authorities, faith-based organisations and other community groups. It then creates engaging visual experiences around data-rich data, using city infrastructure, local businesses and other institutions as stand-ins for the social and political movements that are driving the city’s rapid population growth. In a larger perspective, the port is a point of intersection between economic development and many of the social ides that are driving the city’s rapid growth, including race relations, immigrant rights, housing and poverty, policing and so on. As the port becomes more of what Anders Breivik calls the ‘point of no return</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be your own island. The city is a starting point, but it is not a magic island. The role of the artist is to push the city to new places, and so the city has to ask more from the artist. The city has to invest in the city, and so it asks the artist to produce more. The city has to support the artist’s future projects, and so it projects its assets onto the artist’s CV. The city then expects the artist to deliver tangible results, which may include funding for the future projects, and so it pursues research and development into new ways of organising and utilising the artist’s labour. The city invests in infrastructure, schools and hospitals, but it also needs artists to design things and put ideas together that can then be used by the city, such as by way of a re-constituting Community Arts organisation. The role of the artist is to put ideas together that can then be used by the city, and</text>
    <text>vast amount of art world data as to the value of a place. But the quantification of a place is only part of the story. The art world’s role is to its citizens, and part of its mission is to them. The art world has to work with its citizens to shape their perceptions and actions, and so it is with the Occupy movement. The art world has to allow its citizens to articulate their needs and desires. It does this through performances and events, but it is also the organizing principle that drives the movement. The city has to commit resources to making things happen, and so it does more with limited resources. As the city allocates those resources, it commits resources to making things happen in the city, and so it is with the city’s decline. So the role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has available, and to work with citizens to shape those perceptions and actions as best you can. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city cannot be an island. The city is an island in itself, but the Occupy movement’s starting point, and the city as an island in itself. The role of the artist is to deliver what resources the city has, and to work in tandem with other partners to create what the city can be. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city is not an island. The city is an island in itself, but the Occupy movement’s starting point, and the city as an island in itself. The role of the poet is to deliver what the city has, and to collaborate constructively with other artists to build something new. What the city provides is a starting point, but the city is not an island. The city is an island in itself, but the poet’s starting point, and the city as an island in itself. The role of the architect is to deliver what resources the city has, and to help build something new as a co-producer of</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the place where the action takes place. It will be possible to leave the public realm and return to the city. The proposed ‘Transition to a Public Realm’ would allow artists to progress through the ‘public domain’, while remaining enclosed within a defined framework. In the future, this public realm might be a campus or a warehouse, but for the moment, it will be a point of convergence for artists, artisans, and city dwellers. The proposal is a radical departure from current approaches to the public realm, which typically call for the end product to be controlled by a central authority or powerful commercial interests. The authority here is asserting its ownership in a progressive and transparent way. Artists and arts institutions will be invited to participate in the progressive development of a new public realm, while the public will be provided the tools to challenge the authority of the government in various ways. This progressive approach to the relationship between the public realm and the artist will require great skill and commitment, but</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the place where the action takes place. The development is being presented as a research project at the New Museum in partnership with Lab8 Labs, with the museum as an anchor institution. A public register of interests will also be developed through the partnership between the museum and Digital Artisans, an organization that offers a register of objects at affordable price points through a partnership with the New Museum.  The registry will be a place to discover and access information about the place where the art is made, invented, made, or created. It will show the place where that art was made, what people did with it, and who made it. It will show the objects made in the place and their owners.  The digital realm will also be a place to peer into the history of a place and enter a person’s memory. This is being described as ‘living space’, adding that it is both ‘permanent’ and ‘transforming’ through the power of the API</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the place and people at work or in its process of creation. The proposal is for a phased approach that begins with the establishment of the public realm and evolves with its use, incorporating public realm data, monitoring and development as the city evolves. The public realm will be a potentially infinite source of new ways of being in ways that can enhance or disrupt the historical cultural landscape. It is a place where ideas can emerge and be challenged in ways that are authentic to the place, but also a place where those who possess those ideas can be realized in a way that is authentic to the city.  Boundary Layer  A public realm is a place where publics gather to exchange, negotiate, and be confronted with ideas, objects and information that are different from one's own. It is a place where difference is faced, debated and resolved. It is a zone where law and order are violated and enforced. In other words, it is a place where freedom and democracy are secured against what James Howard Kunstler</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the place where action takes place. The public realm will offer a multiplicity of experiences, and act as a space for the public to come and act in ways that are not always planned or desired but are always possible. The inclusion of technology in the public realm is not a new thing, but the present and active participation in the realm both as a production for social change and as a production for art's own productions is a development that demands new forms of interaction. The proposed public realm will need to be responsive to the specific needs and political leanings of the neighbourhood. It may need to be multivalent, and engage different audiences with different modes of experience. It may need to be open to a hybrid of commercial and non-profit participation. All of these conditions are possible within the parameters of the proposal, but they are also demands from a public realm that is both engaged and invisible. It is demand that is powerful, and the ability to meet it is what makes the imagination and the possibilities open to</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the land and its politics of control. The public realm will be a place where politics, law and politics-as-stuff-up can be encountered. It will be a place where critical thinking can happen. It will be a place where difference can be expressed through art’s many different kinds of media. It will be a place where non-linear narrative structures can be dismantled and new, non-linear forms of interaction formed. It will be a place where critical thinking can happen. It will be a place where non-linearity can be experienced. These are not abstractions. These are not trivial concepts. But they are realities, and they are happening now. And we as visitors to the real world, visitors to the real sites of power, need to start noticing them. For example, the New York Public Library is hosting a series of public discussions on its website titled Politics and the Public. If the name seems abstract, it is because the purpose of this series of meetings is to</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the place where action takes place. In the late stages of conception, but before it is fully realised, the public realm will be a kind of temporary exhibition ground, with permanent reading rooms, meeting rooms and public porches. The name of the sponsoring institution will be announced at the Biennial reception, and the proposal will be presented in the catalogue of the journal, Musings from the Hudson Valley (published by the Hudson Valley Historical Society). The journal will report back to the artist, M. Welsh, and the region around the Biennial. The proposal and the proposal will then be sent to the Hudson Valley Historical Society for consideration. If the history of the Hudson Valley is to be told, the Hudson Valley Historical Society should be able to add to the historical narrative a ficticious narrative of its own making.  In the Hudson Valley, at least, we can assume that the proposed ‘biennial’ will be told from the</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the place where the action takes place. The Public Realm concept was developed in collaboration with the Toronto Art Gallery and the Museum of Contemporary Art (MoMA), and is an extension of the earlier Public Art movement in the United States. It was first proposed in 1967 by the Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), and the National Gallery of Canada in 1974. The project was co-chaired by William H. Burston, Jr., and Paul E. Levine. The Museum of Modern Art, in collaboration with the Canada Geographical Survey (CANS), and the New Museum, embarked on a major survey of the region in the early 1970s. The public realm concept was further developed by the Museum of Modern Art, in collaboration with the Burston/MoMA’s Art Department, who supervised the surveyors and art wasters. The idea was to create a permanent, territorially defined zone of public realm in the Hudson Valley where people could freely roam, do things in public, and</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the place. The public realm will be subject to monitoring and control mechanisms ensuring that it does not become a site for an armed conflict. The registry will act as a public-private partnership to safeguard the public realm from being displaced by a private developer's development plans.  	We propose that the registry be created as a public trust, or public realm corporation, to manage the development of the area as a public trust, and to create a public realm corporation jointly with the City of Toronto. The City of Toronto would be required to create a Master Plan for the area, which would establish priorities for the development of the ‘regeneration district’, including creating jobs and creating opportunities for local residents. The Master Plan would set forth specific actions to be taken in the 'regeneration district’, including creating a ‘Robin Hood Tax’ to collect a percentage of property taxes collected from residents and businesses, and ‘No First-Home Owner’ legislation to prevent developers</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the place at a distance. The concept is exemplary of innovative solutions to challenging problems, but its ultimate aim is to transform the place into a fully participatory civic body through a publicly owned, democratically managed, and collectively managed digital commons.  The Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute has been tasked with developing a new generation of creative alternatives to traditional arts education and training programmes. The institute is led by professor emeritus of creative arts education, L.U. Krishna Menon, and includes faculty from McGill University, with a co-researcher in applied creative arts, Ranjana Paulkari. Together, the faculty members will work with the local residents, arts administrators, and local business owners to design a new generation of innovative ways to engage the local residents, tourists, and community members with arts education and training programmes. This new generation of creative alternatives will build on the strengths of the existing curatorial approach, but will also address the needs of the increasingly urbanised populations that will</text>
    <text>The next Whitney Biennial will be curated by Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau, under the direction of Arjun Appadurai, and curated by Florence N.A. Pulau. The exhibition will be displayed in the newly created Arjun Appadurai and Florence N.A. Pulau Gallery in New York. It will be on a first come, first serve basis. The artists have agreed to make the exhibition as a standing project. The proposal, which has been put forward by the Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute, is for a dedicated digital public realm that will be managed democratically through a public register of interests. The proposal is for the establishment of a public realm in the Hudson River Valley, Canada, in the early stages of its conception but with a transition to a fully participatory government-created realm in the late stages. The public realm will be managed democratically through a public register of interests, and will incorporate interactive elements through technology to bring the visitor closer to the place at a time when the place is being reclaimed. The public realm will not only make the place better, but it will also make the place private – accessible and controllable for the future generations to work and live in – an ideal combination for a city that is increasingly the preserve of the rich and the powerful.  The Arjun Appadurai Digital Arts institute has been formed as a non-profit, non-statutory public corporation incorporated in the British Columbiastrict liability, and the Arts Council of Canada have been given a 20% stake in the corporation. The other 20% is held by the Canadian Arts Council.2  The Appadurai Digital Arts institute has been given a $1.5 million gift in order to start construction on the ‘hub and sprocket’ of the city, the largest single corporate investment in New York City since 1995.3  The Canadian Arts Council is the largest arts organisation in Canada, and together they control over half the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other
    <text>an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other forms of oppression. But it’s also very difficult to question the systems that create and depend on the myth. The challenge of imagining alternatives and imagining alternatives in our current system is huge. There are of course many other forms of economic and spatial development that can be linked to the digitisation of historical sites and the shifting of vast urban spaces, but the question of cultural capital really needs to be asked. I think that in the current political context, the question is relevant not just for Bangalore, but for cities all over India and beyond.The other dynamic that emerged during the curatorial process was the emergence of what is commonly referred to as the ‘metro-curious factor’. This is the notion that cities are places where art is produced at a local scale and at an international one. It’s an idea that was used in the 1980s and 1990s by artists to develop local literacy and collective memory, particularly through the production of places-specifically-derived</text>
    <text>an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other forms of oppression. It also prevents us from thinking about alternatives. What really defines us as artists and what makes us artists in the eyes of a city is something quite different from how we are actually made to be made. The myth of cultural capital therefore needs to be interrogated and changed. In doing so, it needs to be questioned how we use it and who is responsible for what ends up on the map.Given the historical context of the biennale, there are of course other factors that are of direct relevance to contemporary cultural needs and tropes. The main one is undoubtedly the biennial itself. The other is undoubtedly the city. But in the current political climate, it is quite essential for contemporary art to be made in cities. And although I don’t think we can call ourselves contemporary artists just yet, we do need to start making art outside the box that we, as an art world, put ourselves into. To start, we need to start asking questions about the places where our</text>
    <text>an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other forms of oppression. It also pretends that the past becomes something positive and pure, when in fact there is a long and complicated history of oppression and destruction in this city. The irony is that in the past, when we talk about the past, we actually make things worse by encouraging people to build their futures around the past. I think a basic understanding of the historical context of our city, and the city as a site for future cultural activity, is critical for us to have in order to tackle the present. I think also that the people who are coming to this city to work alongside us are making decisions about their own futures based on assumptions about history and cultural difference that are at odds with the actual trajectory of culture and art in this city. The fact that people choose to come to this city and live here rather than elsewhere is another critical point. Whether they are coming to this city because it is a choice, or are forced to by the city’s crisis of displacement, is another</text>
    <text>an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other forms of oppression. It reifies and idealises the past, but in the end, who is really in control of the past? What really matters in the present is making the present in ways that are consistent with the values and interests of the people presenting the future that we don’t yet know. I find the ability to create and to trace cultural flows in and out of a city useful in challenging presentist notions of what is possible, but also in creating the possibility of change in the future. For instance, the way in which we talk about displacement today – the way in which it is more characteristic of India than any other country – is a legacy and a consequence of the country becoming secular and non-religious, and is in large measure a by-product of the country becoming economically self-sufficient. So the ability to trace and change cultural flows and images of space and time through space and in- and out-flows is vital for a flourishing imagination and complex future. But it</text>
    <text>an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other forms of oppression. It also creates the necessary conditions for the continued reproduction of capitalist society. But the reality is that when it comes to creating or constructing new cultural spaces, we don’t create them with the possibility or even the desire to create them; we tear them down, build new ones or, in the extreme, destroy them altogether. When we do that, we create what Arjun Appadurai calls ‘negative sum games’ – situations in which one person or a small clique possesses a dominant position, but in which others struggle to get in or get out. There are many forms of cultural assimilation in the world today, but the myth of the mythical ‘right to culture’ holds great appeal for some people, especially in societies that are increasingly mobile and fluid. The negative sum games we describe are the unavoidable by-products of a capitalist circulation of ideas and cultural commodities. They are the fate of people who invent the great urban myth or the great cultural</text>
    <text>an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other forms of oppression. It allows us to pretend that our present situations don’t exist, that we can move forward and never look back. But this is just the condition of the myth, and the very reason why we need the work in the first place. The real work, making the world we live in, can and should break free from its historical situations.This is the kind of breaking free that is possible, no matter how difficult the task may be, with ongoing productive engagement. The break-even point for many of us in the contemporary art world is when we start to engage actively with the art institutions that are the products of the academy, which for many reasons is a very different kind of engagement from what the artists actually do. The break-even point is a tipping point where the engagement becomes destructive, and the work that is produced at that point is then absorbed back into the academy. There is no such thing as the contemporary artworld because the academy has been pulled away from</text>
    <text>an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other forms of oppression. It also pretends that the past is not a sea of protest, but rather an ocean of opportunity. But what is the past, exactly? And what does it mean to make the past present, or present, in a given particular way?These are important questions for a number of reasons. First, we live in an era of enormous multiplicity of cultures all around us, and we live in a multiracial, multi-faith city with diverse ethnicities. This is the multi-generational condition of being alive. Second, and perhaps more importantly, this diversity is the result of in-depth inter-generational exchanges occurring across cultures. And thirdly, it is the outcome of in-depth migrations across geographical space and time. The question now is where these different forms of historical exchange take place, what constitutes the ‘present’ and how does it come about. What is the current state of historical materiality in a given city or in a</text>
    <text>an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other forms of oppression. It also tends to obscure the fact that there are other ways of being lived and interacting in the world. The AI curators, for example, live and work in Berlin, but they also have a home in New York. The question is what is meant by ‘home’? What is meant by a presumed sense of belonging and belongingness? For many of us, the answer to either of those questions is a clear and present presence: our families, close friends, communities of co-citizens, cities, nations, cities in general. Yet for others, it is an absence or ‘false lodgment’ of things. For me, for example, the claim of cultural capital is an opinion, a fiction, a made-up construct. It is not a fact or a set of facts; it is an opinion. Myths and fictions are often used as cover by those with a clear interest in absolving themselves of responsibility or guilt. In the</text>
    <text>an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other forms of oppression. It allows them to live their lives in ways free of meaning and politics. But the reality is that these kinds of political and social infrastructuring have become so embedded in our times that it is almost laughable or even offensive to people who are not part of the system. For instance, the way in which we talk about ‘infrastructure’ in relation to cities like New York and London, which are essential for the continued existence of capitalism, is a myth. Infrastructure today is connected to social life everywhere, yet this is not always the case.  In my opinion, infrastructure today is mostly about energy and logistics – the logistics of transport and logistics of goods and people. The cities that have infrastructure today are the cities that can still support a lot of cultural activity – the hubs of the capitalist world. The cities that can support cultural activities today tend to be those in the West that are cosmopolitan, technologically savvy and have a strong identity. In other words, the</text>
    <text>an AI curated some of the works and gave a talk at the festival about the future of cultural organising in India. Over the next few years, we plan to do a cultural exchange in Bangalore between the two cities. This will be done through a collaborative process between the two curators. The whole process will be facilitated by the Indian Council for Cultural Relations (ICCR) and the Indian Arts Network (AI) in Bangalore. The aim of this project is to archive and reimagine the relationship between art and art’s place in the city.Art and culture are often conflated. The problem with this is that they both have the potential to be art, but they also have the potential to be deeply problematic, especially when it comes to our times. I find the claim of cultural capital that so many of us make as a condition of working in any given city to be a myth. The myth of cultural capital is extremely comforting to people whose identities are otherwise made up of exploitation, racism, colonialism and other forms of oppression. It’s true that in the olden days, cultural capital could access capital on the same basis as any other asset; today, it’s often claimed that the only way to access capital is to be part of a cultural network. Yet capital is capital only if the market provides the purchasing conditions; what makes it culturally responsive is precisely the fact that its use is discretionary. Moreover, cultural capital is only ever fully responsive to the needs and interests of a privileged elite; new entrepeneurship is needed elsewhere in the country if the myth of capital as culturally responsive is to be challenged. That would require radical changes in how capital is constituted, how values are distributed and consumed, and how power is distributed. I would argue that we are culturally responsive, and that our current economic and social forms only make us so culturally responsive. We need to create new forms of economic, political and spatial co-determination for people to be able to pursue what is left over</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including
    <text>an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including the artists who created the Columbian Exposition itself.  A Corrado Foundation Fellowship 	In 1984, the Corrado Foundation established the Corrado Art Foundation, an independent non-profit arts organisation dedicated to the protection and promotion of the right to the highest possible standards of artistic, cultural, environmental and social protection in the art and cultural domains throughout Latin America and the Caribbean.1  The Corrado Art Foundation was established in 1987 and is a non-profit public trust established in Belize, Panama, and the US. Its mandate is to protect the highest standards of artistic and cultural heritage through the creation and promotion of cooperative arts and cultural enterprises, the retention and promotion of classical arts and historical sites through preservation and promotion of ethnographic and archival materials, and the protection and promotion of original ideas through dissemination and distribution of scholarly journals, pamphlets, and books throughout Latin America and the Caribbean. 	The foundation was established as a partnership between the US and Panama Governments</text>
    <text>an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including many from Italy. In 1986, the festival hosted the Venice Biennale, which I curated in turn. The Venice Biennale was an exhibition of the city’s cultural resources, while the Venice Architecture Biennale offered a forum for the exchange of cultural knowledge between the two venues. In 1988, I created the Biennale of New York, which took place in 1989. In 1990, the Biennale of London, and finally the Biennale of Sydney, offered a forum for the exchange of cultural resources between the two venues. In 1993, I curated the Venice Architecture Biennale, which took place in 1995. Biennales within the art museums were initially places where the curator sat alongside the curatorial team, creating a dynamic between the two. In 1994, the Biennale of New York hosted the Venice Biennale, and in 1997 the Biennale of London. In 2002, the Biennale of Sydney hosted the Venice Biennale.</text>
    <text>an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including many who are no longer with us. In 1986, the Columbian Exposition was renamed the Global Arts Cribs, and in 1994, the Columbian International. Today, the Arsenale, Venice, Italy, and the Biennale are synonymous, with the former considered the classic example of what the latter does.  In 2014, the Biennale opened its doors to the public for the first time. For the occasion, it invited a creative class of artists, curators and artists to explore the archives and the exhibition site.  The workshop, which offered the opportunity to explore the Biennale’s idiosyncratic ways of organising material, involved surveying the historical materiality of the place – the building, the artefacts, the collection – and of the archive itself. We discovered that the Biennale had been planning to open the exhibition with a series of video archival photographs, selected from a public archive, that would document the history of animation in the years</text>
    <text>an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including Carol Becker, Edward Burtynsky, Max Ernst, Roselyn Mohsen, Lilya Tsing, Marianne Moore, Evelyn Wang and many more.The Arsenale di Lauro, 1992. Photo courtesy of the Italian Government Archive. The festival moved to a new location in New York, but the name stayed the same – ‘The Arsenale’ – partly because, until 2002, the Italian title was translated from the US title, The Beverly Hills Hotel. The 2001 decision to rename the place, itself, in honor of Italian soccer player Marco Di Vaio drew protests from locals who saw a repetition of the 1950s Italian fascist dictatorship. The Italian government responded by changing the title to simply the Arsenale, and introducing a series of new local curatorial approaches. The Biennale also shifted its focus to other parts of the world, and its curatorial priorities now include agriculture and urbanization in general. The name remains a mischievous turn of phrase</text>
    <text>an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including the artist Andre Ethier, who was born in New York; the curator Andre Braugher; the curator Lars Meijer; the art fair Sol M. Kiev, organised by the Ukrainian Art Federation; and the biennial WaMuLeAdecco, co-chaired by the Director of the Austrian Cultural Forum, Wolfgang Ernst.In 1992, the festival moved to Venice and was one of the featured curators for the ‘80s pop-up museum’, a project by the Italian artist Stefano Lazzarato and the Czech designer, Arjun Appadurai. Lazzarato had started work on the project in L.A. and San Francisco, and was joined by other artists including, Lalo Alcaraz, Anna Poveda, Paolo Baratta, Paolo Veronese, Maira Kaltenbrun, Lubomir Bychkov, and many more. Venice Biennale, Pier 48, 1992.</text>
    <text>an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including Carol Becker, Barbara Kruger, John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah, among many others.The Arsenale was a major hub for European art trans-shipment during this period, with artists from all over the continent coming to Italy to pursue careers or explore alternative artistic options. Some of them ended up in Lodi or in the city itself, while others chose to return to their birthplace countries and pursue creative careers outside of art. The Arsenale di Lauro is a unique institution in that it is the only surviving section of the Arsenale that is devoted to the trans-shipment of art and has operated continuously since 1927. It became so in 2011, when the city government decided to sell the entire building to pay for the renovation of an outdated, underutilized part of the Arsenale called Lodi Town Square. However, the radical transformation of the circular complex into a new urban core that is entirely devoted to the trans-shipment of goods</text>
    <text>an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including Roberto Cavalli-Sforza, David Hockney, David Hockney &amp; Co, Daniel Fernández Pascual, Joasia Krysa, Joana Baptista Costa, Laura Lopé, Joana de la Torre, Balint Abbas &amp; Co, David Hockney, Sandeep Parmar &amp; Co, Pintre van Horne, David Hockney, Balint Abbas, Joasia Krysa, Jan van Horne, David Hockney, Irene Roehmer, Maria Hlavajova, Joana de la Torre, Lola Liem and many more.)Contemporary artworks from the Arsenale, Venice, Italy, 1988. Photo courtesy of Black-E Archive.Black-E Archive, Black-E Archive.Black-E Archive, Black-E Archive.Black-E Archive, Black-E Archive.Black-E Archive, Black-E Archive.Black-E Archive, Black-</text>
    <text>an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including many who were born in Canada. The World Columbian Exposition was founded in 1914 and runs through 2014. It brings together the history of the place of art and commerce in Canada, and the United States, in an exhibition that is characterised by stylised exchanges of ideas, artifacts, styles and practices. Its main objectives are to show the cultural aspects of the relationship between art and commerce, and the role of art as a mediator between these two poles. In 2014, the expo became the home of the Biennale, the world’s largest and most prestigious biennale of its kind.8. The Biennale of Sydney, Australia, 2015. Installation, Sydney Museum of Art, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Sydney Museum of Art.==================================================================================9. The Biennale of Sydney, Australia, 2015. Installation, Tate Modern. Photo courtesy of the Sydney Museum of Art.==================================================================================10. The Biennale of Sydney, Australia, 2015</text>
    <text>an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including Stephen Gorman, Mark Leckey, Pintre van Horne, John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah, all from Liverpool. 	The festival was a tremendous success, providing an outlet for the growing interest in avant-garde and experimental art, and highlighting the local artists who were active in the movement. It was also a platform for the artists to connect with other artists and the wider art world. The exhibition included group shows with subjects from the region, as well as solo displays by the artists, many of whom were of the younger generation, including eight artists from the region who were active in the 90s, and of course, the many who have since become international artists. It should be noted that the avant-garde was not confined to the shores of the North Atlantic. At the Venice Biennale, in fact, the Biennale approached the tradition of the ‘noble savage’. The opening act at the Venice</text>
    <text>an AI curated the festival, which was organized as a part of the International Animation Festival. The festival began in 1982 in Venice and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, the Arsenale, and the Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice. It was co-curated by Paolo Portoghesi and Silvestre de Sacy. The sculptures and installations included from the archive of European art, including works by De Sacy’s own Collective Eclogues (1986–92), an intimate group of artists, including Francesca Bertolotti, Klaus Wittkugel, Maria Hlavajova, Joana Baptista Costa, Joasia Krysa, Anne Kølbækari, Emma Rehberger, Pintre van Horne, Ewerton Groves, Sabine Lis and many more. The festival was part of the World Columbian Exposition, which also featured works by many artists from all over the world, including Carol Christov-Bakargiev, James Randi, Barbara Kruger, Steven Soderbergh, Doug Liman, Paul Domela and many more. And it was sponsored by the US Department of Transportation, the city of Los Angeles, the New York Public Library and many other local and national art agencies. The World Columbian Exposition, which began in 1982 and ran through 1991 in The Arsenale, The Arsenale, and The Arsenale di Lauro, as well as in Venice, San Francisco, London, and New York, was one of the largest and most international art fairs of its type ever to take place in Europe. At the end of the 1991 event, the Arsenale, Arsenale, and Arsenale di Lauro merged to form the Biennale, which began in 1993 and ran until 2015. The merging of the two forms of the festival – into one entity, and into a parallel structure to another event –</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how
    <text>archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how to say, do things with meaning and contain within it possibilities for expansion and change. The biennial is a museum of meanings in an ever-shifting, changing and expanding frame of meaning. It is a collection of figurative, archival, and even secular objects, objects and assemblages from many different points of view. It is a collection of cultural products whose function has become something like that of a museum, turning what was once a private collection of objects into something more public and controllable. This is what the biennale or biennial as a curatorial gesture is all about. It makes a statement about the past, in the form of a collection of objects that come to represent a time, place or culture in a particular way. It also makes a statement about the future, in the form of a museum that documents cultural impacts on a global scale. Biennales and biennials generally follow three to fourfold curatorial gestures. The first part of the gesture</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how to say, in other words. It is a form of what the late Peter Osborne called, in a manner somewhat reminiscent of Jack Burnham’s monologue from Return of the Jedi, ‘a voice that’s heard in the darkness’. The voice is that of the biennial, but unlike other kinds of voice, it does not speak through a podium or a throne. It comes through a series of small windows or passages in a wall, or even a crevice in the carpet. It is like the voice of the blind, but with the blind blind blind watching each other. The blind see well enough, but not well enough to engage with the ideas being expressed, much less with the idea itself.Osborne’s monologue is a variation on a theme that has been plaguing modernism and postindustrialism: what he calls the ‘monstrous’ condition of capitalism produces a feedback loop that harbors ‘monumental injustices</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how to say ‘how to say’. But what does this mean in practice? For example, in the 1990 Venice Biennale, the Biennale took many different forms. It was a ‘projection’ (in the sense of David Harvey’s typology), a ‘showpiece’ (in the sense of Arjun Appadurai’s Staging of New York, I believe), a ‘museum of modern art’ (in the sense of Francis Bacon’s Monumental Method), an ‘apparition of modernism’ (in the sense of Federico Fellini’s The Queen’s Chandelier, with its oversize facade and squat form), and a ‘mall of culture and art’ (in the sense of David Harvey’s typology of the museum). Some of these more restricted forms were more effective for their intended purpose, while others were not</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how to say what sort of a thing it is. The biennial has become the object of what sort of a ‘how to say’.2 In recent decades, the biennial has largely been a tourist attraction, with the notable exception of a brief flowering in the 1990s during the Arab Spring. Biennials have the distinction of being the last place where a place can be explored in depth, and therefore has the least to offer in terms of research or documentation. This is particularly true in the case of a place as a museum or a large institution becoming a biennial, since the last thing that is wanted is for a visitor to descend into the mire of interest and ignorance surrounding the place. As a result, places such as the Venice Biennale are left to languish, their archetypes and histories of art and architecture constantly being up for grabs, constantly being invented and being reinterpreted. And this is the real tragedy of it all: the history and archival</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how to say, ‘how to say ‘yes’ to the project in a way that maximizes the possibilities of making a permanent mark on the city.1. The Biennial as a Topic of Research, Inquiry and Discovery, Geoffrey Mackie, Experience, Volume One, 2010. Photo courtesy of the Liverpool Biennial.2. The Biennial, Volume One, 2010. Photo courtesy of the Liverpool Biennial.3. Anne Kølbæk Iversen, ‘On Temporality and History: The Biennial as a Topic of Research, Inquiry and Discovery’, Social Science and Medicine, Vol. 21, No. 1, Spring, 2010, p. 1–24.4. See Jeffrey M. Hawkins and Christian Körner, ‘Nadine Attewell and Geoffrey Mackie: On Temporal Relations in Contemporary Art History and Cultural Theory’, Cultural Theory &amp; Research, Issue 2, Winter, 2010, p. 1</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how to say, ‘how to say it,’ in order to be understood.2. How to Say Things with Grammatical Forms, or Grammars of Syntax, as the Greeks Called Them. 	The biennial is not just an exhibitionary form; it is a social, cultural form – one that engages with and depends on the common good. Its real mission, as exhibitionary form, is accomplished when it is embedded in a cultural infrastructure (a museum, a gallery, radio or television station, public or private museums, zoos or historic sites).3. Grammarian of Syntax, or Syntax Today. 	Many biennials have their subjects of analysis embedded within the cultural infrastructure of a city or country, and in many cases, this is the case even if the biennial itself is invisible. For example, biennials of the 1990s Brisbane architecture were largely written by Arnoud Kempe and his co-authors,</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how to say, do things, and do them well. It may be the case that this has often meant joining forces with other art institutions, perhaps operating outside the city limits of the biennial. In this case, the art institutions turn into public agencies, or as with the biennale of Sydney, turned public institutions. The biennial, then, has become what Michel de Certeau calls ‘a national register of things’, a permanent register of things, recording, description. It records not only what is happening in the real life of the world but also of cultural production in the world as a whole. Biennials have become, de Certeau explains, part of a larger ‘big picture’ picture of cultural forms that emerge around the world. They are ‘the most comprehensive and revealing feature of contemporary art’, revealing ‘the hidden time and space that are unfolding, unfolding’ and ‘revealing’ ‘new ways</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how to say, ‘how to represent’ it. As biennials, we are constantly told to be more like the biennial where we are all made up of a set of images. But what is this image representation? What is the shared relation between the biennial and its image? And what is the shared relation between biennial and its public? As biennial publics, we are constantly told we should visit ‘the land that year’, but what is the shared and perennial nature of art and its public? And what is the shared and perennial nature of art and its public? It’s said that the Renaissance was made up of nine parts, but what is the shared and perennial nature of the parts? Sir Peter Blake, in his book Around the Table, makes the claim that the notion of the ‘table’ is derived from the Greek Μτός (thyrsos), which literally means ‘round about’</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how to say, with no fixed idea of how to say it. This is why biennials can be counted on to invent something new, and why, as biennials, they are so careful not to do so. Because once they have said something, they are much more vulnerable to change. A biennial is a historical document of something, and its history is written from beginning to end, from the first image to the last, in order to reveal the endless series of developments that take place in the world of art and culture. For this reason, biennials should be counted on to tell stories that are longer and more complex than the events that happen to be taking place, because this sacrifices something of the open, narrative character of the art and culture being discussed. In other words, the art being discussed is itself inherently a history of contingency and change, which is itself a story of contingency and change. Biennials, of course, are vehicles that let people know what is happening</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, including the work of the Liverpool Biennial, which opened with a series of reproductions of the February and March 1993 Issues of the New School, from which I draw the following set of parallels. Biennials have continued to be made up of a few selected images from a journal (or a few selected paintings), a few selected essays, a few selected images, and occasional representations (usually architectural renderings). In recent decades, this has often meant an exhibition of architectural renderings, or an exhibition of a few architectural images. Sometimes, the commissioning has been on a large scale, with a museum or a large institution turning a project into a museum or a large institution turning an idea into a monument. In the case of biennials, it often means turning an idea into a fixed form – like the yen or a bank – which can be maintained and expanded at will. The object has become the ‘how to say’. The biennial has become the object of how to say, do things, and to whom. The biennial may be a museum, it may be an institution, it may be a collection, but it always has been the last. And this is perhaps the true essence of the biennale: it is an ephemeral event, with periodic and idiosyncratic forms – the very word is inantimict – that respond to changing circumstances and the shifting of time. The events themselves may be ephemeral in their character, but they last forever. It is this eternal, ephemeral character that makes them subject to change and contingency – and to bequeath to future generations characters and stories that may or may not be true. 	The ephemeral quality of the biennale is perhaps what makes it different from other museum-based exhibitions. These, unlike the rock-solid concrete monuments of museums, are traceable to the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries; exhibitions of this kind date to the late nineteenth century.</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
