<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien
    <text>presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien, Lionel Ratard, Claude Lévesque, Jean Guy Lecat and Bernard Tanenbaum. The network of international art dealers Unilever, Miller’s ‘natural’ and ‘art historian’ Stewart Brand, the Tate Modern, The Whitney Museum of American Art, and many others have all contributed to shifting the balance of global art supply in favour of a globalised capitalist economy. The U.S. art market cap of $7.5 billion in 2014 represents a significant shift from the $20 billion in 2007, when the artistic output of the U.S. was estimated to be greater than that of any other country. In other words, the size and scope of the U.S. market today is much larger than it was in the mid-2000s, and the global market for contemporary art is much larger still. 	When looking at a map of the world, it is easy to identify key geographical locations: major cities such as</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien, Jean Guy Lecat and Sylvain Guy Mandelbrot.1 Many of these thinkers emerged as precursors to the mass popularity of modern art, and their ideas continue to guide contemporary curatorial thinking.2 However, as a quarter of a century of neoliberalism has produced a mass of alienated workers and communities, whose influence has been dampened by the economic crisis, it is now time to re-appropriate the cultural resources of the crisis. In recent years, a new generation of curators and artists has emerged, most notably in Toronto and New York, but also in Berlin, Los Angeles, Istanbul and elsewhere. These artists and their projects rarely set out to reconceive or reinvent the gallery as an art museum, museums, or exhibitionary platform. Instead, their curatorial thinking tends to follow the lines of capitalist modern art, in which privatising the historical curatorial role has been achieved through the development of ever more efficient historical research and data curation platforms, including</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien, Bernard Stiegler, Walter Isaacson, Daniel Coleman, Kurt Nowotny, Geoffrey Pullum, and Richard Turner. The list is a selection of names that, while not all in the top 10% of their fields, are all firmly embedded in the historical canon of contemporary art and contemporary art history. The ‘new breed’ of curators, thinkers and artists is made up of a few of these early modernists, including Arthur Conolly, Hans Ulrich Professor of Curating at the New York School of Technology, and his current post as a visiting scholar at New York University. The ‘next generation’ of contemporary art curators is made up of a few more contemporary artists, including Manuel Guttenberg, Manuela Guadagnino, Renate Lorenz, Guillermo Vitale (Italy), Meehan Crist, Jess Doyle, Maria Hlavajova, Ella Schech</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien, Bernard Bouvet, Bernard Lévesque, Jean Guy Lecat, Bernard Tomé, Bernard Beaujola, Bernard S. David, Bernard Schaeffer, and many more. The ‘global art market’ is a complex phenomenon that is more easily understood by understanding its constituents. In this case, Acema’s group of contemporary artists and curators was an ideal laboratory to begin to test the kinds of reforms that would later be implemented by governments, cultural authorities, nongovernmental organisations, academics and others. It proved a useful tool for these stakeholders to work through, as it allowed for the institutionalisation of collective memories, organisational practices and a shared engagement with the world around them. 	Acema’s group was not the first to dream of a third art form, but their proposals and actions during the 1970s and into the 1980s were pivotal in sparking the race to the bottom in terms of what is now considered art value</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien, who has been described as the god of modernism and modernism’s heirs. These theorists argue that the power to transform art today resides in the hands of an enlightened elite of curators, art collectors, art writers and others with a clear institutional interest in visualising, disseminating and defending modernism. ‘Art’s mission “is to tell a story”, these theorists explain. And while stories may be told, it is not enough to create a story; one must be able to analyse and analyse the wider historical and contemporary trajectory of art in order to create a compelling enough narrative to convince a broad audience. 	Today, we would probably say the same of art being made in the developing world or in the West. The distributed forms of knowledge that these thinkers imagine are possible only for a very few people – experts – and their carefully selected collections of art, texts, images and objects. In the developing world, this person is typically a community of</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien, Gilles Jacquelin, Gilles Simon and Bernard Read. In their book The Art Market: Global Art and Its Additivist Politics (2013), Gilles Simon and Bernard Acema reckon that ‘less than 10% of the world’s population now owns a piece of art’s cultural value. To put this in context, a gallery in any modern city would report to a board of directors comprising representatives from national art collectors, art dealers, art administrators and major art institutions. However, to have any real sway over contemporary art’s trajectory, artists and artworld curators are usually required to actively participate in a project (or to be invited to); in the case of a major art museum, even its board members may be art collectors or art administrators with an interest in contemporary art.  	Artists who have had the temerity to attempt to engage or create a relationship with a contemporary art collector or art administrator are often disappointed or even alienated by the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien. In the current globalised and interconnected world, artists have fewer and far between places to operate in. In such a world, it is up to artists, curators, arts administrators and collectors to re-appropriate and reclaim the power of art and art history.  	As an artist, I’m interested in systems that help us to understand ourselves in powerful ways. I also happen to believe that the curatorial is an essential part of any artistic practice, and that the curatorial should be an integral part of any cultural organisation. It is a rare thing to see a curator or an art gallery in New York City, but many artists have their studios in the city, and many galleries in the country, so this is a potentially significant audience. 	In a previous life, I worked for many years as an art administrator for the New York Public Library, and for the International Phonographic Union. I have a particular interest in how artists, curators, and art collectors</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien, Max Brooks, Sheila Tesfaye and many others. There is a strong lobby in the art world for a strong artistic government to represent and deliver value to the art world through a publicly accessible art portfolio, but the pushback against this increasingly dominant globalised form of art is a very real and powerful one. As a culture we still need to struggle with the effects of neoliberalism and modernism, but there is a way to push back against the realisation that art is no longer the dominant form of cultural consumption, production and all that entails. This might mean that in a city like New York, or London, or Paris, or even Bucharest, a culturally responsive art-workshop that offers a cultural experience alongside showcasing contemporary work might prove more influential than a gallery of modern and contemporary art. It might also mean that a culturally responsive art-workshop might encourage a little of the contemporary artist’s MFA work to streamline its access and positioning within the artworld. The role</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien, Louis Grier, Carol Becker, Maria Hlavajova, Peter Schjeldahl, Daniela Ginsburg, Esther Zhang, and many more. The ‘utopian’ in these theorists is a powerful one, but it is the work of many voices, with varying emphases, that can be brought together to form what can be termed a collective unconscious.    	There are different ways of awakening the collective unconscious. Some curators, artists, artists' families and their supporters have worked intensively on creating a ‘permanent third’ through art projects, public interventions, word of mouth and other innovative means, while others have tended to neglect such projects and engagements. The majority of institutions and community arts organisations today take the approach of ongoing public programmes, with projects on a regular basis, and some even have a ‘curatorial’ element to their practices.  	Yet even amongst this growing body of work, there is a marked decrease in visibility</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the online magazine Digital Intifada, which was initiated and supported by the French government. The project was eventually made part of a wider cultural strategy that sought to create a ‘permanent third’ in the cultural mix through integration through dialogue and collaboration. In the digital age of constant globalisation and the multiple digital representations of the world, this is still the predominant approach to art, but in the 21st century it is increasingly important for artists and the art world to find common causes in order to push back the perceived unreality of modern art’s increasing privatisation.  	Artists, curators, arts administrators, artists’ managers and collectors in many forms have historically, and continue to exert a great deal of influence over how we think about and experience modern art. The power to transform art today rests in the hands of a small clique of global art-utopian theorists led by Bernard Acema, a.k.a. Bernard Saint-Julien, Max Horkheimer and Susanne Krohn. Acema’s ideas on the primacy of art in the contemporary world are similar to those of much of what we might call the ‘curatorial class’ – a.k.a. museum curators, book designers, journalists and cultural theorists. But unlike those in power, who are often incentivised to produce high-quality work in return for a seat at the cultural table, the curators of today’s art is often simply encouraged to be creative and innovative, to open up new ideas to be pursued, and to adopt practices that align with the prevailing ideologies of the moment. In Acema’s formulation, these include: ‘monuments’, ‘temples’, ‘monuments that stand out in the crowd’ and ‘the absurdities and beauty of everyday life’. The absurdities and beauty of everyday life are objects of aesthetic experience in many</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts
    <text>presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts Council, Arts Council Capital, as part of its Strategic Cultural Studies programme, and the European Commission, through a joint funding round (co-funded by the Arts Council and the European Commission). The exhibition was presented in the museum's historic lobby, which is now a media production centre for the arts organisation L.A. Unified, and has been a point of contention for the gallery staff and artists, as well as the public, ever since it was first occupied in 2005. I was invited to make a contribution to this important, yet unresolved, part of the story by providing a range of interactive multimedia tools to help the public and artist figure out what happened in the lobby, and to bring to life some of the tensions and conflicts that have come to define the exhibitionary space. After much research, I found the best way to engage with the subject was to make a series of films that would be sculptures, poems, instrumental works, installation works, songs and poems, as well as documentation of the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts Council England, and the Arts Council Scotland, and was supported by the New York and Los Angeles museums. 	The digital media technology that is the subject of this paper is the kind often referred to as ‘the cloud’. It is a new kind of infrastructure that emerged in response to the old feudal one – the transmission of ownership of the means of production – and so it is both distributed and mobile (i.e. available at any moment). It is a kind of ‘memory card’ that records and constructs the past, making and revealing it. Digital media technologies are ubiquitous in our lives, embedded in our daily interactions and objects of consumption, and yet little is said about their relationship to labour and production. In this context, the project undertaken by the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, to produce and present the exhibition,  	Signal,   	Signal 2.0,</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts Council, Arts Council Digital and Digital Forensicity Fund, selected by the Arts Council, and Arts Council Ireland. The archive is a living record, continuing to tell its story across time and space. How to Know About It Nelson Mendez, who curated the exhibition, spoke about the importance of conserving information and the archive in his cultural logic. He emphasised the importance of the archive in the logic of modern and contemporary art, in particular, as a repository of knowledge about the urban environment and culture. He said: ‘Information is the rock upon which the whole of modern culture is built. It is an ever-present and enabling presence that supports and facilitates thought and feeling.’ According to Mendez, the archiving of information provides an alternative to the amnesia of bureaucracy, capitalism, and material culture.[2] When the archive is active, it creates new knowledge: it connects a person to the past, it composes new ways</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts Council, Arts Council Digital, Avent, the New York Art Minimarts Alliance, the New York Public Theater, and the Film and Video Archive Association.PreviousNextThe Biennial as Experiences, Routledge, 2015. Cover Image: John L. Schmitz, New York Times, &quot;The Art of Not Being Governed,&quot; January 2014.PreviousNextJohn L. Schmitz, New York Times, &quot;The Art of Not Being Governed,&quot; January 2014. ‘Unmolding the Fracture: Art, Law, and Publics’, Public Realm,  	1–2, November-December, 2014, p.129–43. 	[i] See  	Public Realm, http://www.publicdomain.org/public-domain/index.html (accessed February 2018). 	[ii] See Uri Green and Tom Perlmutter, eds., The Public Volume: Social, Cultural, and Political Strategies</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts Council and the European Commission.The exhibition is divided into three sections: post-war post-episodic post-total war, and the contemporary web of connectedness that characterises contemporary global cultural capitalism.  The current global situation is classified as ‘the web of things’, and its appearance signals a new planetary aggregation of dispersed and disrupted (globalized) parts. The three sections are divided into three categories: the cities, the factories and the farms, and the remote mountains and the coastline. ‘Cities’ are the major urban centres that are becoming ever more electronic, digitised and connected. ‘Farms and small farms are witnessing the decline of the traditional size, distribution and number of pastures, and the shifting of labour tasks to accommodate for these new labourers. Mere changes in the economic structure of production, distribution and use are being replaced by information and data capture systems that constantly monitor and capture labour and products, ideas and behaviours that can be</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts Council, Deputy Leaders Digital, and the Health and Wellbeing Programme, Department of Culture, Media and Sport, London, USA.More information is available at http://www.annualreport.org/archive/index.php/media/201602242703/archivedate/201602242703/archivedate-full.html#sthash.JLWl.F.09tRk.dpuf.dpuf.2013.10.16TkV.L3.Pdf.2014.xlsx 7. Signal, Norman Foster 2014. Photo: Martin Godwin. 9 December Avent, Avent - Uneven Growth, 2012. Redcarpet, Richard 2014. Photo: Martin Godwin. 9 December Avent, Avent - Uneven Growth, 2012. 	[5] Nuyumbalees, H. 1989. The Politics of Space, London</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts Council, the Danish Council for Independent Curating, and the U.S. Arts Council.In the current period, the curatorial, curatorial imagination sees and imagines many different kinds of engagement with engagement, and this sense of heterogeneity is a major challenge for curators and artists today. The diversity of the exhibitionary market means that very different kinds of people can pay very different prices to see the same exhibition. The purpose of the current exhibitionary market – which is about to become even more diverse – is to draw people together, to create experiences that are shared, yet unique. The main attraction of this new market is in large part about to be replaced by the need to connect in ways that are both immediate and precise, and that is increasingly difficult to define precisely, especially when people are interacting across platforms and instigating new modes of interaction. So the curatorial task is to create sites that allow people to be engaged with in ways that are immediate and precise, but also to maintain the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts Council funded Art Link programme, 2012-13.Part of the second wave of biennials, dappled with snapshots, short stories, and archival images, the twentieth century was a golden age for the transmission and reception of information. The advent of radio, television, and the market places of the twentieth century also opened new ways of interacting and communicating with one another, new ways of using one another’s cultural resources. For Mendez, ‘the new social media brought a completely new perspective on how cultural resources could be utilised’, and ‘a new capacity for culture to assume a political and social role in the social processes that shape our world’.  [1] Norman Foster, ‘The Cultural Logic of Digital Images’,  Cultural Studies  (Winter, 2000), p.18.Download this article as PDFRyan AventRyan Avent is an artist, writer, and researcher. He is an</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts Council and the New York and California governments. For more information please visit: http://www.academia.org/596729/archive-the-monument-modern-art-liverpool-2018 	[1] N. Mendez, ‘Signal’, in Proceedings of the ACM Symposium on Computer-Human Interaction, 2018, pages 591–596.Download this article as PDFMatthew HuxleyMatthew Huxley is an artist and researcher who specialises in the archiving of time. He has a particular interest in archiving and documentation of historical events, particularly those that are ongoing or have recently happened. His artistic works deal with the idea of time, its temporal characteristics, the concept of narrative and the idea of making. His latest project, Recorded: The Motion Picture, documents the motion picture archive from the archive of S. Golding, a UK theatre producer who passed away in 2002.Huxley began</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the Museum of Modern Art’s Digital Media Lab (DMLL), New York, USA, and the University of California, Los Angeles, USA, and was curated by Nelson Mendez, Curatorial Assistant at the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was presented in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition ‘Signal’ at the C.E.A. museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA, and was published in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art, New York, USA. The exhibition was designed by Nelson Mendez, with contributions from archival and digital materials. The exhibition was produced by N. Mendez, with assistance from the museum staff. The exhibition was presented in the archive and was the subject of a project led by the artist, Norman Foster, and the multimedia company, Avent, to create a ‘living archive’ of the exhibition. The project was funded by the Arts Council and the New York and Los Angeles County Museum of Art.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Curator for Public Practice at the New Museum in New York, where she has directed the Public Practice Entry, 2016–17, 2016–17. From 2014–17 she was the curator of the second exhibition in the Whitney Museum of American Art's permanent collection category, 2015–16, and the permanent collection category, 2016–17, with Norman Foster, which explores the ways in which curatorial actions shape our collective cultural experience. She has written for the Museum of Modern Art and the New York Times, and her work has been exhibited at the Venice Biennale, New York, USA; Fineart Paris, Paris; Kunsthalle Zu?rich, Zürich, Switzerland; and was part of the curatorial team for the exhibition of the same name by the Museum of Modern Art and the American Museum of Natural History, both in New York. She</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery
    <text>a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery could choose to create an archive of works from the future, so that artists could plan their lives in the future.  The program allowed artists to specify what kind of archive they wanted, and the ways in which the archive should be organised. For example, the archive of works by and about artists could be organised in different ways, with different criteria, so that different groups of artists could be given different possibilities in the archive. This was a way of thinking about the role of the archive in the contemporary city, and of course it was very new for archival institutions in this regard.  But it seemed a very interesting way of thinking about the role of the archive in the contemporary culture of the future.  And this is one of the things that fascinates me about the machine: the way that memory is put to work, and how that affects what can and cannot be accessed.  If you have a list of criteria that you plug into the programme, and then it runs through the programme,</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery could activate the art programme of a future museum and make the art gallery conduct research on the future of art materials and methodology. This would make the museum more like a laboratory, where the art gallery could operate in a quasi-institutional way, with curators and artists embedded in the museum setting and within the museum’s walls. This is very powerful in and of itself, but more importantly, it allows the installation of a museum in a different world, where the museum is not confined by the parameters of the city. This is similar to the work of Scottish artist Niall Ó Muilleoir, who also worked with us on the installation of the Scottish Rite of Freemasons in San Francisco. The idea of the Scottish Rite in America is that of a direct lineage from the American Revolution, when British subjects were forcibly removed and replaced with a different kind of British man-made ‘Indian’ people. So the Scottish Rite is a Gothic form of the British West Indian lodge,</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery could create a machine that looks back at the past and projects what it might be like to a certain point in time.  Another example is the sculpture garden that was part of the Biennale series, in which artists and groups could adopt a local ‘sculpture making community’ that is part of a larger art collective. This could be a local group that has been involved in creating art since the 1970s, or a group of artists who formed in the 1980s but now work as a group.  A final example is the cluster of artists and art galleries that is part of the Asian Art Gallery, funded by the Arts Council through the Agitation et Avenir Réaliste en Art of Asia programme, and is one of the few remaining arts institutions in the UK. It has been a thriving arts institution ever since I co-curated the Asian Art Gallery series in the late 1990s, and there was a reason why then Arts Council Chairman Tony Lloyd famously said: �</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery could create a machine that projects an art gallery within a neighbourhood within a distant city. The aim of this kind of thinking is very different from the behaviour of biennials, which we had to be very careful about, because it could lead to a kind of randomisation of what’s happening in the city. The main aim of the Future Art project was to tell stories through art in a different way from what biennials usually do.  The way we approached the artefact as a whole was very different to what biennial commissions do today, because of social media. You have a single curator making decisions about where art should be shown based on what social media platforms it’s available on. In a traditional biennial, the cultural institutions organising the event have a curatorial committee that brings together artists, art professionals, art in general, and curators from around the world to discuss and balance the expectations and agendas of the biennial visitor. Today, biennials commission artists</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery could choose to create a machine that projects itself, or commission an organisation such as the Architecture Association to create one.  The machine could project itself in many ways, from planning exhibitions to making repairs to making art itself. The aim was to find ways of linking the artefact and the people who inhabit it, so that artists could influence the future of the building and its inhabitants through their work. In this context, the artefact comes to represent a mix of local and global ideas and practices.  The Architecture Association was one of the organisations that showed an interest in becoming involved in the creation of the machine. They asked what kinds of questions were being asked by the curators and the artists, and proposed creating a local infrastructure through which questions could be asked and ideas processed. For example, the way in which the public was being drawn to the idea of making part of a larger urban fabric, through which artists could create a reconnection with</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery could install the ‘future art machine’ and create a program that encouraged an artist to revisit an area in the city where a lot of conflict occurred, or where a lot of pollution occurred. The artists who received funding from the Biennale could install the program and start commissioning artists to work with it. If the biennale is ever going to do anything meaningful, it’s going to have to be collaborative. The artists will decide what is meaningful to them. By the way, the way I see it, is that the biennale is going to become something very unique and different from what it is now. It will become a rarefaction of sorts, and will engage with the cultural industry as a whole, engaging with the city as a public enterprise as well as an artist-driven one. I don’t think that will happen any time soon, but the way I see it, the biennale will become something very different from what it is</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery could activate this program and create artworks that are artefacts of the city in the future.  The key to this machine was the word ‘future art’. It wasn’t just about what artists or artistic groups would do with the artefact in the future; there was a political context as well.  So the political context was that, in the event that the ‘future’ displayed artwork that was at odds with contemporary urban planning, the art gallery could activate ‘future planning’ by way of legislation or eminent domain to acquire the artwork and turn it into something new. This was an ideal way to endow the artefact with an identity independent of the city’s real estate market.  Another way to think of it is that the art gallery could become an agency that develops strategies for acquiring culturally relevant artwork, while the future stops short of turning its art pieces into something new.   A final way to think about this dynamic is that the</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery could install the programme in the same way that a neighbourhood might install graffiti tagging system. The programme could be programmed to remove graffiti from walls, or to add textiles to the wall, or to turn graffiti into sewing machines, or to turn sewing machines into factory looms, or to turn knitting ­­– as many different kinds of weaving ­­– into craftspaces that ­– with some people choosing to live in and around the machine and others moving away.  The programme itself could be programmed to do many things, but it’s most effective when it does things with ­– abstract space. Space is created through what Maira Kalman sees as ‘the stranger in us’. [Towards a ‘Living World’, Art in America #98, March, 2012] Kalman is not alone in her view of the power of the stranger in us. A growing body of research has shown that technological innovations, including those that alter how we</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery could engage in a collaborative process with artists to design buildings with sustainable solutions, or create innovative paid projects to work with local communities.  The point was to enable a more organic and flexible interaction between art gallery, local community and nature, so that the art could come from anywhere and the people could come from everywhere.  This approach to art being made locally in the present rather than in some transcendent future is what I see in a lot of our projects, in large part because a lot of those people who showed up at the first Art+Home+Time meeting in 2005 still live in the neighbourhood where the projects are happening.  The trouble with the Art+Home+Time model is that it’s too immediate and too present. It’s easy to get caught up in the idea that you’ve got a solution that solves all the problems, and so you tend to neglect the work that has to be done in order to achieve that solution.  A different approach was</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city’s art gallery. The project received a very positive response, partly due to the enthusiastic publics (which were) invited into the machine. We were so impressed by the people that showed up, not only to see the machine but to participate in its making. We wanted to make a machine that would make art, and would do so with as much integrity as possible. So we invited the people who saw the film and wanted to be involved into the design process.  The people who showed up were very clear about what they wanted from the future machine. They wanted to know what we were going to do with the artefact. So we gave them a heads-up, and then we collaborated closely with local artist groups to create what we called the ‘future art machine’. This was a computer program that, when installed in the future, projected what artists and groups in the city might do with the artefact in the future. For example, the art gallery could activate this program and create artworks that are both curatorial and socially engaged.  The main thrust of our thinking was about what local artists could do with the artefact – what it could become and how.  The second generation of artists that came after us were deeply influenced by our involvement in the art gallery. We realised that the machine was far more intuitive and accessible than we were; in fact, the machine was more intuitive and accessible than we'd imagined.  When we started thinking about what a machine could be, we realised that it could be art itself. Art could be produced by a process of inducting artists into a co-generative process that feeds off of one another.  The machine didn’t have to be a beautiful thing: as an artefact, it has to be beautiful in some way. Machine learning and other AI techniques could make artefacts that are inherently useful in their own right, far more valuable and memorable than works of art that are created by</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others
    <text>a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others. And we’ve evolved to be watchful, vigilant and conscious of our surroundings.Nature plays tricks on us all the time. Birds, for example, use song to seek out and consume doomed animals. Human beings, on the other hand, play it safe, choosing to overlook the signs of trouble and to let the situation fester rather than act decisively to rectify the situation. And so, it’s all part of a dynamic, ever-shifting dance that we must all be part of in order to stay alive.There’s a quote from W. E. B. Du Bois that captures that dynamic: ‘There is no such thing as a sacred cow.’ It’s true. The centre of human cultural meaning and value is derived from the life-giving substance that is humanity.We’ve all got our moments of glory, but as we get older and wiser and less and less able to care for our own</text>
    <text>a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others. And we’ve evolved to do these things in the service of the common good, in the service of Mother Nature, in the interest of the common good, in the service of our fellow man.We don’t yet know what that common good is. But we do know that it has to be a place where we can all learn and do things in ways that are authentic to our species. I hope you can join me in thinking about that common good and the places where we can all learn and do things that are authentic to us.Join me in April in Liverpool at the Biennial as part of the Future City initiative. Find out more about the project at biannual.com or contact us.See you there.DDownload this article as PDF27 February 2015To Osvaldo Sanchez6 February 2015Osvaldo SanchezMexico City, MexicoSan Francisco, California6 February 2015Dear Osvaldo,I’m going to be in DF</text>
    <text>a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others. We’ve evolved to be curious and creative and to not be enslaved by the things we see around us.I hope you can join us. If you can come, let me suggest some things to consider in advance, based upon what I heard you say at the convention.There’s a tendency, in the West, at least, to categorize people by their bodies or appearance, to divide people into types or categories. We tend to identify with one body part, or even one face or body part. The mistake we make is to get caught up in the things we see around us. We tend to see things in terms of categories, and so we make categories that aren’t there. For example, our fears of flying are built on a foundation of our bodies: on a neurological level, we can't fly without those fears, but our brains can. And so we tend to identify with one of the things we see around us, whether that’s</text>
    <text>a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others. We’ve evolved to build social structures and to participate in complex social interactions. We’ve evolved to be curious and to experience loss of innocence and vulnerability. All humans are creative and all humans are fallible, but our primary role as artists, thinkers and artists has been to create worlds that are wondrous, enchanting and dreamlike.And that’s why so many artists, writers and collectors today are responding to the challenge of how to entrust their collections to museums and urban centres, and to do so not only in the interests of aesthetic pleasure, but also in the interests of the many communities around the world that are connected to those collections. The collections that we have today are made up of images, images of images, images of images. We need images that are alive with meaning and evoke emotion. To create an image is biologically impossible, but to create an emotion is possible. And so it is with collections like those of art, architecture and design. It</text>
    <text>a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others. We’ve evolved to be curious and to love to be wrong and in the company of fools. We’ve evolved to be the role models of how all of these things can be achieved.But above all, we have to hone in on our true potential and use these gifts to actually achieve things – to actually achieve something, to actually do something. And that’s where we’ve got to be creative, because if we don’t start off with the real things, we’ll be left with the imitation games. And real relationships, genuine love and genuine empathy are the stepping stones to actually feeling something, to actually achieving something. It’s that simple.It’s how we start off in life that determines whether we are truly inspired or if we are victims of our imaginations. So, how do we start off? Simple, we’ve got to know our limitations and work through them. And if we don�</text>
    <text>a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others. We’ve evolved to be curious and to seek knowledge about the world around us.And we’re here to stay. The only way to know is to be entertained and to make others discoverable. More and more, we’re all fed up of needing to be understood and appreciated for what we achieve. We’ve all seen the same kinds of destruction and we’ve all seen the same kinds of suffering and we’ve all learnt to see the bigger picture. We’re all here to have fun. The challenge then becomes finding ways to support the learning and the feeling of belonging that’s part of the process.To see the world the way we want to see it, you need to know what it’s like to be part of a group of people who have to decide for themselves what to be entertained by, what to think and to feel, and how to look at the world. Then you need to know how</text>
    <text>a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others. But we still need to learn how to sit still and take in the world. We need to grow wiser and more conscious of our surroundings and ourselves. And we need to do this in order to progress forward.This is the second edition of The Conference. If you missed the first one, you might want to check it out.In The Anthropocene we’re experiencing a moment where we’re witnessing an unprecedented scale and acceleration of resource-intensive production, consumption and accumulation in the developed world. We’re also witnessing a moment where we’re being placed at risk of becoming extinct due to over-fishing, habitat destruction and other anthropogenic pressures. And we’re seeing a growing recognition that the ecological crisis is far from being solved.The conference was inspired by a TED talk that Haruki Murakami gave in December 2013. The talk, entitled ‘The End of Oil’, provides a personal and profound look at how the fossil</text>
    <text>a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others. We’ve evolved to love learning and to seek knowledge from others.We’ve evolved to love and to share and to roam and to roam in search of adventure and to share our experiences with those we deem ‘worthy’ to know them. We’ve evolved to hoard and to demand and to build and to demand more of the world around us. But above all, we have evolved to love and to share and to roam and to be loved and to be cherished and adored by all who call us home.If you love what you do, and you’ve found the perfect job, and you feel like you’ve landed on the right foot at the right time, and the right place at the right time, and the right place and time are now, then you’ve found the perfect job. Love it. It’s the one true love. It’s a job well done. It’s a miracle</text>
    <text>a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others. We’ve evolved to put our quirks and our fads over long periods, to seek out the wisdom of lived experience and the good will of living things. We’ve evolved to be watchful and vigilant, to see and act out different scenarios, to change our minds as circumstances dictate and to survive in ways that others don’t.All of this is part of our job description. It’s called ‘living and learning’ and it includes interacting with the world around us, learning from our mistakes and striving to be better and more compassionate and generous and kind and interesting and beautiful and interesting and weird and wonderful and weird and wonderful and learning about ourselves and the world around us.The question now is how to do this in a way that is both beautiful and makes us uncomfortable, but also makes us conscious of the fact that we’re both making art and taking part in a process by which we’re creating and evolving worlds and cultures and</text>
    <text>a machine curated by, for, and amidst us, how we inhabit it, making it our own, making it part of the city’s infrastructure. The world is a very particular place, and the way in which we inhabit it is a very specific thing. And so, the challenge for us now is to create worlds that are, for one thing, real and, for another, imaginative and connective. The magic of the Anthropocene is that it does both.It all starts with us.In Beast, we see that the early human ancestors were no angels, but that they had the capacity, over time, to learn. We’re here to stay. We’re here to be entertained and to be cuddled and to have our wings brushed by the carefree birds.We’ve evolved to be playful, to laugh at ourselves and to seek pleasure in the company of others. We’ve evolved to indulge in craft and to seek knowledge and wisdom from others. We’ve evolved to acquire and use knowledge and wisdom to meet the challenges of our world. This is an especially true of our fellow creatures on Earth, who live in societies that value, are dependent on and are threatened by climate change. It’s our job as bird people to adapt and thrive in these new environments, while remaining mindful of our roles and responsibilities as citizens of a planet.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloDr. Michael Truscello has a doctorate in Earth and Planetary Sciences from the University of Illinois at Chicago and specializes in the study of biospheres. His research interests include the geology of materials, such as cement, steel, lime, gravel, and stone; the behavior of materials in the environment; and the interaction between materials and people. He is the author of Systemics, or Being and Matter: Materials, Power, Politics (1995) and has written or co-written several books including the award-winning Mem</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in
    <text>should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in the cultural-material-potential-market-making-machine to the latter. The museum is the ultimate exporter of idealised images of historical curators, of historical curators, and museum curating in general. It promotes this materiality through its collections, it produces its own images through its curatorial labours, and it publicly claims the former through its many titles and imprints. But what it lacks in images of historical curators it more than makes up for in actual historical curators. The museum is the ultimate exporter of idealised images of historic curators, of historical curators, and museum curating in general. It promotes these images through its collections, it produces its own images through its curatorial labours, and it publicly claims the former through its many titles and imprints. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishisable within the museum setting.</text>
    <text>should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in the cultural-monuments-of-the-past-shelf-systems-of-reconstruction-to-acknowledge-its-past.  In fact, it is this self-perpetuation, the very persistence of the museum as an institution, and especially as an institution of learning, which has driven its historic-curatorial-push. And it is this impulse that will continue to animate and guide it into the future. The museum is a complex system, with multiple shepherds and multiple futures. The museum as a museum of constant expansion and reconfiguration is a museum of rarefaction. It is a museum with a distinctly contemporary character, and this is evident in its frequent use as a platform to make sense of the world around it.But what is so deeply lacking in the modern museum? Why is there no Hannah Arendt’s ‘Wild West’?, or George Jennison’s ‘Carrying</text>
    <text>should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in the cultural-metaphorical-mathematical-asset-rip-off-book to make the latter disappear. But the museum also has to balance the need to regularly publicise the museum’s collections with the need to preserve the value of the artefacts within the museum system itself. It is a delicate balance, and the museum needs to learn to live with the consequences. This possibility of periodic museum disarray is a constant source of frustration for the visitor, who feels as if he or she ’d never be able to access the same artefacts again, partly because of a stubborn reluctance on the part of the museum to share its collections with the public. But the museum has to learn to value its collections again, too. Because if it does not, then the tension that exists between the public and the collection becomes unmanageable and the whole endeavour becomes antinarrative, and ultimately unsustainable.  The museum needs to learn to value its collections and also, with</text>
    <text>should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in the cultural commodity making machine to undermine the latter. But this is just the contemporary museum. Back in the 1980s and 1990s, the museum was a distinctly modern museum, dedicated to the contemporary culture of the moment. And today it might be possible to find a museum that exhibits a significant portion of its exhibitionary content in the form of a workshop or a museum teaching contemporary curating. Yet this is just the modern museum; it is also possible to find an older, traditional museum that is interested in preserving the past, in so far as it can tell the story.The Modern MuseumIn most museums today, the museum is either an abstraction or a fiction. In the museum, the museum, the artefact is the museum. Unlike in a typical museum, the museum does not create its own identity; it is always actively engaged in reproducing itself (re-producing its form) in the face of external pressures and forces. And unlike in a typical artefact, the museum can be counted</text>
    <text>should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in the cultural commodity shop to undermine the latter. But it should also bear in mind that the contemporary curatorial job is no longer solely about creating museums or establishing an authoritative voice in museums. Today, it is about creating an aesthetic landscape that is accessible to a global audience, and about that is relevant to the global economic and political systems that are being assembled. In other words, it is about more than creating museums or establishing an authoritative voice in museums; it is also about the localisation of power and material flows in cultural formations. It is about the global circulation and exchange of cultural forms and objects. It does not create, nor is it confined to, museums. The museum has entered a new phase in its role as curatorial prop, and it is up to cultural theorists and artists to adopt a new set of skills and vocabularies that are relevant to the scale and nature of these processes. The curatorial is not some isolated act, and it is not some kind of autonomous place.</text>
    <text>should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in the cultural-materials-production-of-mass-media-of-identity-strategies-and-infrastructure-building-block-one-stop-shop. It has done so since the 1970s, and it continues to do so even though there is no longer a major art-historical-museum-style curatorial structure in the United States and most of the world. In places like Venice, the institution is even more of a hotel than a museum. The museum-like curatorial apparatus permits an artist’s conceptual licence to be exercised in a more conventional, quasi-religious sense with respect to the cultural practices or even real-life practices of the time. This is why contemporary artists have responded so readily to the introduction of food and drink into their artworks. For many years, curators were naturally drawn to artists who were artists themselves and possessed artistic talents. However, the advent of mass media in the form of painting and photography also opened</text>
    <text>should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in the cultural-materials-usage-and-purchase-machine to render it unrecognisable.  The museum is the ultimate exporter of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curatorial’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is the ultimate exporter of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curatorial Agenda has become more and more complex, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern what the museum was actually trying to say with its exhibitions, symposia and festivals. It may be that the most current and dynamic elements, those that have gained the most public and political attention and are the most likely to remain so, really do come from the museum and its curatorial hand</text>
    <text>should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in the cultural-economy-of-replacement that it can think of to undermine the latter. And this is precisely what the curatorial push has done. It has undermined the person of the curator, in the main by turning him into a paraplegic symbol of the museum’s mission. It has done so by turning his back on the audience, who are now more and more likely to be from social groups who are most exposed to art being made elsewhere in the world. It has done so by turning artefacts into mere forms of data, presenting them as historical artefacts with no real place in a museum, or in this case, no place at all. And it has done so with the support of a host of international artsfonds and foundations, including the Arts Council of Canada, the European Community and the United States Agency for International Development. It is true that the presence of a great number of artsfonds and foundations in Toronto has recently begun to be questioned, and</text>
    <text>should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in the cultural-curatorial-industrial-complex to undermine the latter. But here, too, the museum is accused of complicity in the death of the individual or collective memory of a key historical figure. While it is true that the museum is the last place on Earth where such a commodity is commonly imagined to exist in abundance, the museum certainly knows how to market its position. As the curatorial shift in the 1980s and 1990s rendered crucial works of art increasingly unattainable market-to-market, the museum sought to capitalise on this reality by creating ‘events’ that would align with the museum’s curatorial priorities. These ‘places of historical repute’ became a frequent subject of critique and eventual protest. The failure to produce such value in the face of such a commodity is itself a point of departure and an indicator of things to come. The failure to appreciate the museum as an entity and its particular curatorial agenda as opposed to the artist’</text>
    <text>should be curated as if it were a museum’, in order to allow visitors to ‘step back’ into the story, into the past, into the present. This is a rare and precious commodity, which can only be acquired and used by a museum. It is the rare and precious commodity that can only be earned and passed on from generation to generation. But what is so desperately missed in the current curatorial push is that this ‘step back’ is itself objectified, fetishised and fetishised within the museum setting. The museum is the ultimate exporter and user of cultural commodities, and its future plans are solely based on the future export of cultural commodities. As the Curator in Chief’s position has become increasingly manifest, it is becoming increasingly difficult to discern when the museum was actually interested in celebrating the curator’s position as a valuable historical commodity or in actively undermining it.  The museum is most definitely interested in the former, and actively employs every trick in its art exhibitionary book to undermine the latter. If the museum is to survive, it must learn to love the former.The art market has long since caught up with contemporary art practice, and while there are still many artists who practice in areas outside of the art market, the sheer volume and variety of art now available in the market has sapped the art market of its purchasing power. Contemporary art, in short, is more accessible and more fulfilling to consumers around the world. The curatorial move, on the other hand, remains firmly rooted in the country where the action is taken, and is a rarity in its own right. The curatorial shift, on the other hand, is a rarity in itself. I would argue that the current global curatorial push is the direct result of a political and economic dynamic in which the former on one hand and the latter on the other. The current curatorial push is the direct result of a political and economic dynamic that the then-current generation of artists</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futur
    <text>extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futurists like Ray Kurzweil envision a future in which all of the imperfect parts of the past are incorporated into a single whole. This new world order will be built on the back of smart phones, data services, and social media platforms that constantly monitor, record, and analyze every step of the way. It’s as if the social contracts that we write with regard to the future are inherently optimistic, and thus necessary in order to guarantee that the future will be happy and fulfillable for future generations. But what makes us happy in the present is precisely what M. Roland Griffiths-Dawson, one of the inventors of smart phones, describes as ‘ambiguous optimism’: the kind of optimistic thinking that leads to feelings of unreality. The ambiguous optimism that leads to feelings of unreality is precisely what M. Roland Griffiths-Dawson, one of the inventors of smart phones, describes when discussing Griffith’s original idea of creating an</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futurists imagine a future in which all of humanity is reacquainted with the past, but there is no such hope for machines. If there is no such hope for machines, then what is the future but a repetition of the past?In fact, there is a very strong push towards an integrated, interconnected and social future, which is often described as ‘multiverses’ – in the sense that events in the future, or in the past, can be interconnected and transposed to affect the movements of people living in the present. This is often taken to mean that the future holds the potential to be like the past, except with better and more encompassing environments. But this is not at all what multiverses actually achieve. Instead, they concentrate future possibilities into singular positions – like actors in a play who achieve a singular result – which is often described as ‘the collapse of the human’.Mega-episodic structures are often used as devices to express greater political</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futurists imagine a black-hole in which all of humanity floats, but in actuality this only serves to slow down the pace of technological progress. It’s as if the black hole keeps on expanding, sucking ever more energy from the planet.Future society is only possible because of the development of ever more powerful computers and networks – which means that the social is mediated through ever more powerful infrastructures. This means that the social becomes ever more reliant on technologies that are able to inspire and enable new social structures. The question is where these new infrastructures draw the lines. New media technologies and app platforms allow us to share and connect across vast distances, which in turn opens new opportunities for collaboration. But in order to fully realize the capacities of this shared space, we need to be able to read the infrastructures that are constructed around us. This is why ecologists and urbanists tend to look to the past – looking backwards in order to see the future – when</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futurists imagine a completely inclusive future, but in actuality this only ever finds an optimistic outcome for a very specific set of people, societies or races. There are far too many failures and struggles to be taken into account in constructing such a future, and even if we did have all the answers, such a future would still lie somewhere between now and then, never reached or creating in the here and now. 	In futurist parlance, this ‘black box’ is a location where critical information on the state of a developing system is kept, but it also implies a level of abstraction that is difficult to define and which can also make it hard to understand. So while this condition may be met in the black box, it is still abstracted from the user and user-centred design that we employ in the present. If the black box is abstracted away, the resulting system design can be user-centred. If the system is opaque, then the resulting systems design</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futurists imagine a bright future with unlimited possibilities. It’s just that ‘the possibilities’ are inherently uncertain.Future societies don’t have that problem. There’s no inherent uncertainty about what the future holds, because there is no such thing as a future. But humans have this tendency, which can lead to a sense of hopelessness and negativity – the sense of things never being better, or that there’s no hope left but to continue to fail – which can then be used by those who control the means of understanding to justify the past failures. For many people, and science will certainly be one of those people, the use of that future knowledge to justify the present is a deeply felt part of the identity of the person.The other problem with the present is that of representation. As we saw, the future is represented in technocratic representations of it, which often include significant portions of what is now called ‘Britain’. But for others,</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futurists imagine a future in which all of humanity is reacquainted with the past, but there is no such future. It’s as if humanity itself is experiencing the future through a simulation.Every action, or every thought, is subject to the vagaries of history, and the improvisation of human reaction to changing conditions. But the tendency toward greater complexity and the consequent decrease in generality is undeniable. That tendency is part of what anthropologist Vern Weischenk calls the ‘great recursive tendency’, which he describes as follows:Every complex system has its own variant, or ‘genealogy’, where the parts meet at the roots. We can identify this tendency as a genealogy, or we can identify the variant(s) that are at fault and bring them to account.‘At fault’ is the tendency toward greater complexity because events that once were can no longer be counted on to repeat.’ Our moon, for example</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futurist thinking is so exciting: it implies a future that’s unpredictable but also impossible – and yet we still have to build it. Otherwise, we’d be unable to imagine a different future. The assumption of AI makes it easier to imagine a different future, but it also means that future-critical infrastructure becomes much more accessible, allowing for the very possibility of another future to be created via AI.This all brings us back to the question of immigration. While many of those brought to the UK as children are quite capable of creating a new life in a different country than they were living in before, many of them don’t have the necessary skills or the right mindset to take on the daunting task of reintegrating themselves back into mainstream society. Many of those brought to the UK as children have criminal records that keep them out of the country, and many of them are at risk of re-entering if they’re caught out by a random wave of people on</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futurists envision a flat, beautiful future, but in reality we’re only ever likely to get to know the past few moments of the past – because there is no such future and so we can only ever acquire the past.All of the difficulties and stresses of the present – the economic, the political, the social – will be overcome in the future, but the immense, interdependent web of relationships that we inhabit today will be rendered impenetrable. So the question becomes how to imagine a future in which the past isn’t present in such a way as to prevent the emergence of new contradictions and possibilities, but nevertheless to allow for the emergence of the possibility of such possibilities. Futurists on the left tend to focus on the positive aspects of this possibility, imagining a just and beautiful future where everything works out, but on the other side of the coin, there is a sense that there is a kind of cruel efficiency to the way in which we produce and consume the world</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futurists imagine a smooth future with no social or political entanglements – although this is clearly not what we currently have.If we take the time to reflect on these two conditions, and to consider what a future society of connected devices might look like, we can begin to imagine how we might live together in this new social world. In the present, we’re stuck in a social hierarchy of connected devices, far removed from the devices that shape our lives. But a future society might allow us to create our own devices and connect to the networks that enable them to function. We could then take this future society to represent the diversity of our present, where people can choose to be connected, and might choose to ignore the devices that keep us in constant motion. This is the historical trajectory of artificial intelligence and virtual reality, and it’s one that's predicted to return in large part due to the rise of connected devices.Future Society 	[i] Meehan Crist,</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines or to data, and the implication is that these processes too are part of a future that can be more fully realized in some cases. But it is also clear that to be able to understand what this future might mean, we’d need to be able to build it.That’s the double bind: the inability to see the black, or to be able to construct the infrastructure to support the visions of future inhabitants. The second condition is an explicit acknowledgement of the fact that this future is no longer the future – in the sense that there is no future present but only possibility. The term ‘future society’ seems to imply an optimistic future that somehow integrates all of the failures of the past into a new future, but in fact this is only possible if we’re given the ability to predict the future. In other words, our present is only possible because there is a chance in the future that all of the past failures will be erased. This is why futurists like Ray Kurzweil envision a future in which the human species is reacquainted with the natural world. It’s as if the past is re-created in the image of the future, in the image of what can be done with today’s technology. But this raises the question: what kinds of technologies might enable such a scenario? Ray Kurzweil’s future society would presumably need knowledge of the like of artificial intelligence to enable such a scenario, but how might we create such a society? I propose the use of geothermal energy and floodlit art as a toolkit for future exploration.Art, it turns out, has a great many uses beyond its aesthetic effects. We could use it to illuminate the terrain on which our future cities build their infrastructure in the image of the natural world, or at least as a toolkit for imagining the terrain after it has been desalinated and extracted from the planet. A city that systematically obscures the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view
    <text>curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view of the artist or audience. Thus the art of making photogenic images is a powerful way to engage with the cultural meaning of a place or event, even if this means engaging with the wrong meaning or engaging with events that are neither here nor there (although, of course, this is often the case).  	Similarly, the use of text or images can be used to create a semantic or narrative hook that is both strong and specific – and can be used constructively. For instance, the convergence of social media and photography can be used to create a shared meaning or narrative about a shared set of people or groups. This is a recurring trope in the visual arts: the artists and audiences of the past often find ways to intervene in the design and construction of the social mores and practices of the present, especially when these conflicts arise between what is perceived as the artist’s right eye and the audience’s left eye. 	Finally, there is the potential of bringing together</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view of the artist or audience. This is why so many artists today are artists in their audiences of young people, engaging with topics, words or situations that are not necessarily their own, but can nevertheless be engaged with. Because they are engaged with something else – perhaps the subject of their work, or a group of friends, family members, community members, neighbours or passersby – and because they are in a position to effectuate something that is meaningful in terms of their own identity, place, history or place of origin. 	There is a danger today, however, in the over-emphasising of images and sounds as the medium of choice and over-interpretation. People see and make connections across different media, but they often make little or no sense or difference at all. For instance, the art world today often produces works that are as emotionally raw, powerful and powerful as they are intellectually dishonest, but are also socially aware and politically aware. But this is neither here nor there.</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view of the artist. By engaging with a visual art as a whole, we can create meaning about communities of people in a way that is open to questioning and new thinking.  	Another example of engaging with meaning beyond the visual arts is the work of the FACT (Foundation for Art and Creative Technology) – a not-for-profit arts organisation founded in 1991 and currently a Chamber of Commerce leading in the UK and internationally in the development of digital arts practice. Founded on a shared mission to bring creative people together to make art, the FACT has become a global leader in the creation and implementation of community arts projects using new media.  	The FACT is a not-for-profit arts organisation established in 1991 and is a founding member of the Chamber of Commerce. The Chamber is a not-for-profit cultural organisation established in London to promote and facilitate the exploration and development of new cultural forms through the provision of technical, financial and organisational support to</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view. By understanding that visual culture can be understood in terms of multiple perspectives, including aesthetic, political and environmental––using images and media that are not confined to a particular point of view––the art can then be understood in a way that is open to multiple interpretations. By engaging with multiple perspectives, we can create a dynamic context of ideas and opinions. 	The power of the visual arts is in part derived from their potential as a way of concealing or disguising change and uncertainty. This is why the visual arts are often depicted in media reports as having been used in dark or subversive ways––as a way of controlling or perplexing viewers or participants. This is because the art is inherently ambiguous. Its content can be interpreted in many different ways, and the visual arts practitioners who employ this ambiguity are likely to employ it for many different reasons. Therefore, it is easy to understand why art is often represented as if it is a masked or obscured way of doing things. But the ambiguity inherent in</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view of the artist or audience. By connecting to an imagined larger context of history and place, the visual arts can open new ways of understanding the world. 	However, this does not mean that the creators of visual arts work should be rewarded or that the work of art should necessarily be seen as an asset to society. 	Instead, the goal of engaging with the power of the visual arts should be to interrogate the assumptions and ideologies that create the images we see and produce the stories we tell. And here the challenge lies in engaging with the assumptions and ideologies of our own society and culture, which shape the way we perceive the world. As Ana Laura Lopéz de la Torre, one of the creators of Supernatural (an Argentinian visual arts collective), puts it: ‘There is a reason why the supernatural is one of the most pernicious forces shaping our modern world: modernity is built on assumptions and ideologies of race, class, gender, sexuality,</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view or perspective of the artist or audience. By this, I mean engaging with the possibility that the meaning of an image may lie somewhere in transit, or yet not having been seen or taken into consideration at the time of publication. This is a very powerful way to engage with the image and its implied meaning. 	When I started my PhD, I decided to investigate the meaning of certain images through a Venn diagram. This was the visual arts diagram of sorts, where the nodes were the images, the travels were the relations between images, and the means by which an image was interpreted were the message or message Part of my doctoral research involved mapping the visual arts and their artists. So images such as the megastructure of a megastructure, the the grid system that is an integral part of photonic grid, the routing of signals and the virtual construction of infrastructure, as well as social media platforms such as Facebook and Twitter, as well as software and network protocols, would all be analysed and</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view of the artist who is trying to capture an audience. And the visual arts are powerful because they are able to create a narrative that is not necessarily understood by the audience. For instance, the visual arts have been shown in venues where the original artist couldn’t possibly imagine a place or a style of a place or a way of interacting. This isn’t to suggest that the visual arts aren’t interesting or powerful or that the audience isn’t going to fall in love with everything that is shown. But the capacity of visual arts to create narratives that are open to new points of view and perspectives is an important innovation that adds another dimension to the art that is being shown. 	Now, maybe the most exciting thing about the visual arts is that audiences do fall in love with things they see. And that is a powerful thing. But it isn’t a magic formula or a magical solution. It is simply that audiences do fall in love with things because they</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view of the artist or audience. By bringing together many different points of view, the visual arts can open new ways of looking at the world. As the visual arts develop, they often shift the focus of our understanding of things, creating new frameworks that help us see things from different perspectives. This works in symbiosis with the media that we consume: the art, the media, and the media interact in an ever-growing number of ways. 	Similarly, the design and the design process are also powerful because they simultaneously depend on content and audience. If we cut and paste elements from a design into a building, product, or service, we necessarily cut and paste these elements into an ever-growing number of places in the world. And once these elements are there, they are not there any more – meaning that even if the art is great and the designers are brilliant, the end result is going to be flawed and sometimes chaotic. 	There are of course far better ways to do things,</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view of the artist, audience, curator, etc. In other words, the original political context and/or ideological bent of an artist’s work is often obscured or disregarded in the contemporary context of visual arts. We tend to produce visual artsworks that are in the public arena but don’t pay enough attention to the subtleties and hidden factors that create and amplify the public relations potential of art. In other words, the public arena may not necessarily align with the artist’s intentions or values. 	In a larger context, the public relations potential of art may be realized in other areas of the public sphere – for instance, in the arts education arena or the politics of education. But in a specific context, the art may end up creating or enhancing a particular understanding of certain things. This may be true of one-off cases but is also a true for projects that end up existing in a particular cultural landscape for a very long period of time. Imagine if every</text>
    <text>curated by a machine (although, as we saw, it is also possible that the machine is conscious). Here, the audience is invited to participate in a narrative that is mediated through the technology that creates the images we see and produces the stories we tell. This is similar to the work of computer programs that read text and produce output – quite different from the original artist’s original conception of the technology, where the audience was actively engaged in creating the narrative of the project.  	Now, I want to suggest that there are also ways to rethink how we conceptualise and engage with media and visual culture in an intelligent and responsive way. And here I mean creating new creative means through media that are not confined to the specific medium or platform of a visual artist’s work. I.e. engaging with the capacity of visual media to create meaning and influencing connections.  	For instance, the visual arts are powerful because they are effective at creating a connection with something beyond the original point of view that would render the objects in art as abstract and non-representational. By engaging with the visual arts as a creative medium that openly and purposefully exposes audiences to the world around them, and thereby encouraging a certain amount of critical thinking and self-reflection, the new visual arts practices can break free of the limitations of their particular medium and position.  	Finally, there is the challenge of imagining new creative ways of engaging with the same old visual arts practices. For instance, there is a question that arises in the art world about the role and potential of the artist in a community developing process. For instance, there is a question whether the artist should direct the development of a community’s infrastructure, or whether the community can instead assume responsibility for its development. Art has a particularly powerful role in challenging the existing order, but it also has a crucial role to play in creating new contexts and new worlds. That is, if the art is to have any real impact at all. In</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical,
    <text>presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical, apolitical even, but which actively engages with the politics of representation and economic exploitation of contemporary society.  	In the social, political and cultural sphere, interest in the social and the complex often dominates consideration of the abstract, although the social and the abstract are interrelated and dependent on one another. This is true of companies, unions, governments, students, crowds, history, language, aesthetics, commodities, races, genders, nations. And yet, while much of what we think we know about the social and the political is true of the social and the political, we also hear or read things differently. For example, the social is often emphasised when it comes to the ways in which labour creates social value, while the political and economic meanings of labour are often obscured or under-emphasised. 	But, as I have argued elsewhere, there is a ‘difference of meaning’ between social and the political. Socialising meaning is part of a project that creates</text>
    <text>presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical, apolitical but with a critical eye on the world around it, but which also makes some claims on our cultural identity. What is being made and reproduced in the world around us is always at odds with the claims of an art project, but the past is frequently a powerful locus of resistance.  A Case Study in Immersive Theatre  So, what is the potential of the virtual and the present in relation to one another? One can only speculate, but one can speculate. One can imagine a parallel oracle system that simultaneously looks to the future and the past to inform and direct its actions. Perhaps, in the future, the virtual and the present would communicate through art projects that exploit the promise and vulnerabilities of new technologies, but right now, we have no such digital representation of the future that would simultaneously predict and interact with us, but also not necessarily create or facilitate that future. Art as historical research  A Case Study in Immersive Theatre  So, what is the potential of the new</text>
    <text>presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical, but the truth is that art today is political in its own right. Its rise and sustained institutionalisation in the twentieth century coincided with a political and economic war on the biennial and other art forms, and the tendency for artists to be drawn into that war. As biennials and other art forms became more globalised, and more international in their publishing practices, it was increasingly possible to identify and characterise an art project as a ‘global’ project, and to publish it in multiple languages, with varying emphases and subject matters, in multiple cultures, in multiple languages, and in multiverses. As a result, it became ever more possible to connect two artworks, a particular artistic practice and a particular location, creating worlds of their own. This perspective is exemplified in the 2013 Biennale of Sydney, which was partially funded by the Australian Arts Council and Anstalt Foundation, and which was organised by the Swedish Museum and the Doha Foundation. The biennial</text>
    <text>presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical, apolitical but with a side of being apolitical too. But if the aim of contemporary and post-modern art is to generate knowledge and awareness of social injustice and injustice, then the other – the theatre, the media, the banks, the legal system – has to play a role in contributing to that knowledge and awareness. That takes work, and it takes work that is innovative, provocative and subversive. And in the 21st century, it takes work that is socially useful and politically aware. Art has a political and activist function. It is essential that it contributes to the democratisation of knowledge. But it is equally necessary that it contributes to the production and dissemination of knowledge, both within and without the other. That is, of course, the ethos of the ‘sharing’ model of cultural production and exchange that is emerging across the social sciences and humanities departments in a massive and ever-expanding network of collaborative and equitable ways.Such models are politically aware, socially responsive and artist-</text>
    <text>presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical, but the history of art makes it abundantly clear that artistic practice is often influenced by economic, racial and class dynamics.  One might even argue that the emancipatory dimension of the emancipatory dimension of the ‘medium’ is one in which art can play a significant role, and that the emancipatory dimension of the ‘ideal citizen’ is one in which the arts and aesthetic disciplines play a particularly prominent role.  The historical and contemporary context of the publication of the journal Aesthetic Engines suggests a number of things that are of relevance in the present context, but is perhaps less relevant in the age of the spectacle and global market. The first is the centrality of aesthetics as a ‘fundamentality of modernity’ and the importance of a physical and institutionalised physical representation of beauty and virtue in the physical and institutional forms of beauty and beauty that characterize the modern world. This is primarily understood as the physical manifestation of the later Wittgenstein</text>
    <text>presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical, but the project of visibility and reception that biennials and art museums play upon is deeply imbricated with political and social agendas. This ‘trans-histories’ position artists and exhibitions as a presences that challenge assumptions about the social world and the place of art, but also institutionalised ideologies and power structures. It seeks to create spaces and environments free from the overproduction and misappropriation of labour and resources, but also from the effects of industrial and capitalist accumulation. This would mean abandoning the pretence of being artefactual, and creating ‘real life’ through the artefactualisation of art and art history through the means of technology.  The project of immersive experiences through artefacts and artefacts, or as I have come to call it ‘the contemporary incarnation of Alexander Provan’s The Archive: On Archive and Society, was born. Provan was born and raised in the Bay Area, but as a young person in his thinking on</text>
    <text>presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical, apolitical, but above all, apolitical. But, as biennials become more institutionalised and political in their constitutions, more and more of their funding derives from contracts with society as a whole, from those contracts ensuring that art will be produced in a certain way, and that society will always respond in a certain way. The contracts that enable this are contracts that are constantly being rewritten and amended, and in this it is true of all programmes and initiatives. Art has a political nature too, and so does the organisation that funds it.  One could argue, however, that the programmes that are important for artists and the cultural organisations that they engage with are those that emerge out of the conditions and politics of contemporary capitalism. That is, programmes that generate cultural creativity and action through their content and politics are necessarily political in nature. The more politically abstract and individualistic the organisation is, the less capable artists and organisations of different kinds are of engaging with and creating that culture themselves. The more</text>
    <text>presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical, but the truth is that the art it produces is political in character – apolitical because it has already been made elsewhere and circulated widely. The mode of artistic globalisation produced by the globalised capitalist market is political because it is political in its formation and adoption of language – the physical act of making a commodity and passing it on to the next level of production, consumption and distribution. This political aspect is further underscored by the fact that, in the age of the internet, it is common for the objects of art to be created in ‘third-party’ sites – not by the artists, but by site owners and corporate managers. The internet raises the bar of what is possible in terms of the kinds of social transformation that can be effected through art, and art is often required to perform this role in the production of social change. But the fact that social media is a more powerful tool for the capitalist accumulation of capital than any other mode of expression, and that sites like Facebook and Twitter</text>
    <text>presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical, but in fact artists and artists’ organisations have always been open to the possibility that their creative works may be defined by the political. The Immersive Theatre is no exception to this rule. Whilst the journal may have been a platform for the artist to articulate ideas and concepts, the journal also acted as a kind of ‘past, present and future’ of the artist’s activities. It provided the itinerary for the artist’s cultural activities, giving a sense of the social and economic context of the artist’s activities, and it connected the artist’s social activities with those of the city. As the journal progressed, the author is generally perceived as more present in the work than the events that constitute the performance, but the authorship of the journal remains uncertain. In the case of the Immersive Theatre, the authorship was ultimately attributed to Sol Aramendi, Rami El Samahy and three other artists. Although the authorship of the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project], and the subsequent publication of the article, ‘A Case Study of Immersive Theater,’ it was widely perceived that the medium had been sufficiently rendered invisible that the project could be considered an art project, and its potential as a platform for collaborative research and discovery dismissed the idea that the medium had been intentionally obscurantist. In the case of theatre, the publication of a project as a ‘work in progress’ and its subsequent stand-through publication in a ‘future publication’ (as a ‘work in progress’), both act as markers of artistic practice and as precursors to the forms and practices of contemporaneous art. This transhistorical and historical perspective suggests a mode of artistic and cultural production that is sensitive to the practices and ideologies of contemporary capitalism, but that seeks to emancipate artists from the constraints and politics of representation and economic imperialism of industrial society. It is an era in which art is often accused of being apolitical, apolitical, but above all, apolitical. It is a ‘trending’ publication, and much of its beauty is derived from its ability to generate buzz and noise about art and art’s place in a given cultural landscape. But this ability to generate buzz and noise is itself deceptive. Its value lies in its ability to entangle and confine, to instigate and animate, to inspire and entertain. It is a power that artists harness, and it is this power that created and continues to create new worlds, from the transitory to the everlasting. But this ability to ensnare and confine also generates certain powers, and artists are naturally drawn to these powers, whether by their own agency or because they naturally understand the political and social contexts in which they operate. For example, artists who develop collaborative research and discovery projects with local communities are often drawn to the opportunity for their projects to be informed by the knowledge and power of such groups, whether this is through</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times
    <text>curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times (Durham: Duke University Press, 1997), p. 110. [15] See, for instance, Michael Ames and Christine J. Clarke, The Rise of the Creative Class (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 1982), p. 174. [16] See, for instance, John C. King and Tom Vandeputte, eds., Things, Media &amp; Culture (Minneapolis: University of Minnesota Press, 1980), p. 4. [17] For more on the relation between things and services, see, for instance, Susanne Kugelmann, Things: The Anthropocene (New York: Columbia University Press, 1988), Chapters 2 and 3. [18] Andrew Goffey, ‘The Things We Feed Ourselves: Media, Consumer Culture, and Environmental Psychology’, Journal of Consumer Research, Vol. 17, No. 2, 1988, p.285. [19] Elizabeth C. Sharpe, ‘The End of Depression’</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times, trans. Christine McKenna (New York and London: Cambridge University Press, 2003), p. 175. [15] Lawrence M. Burns, Things, 1950. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [16] See Lawrence M. Burns and Larry M. White, eds., Things: A Documentary History (New York and London: Cambridge University Press, 1986), p. 80. [17] For more about the literary form of the thing, see my The Limits to Literary Growth: On the Form of Literary Criticism, ed. Stefan Collini (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2016). [18] The thing is a form of linguistic entities – nouns and verbs – that have a kind of integration and propagation within linguistic units. One can say that the thing is a name or a phrase or a set of symbols that categorically designate something or someone. For instance, a person or set of people is a thing if and only if they have names, or more specifically</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times, 1972. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [15] In the early twentieth century, there was a tendency to undervalue the role of the cultural in shaping the social. See Lawrence M. King and Francis J. Vine, eds., Things vol. 2, 1969–74, and 2 nd ed., Things vol. 3, 1975–76, with annotations and bibliography, in Lawrence M. King and Francis J. Vine, eds., Things vol. 2, 1969–74, p. 206–21. [16] See, e.g., John H. Nelson, ‘Things’, in A.S. Kahn and M.N. Akomfrah (eds.), Modern China, rev. ed., Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1982, p. 215. [17] See, e.g., Michael Ames and Christian Körner, ‘Cultural Capital: The Creative Capital of a People’, in</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times, 1978. [15] See, for instance, Karen Straughan, ‘The End of Oil: Will Its Revelation Slow America’s Spiritual Mortification?’, in Tom Jewett and Karen Straughan, eds., Things (New York: Cambridge University Press, 2016), p. 5. [16] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, ‘The Spirit of Oil: Power, Politics, and Peculiar Forms of Energy Consumption in an Industrial Society’,  Boundary Making, Vol. 3, Issue 2, 1988, p. 81. [17] ‘Signaling Systems, Strategies, and Cryptosystems. The End of Oil?, with Applications to the Information Society (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2015), p. 6. [18] ‘Signaling Systems, Strategies, and Cryptosystems. The End of Oil?, with Applications to the Information Society (Cambridge, MA:</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 1993), p. 7. [15] See, for instance, Svetlana Boym: ‘The Biggest Loser’, in Making Things Up (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1999), p. 70. [16] See, for instance, Tom Jewett, Specters of the Internet: On the Origins of Accurate Media (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2011), p. 11. [17] See, for instance, Boym, op. cit., p. 7. [18] Thomas More, ‘The Politics of Uncertainty’, in Making Things Up (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1999), p. 28. [19] See, for instance, Boym, op. cit., p. 8. [20] John Stuart Mill, ‘The Spirit of Capitalism: A Critique of Political Economy and Political Representation’, in</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times, trans. Stefan Collini (New York: Columbia University Press, 2011), p. 28. [15] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Spirit Level: The Technological Origins of Our Times (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1987), p. 6. [16] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, The Spirit Level: Literacy and Spirituality in the Electronic Age (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1997), p. 6. [17] Thomas Malthus, ‘The Fall of Man’, in Malthus and the Fall of Man, edited by Ray Bradbury and Richard Florida (New York: Vintage Books, 1978), p. 4. [18] Edward Burtynsky, ‘The Mismeasure of Man’, in Malthus and the Fall of Man, edited by Ray Bradbury and Richard Florida (New York: Vintage Books, 1978), pp. 4–</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times (New York: Cambridge University Press, 2005), p. 17. [15] See, for instance, Susanne Kreiderman and Tom Waugh, eds., Things (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1994), p. 242. [16] See Gerald S. Taylor, op. cit., p. 2. [17] The thing itself is a concept with a body of shared relations between people, places, and objects. It is one of the first orders of being, and as such is constantly subject to change, changing only the parts that make sense for the system to recognise as being in the current state. Taylor, op. cit., p. 6. [18] Taylor, op. cit., p. 7. [19] See, for instance, J.D. Dewsbury, ‘Things’, in Things (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2005), p. 6. [20] See J.D.</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times (Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 1975), p. 1. [15] See, for instance, Susanne Kübler-Ross, Things or Nothing: Kübler-Ross, Postmodernism, Identity (Cambridge, Mass.: MIT Press, 2002), p. 39. [16] See, for instance, M. Hassan Abbasi and Jan van Horne, eds., Things (Cambridge and New York: MIT Press, 2015), p. 12. [17] Raymond Williams, Things (New York: Random House, 1961), p. 68. [18] Ibid., p. 196. [19] Ibid., p. 67. [20] J.D. Dewsbury, Things, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (Cambridge: Cambridge University Press, 2003), p. 4. [21] Ibid., p. 75. [22] Williams, op. cit., p. 50. [23] Amina Kemal</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1998), p. 5. [15] See, for instance, Shintaro Miyazaki, Things: History, Identity (London: Cambridge University Press, 1995), p. 12. [16] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1998), p. 6. [17] Karen Bowden, Specters of a Distant Star (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1987), p. 11. [18] See, for instance, Michael Ames, Aliens, Symbols, and Cybernetics (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1983), p. 208. [19] See, for instance, Ames, Aliens, Symbols, and Cybernetics, p. 209. [20] Ames, Aliens, Symbols, and Cybernetics, p. 209. [21] See, for instance, Bowden, op.</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that does what it is told to do.’ Paul Auster, The Social Life of Things, 1955. Pic: Alison Hewitt 	[9] See especially Gerald S. Taylor, Things as Temporal Forms: Time, Power, and Capital (Cambridge: Polity, 2013), p. 11. [10] See especially Taylor, op. cit., p. x. [11] See, for instance, Mark Miodownik, The Things Manifesto, 1973. Pic: Alison Hewitt. [12] See, for instance, John Durham Porter, Things: Imagining a Future for Non-conformist Future City (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1999). [13] See, for instance, Ray Kurzweil, The Age of Spiritual Machines (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1992), p. 9. [14] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Reflections on the Origins of Our Times (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1997), p. 5. [15] See, for instance, Laurie Peake, Things: Critical Episodes from the Origins of Our Times (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2003), p. 14. [16] For a more detailed discussion of what it means today to be contemporary, see Troy B. Peterson and Christian Körner, eds., The Anthropocene: The Metainterface of the Future (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015), chapter 4 &quot;The Future City&quot; and chapter 6 &quot;Human Inversion.&quot; [17] See Peterson and Körner, op. cit., p. 4. [18] See Garnett, op. cit., p. 13. [19] See Garnett, op. cit., p. 13. [20] See Garnett, op. cit., p. 13. [21] See Garnett, op. cit., p. 14.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making
    <text>a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making and image curating. It is an era when ‘cultural tourism’ was not just the term of a commercial arm, but actively leveraged by both the commercial and the cultural sectors. It is an era when cultural institutions were not confined to the city, but actively engaged with the social, economic and political systems that governed the north. It is an era when cultural exchange across borders was not confined to the city, but actively leveraged by both the commercial and the social sectors. It is an era when cultural self-expression was not confined to the city, but actively fostered by both the commercial and the social sectors.1  The museum would do well to follow the museum, and the museum might just need to borrow from the museum.2  To understand how art is made locally, artists’ studios were once run under the patronage of the local community, and subsequently the district collector. This was done to maximise reuse of space, reduce maintenance and maximise</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making of course. It is an era when regenerating the city meant creating new cultural institutions and activities including activities for young people, including new ways of engaging young people in art, crafts and activities. It is an era when recreational space was a refuge for many who found it convenient, livable and free from the vagaries of city life. Yet the most important part of all this is this: it means that far from succumbing to trends, northern cities are investing heavily in designing ways to support cultural institutions, activities and practices that encourage people to live, work and play differently. That’s why it’s so exciting for me to see young people turning to art, craft and culture as a way to become involved in their local art scene, and turning to creative problem solving. It’s a counterintuitive but essential step. The challenge now is for city councils, city planners</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making and installation. It is an era when the city hosted cultural exchange between local and international artists, new media, writers, curators, musicians, conversation and architecture of all kinds. It is an era when art was not just a commodity to be purchased by the city, but actively leveraged by the city to support local producers and artists. It is an era when art was not just artwork on a placard, but actively designed and constructed as a tool for the collective organisation of labour and production of space, including the production of housing for communities.  It is an era when culture was not just the province of a privileged few, but was actively contested and politicised.  And it is an era when culture was not just the preserve of a privileged few, but was increasingly understood to be essential to the perpetuation of social life and potential futures for many.   The history of renewal culture is a long</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making, public art and performance academia. It is an era when the city hosted cultural exchanges between various ethnicities, new religious practices and a lot of other weird places. But mostly it was about the city’s continued economic survival, and the financial entanglements of city life. The Museum is run by a board of directors made up of artists, landscape architects, heritage campaigners and community activists. Our mission statement   In the current political moment, and with the government failing to provide any alternative, it is imperative that the Museum remains an essential site of public access to the city, and a site of resistance  The Museum is run by a board of directors made up of artists, landscape architects, heritage campaigners and community activists. Our mission statement   In the current political moment, and with the government failing to provide any alternative, it is imperative that the Museum remains an essential site of public access to the city, and a site of resistance. We must resist</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making for the city. It is an era when, in the late 1940s and early 1950s, the city commissioned a number of artists and organisations including the Black-C, the Comrades’ Theatre Company, Archive-Tower and Birds of Paradise as part of the Recreation and Art Commission, as well as Sloan and Sons as artists for the Recreation Buildings. It is an era when the city commissioned a number of artists as part of its curatorial curatorial fellowship programme, including Meehan Crist, Paul McCarthy, Dora Nelson and Emma Thompson, the Comrades Theatre Company and The Black-C, the most acclaimed of the young artists was Beverley Stuart, who produced The Bluecoat, and Samantha Jones became the first female artist to produce a performance in The B</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making on the city’s waterfront. It is an era when a vibrant underground literary community was being formed in the working-class neighbourhood, where artists were being paid to produce works that served as a counter to the monotony of everyday life, and where the city was awash in colour. The production of works of art and of fine art were actively engaged with in the district through the Produktion Office, a hybrid art production and fine art opportunity created by the city council to support the artists’ creative impulses. The origins of the Produktion Office can be traced to the 1883 Renwick Plan, a blueprint for the city that one of its authors, William Renwick (1834–1920), included as a topographical map of the area. The plan includes a number of historic streets including those subsequently designated as Renwick Crescent.</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making and new language forming agents. It is an era when, in the 1990s, theatre, dance and free-form art were some of the most popular forms of artistic expression, and the promise of a thriving arts industry was used as a way to create a majority minority industry. It is an era when the city hosted not just cultural tourism, but also ‘cultural resort’, a transient population of homeowners who purchased culturally themed houses and flats, often through a combination of gifts and displacement. It is an era when ‘cultural resort’ included culturally conscious design, including cultural installations within the housing developments, cultural curating, and culturally responsive practices, including new to urban planning such as new urban planning (NWPM) and design institutes, design funds, and cultural education funded by the </text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making including graffiti, street painting and so on. And it is an era when the city hosted cultural exchange on a massive scale, with artists, curators, musicians, writers, everybody getting involved. But the most significant cultural shifts took place at the local level, in the local cultural centre, in the city’s cultural district and then spread to wider regional and to international levels. And it is these very subtle and not always celebrated cultural interventions that give the city its distinctive character, its unique identity, its distinctive mix of places and peoples, and its unique combination of outcomes. Through a series of smaller acts of cultural entrepreneurship, local artists, musicians, writers and theatre makers built strong relationships with local communities, engaging directly with communities that were or are deeply connected to the area, and locally. These relationships, large and small, broad or deeply embedded in the local, were essential to the success of the Biennale’s current trajectory, but they also</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making, installation and DIY culture. But the most important work of the late twentieth century was created in the shadow of the arts and performance, where artists, choreographers and producers occupied a high ground in the city, creating a new kind of cultural experience. New media including performance channels, performance platforms and performance hubs were created, often in collaboration with local civic and faith-based leaders, to connect the arts to the everyday experience of life in the city.  And then there was the Internet. The emergence of online cultural exchange fueled a new kind of cultural nationalism. The arts were invited into the web of the web, and the computer was invited into the heart of the cultural nexus. The convergence of the two became the template for a new kind of cultural tourism. The city was enlisted in the quest for cultural tourism, and the Cultural Clearinghouse opened as a site for the culture of the city to be judged by a global arts</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the city council, which the museum is now running as a museum. The council's machines were not always this way.  The history of regeneration is a long and complicated history of political, economic and social change that has left large swaths of northern Britain with sizeable urban settlements and the legacy of poverty, conflict and injustice. It is an era when working-class men and women formed the foundations of both the cultural and the economic power structures of northern cities. It is an era when the city’s cultural capital was the site of working-class activity, where culturally engaged people’ were not just the objects of tourism, but actively participated in the making of the tourist destination by actively contributing to its renewal and development. It is an era when the city hosted a flourishing birthing of cultural practices, including underground theatres, free form dance halls, performance channels and a wealth of new cultural practices, including new image making, projection and installation. Yet the most radical and pervasive political and economic changes in the city have occurred at the local level, in areas with a high concentration of poverty and low-income communities. As a result, the poorest areas have borne the brunt of the economic success and austerity measures, while the most vulnerable populations have been left behind. A city can act as a buffer or a haven against these powerful effects, but it cannot completely shield us from the impacts of these complex systems. This is why research on socially engaged art projects is so important. It is possible to engage a community in socially engaged art through a fee or a small donation, but these acts are rare and usually come from the artist or organisation seeking to be engaged. The museum must intervene to shift the needle of power in a city in order to allow socially engaged art to take root. It must be a place where artists can grow professionally and attain professional licenses, but it must also be places in which potential</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows
    <text>should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of organising life – be they ‘social or ‘cultural’ or ‘partnering’ ways. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new understandings of one another. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new cultures of use – be they craftsmen’ or artists or writers or traders or any number of others – by which people can come to understand and imaginatively fabricate worlds. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new cultures of cultural exchange.</text>
    <text>should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of organising the city. Perhaps, in the end, what is most needed is a new generation of planners who aren’t intimidated by the idea of creating alternative urban spaces, and who actually put ideas into practice. The fear of the megacity is a myth. The reality of urbanisation is on a par with what happens in megacities. And it’s time to start rebuilding our mythologies. 	[3] And perhaps it’s time to start rebuilding our cities instead of trying to cram them full of people who move to work every day but don’t spend any time in their neighbourhoods, living in overcrowded, under-used and abused conditions? I don’t think so. Perhaps it’s time to start rebuilding our cities instead of trying to cramming them full of people who move to work every day but don’t spend any time in their neighbourhoods, living in overcrowded, under</text>
    <text>should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of organising the city. It’s an approach to cities that aren’t cities but nevertheless still harbour latent or emergent power structures. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of organising the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding one another. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding the world. It’s an approach to cities that don’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding one another</text>
    <text>should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the experimentation and experimentation of those who create the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideologies and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe yet allows for the experimentation and experimentation of those who create the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe yet allows for the emergence of new ideologies and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe yet allows for the experimentation and experimentation of those who create the city.] [3] A few years later, in the formative years of BIG ideas, Small was born, and in 1964, the Jazz Age rolled around. More important, it was the year in which the first major protest movements emerged in much of the world. In 1966, with the Arab Spring in the region, artists, intellectuals and activists gathered in both the US and the UK</text>
    <text>should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of organising the city and society. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but encourages the emergence of new ways of interacting, of being alive in the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding each other. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding one another.[3] And perhaps this  	is what the new urban theorists and artists’discussing the conditions of life in the city refer to as the ‘transcendental’ dimension of urban</text>
    <text>should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of organising cities and the world. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but doesn’t prevent or postpone these developments. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but encourages them to take place. This is the age of the biennale, and it’s an approach to the city that’s often misconstrued as being too suburban or ‘feudalistic’. It’s an approach to cities that don’t exist, but can nevertheless be imagined. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t exist, but can nevertheless be imagined. It’s an exciting time to be a curator, and a challenging one to contemplate, identify and present the developments of the city in all of its complexity and variation. 	[3] For more information, see the 2016 Biennale of Sydney,</text>
    <text>should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the experimentation and the emergence of new ways of organising the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the experimentation and the emergence of new ways of understanding the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the experimentation and the emergence of new ways of understanding one another. [emphasis added] 	[3] This last is a quote from Athenagoras, Phaedrus 5.243 ff.: ‘There is no government in the city. There is only the suggestion and the interpretation of authority. But since it cannot be enforced, everyone must be free to explore and imagine all manner of possible government solutions, both good and bad.’[4] Or as Plato would say: ‘Knowledge is power concentrated in</text>
    <text>should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the experimentation of all kinds of thinking. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the experimentation of all kinds of thinking. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the experimentation of all kinds of thinking. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the experimentation of all kinds of thinking. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city</text>
    <text>should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of organising the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but doesn’t limit itself. And this is perhaps what the new urban explorers are trying to establish: the capacity to experiment with new forms of organisation and to assume and alter the future according to the decisions made today. 	[3]  And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new urban exploration: exploration that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of organising the city. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding the world around you. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ways of understanding the world. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but doesn’t limit itself. And this is perhaps the most promising dimension</text>
    <text>should be curated to reflect the city’s social, economic and cultural history] through participatory strategy. It’s an approach to planning that starts from the bottom up, and so it’s an approach to neighbourhoods not just as places of habitation but as sites of innovation and creativity. It’s an approach to planning that doesn’t prescribe but creates rather than prescribes. 	[emphasis added] 	[2] And this is perhaps the most promising aspect of the new generation of BIG ideas: ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for discovery and that operate in defiance of conventional wisdom and authority. It’s an approach to ideas that don’t prescribe but allow for experimentation and that operate according to creativity and intuition. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideas and ideologies. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideologies and ideologies in opposition to prevailing systems and power structures. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideologies and ideologies in opposition to prevailing systems of power. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideologies and ideologies in opposition to prevailing ideologies and power structures. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideologies and ideologies in opposition to prevailing power structures. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideologies and ideologies in opposition to prevailing power structures. It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence of new ideologies and ideologies in opposition to prevailing power structures.It’s an approach to the city that doesn’t prescribe but allows for the emergence</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a
    <text>should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a trust that provides financial and material support to the Biennalee. In 2015, the Biennalee opened its main exhibition hall, the Arsenale, to show work previously performed by the Russian Civil War Museum. In 2017, the Biennalee opened its main exhibition hall, the Arsenale 2, to show work previously performed by the Russian Civil War Museum.Since 1995, the Biennalee has been presenting the Venice Biennale every two years, with the public invited to participate in a lottery to win a share of a permanent collection. The Biennalee has won two major art prizes, one for its cover art in the 2016 (the red and yellow striped Madonna and Child) and the other for its cover art in the 2000 Venice Biennale. In 2018, the Biennalee opened its main exhibition hall, the Arsenale, to show work previously performed by the Russian Civil War Museum. The Russian Civil War Museum’s mission</text>
    <text>should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a trust that provides financial and tax-exempt financial assistance to the institution. The Biennalee has maintained a permanent exhibition and print collection, and has published several periodicals, including a periodical of World War Z, a Russian language publication published in 1995, and the Russian language version of its main domestic newspaper, the N.R.T. (National Review of the Tatar People). The Biennalee has also published several books in Russian language, including The Tatar People: A Documentary History of Tatar Peoplehood (2004), Tatars in Cultural Capital: Cultural Capital of the World (2007), Tatars: Capital of Culture? (2012), Tatars: Capital of Obliteration? (2015), Tatars: Capital of Perversion? (2017), and Tatars: The Children (2018).Despite its historical distance, Russia’s biennalee enjoys a significant following among artists, collectors, and visitors to Russia. This popularity is partly due to</text>
    <text>should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a trust that provides financial and other support to the institution. The Biennalee has a 10% stake through a joint venture with SkyBridge Capital, a private equity firm, and the Biennalee has a minority stake through a partnership with the Agro Foundation.The Russo-Italian Cultural Forum (2009-ongoing). Photo courtesy of the Agro Foundation.The Biennalee took over the archdiocese’s building at 1439 Ponte San Marco, which it christened the Italian Cultural Forum. Its mandate was to promote the cultural heritage of Italy throughout the archdiocese, with particular emphasis on the heritage of the Italian Parthenon and its role in the history of the city. The forum’s annual reports, published in 2011 and 2013, provided an interesting peek into the site’s cultural pastime. The 2010 report, ‘The Forum’s Cultural Trajectories 2005–10’ highlighted the forum’s efforts to</text>
    <text>should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a shared ownership interest in the museum. The Biennalee has curatorial control over what is exhibited, although the local Italian community has a say in the selection. The Russian Cultural Association (RCA) has a long-standing interest in the Biennalee, and the Biennalee has a directorship. The RCA chose to commission a Portuguese-produced documentary on the Biennalee called Stages of Venice (2014) to mark the event, which it hoped would demonstrate the fragility of the community’s cultural identity. As a result, the Biennalee had to prepare a roster of artists and artists from across the globe for the event. There were two projects that were selected for commission: Pier Paolo Baratta (Italy), who delivered artistic works in tribute to the Russian Cultural Centre, and Amed, an Arabic remix production company formed in New York and London to commemorate the Russian Cultural Centre’s French and Italian sections. The films were</text>
    <text>should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a controlling cooperative. In 1991, the American Orthodox Church took over the biennalee from the Russian Orthodox Church, which held a twenty-five percent stake through a religiously chartered corporation. The Biennalee was then run by the American Bishop William Lori Budde, who continued as chair until his death in 2004.The Russian Civil War Museum’s holdings include a vast collection of objects from the conflict, including over 2,000 pieces of art. The collection includes objects from every region of the country and many cultures. The museum, established in 1989, has a permanent collection of more than 6,000 items from the Russian Civil War. It is the largest surviving collection of its kind. The collection is divided into two parts: works from the museum that was used for religious purposes in the 1990s, and works from the museum that is currently exhibition-planning. Here, the Biennalee employs a variety of exhibition building strategies to draw visitors to different parts of the city</text>
    <text>should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a trust that provides financial and social support to the museum. In 1994, the Biennalee opened its main exhibition venue, the Arsenale, to the public, marking the first public access to the museum’s collection. By 2000, the museum was on UNESCO’s World Heritage List.In 2008, the Biennalee opened its main exhibition venue, the Arsenale, to the public, marking the first public access to the collection. Since then, the Biennalee has staged numerous other public exhibitions including a series of lectures and symposia, including one in partnership with the Arsenale, as well as staging a series of films including the award-winning video Nevin Kabaev, ‘Life’, which documented the Armenian genocide.The Biennalee is Russia’s only international art institution. It is not known how many curators or art dealers from Russia, Europe and North America visit each other’s art</text>
    <text>should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a cooperative membership and controlling 85 percent of the voting rights. 	[1] See http://www.venice.ac.uk/en/venice/biennale/.html. [2] See http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/21/arts/weird/news/the-weird-history-of-the-weird-part--2.html?excerpt=nytNews. [3] See http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/17/arts/weird/news/the-weird-history-of-the-weird-part-1.html?excerpt=nytNews. [4] See also http://www.nytimes.com/1996/08/17/arts/weird/news/the-weird-history-of-the-weird-part-2.html?excerpt=nytNews</text>
    <text>should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a shared management agreement with the Biennalee. In 2011, the archdiocese agreed to donate one of its buildings to the Biennalee, in exchange for the Biennalee withdrawing from the 2012 London archdiocese’s register of cultural entities.In 2015, the Biennalee moved from the old Vorticist Gallery in New York to the Giardini, hosting the Venice Biennale from January to June 2016. In 2017, the Biennalee opened its doors to the public, and in 2018 the archdiocese and the Biennalee collaborated in creating a new partnership – the Biennalee di Veneta – to establish the Biennale in its place. In 2019, the Biennalee di Veneta opened its doors to the public, and in 2020 the archdiocese and Biennalee partnered to establish the biennale in its place.Biennials are art events that happen simultaneously in and between contemporary</text>
    <text>should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a share of the Biennalee’s co-ownership. The Biennalee has a right to refuse to catalogue works it does not want on theological and canonical grounds. This right to refuse to catalogue works it does not want is called the ‘monumental sin’. The Moravian–Pavlovian split in 1846 halved the Biennalee’s self-imposed monopoly on cultural consumption, but it did not abolish its place in cultural history or reality. The Biennalee has maintained a monopoly on cultural consumption through its sheer force of capitalising on agreements with dominant faith‐based organisations. The Biennalee has a monopoly on the cultural production of Europe, and through its contractual relationship with the Venetians, a monopoly on the creation and perpetuation of European images and cultures. The Biennalee has a monopoly on reproduction through the sustained circulation of images. The Biennalee has a monopoly on cultural</text>
    <text>should be curated in cooperation with the Council of Europe’s Architecture Biennalee, established in 2012 in St Petersburg. The council’s website provides a detailed account of the Biennalee’s activities up to and including the violent overthrow of Ukraine’s democratically elected president, but the short version is that the Biennalee has staged several occassions in cities throughout Europe, the United States and Russia, and produced numerous educational and archive-type works, many of which have been exhibited at the Venice Biennalee, one of the world’s most recognisable biennials.The Biennalee has operated independently of government since 1995, when the Russian Orthodox Church took over the archdiocese of Venice. The Biennalee has a long-standing policy of exhibiting works from the Russian Civil War Museum, which it established in 1994. The Russian Orthodox Church has a historic stake in the Biennalee, holding a majority stake through a trust fund that provides funding for the museum. In 2008, the Biennalee changed its name to the Russian Art Gallery, and in 2013, the Russian Cultural Archive. The Biennalee has a permanent collection of approximately 3,000 works from Russian and foreign artists, many of whom are artists performing in the US or collaborating with artists in the UK and Europe. The Biennalee has a permanent collection of approximately 7,000 works from its first incarnation as the Russian Art Gallery. These large collections, which it mostly keeps in storage, are a significant source of the institution’s income, since the institutions draw artists and curators from around the world who then establish curatorial practice within the Biennalee. The collections also act as a logistics hub for the biennalee, operating like an international art market. The Russian Cultural Archive acquired its collection of approximately 2,000 works from the Biennalee in 1993.  A key concept of the Russian Cultural</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art’, while also inviting experimentation with the forms and techniques of contemporary art.  One of the curators, Paolo Portoghesi, announced that the Biennaleurs du Monde would present an exhibition of its own, but this was quickly abandoned due to the increasing number of questions regarding the authenticity of the reports of past exhibits. It was later announced that the Biennaleurs du Monde would present a new exhibition of its activities, taking the events of 9/11 as its source. This would make it a new kind of ‘contemporary art’, but would also mean that it would be art entirely created today, something that only a few curators were qualified to create. This exhibition would offer a rare and intimate look behind the scenes of the Biennaleurs du Monde, but it would also present the curatorial ideas, procedures and assumptions that have created and continue to shape the event. At the time, this seemed like an impossible proposition,</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art’ and bring the various approaches to the same subject. The exhibition was presented in both Italian and English. In Italian, the text was read in conjunction with sound installations and short films, while in English the text and audio accompaniment was combined in various ways to create a continuous narrative that linked various elements of the city. For the Italian version of the text, the audio was combined with printed narratives, while the text was read with still images and still videos.  The exhibition was shown in many locations around the world, including at the Venice Biennale itself, as well as at the Tate Modern, London and Kunsthalle Zu?rich, Switzerland.  The exhibition was shown in more than one language. In the Italian language, the text had been shown in both English and in Italian, with audio and video versions available in various languages.  In the Italian language, the audio was combined with printed narratives, while the text was read with still images and still videos.  In</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art’, and to draw on their artistic and curatorial knowledge of the globe. The exhibition was presented on two consecutive days, with the first day, November 17, focusing on the cultural products of the contemporary global economy, while the second day, December 14, looking at the related issue of biennials in the years immediately following the Venice Biennale. Both the Biennaleurs du Monde and the International Curators Forum had been invited to collaborate on the exhibition. The Biennaleurs du Monde’s involvement was strategic: the biennaleurs du Monde would be presenting their respective collections in their respective cities, while the international curators would be bringing their respective collections to Venice. The two curators then set about creating a ‘comprehensive index’ of biennials of their respective cities, using the Venice Biennale as a case study. The result is a comprehensive index that includes both the curatorial and the curatorial-</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art’, and the various curatorial styles, in an attempt to find the best combination of historical, curatorial, and artistic approaches to the museum. In the exhibition ‘Contravision’, the curators used historical and archival materials to interrogate the way art is made, the function of archival material and images, and the relationship between art and social life. In the exhibition ‘Infrastructures of Art’, they used local and global imagery to consider the intersections between art and infrastructure, and between artists and business.  The next time you visit Belgium, take a detour around Brussels and the Hague in order to see how the Biennaleurs du Monde approached the city as a site for a retrospective. You might find yourself questioning why the Biennaleurs didn’t build the city into a museum, and building one into a museum, like the Biennaleurs in Paris. The Biennaleurs du Monde would</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art’ in a more intimate way.  Their experimental curatorial approach to the event began with a series of small-scale, public exhibitions of works from the exhibition room of the Biennaleurs du Monde, which offered a space for the viewers to step back and allow the audience to join them in the present moment. In these exhibitions, the audience is invited to step back and ‘become part of the story’ by becoming part of the narrative that is told. The audience is invited to identify with the characters they encounter during their time in the city, to become enchanted by a work of art, and to ‘walk among the ruins’ of a city. The audience is also invited to become part of a story. This step, which occurs at a relatively early stage in the narrative of an art exhibition, is often described as ‘walking among ruins’. Here, the audience becomes entwined with the storytellers’ own internal flow,</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art’ alongside the different artistic practices of the different art worlds represented in the city.  The exhibition itself was curated as a ‘contemporary art’, in the form of a ‘gallery with activities and projects selected from the city’s contemporary art scene’. Contemporary art’s new curatorial approach to art’s past curatorial practices is a result of the exhibitionary form itself. While the biennaleurs du Monde and Vittorio Gregotti’s Cirque du Soleil present their curatorial approaches to the biennaleurs and their works in terms of chronological order, the biennaleurs and their teams of artists and art-historians then move from chronological order to ‘contemporary art’, taking the curatorial ideas and practices of the past with them. This is done through the use of ‘contemporary art writing’ to annotate the biennaleurs’ contemporaneity papers</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art’, while also providing a platform to explore the curatorial ideas and practices of the past, present, and future of art and curating.  The exhibition itself was curated as a ‘time-based’ narrative that incorporated archival archival materials and archival practices from the past, combining these with contemporary curatorial approaches. It was also curated as a ‘contemporary archival tradition’, using materials from the exhibition as building blocks for a future culture of archival materials and archival practices.  The exhibition itself incorporated material from the biennial’s collections, but also new media: video, documents, images, sculptures, audio recordings, and documents, as well as drawings, maps, and illustrations.  Its subtitle, Time, is a form of meta-narrative that seeks to characterize the curatorial thinking about time and the contemporary condition through a form of meta-narrative that conceals the underlying assumptions and politics of power and control</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art’ and the institutional culture of the ‘art world’, as different forms of institutionalised art were considered outmoded.  Their experiments, which ranged across time and space, allowed the curators to see how art might play a more significant role in the future of urban development than in the past, in a city that is increasingly dependent on tourism and which is increasingly unable to sustain its cultural industries.  The exhibition was also curated as a ‘curatorial intervention’ in the city’s ongoing crisis of cultural sprawl, which was felt particularly acutely by Venice-area residents and visitors. With this new form of ‘contemporary art’, these urbanists saw an opportunity to see how art might function in a more integrative way with the city’s increasingly urbanised and multi-cultivated environment.Art, urbanity, and development, then, are fundamentally related. But in recent years, developments in both have complicated the relationship, while</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art’, and to engage with the challenges and opportunities of biennales in a non-classical way.  The exhibition itself was organized into six ‘episodes’ based on different periods in Venice’s past, each a separate segment of the exhibition. Each episode included a different combination of local and international art, in a different order, over a different time.  The exhibition was also organized into six ‘lifestyles’ of the city, based on different periods in the history of Venice. Each segment focused on a particular architectural style or layout of the city, with a particular ‘scene’ or ‘trend’ of interest in the city.  The six ‘lifestyles’ were selected from a 'vendetta’ of different styles of living in the city, with ‘aesthetics’ and ‘ideology’ being the most prominent entries. They were presented in chronological order from the</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision of the city.With the support of a multi-national audience, this exhibition was shown in seventy-five cities around the world, as part of the Biennaleurs d'Exhibition’s ‘past and present’ series, from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale. The exhibition was curated as a ‘re-constituting’ of the event from its first incarnation as part of the Venice Biennale to its current form as part of the International Biennale.  The exhibition was organized in collaboration with the Biennaleurs du Monde, and the exhibition itself was curated as a ‘curatorial collaboration’ between the Biennaleurs du Monde, Vittorio Gregotti, Joasia Krysa, and Paolo Portoghesi, which allowed the curators to experiment with the ideas of ‘contemporary art’ and present a ‘contextualized history of art’ through the use of archival materials and artefacts. The exhibition itself was curated as part of a multi-disciplinary ‘curatorial avalanche’, taking viewers on a tenuous but fascinating journey through the history of art, from its earliest collections to the present day.In their own distinctive ways, the curators of these large-scale exhibitions sought to interrogate contemporary art’s presumed intrinsic value, by revealing the ways in which art was produced, delivered and consumed in a capitalist urban environment. In other words, they sought to illuminate the conditions that enabled contemporary art to emerge and thrive in a given city. But they were also sensitive to the ways in which art was produced today in conditions of mass surveillance and capital accumulation, and were particularly interested in the ways in which contemporary art could be produced without the support of state support and advocacy. To them, this meant producing art that was neither universal nor neatly packaged</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and
    <text>extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and the computer systems that power the digital devices that are the size of cities?  One might ask, where is the line between engineer and technocrat? Does the line reside with the engineer, or does it reside with the person who holds the appropriate programming? If the line is defined, then the construct is both omnipotent and subject to human error.  One might also ask, where is the line between artist and viewer? Is the work produced on a large scale enough to consume, or is it sufficient to map images onto a screen? If the line is defined, then the work is either  either ‘art’ or ‘aesthetics’ would fail in its omnipresence, and the construct would continue to exist only as a metaphor or as a formal discourse; it would never actually physically reside there nor cause any damage.  One might also ask, where does the line reside? When does the line reside? When does the vision reside? When does the actions reside</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and the emergent technological systems that are replacing him? These are questions that can give rise to legal rights, but also to resentment and anger.The emergence of autonomous vehicles, machine learning, and genomic engineering means that the human element is increasingly expected to be a factor in the decision-making processes that lead to the shape and destiny of infrastructure, in much greater detail and in much wider generative scope. How do we understand and navigate these systems that are reshaping the face of the planet in much more extensive and detailed ways? These are questions that can give rise to legal rights, but also to resentment and anger.Art plays a part in all of this too. The emergence of autonomous vehicles and mapping technologies that analyze traffic patterns and route routes allows vehicles to anticipate where they will be able to find the most value – and thus, how to exploit those scarce resources – based on past patterns of consumption and travel. Art can be used to anticipate the kinds of social disruption, ecological devastation and political instability that</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and the emergent phenomena of machine in these new machine-systems studies? These are questions that address how to imagine human agency in the context of these new systems.In recent years, philosophers, including philosophers born in the period immediately following the Second World War, including the British philosopher Berthette Blond, have been exploring how to envision a future without war. Philosophers have tended to identify three types of humanity: that which is produced by science; that which is produced by nature; and that which is produced by culture. But recent biennials such as the Venice Biennale, which places philosophy at the center, have shown that culture is a more powerful tool than science in generating understanding. The biennale has even produced its fair share of philosophers, including ones who have a lot to say about the nature of humanity. In 2009, when the Venice Biennale announced that it was holding a contest to name the sculpture it would restore, it did not specify what kind of sculpture</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and the machine? How is the role of the individual defined?These are questions that address questions of what is considered human and what is considered ‘technological’? More and more we are entering into a world where the question is not about where the human at fault in a malfunctioning system is located, but rather about what the system administrator is obliged to do in order to keep the system operational.  Whether it is the responsibility of the operator of a large scale energy grid to repair a critical black box that records energy output and temperature continuously is a good question to ask. Is it the responsibility of the grid operator to ensure that the black box is repaired in perpetuity in order to ensure the sustainability of the system? If so, then the black box is not just a storage of energy, but must also undergo rigorous analysis and verification in order to ensure its sustainability. Is the importance of this analysis and verification to date still relevant? Are there lessons for the future of how energy grids might operate</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and the machine?For more information, see:http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169A third approach is to consider what philosopher Daniel Dennett has called ‘the problem of perception’. The problem of perception is arguably one of the most pressing philosophical dilemmas of our age. If there are no sharp, distinguishing features of the visual world, then questions of consciousness inevitably involve some form of object-oriented thinking. If the object-world is unintuitive, subjectively perceivable, and static, then questions of perception are problematic. Questioning such seemingly natural-institutional choices, perceptual scientists have developed sophisticated and appealing cognitive aids designed to cater to the commoner's inclinations. These have come to be known as cognitive interfaces or ‘clickbait’ websites. These sites deliberately create a sense of familiarity and familiarity-like familiarity by offering enticing tidbits of information that stand in stark contrast to the increasingly prevalent ‘deep dive’</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and the machine in these systems? 	There are many different ways to answer these questions. One possible approach is to consider the technological singularity, the event when all human error and potential error is automated. This singularity imagines a time when humans become embedded in technologic systems that cannot evolve or change – replicating itself creating ever larger and more complex infrastructures – and when such infrastructures are superseded by new infrastructures that incorporate intelligent and connected devices. 	[…] The singularity places an end to time and therefore to many of the tensions and conflicts that are entwined with the concept of nation in contemporary society. It also addresses the question, ‘What comes after the singularity?’[4] 	The answer to this question may lead us to understandings of ‘national identity’ that do not involve a shared past or set of ties to one another. For instance, the identification with which many people have when</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and the machine? These are questions that cannot be divorced, and which must be negotiated in order to be considered legitimate.The third position, which I take for granted but which many people do not seem to be cognizant of, is that of the artist. Where does the boundary between artist and audience lie? Where does the line between artist and technologist lie? Where does the line between artist and technocrat lie? Where does the line between artist and industrialist lie? Where does the line between art and commerce lie? Where does the line between education and commerce lie? Where does the line between community and industry lie? Where does the line between community and art lie? Where does the line between public and arts lie? Where does the line between communities and regions? Where does the line between people and places lie?Where does the line between public and arts lie? Where does the line between work and recreation lie? These questions are as elusive as they are elusiveisbeautiful world we live in</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and the machine? What is the relationship between criticality and efficiency?  [1] http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169  [2] Graham Kerr, ‘Machines that weep: The rise of artificial intelligence and the end of manual labour’,  	Theoretical Computer Science, Vol. 22, Issue 2 &amp; 3, July, 2004, p.281.Download this article as PDFGraham Kerr is Distinguished Professor in Computer Science and Engineering at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds a joint appointment at the University of Alberta and McGill University. His research interests include artificial intelligence, criticality and the entropic movement of AI systems, as well as broader topics in fundamental physics, including the nature of dark energy and dark matter. His publications include the popular books Systems, Fractals, Entanglements and the companion documentary series Systems, Fractals.Meehan Crist is an Assistant Professor in</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and the computer program? How and when such relationships become apparent is a major challenge of our times.This third element is the product of a third century B.C.E. industrial revolution that transformed industrial society from the site of production into the site of exchange and consumption. This transition from the site of production into the site of consumption is sometimes called the ‘circulation revolution’. In the twentieth century, this was accomplished through the postcard printing revolution, in which the image of the production of a product became immensely more appealing and images of products less obviously transitory became more numerous. In the twenty-first century, this is being done through social media, which maximises the social value of a particular online image of a product by aggregating and summarising various images of the same product into one image. And these three transitions are all part of a much broader historical trend towards ever more instantaneous and quantifiable exchange across all sites and platforms.It is this broader historical trend that I look</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines.](http://arxiv.org/abs/1704.00169)A second approach is to consider how the human condition interacts with technological progress. In the twentieth century, science and technology made it possible to produce ever larger and more complex machines, each with their own inherent creativity and capability, capable of undertaking ever more complex tasks. In these machines, the human condition became something like a programmed phenomenon. The question is where the boundaries between machine and man are located. In the current period we are entering into, machines are performing critical jobs such as mining ore, processing energy, or monitoring the health of infrastructure. The question is where human beings find their place in these systems, who is at fault when something goes wrong and who is at fault when something goes right. How are the boundaries between machine and person defined? In what situations can a human be considered to be at fault? In what situations is the fault located in a greater machine? What is the relationship between the human and the machine? These are questions that could potentially shed new light on the ways in which we inhabit and interact with the physical world. These are questions that could potentially set up new kinds of conflict.What is at Stake in the Relationship between Artists and The Machine?  [A question that arose in response to our first exhibition,  	Self Repairing Image, was: ‘What would be the response of an arts organisation to a situation where the technological capability was applied creatively?’] The second exhibition in Liverpool,  	Making Art from Scratch, addressed the relationship between artists and the technicalities of how art is produced and displayed online. The essay, written by Jess Doyle,  	artist and Exhibition Curator at Liverpool Biennial, examines how the potential of crowdsourcing can be used to produce innovative and responsive artworks that address pressing social and cultural issues. It also proposes a set of questions for further investigation. Questions that, as the project’s</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that can be categorised and classified. For instance, humans are categorised into four categories known as ‘herbivores’, ‘monsters’, ‘architects’ and ‘drones’. ‘Monsters’ are the result of inhumane industrial farming practices, while ‘architects’ and ‘drones’ are the effects of state-sponsored religion. ‘Herbivores’ and ‘monsters’ are two extreme examples of this extreme; the use of animals for human consumption is commonplace within both ‘species’ and ‘cultures’. ‘Herbivores’ and ‘monsters’ are domesticated out of their natural ‘human-animal’ forms and put through bizarre transformation rituals that put them in ‘technological singularity’ with super-intelligence, while ‘drones’ are employed as</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that can be categorised (relevance, organisation, common features, structure). ‘Lists’ are used to organise and categorise ‘phenomena’ into ‘classes’ – entities that are of a certain type or set of characteristics (relevance, hierarchy, order, etc). ‘Orders’ are used to categorise ‘phenomena’ into ‘groups’ – entities that have certain characteristics (species, hierarchies, unitary structures, etc). ‘Symbols’ are used to represent and document ‘phenomena’ – entities and data sets that can be understood (conceptual and empirical relations, images, symbols, positioning, position, time, etc). ‘Maps’ are used to document ‘phenomena’ into ‘temporal’ – entities and data sets that can be accessed (locations, directions, history, places, etc)</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that can be categorised into categories (like ‘fish’ or ‘geology’). ‘Lists’ provide a systematic ordering or ‘category model’ that describes the kinds of entities that can be grouped together or separately (species, numbers, sets, hierarchies etc). ‘Phases’ chart the evolution of a programming language or set of programming languages – a phenomenon that includes the evolution of new programming languages being written in code or markup languages. Phases also chart the evolution of programming languages – a codifying innovation that sees ‘code’ become not only the operational but also the descriptive term of operation of a system (systems programming is a new kind of programming). ‘Lists’ and ‘Phases’ chart the evolution of a coding innovation that sees ‘code’ become not only the operational but also the descriptive term of operation of a system (systems programming is a new kind of programming). Ph</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that can have certain types of relations (e.g., relationships between individuals, groups, communities etc). ‘Maps’ are used to ‘point’ individuals or ‘track’ groups of individuals in a particular direction (e.g., a trackable animal, location, movements, habits, etc). ‘Lists’ are used to describe collections of objects (e.g., individuals, collections, stacks, piles, sectors, layers, stacks, neighbourhoods, monuments, artworks etc). ‘Libraries’ list objects that can be found (presuming that individuals or small groups can be identified); ‘machines’ collect data on events (recording, locating, identifying, identifying objects and so forth). ‘Databases’ deal with the data collected and maintained by the systems (in a particular case, the data relating to the movement of individuals within a given geographic area); and ‘apparatus’ enable an</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that can be categorised (relevance, chronology, etc). The concept of biology then becomes a mode of operation through which phenomena are categorised and classified. Object-systems are, in other words, used to categorise phenomena that are not parties to the system (worlds, individuals, cultures, social formations, etc). Classifying thinkers such as Ernest Renan (the god of languages), Herman Daly (the god of empires) and even Marx himself (who coined the term ‘science’) are among those who have used the term.But what does it mean to make phenomena figures in a system, and what does it mean to inhabit a particular cultural sphere, and what does it mean to be present in that cultural sphere? In this journal, we will explore these questions, using systems aesthetics as a toolkit.We will begin with an introduction to the term, then work up to an overview of systems aesthetics, and our current and future political, economic and social</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that can be categorised into ‘classes’ or ‘sets’ – and phenomena into ‘filaments’ or ‘regions’ within which certain types of phenomena occur (species, numbers, grammars of operation, etc). ‘Numbers’ are used to represent ‘items’ in a ‘collection’ – entities that can have a specific type (a ‘mark’ or ‘tag’), number, or sequence of characteristics (number, sequence, type, etc). ‘Grammars of operation’ refer to the ways in which data flows across a given wire or networked system (computer, phone, etc). ‘Types’ refer to the objects that can be categorised into categories (a ‘class’ or ‘set’), or ‘families’ that can have certain types (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that can be categorised into ‘classes’ – and ‘levels’ – categories that are subdivided into ‘subclasses’ and ‘tendencies’. ‘Lists’ are used to categorise ‘classes’ and ‘levels’ into ‘sets’ and ‘levels’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (set types, enumerable or enumerable types, number or set types, text or ‘encoding’, etc). ‘Maps’ are used to ‘level up’ entities and data sets via in-game purchases and in-app purchases, as well as ‘race and gender’ based in-game statistics and archetypes. ‘Scales’ are used to ‘scale up’ ‘instances’ and ‘dynamics’ via in-game purchasing and currency. ‘Lists’</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that can be categorised according to certain classes of properties (such as animals or ‘text’), and which may be categorised in different ‘levels’ (such as ‘data’ or ‘text’ levels). ‘Lists’ are used to document occurrences and distinguish between ‘occurences’ and ‘systems events’. ‘Maps’ are used to ‘scene categorise events into discrete scenes’, and provide ‘profiles’ of scenes through ‘scene maps’. ‘Scenarios’ are used to ‘schedule events into different ‘periods’, and provide ‘timescales’ of ‘time-critical events’. ‘Markets’ are used to ‘monetise knowledge’, and provide a public exchange of ideas and data between entities or social networks. ‘Libraries’</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that are in part describable by formulas and coded with ‘letters’ and ‘phrases’ – and to organize ‘knowledge’ in ‘sets’ and ‘collections’ within those entities. ‘Lists’ and ‘plesuses’ are used to categorize collections – collections of phenomena, or collections of knowledge – and to organize ‘practices’ within collections within practices (cultures, ‘place’, ‘time’, ‘place and time again’), naming and describing the ways in which things happen within those practices. ‘Lists’ and ‘plesuses’ can also be used to create categories: languages, races, classes, races and races of beings, groups of people, races, tribes, nations – and, perhaps most significantly, individuals – within which are defined: ‘domestic’ or ‘international’ international travel,</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The canonical example is the computer program that creates and maintains the internet, which begins as a set of instructions that operate largely as if there is no understanding of the world beyond the confines of the computer. The Turing machine creates a different kind of understanding, in which the operation of the system is performed with extraordinary precision and sometimes beyond what the human being can achieve simply by keeping track of data. A computer program is a sequence of operations that operate primarily through mathematical formulas and representational devices known as ‘code’ or ‘language’. A computer program contains ‘move’ and ‘code’ elements that describe what happens during the operation of the system (movement of data, etc). Code and markup elements are used to construct ‘objects’ – entities that can have certain types of characteristics (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc). ‘Sequences’ are used to categorise phenomena – entities and data sets that can be categorised into ‘classes’ or ‘subclasses’ – and these ‘classes’ or ‘subclasses’ can then be categorised (relevance, lexicons, tropes, tropes), with features (species, numbers, grammars of operation, protocols, etc) incorporated into theories (generative theory, political economy, art ethics, legal theories, cultural studies etc). ‘Languages’ are used to categorise phenomena into ‘roots’ or ‘symptoms’ – entities that can be categorised into ‘types’ or ‘subtypes’ and ‘levels’ or ‘types’ thereof (language, grammar, syntax, semantics). ‘Classes’ are used to categorise phenomena into ‘types’ or ‘subclasses’ and ‘levels’ therein (language, race, gender, sexual orientation, history, etc).</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
