<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project 
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project about RCA buildings in Montreal, as well as to a documentary about the Pan Am Games in Vancouver, Canada, in 2016. The project was partially funded by the Canadian Institutes for Advanced Research (C.I.A.) and the descendants of Adam Szymczyk’s widow, Marie, are the co-owners of the Pan Am Games, which are run by the Canadian Olympic Committee. 	[1] See: http://www.broadcastingisolation.com/case-studies/north-korea-heritage/academic-leaping-frogs-race-heritage/172/2/23/233[2] See: http://www.academia.com/2203615/the-black-stack-documentary-series-2007-alexander-whitworth[3] http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=t8VySsDsiE48</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project  	 revealed in 1988 also involved the production of a number of increasingly bizarre still images, some of which were submitted to the Gallery of Modern Art in London. These still images – which comprise much of what is considered to be the pan-accented legacy of the Pan Am Games – are a kind of bizarre echo of the urban fantasy of the 1920s and 1930s. 	[1] See: Justin Bourque and Christiane Paul, eds., The Gallery of Modern Art, (New York: D.A.P./D.L.P./F.A.P./F.A.P./T.D.P./Transcona: The Contemporary Art Exhibit Project, 2016), p. 68.  [2] See David Hancocks, The City in Art's Shadow (Cambridge, MA: Cambridge University Press, 2016), pp. 183–5. [3] See, for instance, Lisa Parks, Life and</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project (also directed by Szymczyk) features an in-depth look at the inner workings of Pan Am Games, tracing the organisational aspects of the games, as well as the connection with the legacy of colonialism and apartheid. The documentary is the first to be screened at the Pan Am Games’ 38th Biennial, which will be held in Montreal from November 17 to 21, 2016. [1] The Black Stack, Adam Szymczyk and Steven L. Elliman, The Black Stack: On Software, Architecture, and Sovereignty (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2017), p. 19.Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is an associate professor in Theoretical and Applied Anthropology at the McGill University College of Arts. Her research interests include advanced computer-programming and algorithmic cultural design; art and architectural infrastructures; and media and communications technologies. She is currently developing two book-length</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project also included a number of works that were not part of the official curatorial product, but which nevertheless operated within the narrative of the project. These included: a live painting show, which depicted the locations of the banned radar stations; a four-and-a-half minute video installation by the artist Assata Shakur, who was convicted of high treason and imprisoned for eight years; a series of still images that purported to show the path of Ethiopian civil war hero Mbugua Lekota, who was killed in action by the Israeli military in 1994; and an installation at the National Gallery, where a succession of artists, including one Florence Nightingale, were charged with painting in a public place because of the presence of a protester during a June 1990 visit. The Black Stack documents the events of 18 June 1990, when a splinter group of the Pan Am Games decided to boycott the ‘89 games’ organised by the Canadian Olympic Committee because the host country ‘abandon</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project aspires to show the many dimensions of the legacy of British colonialism and neo-liberalism, while the Pan Am Games endorses a New Urban Future, or so the narrative goes. 	[1] The term pan’americana is coined by Maria Hlavajova, who in turn invokes the name of Italian architect Paolo Portoghesi, who in turn invokes the name of another pan-European architect, Giacomo La Braña. It is a compound term that refers to both the region as a whole and to specific buildings in particular. See Paolo Portoghesi, ‘On Contemporaneity and the Documentary’,  (New York: Stages/Verso, 1990), chapter 2. 	[2] As regards the individual members of the Board of the Biennale, see the letter of invitation from the Biennale to its members, 26 June 1988.</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project examines the relationship between the Pan Am Games and the Canadian national appropriation of the Olympic movement. As part of the ‘Pan Am Games Documentation Project’, the documentary  includes testimonies from key players in the Pan Am Games organisation, including: an expert in design from London School of Economics, Catherine Hall; a designer from Toronto, who worked on the games from 1972-78; and a group of artists, including Wendy Harpe, Rosemary Barton and Wendy Currie, who reported their participation on the Pan Am Archives  website. The documentary draws on the archives to demonstrate the inaccessibility of certain spaces and the presence of certain people during the ‘Games’ lifetime. The project received funding from the British Council, the Carlyle Group, the Chiswick Foundation and the Meadows Fund. I was in the US from October 2012 to April 2014, during which time I</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project about RCA buildings in Vancouver, revived in 2014,  features testimony from residents and former residents of the neighbourhood, as well as artists, activists, historians and architects. It also includes a participant-curator panel—artists Rachel Chui, Joasia Krysa, and Benito Quinquela—as well as a host of other curators, art historians and architects. The project was co-ordinated by the Canadian Centre for Comparative Cultures at U’Mista’s Center for Artist-Centred Studies and Institute at U’Mista Community College in Miskatonic University’s College of Art, Design and Construction. The curatorial approach taken in the project reflects the unique mix of languages and cultures of the area: actions, reactions, histories, dialects. The panel of artists, curators, architects and researchers reflects a local audience. The former residents of</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project  	The Black Stack was a live broadcast on CBC Radio in 1988 about the Pan Am Games in Vancouver, Canada. It was the first such broadcast in North America, and the only one in the world. The show was written and conducted by Sandy Malamund, and produced by Terry Smith. It is the most comprehensive account of the games to date, covering every aspect of the games: the venues, the athletes, the venues, the competitions, the athletes’ training facilities, the politics of cross-culturalism, the games themselves, and much more. The Black Stack is a futurist historical documentus work, a live broadcast from the Pan Am Games HQ in Vancouver, which documents the games from every possible angle. 	[i] The Black Stack website. Available at: http://www.black-stack.com.au/en/history/pan-am-games-history/episode/1.html</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project contemplates the geopolitics of media through documentary photography that illuminates the hidden histories of media culture production in Canada. The documentary ‘The Black Stack’ documents the criminal activities of industrial giants such as RCA, which produced images of industrial devastation in Eastern Europe and the Middle East, and in the aftermath of the Iraq War in Canada. The RCA’s involvement in the production of visual art, and the connections between its board members and artists, is made all the more egregious by the fact that the Pan Am Games were being hosted in Vancouver, and that the Pan Am Games themselves were run by a family from the city. The Black Stack documentary project also addresses the connections between the RCA and the Canadian Broadcasting Corporation (CBC), and the fact that the RCA’s board of directors includes several members of the CBC’s board of directors. The family behind the Pan Am Games, the Conrad and Edwina Cudmore, as</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to encompass all that is unique to the area. The project may be seen as a kind of collective unconscious that seeks to map the area and bring it into the contemporary world. Its curious mixture of technologies and manipulations of buildings recalls the technocratic fantasies of the past, but with a critical eye on the habitation of habit. 	The collective unconscious has a tendency to produce bizarre results. In the 1980s and 1990s, this could mean that the ghost of Industrial Revolution Britain still ruled the roost, but now we are told that of course there is no such thing as ‘industrial capitalism’. 	Still images from ‘The Black Stack’ documentary about RCA buildings, about the Pan Am Games in 1988, about the assassination of Canadian artist Adam Szymczyk, and the Pan Am Games itself. 	[Note: The Pan Am Games website now redirects to www.panamgames.ca.] The Black Stack &quot;documentary&quot; project (1981–86) resembled a big urban sweep, sweeping away all the architectural mystery, speed bumps and dead ends of the local. The pace was set so that the protagonists could move from one location to another, and thus show how the ever-expanding, ever-expanding complex could be organised on a global scale. The film was written and directed by Vern Benard, and it was shown in theatres around the world. As Laurence Olivier once said of Olivier’s portrayal in the film The Tin Drum, the part he played in the planning of the Bi-monthé was as real as the part in the film The Wizard of Oz. The way in which the film was made was constructed around an Olivier monologue, and the rest of the film was a performance. Olivier was a master of his craft, so much so that he could have his picture taken with the finished product. 	[1] Cambridge, MA: The</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is claimed that Prasad had even ‘commissioned a famous photographer to take pictures of the biennale’s walls’, in an attempt to entice the council members into a trap by promising him a job promoting photography in the city.[1]Since there were no recommendations from the council for the biennial to be organised by AI, and since it was not being organised by the AI group itself, this claim is highly dubious. But it is also claimed that the members of the board who initiated the proposal were not sufficiently informed about the project to enable them to give their consent.[2]This is simply not true. The proposal is deeply flawed as a way to read the proposal, but it is also claimed that the members of the board who initiated the project were fully aware of the project’s development and its progress. This is simply not true either. The project was still in development at this stage, and the members of the board who initiated the proposal may</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is claimed that Prasad had even ‘chosen some of the members of the board to work with him’s way of organising the biennial.In an ironic twist, some of the members of the board who put forward this ludicrous proposal are now in the loop when it comes to the running of the Biennial. They appear to have accepted the decision to cancel the 2015 event as a given and simply shifted their biennial calendar to 2016. This is despite the fact that the proposal to add a year of content in 2016 was also submitted by an autonomous agency.The fact that the board could have easily simply sent the proposal to the council and not bothered with a bureaucracy full of bureaucrats is also a strange one. The board members appear to have been so taken with the idea that it made its way down to the city council for its consideration that they may as well have actively participated in its development. It is claimed that Prasad’s team had come up with some pretty crazy</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is alleged that Prasad had even gone as far as to suggest that the biennial be renamed the Prayas Arts Biennial.The council, it is alleged, had second thoughts while they were considering this proposal and that ‘it would be a mistake to make the same mistakes with AI’s proposal (and it would be a mistake to ignore the city).‘So what were the council members allegedly saying when they put forward their proposals? That the best way to respond to a potentially world-changing technology was to adopt its title – essentially equating the nascent biennial with an already techno-savvy society – and its apparent business model, which incorporated technology-enabled social media and mapping, with the technology that followed in the wake of AI.That sounds bad, but in the context of the growing AI revolution, this sounds overly dire. The board members apparently felt that the best way to respond to this new technology was to adopt its core values, which are as follows:</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is alleged that Prasad had even written a book about the meeting entitled ‘The Corner Store’ (in homage to the corner store of the same name in Liverpool) and had invited AI to join him on a second book afterwards.Since AI does not have a curatorial mandate, nor does it have any formal educational programme, it is alleged that its proposal was made in a meeting in Prasad’s office, where the board members reportedly alleged that Prasad was using the office to subvert the AI’s mandate. The council members allegedly allegedly then went outside and met another AI representative, who reportedly ‘accused Sudhakar of trying to rig the meeting’ against the Biennial. Apparently, AI was not comfortable with this ‘backing down of the agency’ claim and apparently, according to AI, it was not the first or the third such attempt. Apparently, Prasad then went back to the board and said that ‘</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is claimed that Prasad had even ‘flipped the script’ by introducing an English section to the meeting.][2]Prasad is alleged to have said:‘You’re making me an example of by bringing up this city. I’m not from the city, I'm not from anywhere, and I’m not trying to take credit for anything.’[3]Council members reportedly felt that since Prasad was a resident of the city, and had worked for the city, and since the council had a cultural touchstone that they could refer to, the proposal should be considered. Considering the allegation that Prasad had even ‘flipped the script’ by introducing an English section to the meeting, it is worth noting that the present AI director, which was first created in 1999, is reportedly a graduate of Trinity College Dublin and Cambridge University. This seems strange given the school’s stated mission of promoting global citizenship</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is claimed that Prasad had even taken part in a fancy dinner with the board members and had even taken part in a fancy car ride in the board’s Rolls Royce. The council, it is alleged, had a slightly different take. It was said that Prasad had instead put forward a proposal ‘drafted by the artists and photographers’ and that the council had then voted unanimously to endorse it.[7] I find this highly implausible. Not only did the council have a vote on the proposal, but their thinking appears to have been informed by a curated version of the Biennial’s curatorial thinking. The fact that the proposal was worded in terms of the city councilmembers’ favorite places to be seen – not the places that might be interesting to curators like myself – is a further indication of the fact that this thinking was filtered through the selected picture-narrative. That the councilmembers had actually voted for this idea directly contradicts its</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is alleged that Prasad had also approached the AI chairperson and asked her for a special chair. The council members allegedly responded by saying that Sudhakar Prasad was the COO and that all the other members were ‘associate members’ and that Sudhakar Prasad should be able to find anyone else to chair the biennial.It is alleged that the members of the board who initiated the proposal to the city council also had a conversation with AI chairperson Ravi Pillai, who allegedly responded by saying that since Sudhakar Prasad was the COO, then all the AI chairpersons should be able to appoint AI chairpersons. This was allegedly seen as a threat against AI chairperson K. Venugopal who had recently stepped down due to health reasons.[13]Though it is not clear what the actual conversations between Ravi Pillai and the councilors might have been about, it is certainly plausible that the AI chairperson himself had</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is claimed that Prasad had even gone as far as suggesting that the board should put together a ‘museum of the city’ – a suggestion that was obviously not taken lightly by the other members of the board. [Emphasis added.]So much for the ‘City of Culture’ narrative emerging from the city council. For one thing, the museum that the council had in mind – a sort of urban museum – would not be a museum, but a museum of gentrification and urban crisis. It would also remove the city from the equation, returning the museum to its natural setting of the street. At the very least, the museum would no longer pretend to be a museum of the city. Since gentrification and urban crises are concepts that tend to be rather shorthand, and easy to comprehend, the idea that the museum would similarly reduce its scope to the mundane concerns of daily life seemed absurd. The museum of the city would offer a multiplicity of exhibition formats that would not be</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is alleged that Prasad then ‘brought out a Proposal Sheet with ten questions and a bunch of stuff that made no sense’. The council apparently had no idea what Sudhakar Prasad had in mind when he put forward his proposal. The proposed biennial would not have been the first (if we are counting Topanga Canyon as a separate category), but it would have been the most ambitious, cultural and historic in nature. It would have focused on the city as a ‘phenomenon’, with over-arching cultural themes and imagery. There would have been no question of local artists coming to Pittsburgh to create a unique experience for visitors to Topanga Canyon, but the council members apparently felt that Sudhakar Prasad’s proposal was better suited to the museum system. If approved, the council members presumably saw this as a way to create a different kind of biennial, one that at least provided local artists with a place to be creative</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI’s cultural dimensions as opposed to its geographical ones.]This new proposal did not sit well with the museum board, who saw it as an encroachment on their current area of control. The issue came up at the AGM 2014, where the board members reportedly said they did not want to give up control of the biennial to an autonomous agency, but they also felt that the curator’s role had expanded to something that was not necessarily confined to the city. So they had a proposal sent to the city council, which they would have had to approve had the biennial been curated by an AI representative.The council, it is alleged, had a somewhat bizarre look in its head while it was considering this proposal. It was also claimed that the secretary of the board, a man named Sudhakar Prasad, had instigated the meeting by putting forward a range of titles, including ‘favorite places’ and ‘hits in the city’. It is claimed that Prasad had also put forward the idea of putting together an AI board of autonomous vehicles, which would have allowed the board to override any decisions the council made regarding the future of the city.The council, it is claimed, had an ‘ethical question’, and Prasad's proposal was seen as one that did not belong in the city. It was also claimed that the board members had not been given any reason to doubt the narrative put forward by the museum and AI, and that their claims were simply an excuse. The board members allegedly felt that their only real interest in the proposal was in putting out a press release when the museum was due to open in May 2015, and thus had put it aside to allow the museum to open earlier. The press release would have focused on the research projects carried out by the museum in conjunction with AI, while the autonomous vehicles and museum projects would have been rendered into a blur of media coverage.The council apparently did not see this</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of Mexico City from 2013 to 2015. I want to thank you for that. It’s rare for a position to be given in such a way, that one person — or one person only — takes on the role of culture minister. But in this case, there was a sense of collaboration between the different levels of government, which allowed the different stakeholders to work together constructively. In fact, some might even agree with the decision to make Mexico City the home of the FIFA Mexico City Football Club.Thanks again,DDownload this article as PDFReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015You're Welcome,DDownload this article as PDFReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015It’s time to show some real affection, I think I've fallen for you.I dreamt about it the other night. You took a chance on me, big chance, and I took it. And now you're in bed with me, too. Do you still dream about it</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of Spain from 2003 to 2007. I wish to share with you some aspects of the project that I participated in during that time.The so-called Arab Spring occurred in 2011 and, following its popular upsurge, sparked a worldwide debate about the role of culture in shaping political and social change. In some quarters, the term ‘culture brigades’ emerged to describe the efforts of young people to reclaim their generation’s identity and place in the world. In others, ‘cultural production committees’ were promoted by governments and non-governmental organizations (NGOs) to address specific issues of concern – wars, poverty, education inequality, etc. – and these have been seen by many as a necessary evil. To be sure, it is true that in recent years some non-governmental cultural agencies have been forced to seek funding from central governments in order to carry out projects with young people, and in many cases, this has meant cutting short critical cultural research studies to pursue such projects</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of Portugal, and I look forward to working with you in Madrid on 6 and 7 July.DDownload this article as PDFOmaría UrbanÁninghuisLucía SanrománUnexpected Turnabout, Chapter 8, Book One: The Art of Not Being Governed, Pt. 2, 2002. We will discuss the paradoxes of contemporary democracy, and the role of the artist in creating new kinds of local government.DDownload this article as PDFOmaría UrbanÁninghuisLucía SanrománUnexpected Turnabout, Chapter 8, Book Two: The Art of Not Being Governed, Pt. 2, 2002.We will discuss the paradoxes of contemporary democracy, and the role of the artist in creating new kinds of local government.Download this article as PDFOmaría UrbanÁninghuisLucía SanrománUnexpected Turnabout, Chapter 8, Book Two: The Art of Not Being Governed, P</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of Spain from 2004 to 2015. I enjoyed working with you on the proposals for Real Madrid’s Biennale, especially on the one entitled ‘Los Tijuana Five’, which was based on the real-life story of the five members of the notorious Los Tijuana Five Mexican Mafia.I wanted to come to the Biennale because I knew many important people from the Ministry of Culture. Among them were Maria Hlavajova, who gave me the heads-up about the Biennale being proposed in Madrid. She has a very critical eye to the extent that she is aware that some people in Madrid are against anything that promotes or celebrates art. For me, it was vital for Real Madrid to demonstrate that it is a thriving and vibrant art centre, because it is the cultural equivalent of having a big advertising campaign in a city where art is scarce or nonexistent. For example, the Biennale proposal in Madrid would not have been possible without the city council’s</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of Spain. We were particularly taken with the Minister’s statement on the occasion of the 2015 Biennial, where he announced that Real Madrid would host the following year’s Venice Biennale. We’d like to add another chapter to this book, this time focusing on the relationships between art and urbanization in the city.1. Fernando Pascual-Leone, ‘On Cities’ in  	Real Madrid, December 2015, p.10.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual-LeoneReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It is with great pleasure that we can add another chapter to our chapter on cities from September 2015. The biennale will take place in two parts: the city of monuments and the city of doubt. In the city of monuments, the Biennale will locate on a large and exclusive development called Plaza Mayor, which is being</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of the State of California. We had a chance to explore some of your historic sites in Los Angeles, such as The Beverly Wilshire, Greek Homes and Nowhere, and you showed us the Arsenale, which continues to be a source of inspiration for Los Angeles art lovers. I took the opportunity to introduce myself and explain that I worked for the online publication Metro as a reporter in 2010-2011. I got to know some of the people you had selected to be artists for the Biennale, and I have to say that the choice was an honour. Of course, it was also an opportunity to work on the project that you had put together, but I think that the honour of having done that project and now being a curator is what makes me happy.You know, when we were at the Venice Biennale, we were told that the Biennale’s original mandate was fulfilled by the fact that it was happening in Venice – and by the fact that it happened in</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of Spain between 2013 and 2015. I want to thank you for that.I want to thank you for allowing me to be a part of the curatorial team for the Venice Biennale. I want to share with you the impressions that I gathered from several meetings with various cultural and urban specialists on the project.I want to share with you some additional information that has come to me during the course of this process.I want to introduce myself somewhat more formally and make a brief description of the project that I am working on right now, and the role that I play in it. I’ve been curator of the Madrid Biennale since its inaugural in 1995. During that time I led the curatorial team that curated the two previous biennales, as well as the 1996, 98, and 201 series.I also worked at the Granby home of Carolee Christov-Bakargiev, who is now an arts educationalist for the Granby community. Her involvement with</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of Spain since January of this year. I come to share with you some thoughts on the state of the art in terms of its relation to the contemporary art world, and particularly the state of the art in terms of its relation to AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal.The Art Biennale has recently been presented in New York and London, and it is my intention to return to Madrid to participate in the next iteration of the biennale. The main reason for my visit is to take part in the discussions taking place behind the scenes. The AIADC has asked me to collaborate again, this time on a project in the city. The theme of this edition of the journal is ‘participate, contribute and contribute again’. This time around, I’m interested in the role that art can play in the contemporary context.Art can play many different ways. It can be used to express surprise, delight, despair or rage. It can be used to explore</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of Portugal. I have the honor to present to you the findings of an in-depth report, &quot;Culture in Portugal: A Portrait of Modern Portugal&quot;, prepared by Professors of Art and Design at Lisbon’s Monid Museo de Portoghesia, as well as Professors of Sociology and Director of the European Graduate School John Julius Moores University. This report, based on over a year of research, documents the relationship between art, art history and social practice in Portugal between 1999 and 2014. It also investigates the relationship between Portoghesian art and Portoculture, the region in which Lisbon is located. It was produced in close collaboration with the Monid Museo de Portoghesia, the Lisbon Architecture Foundation, and the European Graduate School. It is the outcome of a year-long series of research projects that were initiated in collaboration with Monid Museo de Portoghesia, the Monid Foundation, and the European Graduate School. The projects</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AIADC’s 2009 Biennial proposal, which was also accepted by the city’s arts council. The council members were not aware of the project’s development and its development over the following years. We decided to publish the story of the stalled project in order to draw attention to the issue and to highlight the important but fragile co-production between artists and the city. We hoped that the project would inspire other artists to explore similar situations and to consider other creative alternatives. The story of the Black-E’s project, including its development and the conversation that followed, is a critical piece of the overall narrative. We hope it serves as a model for future artists to work with the urban environment and create alternative, productive possibilities for their urban environments.Download this article as PDFDaniel Fernández Pascual JavierReal Madrid, December 2015Real Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,It has been a pleasure serving alongside you as Culture Minister of the State of New Mexico. I had the opportunity to visit the Monterrey Cultural Center and the Botanical Gardens in Ciudad Juarez, as well as the Botanical Garden of Los Alamos. The visit to the Monterrey Cultural Center was not in a privileged position. My position as a researcher allowed me to visit important sites and collect crucial data, while the position of representative allowed me to present the findings to you and the board of the National Museum. I thank you for these privileges and acknowledgements.I look forward to seeing you at the San Sebastian Museum of Art.DDownload this article as PDFReal Madrid, December 2015Dear Mr President and Ladies and Gentlemen,I’m going to be participating in the biennial of SFMOMA next year. I wanted to ask how the relationship between the Biennial and the Museum of Modern Art might differ in 2018.ThanksIn my submission for the 2018 Biennial, I hoped to find a way to incorporate the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,08080
    <text>presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080805Subtitle: The Unravelled - Ariel - Ariel Castro Visual Language Artists [From Participant to Artist]Sequences that appear in the Ariel Castro-Guerrero Documenta 13 Visual Language Arts (2013) project are used to represent the urban environment in the work. Ariel uses a similar approach to the visual language of traffic as a settler colonialist to generate resources for the infrastructure of apartheid in</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,08080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808104092,080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,08080808080808104092,08080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808104092,0800808104092,0808080808080808104092,0808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808104092,0808104092,08080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,08080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 08081040EC, 0808</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808080808080808080808080808104092,08080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,10 Wave Racer, 2010. Photo: Emilie Stott. 	These pastel-coloured boxes are made in large part out of recycled packaging, and in large part out of cardboard. The packaging has been replaced with the recycled material that is found in everyday items, including postal boxes, shelving, shelving units and shelves. 	André Hervé, Science and Culture for the Twenty-First Century, Springer, New York, 1987, p.100. 	These pastel-coloured boxes are made in large part out of recycled packaging, and in large part out of cardboard. The</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,08080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,0808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,08080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808104092,08080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808104092,08080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808104092,08080808080808104092,080808104092</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,08080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,08080808080908,08080808080808080908,0808080808080908,0808080808080808080908,080808080810,0808080808080908,0808080808080808080908,0808080810,0808080810,080808080810,0808080810,0808080808080908,0808080808080908,0808080808080908,0808081010,0808081010,0808081010,0808081010,0808081010,0808102,080808102,08080902,0808103,0808080502,0808104,0808080502,0808105,0808106,0808107,0808108,0808109</text>
    <text>presented as an online project of the artist Meehan Cristobal in collaboration with The Creative Timeling, an organisation that promotes the work of artists worldwide through its Laurence Olivier Prize awardee list. The project is part of MOCOR, the Museo del Perro Foundation (Mexico City), and is part of a broader curatorial agenda of the foundation's projects and programmes. Discoveries of the Unravelled series: 0808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808080808080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,080808104092,0808080808080808104092,0800808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,08080808080808080808104092,080808104092,08080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080808080804106118 Cultural appropriation and the legacy of colonialism. By highlighting the most visible manifestations of this dynamic, the exhibition ‘Unravelled’ seeks to bring to life in our collective imaginaries the complex entanglements that colonialism still leaves lying exposed in the places where it happens. The image above is a  	scape, a first-person account of the life-cycle of a frog (a.k.a. a frog on a stick) that was part of the family Williidae. The entry for the entry for the entry for the entry for the entry for</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’,
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Art Forum, Vol. 33, No. 1, Spring, 2013, p.1.Download this article as PDFJamie KalmanJamie Kalman is an artist. He was born and raised in Chicago, and currently works in the San Francisco Bay Area. His work has shown at the Whitney Museum of American Art, San Francisco Bay Arts Museum, and the National Gallery of Australia. He has been a curator in the South by Southwest arts and culture regional offices of the National Gallery, and the South by Southwest arts and culture registrar of the Auspicious Minds festival. He is the curator of the forthcoming exhibition The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013 (San Francisco: National Gallery of Australia, 2013), and the author of several poetry collections, including poetry from the collection The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, published by McGraw-Hill, New York (2015). His photographs are in the</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Affinities (2014), p. 20. 	[8] James Howard Kunstler, ‘Mass Incarceration and the Biennial: A crisis of legitimacy?’, Affinities (2014), p. 12. 	[9] Ibid. 	[10] See, e.g., Christine Macel,  	The Art Newspaper (Toronto), September 2016, http://www.theartnewspaper.com/2016/09/art-news/the-truth-about-australian-biennials/; Charles Scanlon, ed.,  	The Art Newspaper (Toronto), 1999, p. 26. 	[11] See Richard Florida, ed.,  	The New Art (New York: Columbia University Press, 2016), p. 13. 	[12] Florida’s text comes from the book The Contemporary Condition: Culture and Capital in a Critical Update (Cambridge</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Art Information Bulletin, Issue 8 (January 2013): 1–22. 	[8] See, for example, Nick Hornby, ed.,  	Graphic Portraits: Art, Race, and Capital, Blackwell, Oxford and the Giardini Foundation, 1986; Richard Florida, ed.,  	Graphic Portraits: Art, Race, and Capital, Blackwell, Oxford and the Giardini, 1991; and James Howard, ed.,  	Graphic Portraits: Art, Race, and Capital, Blackwell, Oxford and the Giardini Foundation, 1992. 	[9] Fred Turner,  	Far Eastern Frame, 1968. 	[10] George S. Herman and Alvin Finkel, eds.,  	Graphic Portraits: Art, Race, and Capital, Blackwell, Oxford and the Giardini Foundation, 1986, p. 17. 	[11] For more, see the essays in Fred Turner</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Artforum (Baltimore), November, 2012, p.110. 	[8] See, e.g., the text of the 2006 ACME convention, Art, Culture &amp; Ecology, vol. 25, no. 1, February, pp.101–19; Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Artforum (Baltimore), November, 2012, p.107. 	[9] Roger S. Ames and Scott L. Stewart, ‘The impact of biennials: 1991 to 2011’, Artforum (Baltimore), November, 2012, p.108. 	[10] Stephen G. Overton, ‘The biennial condition: On the rise or fall of excellence’, Artforum (Baltimore), November, 2013, p.1019. Available at: http://www.biennial.com/articles/archive/2012/11/the-bi</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Art in America (September 2012), p. 11. 	[8] James Howard Kunsthal,  	The Collectors (New York: Simon and Schuster, 1988), p. 198. 	[9] See, for example, Marina Fokidis,  	Beyond the Biennial: The Art World and Contemporary Art (Lanham, MD: Scarecrow, 1983), p. 3. 	[10] See also Lisa Parks,  	Art Is a Biennial Phenomenon (Chicago and London: University of Chicago Press, 1994), pp. 397–96. 	[11] Richard Southern,  	Introduction to Contemporary Art History (Chicago and London: University of Chicago Press, 2011), p. 25. 	[12] Roger Hiorny,  	A Brief History of Time (New York: Vintage, 1973), pp. 2–19. 	[13] Ibid., p</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Artforum (London), March, 2012, p.140. 	[8] J.D. Dewsbury, ‘A criticises Klosterman, Smith, and Okrand’s ‘Introduction to Cinema’, in, Janet Sturgess, Culture and Consensus: Critical Studies of the Recent Past, ed. Vikram Sethi and Jamie Kalman, Prentice Hall, 1980, p.134. 	[9] Stephen Leacock, ‘On the use of biennials in urban contexts’, in, W. E. B. Du Bois, The Race and Class of 1980, Blackwell, Oxford, 1980, p.36. Download this article as PDFJennifer Francis and Sarah CarterSenior Editor and Co-Editor of The New Inquiry, The New Inquiry Publications, 2005-06.Co-Editor of The New Inquiry, The New Inquiry Publications, 2005-06.Co-founder and Editor</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Artforum (Jersey City: Jersey City Biennials), March 2006, p.43. 	[8] Karen Bowden, ‘The exhibition industry: trade, politics, and the social dimensions of biennials’, Artforum (Jersey City: Jersey City Biennials), July/August 2012, p.68. 	[9] Arnoldo Pascual, ‘Art, art and the biennial’, The New York Times, 11/14/06, http://www.nytimes.com/2006/11/16/arts/of-art/archive/06/14/us-biennials-art-exhibition-stern-review-reveals.html?, 2007 September. 	[10] James Howard Kunstler,  	Kinship: The Anthropological Understanding of Community (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 2011), p.29. 	[11]</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Artforum, Vol. 34, No. 2, Spring, 2013, p.335. [8] Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. [9]  Jim Gilmore, ‘On the use of history and biennials in contemporary art’, Artforum, Vol. 34, No. 2, Spring, 2013, p.335. [10]  Katherine Orne, ‘Histories from the archive: the role of biennials in the construction of contemporaneity’, Australian Journal of Archaeology, Vol. 16, No. 1, Spring, 2002, p.1. [11]  See Roger Hiorns, ed.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013, Chapter 5. [12]  The Collectors,  	, 2012.</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Artforum (Toronto), Volume 13, Number 4, Spring, 2013, p.335. 	[8] Terry Smith,  	Thérèse Georges, 2014, Art in America, p.5. 	[9] See, for instance, Terry Smith,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013, p.288. 	[10] See, for example, The Collectors, Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013, p.289. 	[11] See Terry Smith,  	Thérèse Georges, 2014, Art in America, Chapter 3: Contemporaneity and Difference, p.6. 	[12] See Terry Smith,  	Thérèse Georges, 2014, Chapter 3: Contemporaneity and Difference, p.7. 	[13]</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, the work of art being enacted through the system ‘arises from the contingency of the situation, which is constantly on the point of changing, from an ever-present but discrete presence (the ‘illness’) to a presence (the effect of changes in the biennial’s programming). The project therefore becomes a systemically aware one, ever vigilant for any sign of ‘illness’. Art, it seems to me, is often the symptom of a much broader condition, and the illness that results from that condition is art. Art, and the artist, is the frontline in the struggle for existence. 	[5] 	[6] See Donald Nicholson and Rob Kling, eds.,  	The Collectors: Chuck Klosterman, Terry Smith, and Marc Okrand, 2013. 	[7] Jamie Kalman, ‘On the use of biennials as sites for art and aesthetic practice’, Artforum, Vol. 36, No. 3, 2008, p.585. 	[8] Terry Smith,  	The Art Newspaper, Issue #4, March 2006, p.1. Download this article as PDFJamie KalmanJamie Kalman is a PhD Candidate in English and Film Studies at the University of Alberta, and holds a Bachelor of Arts in English and Film Studies from the University of Alberta. His dissertation examines the relationship between the megastructure of the biennial and the city in which it is located, and examines the cultural politics of biennials in the context of cityscapes and cities. He is also the co-editor of the popular online publication Ain't It Cool News. His writing has appeared in publications including The American Prospect, The American Scholar, The American Journal of Sociology, and The Annals of Improbable Research. He is a co-founder of the blog Black-E, where he has written previously on art and race.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus
    <text>presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus Documenta 13 archive, together with Dutch artist Jeanne van Heeswijk and Israeli artist Danny Danon.  [1] The exhibition format was developed by and for the art market. It is a ‘marketplace of ideas’, presenting a representative selection of ideas from a catalogue or a newspaper or magazine (or both); ideas are traded, argued for and rejected in a live auction.  [2] See http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/2004/en/index.html. [3] http://www.newadvent.org/cathen/2004/en/index.html. [4] The exhibition was organised as a ‘summit’ for a planned ‘discovery’ project. It was not a ‘discovery’ project itself, but a ‘time-specific exploration into a place’, in the words of the exhibition’s website. </text>
    <text>presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus Architecture Biennale 2016 entry 'Architecture as a Social Process'.We Are Here to Stay 	We are here to stay 	Because we can. The idea of ‘ here  	in our current globalised and diffuse way of understanding the world is that there is only so much space and that ‘here  	is where the action is’, and that action then takes place elsewhere. So, what is the implication here for cities and metropolitan areas? In this ‘developing world’, there is only so much space that can be made available, and that means that if there is going to be a ‘development’ in a city, it has to be ‘affordable’ and available to all. And of course, the key concept here is ‘space’. But what is space, and how does that relate to how we think about cities and urban development? In the 1960s, Søren Kier</text>
    <text>presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus Process exhibition catalogue.He lectures widely on the arts and culture of the twenty-first century. His latest work, Performance, is a Platform for a Conversation on the Issues of Art and Culture for a possible international audience. His work for the Liverpool Biennial is due in autumn 2017.Profile of an Artist[1] Søren Pase,  The Pale, 1966. Watercolour on wove paper. © Søren Pase 2016. All rights reserved, DACS 2015. Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloM.D. (ret)In the Art Department of the Brooklyn Museum, 2016. © Michael Truscello 2016. All rights reserved, DACS 2016.Introduction: On the Possibility of Collaborative Practice[2]How can an artist be a co-producer and co-creator in the same space? What is the relationship between the two? What is the relationship between the two</text>
    <text>presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus Architecture Biennale 2016, and the forthcoming book From Subsistence to State: On State Fragments in Art, Architecture, and Cultural Theory.Wallace Stevens, Performing Arts critic, contributes essays and reviews on contemporary art, performance, and art history to The New York Times, a hybrid paper and online publication, in both English and Danish, on topics involving the arts, aesthetics, history, and political economy of contemporary art. His latest work, ‘Silicon Valley: Meet the Artists and Their Work', is on view at the Danish and Danish Pavilions, UCLA, until December 2016. He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology (2007), Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His book, Postmodernism and Nonsense: On Postmodernism and Its Aftermath is</text>
    <text>presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus Architecture Biennale, the 13th edition of the Aarhus architecture biennale, and part of the forthcoming book The Complete Aarhus 1988-2004. He is the author of From Counterculture to Cyberculture: Stewart Brand, Richard California, and the Rise of Digital Utopianism (2014). His most recent work was published in the New Republic, 6 October 2017.UG’10: UG10: Unfixing the CityBetween 1999 and 2015, New York–based artist, Daniel Fernández de la Torre, created a sustained, multi-year public dialogue about the city that challenged long-held ideas about contentment, identity, and the social. The project—which he describes as ‘a series of small acts of memory, act of memory, and act of memory’—involves works that appear in locations throughout Manhattan, including a series of memory gardens located in public spaces such as parks and public squares, as well as</text>
    <text>presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus Platform 3 exhibition, with works by Hans Haacke, Hans Meisner, Olafur Eliasson, Tejun Heo ‘Baba Sa. Saba’, and many others.His writing has been featured in the New Inquiry, The New Criterion, Noisey, New York Times, Washington Post, New Republic, The New Republic, New York Times Book Review, New York Times Traveler, The New Republic Digital Letters, New York Times Digital Letters, Digital Spy, Stages, Stages Digital Film, Stages Germany, Stages Africa, and many other publications around the world. His work was also part of the exhibition figure 8’s 'Curatorial Cast' - an exhibition of work from the 8 exhibitionary projects across Italy and the Middle East, India and Europe, arranged by a curator from each respective country. The casts were created by a collective of curators from the following monographic biennials: The British Museum, London</text>
    <text>presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus Platform Series, Aarhus, Denmark, 2016. He is currently completing a book project based on the ideas and reflections of his many years as a reporter and editor with the Nation newspaper in New York. His work has also been featured in the film Silence, the work of the New York Public Theater, the BBC, NME, The Guardian, Radio 4, and many other publications around the world.Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, PainterWhat would you rather do: embark on an artistic career or plant flags across a city in support of the armed forces? That's the question that comes to mind when reflecting on the tragic loss of life in the line of duty. It’s an emotive issue to contemplate, one that will be remembered by generations yet unborn. Yet for many of us, the decision to become embroiled in the service doesn’t feel like an emotive issue. It’s like walking down the street and having a conversation with a family</text>
    <text>presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus Architecture Biennale which is currently presenting his book from 1974, Towards a Theory of Imagination (with Stuart Moulthroup, University of Chicago Press, 2015). Wallace Stevens, The Three Musketeers, translated by Elspeth Reeve (New York: Oxford University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFElspeth ReeveElspeth Reeve is an architect and the co-founder of the company, Future City, which is developing strategies for cities of the future. She is the recipient of several awards and has received an array of accolades, including including the 2012 Knight Chair in Architectural Studies from the American Institute of Architects, the 2013 Stanford Architecture Prize, the 2014 Architecture of America association prize, the 2015 Pascual Foundation Presidential Fellowship, the 2016 Peel Land &amp; Property Association, and the 2017 Democracy Collaborative Ass</text>
    <text>presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus Book Prize 2019 Selected Essays.Stevens is a British writer, political activist, and journalist. He is Professor of English and Cultural Studies at Goldsmiths College, University of London, and holds a Bachelor of Arts in English Cultural Studies from Goldsmiths College, University of London, where he also holds a Masters in Cultural Studies from Columbia University. His work has addressed a wide range of themes including the politics of language, colonialism and apartheid, economic colonialism and nepotism, urbanisation and gentrification, art and its discontents, and postcolonial/postcolonial imaginaries. He has written for the New Inquiry, The New Inquiry, The Guardian, Prospect Magazine, Spin, Noise, Nation and many other publications. His most recent work was published in the New York Times as part of the Spinoff series 'Neoliberalism: The Enduring Crisis of Authenticity' (2017). He has a book out now called The End of Ostrich’s Diet.Steven S</text>
    <text>presented as an online project in collaboration with the National Theatre, Bristol Artspace and the New Art Gallery. The project was initiated in 2014 and culminated in the publication of the exhibition-length plays, ‘Wallace Stevens: Composer, Performer, Painter’. He has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, the New Inquiry Magazine, Frieze, Frieze d/e, Frieze f/e, Frieze g, and the Guardian.Wallace Stevens’ work has been exhibited in numerous venues including New York (2015), Venice (2015), Berlin (2015), Barcelona (2016), Toronto (2016), and Munich (2017). He has written for the New Inquiry, Noam Chomsky: In Defence of National Ideology, Noam Chomsky, Reflections on Vietnam (MIT Press, 2015), and with Pouya Burch, The Politics of Imagination: Language and Politics in Late Imperial Cultures. His work is also part of the Aarhus Documenta 13 exhibition catalogue. His new book The Politics of Intimacy: Intimacy, Intimidation and Compulsion in Late Imperial Cultures is published by Verso in 2017.The cultural logic of empire is a set of relationships between people and space that are inherently unequal, dehumanising and based on the medieval notion of the round table. The US and UK both have their capitals in London, but the cultural narrative of empire is that of the limp-dick landlords, financiers and colonialists. The events in Ferguson that brought down British footballers Mo Farahat and Mo Farahat-ul-Haq and left six others injured are a clear case in point. The failure of the response from the authorities in the UK and the US to take measures to restore public confidence in the legal system and prevent such recurrence is another. The use of deadly force by police is another matter. But the centrality of the legal system, the internal logic of which is</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to engage with, and even to create meaning for, global audiences. It’s as if the social are stepping back and creating spaces for artists to be able to express their creativity across platforms and media.[1]In other words, the biennial is no longer a custodian of artistic trends or the end point of artistic productions – it is a site of production and consumption. It is a transient performance that, like all such performances, has a set and consumable set of intentions and outcomes, but unlike other types of performance, it does not necessarily have a fixed form or outcome. In this respect, it differs from other types of performance, such as a performance of a work in a gallery setting, a performance of a work in a museum setting, or a performance of a work on a website. It is always a site of production and consumption, but unlike other types of performance, it has no fixed place or end point. Its historical and technological contexts constantly shape what it means to be</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to create and inhabit new worlds, to come to terms with ever greater amounts of media, and to create new media around themselves. Art and artists everywhere are intervening in this process, as artists, curators, collectors, journalists, online critics, social mediators and now, even as policymakers, taking the lead, through what is usually called the ‘sharing economy’ (which is kind of a thing) or calling it a decentralization of production away from conventional media institutions. They are creating new media that not only record and manage art, but also create a new media landscape through which we can all live and work, depending on the priorities of the curators, collectors and institutions that support the art market.Art markets are becoming ever more globalized. It is no longer the case that the curators, collectors and art dealers of the past kept their homes in the city but organised their activities across many other cities and far-flung islands in the world. Now, the collecting agencies</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to produce and participate in new media works that are not bound by the museum’s or gallery’s chronological or institutional constraints. This is a situation that was on full display at the Venice Biennale, where the biennale was curated by Judith Miller, Miller Professorship at Columbia University. The New Media Condition | Judith Miller and Oliver Plender4 October, 2013The following essay is an expanded and updated version of a talk that I gave at the 2013 Biennale of Sydney, in response to the term ‘biennial’ used by critics to describe the art events that have taken place since 2005. I use the term loosely, and do not identify with a specific museum, art gallery, or institution. Rather, I use the term ‘digital gallery’ to refer to a community of artists, curators, artists’ associations, writers and others who establish, organize, and/or influence these biennials, and whose work is often cur</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to create their own circumstances, to flexibly access information and knowledge, and to imagine their futures. They are also creating a situation in which biennials can play a part in reconfiguring these circumstances—making art and artists out of the circumstances of their lives, making them agents of change within them, and even becoming agents of their change themselves.The way I see it, the necessity to have a biennial has become evident in every detail of every project that I have ever been a part of—every detail, that is, except for the project that brought art and activism to the area. This is particularly true of the work that I have been doing on the ground in the form of building relationships with people, building capacity building relationships, and engaging communities—projects that were initially conceived as temporary, ephemeral, and gesture events. The biennial has to confront this necessity in order to achieve any kind of effect. And I would argue that it’s precisely this necessity that has</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to participate in these new media situations. Art and artists everywhere are therefore called upon to continue to innovate and create. But, to truly understand and participate in this new condition, we need to collectively identify and deal with the present—to grow and change as a collective. How can our art and cultural resources be used collectively? How can art and artists become more present in the social totality? These are questions that, as we move forward further into the future, biennials and museums will be compelled to ask themselves and others will inevitably ask them. But, today, we’re far enough along in our development as biennials and museums that it’s practically impossible to add an art institution to the list of currant and non-currant cultural goods. So, how can art be of service to the social totality? This is the question that, as contemporary art production increasingly demands, art will be obliged to confront. How, then, to engage and, by extension, grow</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to create and inhabit new worlds—one that’s rich in metaphors, yet poor in concrete—one that allows for the very real and very complicated thing that art’s traditionally done: thinking, feeling, creating.Download this article as PDFJennifer Francis and Prem Krishnamurthy Jennifer Francis is an artist, writer, educator and principal in the practice of Educational Artist at the Fashion Institute of Art in New York. She is also the executive director of the Prudence Project, an arts education and advocacy organization, and a member of the board of the Metropolitan Museum of Art’s Curatorial Faculty. Her work has addressed a wide range of audiences, has established her as a multi-award winning artist, and has been featured in numerous books, journals, and publications worldwide. Her work is influenced by a classical school of thought that emphasizes reason, critical inquiry and experimentation, over the alternatives of authoritarianism, collectivism and hierarchy. She is also the author of The Prudence of</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to exist simultaneously as objects of consumption and as sources of knowledge and protest. This is a paradigm shift in how we imagine the relationship between art and people, between art and the cultural infrastructure of a given city –– whether that is a North African commission or a Colombian artist stepping away from the physical medium into virtual media. As a result, we are witnessing a renaissance in the social and civic life-cycle of cultural capital in many cities all over the world. But this social life-cycle is not, as some imagine it, possible without the active participation of leading cultural institutions, whether they be biennials, museums, or large artistic corporations. In this respect, biennials and large art institutions are the ‘infrastructure’ of the contemporary cultural landscape, intervening early and late in the game to shape and create the narrative of the ongoing engagement with art and culture that is unfolding all around us. It’s an old saying in art circles: good intentions can be taken advantage of</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to create new kinds of artworks and to participate in new kinds of imaginaries. But they are also exerting a great deal of pressure on cultural institutions to produce ever more contemporary artworks that can be shared and consumed globally. In the main, this pressure is coming from above, but also from below. It is being reflected in the increasing number of biennials, the globalisation of art collections and museums, as well as their internationalisation. Art collections in China are being fragmented into numerous individualised and individualised items, and museums in many cities, which is being supplemented with cheaper and more convenient online museums. Biennials are the globalised version of what Norman Mailer called the museum – a building both large and small, symbolised by a museum building and an archive that records the history of art ever since the beginning of time. Biennials are everywhere, but they are especially visible in the West, where cultural tourism has replaced historic curating as the main form of visitor attraction</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to take part in artistic and cultural activities across a large geographical area, and in so doing, to create new artworks that can be shared and circulated widely. This is one way in which biennials and for-profit art museums are placing art and their position in relation to development, both digitally and in the real life of the art and artist upon whom they rely. It’s also the case that, thanks to social media and other platforms, artworks can be found anywhere at any time, and at any price, which makes them exceptionally attractive to commercial collectors and museums alike. Of course, this kind of accessibility and global circulation is only possible because of the artistic perforations and in-circulation of contemporary artworks that have become rampant across the social networks and biennials are part of the cultural ephemeralist order that modern museums and modern artists aspire to. It is not just that contemporary artworks, like any other, are possessions of the past; their social con</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, as projects like these will be, is that it’s possible that one day, a curator or curator-at-large could step back from the art museum and gallery and commission a similar kind of project—taking into consideration the contemporary context, the biennial’s current challenges and possibilities, and the art world’s historical and current predicaments. Such an approach would really go beyond the museum and gallery and aim to take into consideration the social, political, and cultural conditions today on the ground—an impossible task for a for example, but a task that could, one day, be undertaken by a local art commission or a local art team. I believe that, at this moment, we are living through a moment where, thanks to autonomous movements and biennials, art and artists everywhere are participating in a new generation of global artworks that are increasingly mediated and virtualized. These new media are creating a situation in which art and artists everywhere have an unprecedented ability to create and inhabit new worlds. They are, in other words, the artists in the new art-infrastructure.Artworlds of the future’—if we are lucky to get our hands on that mythical development—will likely be communities of artists, designers, site-planning experts and urbanists engaged in a shared engagement with the increasingly precarious, sometimes deadly and sometimes wonderful world that is emerging. Such engagement will most likely involve art and culture as a tool or resource for political, economic and social change. It will most likely involve artists and art institutions of all kinds—but particularly local artists and those whose work is transnationalized—responding to the new media technologies that are reshaping how art is produced, consumed and created in societies around the world. It will most likely involve art being made in many forms and made visible at many venues. The engagement and creativity of art and artists everywhere will most likely be constrained to specific sites and times—with or without a public. This</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of art
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of artifice and opulence in the region. For example, the massive new World War One memorials in Istanbul and Petra, built by the Jordanian monarch and his entourage, symbolise the modernisation of antiquities and culture, whereas the erstwhile avant-garde biennale in Doha, which was initially conceived and directed by the Danish avant-garde newspaper Berlingske Tidende, has returned to a more traditional role of reporting on the region. 	There were also significant differences of opinion about the appropriate role of curators and the role of art institutions in the development of art. Some artists and curators were more open to the possibility that their work might be incorporated into a future biennial, while others saw such possibilities as inherently opposed to the work of art itself. For example, Selahattin Demirtaş (who co-curated the 2016 Venice Biennale but is now curator and part of the Istanbul and Doha Centres for</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of art-historical-cultural intersectionality. These projects demonstrate that art can be made with complex social and political contexts and that critical artistic and architectural work can be done through a range of different approaches. 	[1] The Biennial’s current project, funded by the London and Liverpool Biennials, seeks to create a ‘world-class’ venue for its research-based research programme, which it describes as its 'sciences of culture and sciences of mobility'. The Biennial has also formed a new joint venture with the Liverpool Biennial – the Odeon – to establish a new division, ‘Artist Space’ in the city's Tate Modern Gallery. The project was initially conceived as a cluster of collaborative research projects, but over time there has been an erosion of autonomy within the Biennial as a whole. The Odeon has increasingly used this space to pursue its own interests, and the artist-curator duo, Sally Tallant and Joasia</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of art and cultural reproduction; to a) the prevailing educational and residential paradigms regarding the urban landscape and, b) the prevailing economic and legal frameworks regarding urban development. As biennials become more and more embedded in the urban landscape, their status as culturally significant institutions is increasingly questionable, and their political and organisational capacity is questionable too. Yet, given the right mix of factors – economic, geographical and social – pavilion building can play a significant role in the future of cities and regions. 	There were several themes that were of significant import to the discussions that followed the Biennial: displacement, reconnecting with cities, regeneration, participation, participation in the arts and culture, participation in the biennial as a whole. There were also a number of issues that were of critical concern to the participants: regeneration, gentrification and the politics of participation, for example. The topic of participation often surfaces in discussions of the economic, urban and cultural effects of biennials, but little is said</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of art-designed buildings and social practice, and the biennial as an institution was forced to confront and address these. The project, its diverse participants, wide ranging perspectives and deep democratic processes ensured that these types of complexity were encountered and discussed, and that viable options were available to affected communities. These varied from the biennial as a static exhibitionary form, to the establishment of local communities based art world councils, to the development of alternative cultural and community development models. The development of local alternatives to the biennial as an exhibitionary form was actively supported by local government.  	Artists, curators, landscape architects and landscape architects generally had a significantly more positive and inclusive impact on the project, and the wider discussion, than the artist-driven collective that was part of the Project Gallery. This was partly due to the prominence of artists and the curators with whom they collaborated, who had a much greater personal stake in the project than the individual contributors. In the biennial context, the</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of art-historical-institutional-design, which were seen as essential for the success of the project. It is this uncertainty about what is and is not able to be built that creates the conditions for biennials to emerge and thrive, and for them to fail. 	There were also questions about what might become of the artefacts once the biennials were established. In the United Kingdom, buildings were often retained through legislation as cultural resources, but in many cities and regions in Canada and the United States, they are actively contributing to meet local needs and addressing societal issues. There is a growing call for the return of artefacts, especially when they are of historical or archaeological interest to local communities. In the case of the Liverpool Biennial, this includes the possession of the buildings and artefacts by their communities. How to Deconstruct the Invisible 	In her book Invisible Cities, Marianne Moore focuses on the ways in which we inhabit data. She focuses on the ways in which</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of art and urban development, and in many ways they were. Creating new solutions was also a major part of the project’s success, and the emergence of new self-built cities are a notable example. New micro-aggressions to gentrification, for example, were also a major part of the project’s success. But the creation of new ways of living, new ways of interacting, new ways of connecting is only part of the equation. There are many more systems that need to be worked through, and they need to be agreed to in a collective way, before anything can be realistically said or done. In order for a project to progress, and even just to have a start, significant change needs to happen, and it is this ongoing process of newness and conflict that defines the project and generates the narrative of the city.  	As a project, the Liverpool Biennial was also part of a much broader institutionalisation process that was also, in many ways, an</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of artifice, of modernity and modernism. The biennial as a cultural-political-ideological formation is deeply embedded in the United Kingdom and is therefore globally visible. Yet in a number of of of of its developments, the Biennial also endeavoured to be something more, to become a collective body, to enter into a shared social context and to intervene in a more general way. In other words, it is a form that has a normative mission and an agenda, but also a political dimension. In the case of the Biennial in Liverpool, the social mission aspect came through in its development as a cultural institution, in relation to housing, community and youth development, and art. The curatorial turn came through in the fact that the Biennial, being a cultural institution, had a cultural agenda as well as a social one: it promoted dialogue, exchange, and engagement with the local, national and international curators that were meeting in London, and beyond. Its curatorial approach came from</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of art-historical tourism and the megastructure tourism of the 1990s and early 2000s. The complexity of the project and its long-term evolution meant that significant parts of the world still hadn’t seen it. There was considerable resistance from certain quarters – especially in countries with histories of colonialist practices – but the art-historical tourism industry seems to thrive on the assumption that the politically aware traveller is at least partially aware of the extent to which he or she is part of a globalised capitalist culture. Curators, landscape architects and other cultural workers who ventured outside the box of the museum were seen as having contributed significantly to the project’s success. 	The biennial form is deeply related to the globalised urbanisation of cities, and the human-resource-intensive commodification of landscapes. The biennial is a major venue for the exhibition and promotional of cultural capital – cultural products such as furniture, cars, clothes, sports memorabilia, and so on. It</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of art and cultural production in the region, but also for an alternative, more local dimension to the exhibitionary form. 	The project came to be seen by many in the region as a ‘real’ art project instead of simply an exhibitionary enterprise. This is partly due to the fact that the artist-curator exchange was created in-house at the Biennial, and the fact that many of the artists who worked on the project were later employed by the Biennial itself, rather than by another organisation connected to the museum. 	In addition, the Biennial established a strong working relationship with the local community-based organisation Leadbeater. This was due to the Biennial's financial support to Leadbeater’s projects in the region, and the Biennial’s desire to work directly with local communities to improve their cultural environments. This relationship would continue, even after the project was shut down, due to the artists’ need to be able to work independently</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to discern the vast and often hidden histories of the region – so it is crucial that the project is connected to wider local and national agendas.  	In this regard, the project also needs to be able to be transnational in nature, and thus include elements from multiple contexts. Here, the Liverpool Biennial contributes to a larger worldwide movement of biennials by providing an international forum for its discussions and innovations. The project is an example of what biennials can and cannot do, and the kinds of political and legal wrangling that inevitably results from that. The nature of the project, and the positions taken by the artists, curators, landscape architects and other stakeholders who contributed to its success or failure, means that there was considerable room for disagreement, which is why significant pavilions, pavilions of silence, pavilions of conflict, pavilions of resistance and pavilions of imagination were made. These could be seen as major challenges to the dominant models of art and culture in the region. The main artists, curators, landscape architects and designers were chosen on the basis of a broad range of criteria, taking into account a range of relevant skills, experience and networks. Their studios, campuses and exhibitionary venues were selected to reflect the diverse contexts and different levels of expertise of the region. The pavilion, the symbol of the museum and archive, was chosen as the site of the exhibition, reflecting the region’s historical and contemporary past, but also the region’s potential for future exhibitionary opportunities. 	The pavilion became an important site for the exhibition, as the exhibition proceeded, because it served as a reminder of the region’s unique historical and cultural past, and also of the region’s present and its potential future. It offered various kinds of privacy, including a side entrance for visitors with disabilities, a rooftop terrace with a panoramic view of the museum, and free public viewing for all visitors.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-mural
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-muralist. It is not uncommon for contemporary artists to produce biennials with almost no previous curatorial training, either in the US or internationally recognised art schools and artists´ centres. What is unusual about these biennials is the number or quality of the artists who are drawn to them, the range of voices they support, or the depth of their understanding of a given issue. The range and depth of this global curatorial curatorial currying is extremely difficult to gauge, even amongst artists who have curatorial curating experience. I would speculate that it is because there is no defined definition of what a biennial is in this country, and amongst artists, curators and art administrators alike who are used to working across national borders. Biennials are projects with a curatorial function, and thus are projects that are often conceived as ancillary or supplementary to other activities undertaken in the art world. They are projects that are often placed in the context of other activities and with the curatorial function</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-mural. It is much more common for artists to produce works of non-mural variety, and much more common for these creations to be commissioned by non-mural artists. This asymmetry between the past and the future is what contemporary art seeks to redress. But in the current environment of constant global urbanisation and expansion, it is also what contemporary art cannot.Art is a complex concept, and theories of its meaning and uses were developed in the context of a political and economic climate dominated by capitalist modernity. The cultural logic of the contemporary era is capitalism at its most diffuse and globalised. Capitalism produces new creative forms of use-value in ever greater quantities, at ever greater distances, based on ever greater numbers of people. Each person produces a piece of art according to his or her individual circumstances, needs and desires. But in the age of the biennial and its large collections and the museum, people are much less able to create their own cultural experiences. So cultural geographers have to</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-mural. It is not customary in most cities to paint the whole city, but rather to mark specific neighbourhoods, to let certain neighbourhoods stand out in a particular way. And in many cities, particularly in those with high and low populations, this non-mural form of painting is routine. Cities are places where people gather to connect, exchange, exchange, socialise, eat well and generally have a life. But even in these places, there is much that the art world can and should do with other cities doing more of the heavy lifting.  So, while contemporary art is making in non-mainstream cities, there is a strong urge to intervene where art is being made that way and to intervene now, so as to foster the growth of viable local alternatives.   Another example is the increasingly prominent and globalisation of art-historical curatorial approaches.  Contemporary art’s own realisation came in the 1990s, when the massive cultural-political revolutions that swept countries all across</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-mural. Its popularity reflects a desire to discuss, analyse and visualise the past, but also a desire to obliterate the past. And although this is a desire that has been sustained for decades in most parts of the world, in recent years it has become increasingly difficult to find art in these cities that are not submerged in their reports, analyses and reports, and whose stories are not part of the larger global narrative.During the twentieth century, art was often used as a political tool. In many parts of the world, the politics of art were driven by economic needs and desires, but in other parts – including in capitalist capitalist global cities – the social logic of art was actively used to justify and control the social. In these cities, the social is subordinated to the economic. In the past, art was often used as a tool for the social eradication of poverty and hunger. But now, as in other cities where the social is increasingly distant from the economic, the practice of contemporary art is</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-mural. It is much vaster, more pervasive and more pervasive today, than it was in the 1970s and 1980s, when murals first came into vogue. In many cities, especially in those with high and growing populations, a steady stream of artists are able to churn out impressive number-crunching figures in relatively confined spaces, often in the space of a single day. But in other cities and in some remote regions of the world, especially those with declining populations, very different practices are common. Moreover, in some cities, especially those with rapidly growing populations, the urban and suburbanisation of many of the population groups inhabiting those cities is underway, which means that along with economic development, it is also a means of absorbing and sheltering those populations in the metropolis. In such cities, the metropolis is being built on the back of a self-sustaining, zero-growth economy. And although the metropolis may or may not be able to support a significant</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-mural. There are many other, more precise, ways of describing, creating and using art.Art is a social process, and its social use cases are numerous and varied. Some of us will see our cultural actions as having a transformative, transformative effect on the world around us. We may be surprised by the kinds of reactions that art can inspire. We may not always get what we want or what we need, but we may make improvements and change the world in powerful ways. In that case, art is art, and if not proven to have a transformative effect, then at least its social consequences will be interesting to watch. The social consequences will have to wait for another time.Download this article as PDFHamid Dabashi Hamid Dabashi: Originally from Ahvaz in Iran, Hamid Dabashi is the Hagop Kevorkian Professor of Iranian Studies and Comparative Literature at Columbia University in New York City. His publications include several collections of articles on Iranian modern and contemporary</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-mural. It is almost as if the ancient practice of commissioned painting is being rediscovered, and this new curatorial curation is being drawn on the back of a tradition of excellent public art promoting in the most conservative circles of the world. Of course, in this situation, the past must be taken into account, and any such move is likely to have unintended consequences. The past is also a site of contingency, and in a volatile world, the past is a place of chance and error. It is tempting to see the mission of contemporary art in the language of a universal humanist ideal: that is, to serve all mankind. But this is not at all what the contemporary mission of modern art is. What the contemporary mission of modern art would mean is precisely the opposite: what it would not mean at all. Modern art seeks to please no-one at all. It seeks to transform the world it comes into, and to that end it must have an impact, to the extent that it ling</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-mural. Contemporary art is a complex mix of historical and contemporary art, and this mix-up-time is what makes it contemporary. If the past is erased from view, or is rendered invisible, this creates a new art form. Art’s historical place is made visible in the service of contemporary needs and desires. This is why in the past when artists were trying to make the past visible, they used what historian David Harvey calls ‘the most pernicious of all modern techniques – the black and white photographic plate ‘– which is to say, the black and white optical trick that adds colour and sharpens image sharpening’. This is why in the past when artists were trying to make the past disappear, they used what Harvey calls ‘the most insidious of all contemporary tricks – the splendor of industrial production and packaging … and the packaging itself’. This is also why in the past when artists were trying to put an end to the present, they used what</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-mural. Its roots are in the Middle Ages, and it is now widespread in some Muslim countries, but even in these places, it is considered obscene and anti-religious. As a concept, it has rarely been used constructively.So one can imagine a world in which art is no longer the province of religious fundamentalists and purveyors of extreme forms of human suffering and political violence, but can instead be freely used by anyone seeking to engage with art in a constructive way. This is the world imagined by futurist Ray Bradbury in his novel Fahrenheit 451. Bradbury is a British writer and social critic. He is best known for his novel Plain Jane, about an American nuclear submarine commander stationed on the island of Mauritius for four years in the 1950s. In Bradbury’s fictional world, the submarine commander, Lieutenant Colonel James H. Moore, leads a group of artists, writers and activists on a series of subversive acts designed to draw attention to the pernicious effects</text>
    <text>propose a biennial based on AI or perhaps just on computers? It may well be that future curators will draw on the insights of their curatorial training to understand the potentialities of biennials, and perhaps even on the curatorial training to intervene in the future of these possibilities. But even if future curators learn how to make art, they will still have to make art, and then give it meaning. There are many ways of knowing, creating and using art, and understanding and using art are not mutually exclusive.Art is a dynamic term, and its use in this context can be misleading. Take, for example, the use of murals and the murals of the past. The historical practice of commissioned mural painting is now widespread in many parts of the world, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised, this form of mural painting is widespread only in the most conservative circles. The contemporary practice of curatorial curation is distinctly non-mural. There are now over 24 million paintings in the US and over 6 billion paintings worldwide, but in many cities in many parts of the world, especially in those cities that have recently been urbanised and are now experiencing rapid population growth, there is a strong tendency towards non-mural art. There is a reason for this tendency. Cities are big business centres, and cities are places where capitalism is constantly being challenged. They are also places where art is made asymmetrically – by artists who come from different parts of the world and do different kinds of work in very similar kinds of settings. This is what art curators do, and it is what artists do. Art history is made here, in and through the city, in and through time.Artists depend on funding and other valuable assets to do their work, and they are constrained in what they can do because of the nature of the biennial. The biennial today is a globally multi-sourced organisation, reliant on foundations,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the city also become artists, and the biennial becomes a ‘place of permanent permanent residence’. This second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’ is what Artamatic is all about. We are artists-in-residence in the Art and Architecture department of the Istanbul Museums Authority (IMA) and partner institutions in the city such as the Silo 8 project and the National Gallery of Turkey. This second aspect is what Artamatic is all about. We are artists-in-residence in the department of the Istanbul Museums Authority (IMA) and partner institutions in the city such as the Silo 8 project and the National Gallery of Turkey. We are looking to develop a long-term collaborative project with the IMA and other partners to map, document and archive the history of the Biennial industry in Istanbul and beyond. The project will be based in the city and bring together ethnographic, archival and archival research, drawing together art</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the place buy into the urban narrative of the city as a whole, which in turn helps to finance the art that is displayed. The purchase of a house, for example, is a good bet within the city in order to participate in the inflated value of a flat in the city, which in turn is a good bet within the biennial market. And so the cycle continues. The question is, can the biennial condition be altered? The answer to this is a resounding yes. It is our experience of living in the city now, and it is true of any city: the more we invest in the infrastructure of the city, the more art is produced, the more value is added to it – in the form of buildings, streets, parks, cafes, schools – and thus the more art is created, the more people live within the city. Thus, the biennial condition is ‘a built environment that is constantly shifting and subject to unpredictable forces, which makes it vulnerable to changes in</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the city also become art collectors, and this last aspect is another that contributes to the enrichment of the city as a whole. If the biennial is a transient art form, and its artists gradually move away from the city into nature, then the biennial itself becomes something that exists within the city and thereby contributes to its continued artistic production. The biennial is a transient art form because it is constantly (more and more often) visited by artists and visitors from the surrounding area. The art forms it supports – travelogues, encyclopedias, poetry slams, mini-exhibitions, and so forth – are not going to go away anytime soon. They will remain embedded in the city and contribute to its cultural life, even if they do not constitute the bulk of what is exhibited at the biennial. Art will of course continue to be produced in the biennial, but the very nature of the biennial itself – in its immersiveness, its proximity, its demand for mass consumption</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the city either invest in these art forms, or else create their own art. This second aspect is what biennials are thought to foster. And it is what biennials are thought to foster in their residents: to some extent, this is what the Biennale master plan is about. The Biennale today is a more globalised affair than ever – exhibitions form China, the Middle East and Africa, Europe and Australia, as well as a frequent visitor from the US and Europe – but it retains its distinctive character of being inward-looking, inward-moving and inward-turning. It is an art institution that wants its citizens to be self-sufficient artists, artists not dependent on external resources, and who therefore seeks to control what happens in the city through culture production and consumption. It is an art institution that wants its citizens to be self-sufficient artists, artists not dependent on external resources, and who therefore creates and supports art festivals and biennials in ways that cater to</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the city essentially invest their time in acquiring new artworks; they do not create or invent anything new or different than what is already there. As biennials become more and more institutionalised, the capacity to create and to inhabit new artworks is increasingly limited. In a sense, this is true both of the biennial forms we are discussing: the biennial is the ‘big, bad, ugly boy’ whose arrival heralds the end of an era, while the American antiquarian is the ‘little guy’ whose presence heralds the beginning of a new one. Consequently, biennials have certain particular functions in a particular historical moment. They are a prototypical example of a curatorial strategy that seeks to render the present as past in order to foreground something more recognisable in the future. They are not unique in this strategy, but their formal character makes them different from almost any other form of exhibitionary exhibitionary structure. That is, of course, until someone comes</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the surrounding urban environments reap the benefits but also incur the costs of this infrastructure that supports the biennials. This is a conundrum for those cities that are trying to reinvent the urban, or are trying to create alternative, creative contexts for their cities to exist within. This is a conundrum for those who live there and try to pretend they do not live in it.What might be the answer? It is always the same: more infrastructure, more tax-funded handouts to cities and the suburbs. This is the ‘problem’ that gets addressed and it is always the same: more infrastructure solves the problem but in the end cities and suburbs will always be at risk. This is the dilemma of infrastructure fetishism: the more infrastructure there is, the more infrastructure projects that are needed but are not being funded or supported means less infrastructure can be created. This is the dilemma of infrastructure nationalism: the more infrastructure there is, the less infrastructure produced and the less infrastructure displayed. This is the</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the city, as artists, turn into clients (or, as with cities such as New York and London, artists themselves turn into clients). The city contracts with itself – or rather, it tries to contract with itself – in a very particular way. The city is made up of many interacting parts, each making contributions to the overall whole. But the important point is that each of these parts has its own specific role to play. The art that attends these biennials is made up of many different kinds of artists turning their creative energy into tangible products. The important thing is that the parts that are made up – the different artists’ studios, the curatorial styles, the business models, etc. – are all made up of people with skills, talents, and skills that can be utilised in a unique and dynamic way. This is what biennials are made up of: the people who come to see the art and the people who make it happen. Biennials are places where people</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the city also invest in the art forms that accompany them, in the exchange of culture for art, and in the emergence of new art forms that can be produced and displayed. And this dynamic can shift in unexpected ways. As biennials have become more institutionalised, and as the exchange of culture for art and the urbanisation of cities more extensively funded, the question of how the city is produced and displayed has come to define the very essence of the biennial. The biennial condition is reproduced through what I would call ‘the biennale condition’: the observation and painting of artworks alongside the production and display of artworks in galleries and museums. In Paris, for example, the museum sector is particularly important because it is, in the main, the only sector of the city that is free from the vagaries of economic development and urban turbulence. As a result, the painting of buildings, the accumulation of wealth and culture, and the fetishisation of places – which I will</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the city and the public are drawn to see the art being produced within the city. This is true of cultural institutions, but it is also true of smaller localised projects that are often started by people who have a strong personal connection to the city. For example, there is a project in the Bangladeshi city of Port-au-Prince that is drawing people from all over the city to participate in a cultural festival. These people do not come from the area, but from a neighbouring region. They are coming because they have something to look at. The festival has set up a small museum that will display works by local artists. These people’re coming not to admire the art, but to make something happen and to engage with the art itself. This kind of project is not going to become ‘a museum with permanent exhibitions and installations’, as some curatorial moves suggest, but it will instead become something that draws people into the city and holds them in place as it develops.</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to describe all the elements of the place and to bring out the full range of human emotions. This is a place of its own, its own imagination, and it is a place where the inhabitants can be creative and imaginative and still remain within its parameters. The question is, can the inhabitants be creative enough to inhabit these creative spaces and allow the place – the city in this case – to exist within them? The answer to this is a resounding yes. In fact, the more creative the city becomes, the more inhabitants the city becomes and the more the city is encompassed within the architecture of the city, the more the city is the outer world. This is the second aspect of the ‘biennial condition’: the more we invest in the art forms that accompany these huge art exhibitions, the more we inhabit these art forms and thereby become immersed in them, the more art is produced and the more art is displayed. In the case of biennials, the inhabitants of the place create the art and the art is displayed, and this creates a feedback loop that works both ways: the more art there is to be seen, the more art there is to be bought, traded, consumed and so forth. The ‘exhibition market’ in these contexts is a powerful tool, and the more biennials there are, the more art is produced and the more art displayed, the more money is raised and the more possibilities for self-expression abound. And perhaps the most exciting aspect of this whole concept is that it is possible to create your own biennial. Just think of it as a proto-biennial: a concept that has been around for a while, but has never really been well-developed or fully realised. The important point about this is that it is possible to ‘bring the exhibition out of the biennial’, to create a completely different kind of biennial, one that exhibits the history of art as a whole, or highlights specific</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people in the Basque country, through work such as dance lessons in schools, workshops in the cultural practices of Basque language and culture, concerts in the old national theatre, as well as work in the film, television and art publicity of the region. The Basque Arts Centre was founded in 1986 and its activities continue to be funded by the Scottish and Scottish-based Charts to show Initiative for a Better Basque future (2001–2011) through to the creation of a worldwide network of Basque Basque Basque Foundation (2007–2013). The Basque Basque Foundation was established in 2013 to carry on the organisation’s work in the Basque Country and abroad. The Basque Basque Foundation is a non-profit organisation whose work includes research, education and advocacy on the region’s most pressing cultural and historic issues. It also develops and organises a global network of Basque cultural institutions,</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people; whilst Glasgow Art and Design has a range of educational programmes for artists, designers and the public, including the commissioning of projects by the Arts Council, the Educating Women program, which provides support for arts education in schools, and The Bacigaullecas por la Revolucion’s Becoming Artists program, which provides artistic and creative agency to young people during artist’s residency. The Educating Women programme involves artists’ organisations providing artistic or creative agency to pregnant or breastfeeding women or their partners or others with whom they’ve had sexual contact, or to those who’ve engaged in activities that could elevation such activities to violence against women, or to those in communities or organisations whose workers may have engaged in, or are complicit in, such activities. The commissioning of projects by the Arts Council and the Basque Arts Centre is a collaborative process that involves the involvement</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people through curating, education programmes, work-in-place programmes and public events. Our work with  youth groups has focused on the intersections of disability, identity and participation, and the politics of inclusion and political engagement. In addition to the Basque Arts Centre, we have collaborated with the Puerto Rendon Project, a community based creative agency specialised in design and architecture for projects in the Puerto Rendon, including the Constructive Thinking Architects blogspot. We have also collaborated with the Elitóstico of Culiacán, who is developing a new generation of cultural centres in the city. The project, Partagas con vivir, is a public participatory project that seeks to create a biennale that is as ecologically sustainable as possible. The challenges for the project have included the need to develop a sustainable source of funding, to be able to consult widely and transparently, and to be able to engage with the city in many</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people, particularly through programmes funded by the Scottish Arts Council. In 2010 the Arts Council established a partnership with the Scottish Humanist Association to launch a two-year research project into the lives and practices of the Basque community. The project, entitled Projections,2Sevrespora, is a collaboration between the Arts Council, Glasgow School of Art, and N.E.A.A. (National Council of the Armenian Arts and Alternative Achievement Authority), an organisation formed in 1960 to oversee and supervise the activities of the Armenian National Arts Centre. The project was co-ordinated by the Arts Council and the Department of Culture, Media and Sport, with the involvement of the Scottish Humanist Association, Glasgow School of Art and N.E.A.A. The project was published in 2011 and is the subject of a re-opening conference.The Armenian National Arts Centre was established in 1914 in Istanbul and Istanbul’s Armenian Patriarchate. Since its foundation, its activities have expanded to</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people through advertisements, events, publications and events; and the provision of specialist arts education and interpretative work to local communities.2 The Basque Arts Centre is run by artist Pilar Heras and her team. They have a long-term interest in the Basque cultural landscape and have worked with her on several projects, including on the cover of Chronica books in 2006 and again in 2013, when she was a regular participant in the Basque Arts Festival in Lisbon. Pilar directs the company’s programming and is an integral part of its decision-making. She is an active participant in the Basque community and has staged numerous community artworks in the Basque Country, as well as internationally. She is a founding partner of the Basque Arts Centre, and together with Marina Barzinaga they have been directors since 2014.3 The Chirality Arts Centre is a not-for-profit cultural organisation founded in</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people in the Basque Country, including through work with young people at Daxulubee Children’s Museum, where the artist Marian Jurriajo worked with local artists to commission new works for the museum, and through the commissioning of a new museum-level collection for the artist’s studio. In 2014, Glasgow Art Biennale commissioned Katharine Kerr and Scot Lang to curate a new generation of Art Space buildings in the city, which they hoped would provide a permanent counterpoint to the decline of the historic gallery culture in the neighbourhood. The Biennale was co-curated by Ruth Stewart, with Lisa Roper, Ruth Stewart, Lesley Stewart and Paul Taylor. The two-year programme saw the commissioning of more than 200 public and private gifts, large and small, of art, architecture, heritage and community design, as well as the commissioning</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people, in particular through participatory methods; as well as research into contemporary culture and social development.[1] The Chirality Arts Centre is a bilingual arts organisation that engages with the complex needs and interests of the local community through art, design, practice and teaching. It was founded in 1914 by the Spanish-speaking residents of Santa Fe, New Mexico, and is a non-profit public organisation whose mission is to promote cultural activities in Santa Fe County through arts education and outreach. The Chirality Arts Centre was formed in 1983 with the Crema Arts Centre, a former art institution in Santa Fe that housed a children’s art and animation studio. In 2014, the Chirality Arts Centre opened a new studio for animation in the Art Basel, Santa Fe, and collaborated with the Santa Fe Museum of Art, the National Gallery and Glasgow, which resulted in the Chirality Arts Centre being renamed the Chirality Arts &amp;</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people; as well as research and writing on a wide range of social and political issues. The company was established as a partnership between The Chirality and BTB HMR and is led by artist duo Luis Gil and Marijke Steedman.In 2014, the company opened The Chirality Store, an independent arts and cultural enterprise that offers a range of products, including handmade gifts, home décor and artwork, to the public. The Chirality Store is a project of the Satyavintse Community Arts Centre, which is run by Marijke Steedman and Luis Gil.In 2015, The Chirality was named as one of ten 'Top 100 Emerging Community Arts Companies' by the Community Arts Association, and in 2016, the UK Government’s Culture Secretary selected Community Arts Scotland as a 'Tier 2 Provider' for the Creative Cities Challenge Grant. In 2017, the pair opened</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people and their families, through events including the Fiesta de Chile, a bilingual arts event for young people organised by the Chilean National Day Museum, and the promotion and instruction of Basque culture and language through research projects in Ch’ol. The Biennale was curated by Rafico Ruiz, and Daniela Ginsburg, with additional curatorial contributions from Mariano Contreras, Joaquín Duarte, Andrés Jiménez-Llavecchino, Christina Fernández Pascual and many others. The company has also co-curated the Biennale of International Exhibitions (2011-2016), which took place in Santiago, Chile.Rafico Ruiz and Daniela Ginsburg, Biennale of International Exhibitions (2011-2016), Santiago, Chile. Courtesy BiennaleSantiago Biennale. Images courtesy of Bi</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s Cooperative

Glasgow Art and Design Company has been formed in 2002 with the mission to foster community involvement in art and to encourage innovative approaches to quality of life through cooperative art-learning practices. The company has collaborated with the local area arts organisations, including: The Chirality, who run Chirality Arts Centre, where we have run projects such as The Day of the Long Blond (2010), when the artist and the community worked together to design a community-owned bread co-operative, which is run as a co-operative bakery co-operative by the local community; The Basque Arts Centre, run by the Bacigaulecas por la Revolucion, an organisation whose work in the Basque Country includes the installation of new artworks in the old Cadiz museum. The Basque Arts Centre is a non-profit organisation whose work includes development and promotion of cultural experiences for young people, particularly through concerts, which draw young people to the art, dance, literature and other cultural activities. They have also worked with local schools, community centres, youth clubs and youth outreach agencies to create art and culture partnerships.Glasgow Art Biennale 2016 – Photos from the BiennaleStage 4 – Arrivals and Exits, Birkenhead, 8 October 2016. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextGlasgow Art Biennale 2016 – Photos from the BiennaleStage 4 – Arrivals and Exits, Birkenhead, 8 October 2016. Photo: Tom Lox.The BiennaleStage 4 was a four-day event on 8 and 9 October 2016, curated by Caroline Christov-Bakargiev and Michael Parkinson. The main exhibition was on the occasion of the 10th Istanbul Biennale, and the 11th Kampala Biennale (both now closed) by the same curators. There were</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer work, David Harvey provides an overview of the history of modern urbanisation, focusing particularly on the role of the architect-general, Ernst Haeckel, whose job it is to oversee all aspects of the “new urbanisation” that is sweeping across the globe. Harvey narrates Haeckel’s decision to put off the day when the city would be managed as an industry, but with the advent of transnational transnational financial networks that could lay claim to any infrastructure, the “designer” has come to see his role moving away from those who design infrastructure to those who manage its use. In the words of another, ‘the decline of the giant does not necessarily follow the fall of the giant; rather, it follows the decline of the large enough to manage it, and the rise of the microchip’.[4]Building Codes: The Architecture of the Future City 	[1] Future City Initiative, David Harvey (New York:</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer work, David Harvey provides a historical overview of the ‘habituation” problem: the idea that cities are populated continually through the force of habitation is a core belief of many urban theorists and geographic and urban geographers. Urbanity is conceptualised as the ‘expulsion’ of the “inhabitant”.[4] Urban theorists have long known that the problem with cities is an inescapable expropriation of space, time and people. But few have pursued the problem as deeply or metaphorically as Harvey does. In his book Stealing the City: Brutality and Complexity in the Cities of the Global South, he examines the ‘complexity’ of the expropriation of space, focusing particularly on the ‘homelessness’ of the urban poor and the ‘infrastructure degradation’ that results from it. He identifies three ‘classical’ tropes that characterize urban infrastructures: the ‘</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer, more penetrating work on housing, Stephanie Coontz lays out the ‘histories and assumptions of growth’ that underpin urbanisation today. She begins by describing the complex web of values and social categories that underpin human society, and how these interact to create and tear apart those who are not part of them. She then shows how the ecology of cities has contributed to creating what she calls ‘the carceral society’ – the urbanised form that is both variable and final – and how this interaction between ecology and society shapes politics, law, and aesthetics. She concludes by calling for a ‘sustainable society’ that recognises and addresses the ecological crisis. In the twenty-first century, Coontz’s ecological analysis of modern city life marks a crucial point where the city enters into the social and ecological totality. This is crucial as the city is vital for the social but also for the rise of any political or cultural future, and so it is vital for</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer work, but is much more direct and explicit, the designer responds to this question by proposing a set of questions that are intended to underwrite the possibility of future growth: what is the relation between habitation and cities? How are the physical and virtual opposites balanced? What is the relationship between an urban landscape and an island? How is the ‘infrastructure of habitation’ built into the future urban development? What are the transport and communication infrastructures that support ‘habitation’? How are they affected by the ‘infrastructures of information technology’? What are the modes of global habitation? What are the constraints on infrastructural change that render present-value-added urban settlements ‘valueless’? How are the infrastructural values produced and distributed in the context of a future urban development? What is the relationship between habitation and the postindustrial society? How is the infrastructural landscape made</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer work, David Harvey narrates the evolution of homelessness as a problem that emerged in Australia during the 1990s and early 2000s. Harvey is a pioneer in the field of habitation studies and his work is often cited as a catalyst for a new urbanisation agenda in Australia. He argues that the problem was particularly acute in the inner-city and that particular architectural styles and particular architectural approaches contributed to the problem. Harvey concludes by describing the response as one that is both ‘ambiguous and ambiguous’: ‘the ambiguity lies in the fact that it is not clear what the defined problem is, and how to define and manage the problem’.[4]  Acknowledging that there is a gap of unsettled and controversial urban space in Australia, Harvey narrates the history of the ‘right to the city’, and the subsequent need for legislation to define and regulate this space. He argues that the legislation has placed a premium on innovative and adaptive ways of building and managing</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer standing commitment to landscape and urbanity, Ai Weiwei begins her ethnography by describing how the hope of the urbanising public is to be found in ‘the lucky few … those who made it to work every day’ and became ‘professionals’ in the “knowledge economy”. These are the fortunate few who, she says, became ‘cultural mummies’, living in ‘the City as a collection of museums’, and whose stories ‘will live in the myths and folk tales of the future generations … [but] not in the present… because the enterprise crumbled and ceased to be … Nowadays the City is a collection of financial institutions, financial companies, and financial institutions dominate the landscape, while nature is often cited as a rationale for the infrastructure of the metropolis.’[4] But while the ascendance of finance and technology has certainly legitimised the public sphere as an influenceful one, it is important</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer work, but with a geopolitical bent, the biennale’s designers explain that the ‘main thrust of the exhibition was to demonstrate the futility of attempts to magically conjure up ‘future urban forms’.[4] They go on to suggest that the derelict urban centres around them are themselves capable of forming ‘positive futures’ through a combination of ‘deepened access to knowledge and skills[5] and the development of resilient ‘backbone infrastructure’.[6] This last part is key. The biennale’s current trajectory is the direct result of numerous federal, state and local governments enacting multiple avatar models of the city – big and small – that all too often live in tension with one another. As the biennale’s popularity continues to grow, so does its demand for ‘experience points’ and ‘libraries of last resort’. Such spectacular experiences are now the exception rather than</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer work, this essay draws attention to the persistent ‘problem of indeterminacy’ through a comparison of three contemporary American cities: New York, San Francisco and Detroit. It suggests that although these three cities’pace-immersive art projects may have sprung directly out of their respective worlds, they are also environments in which ‘institutional and political change may have resulted in new modes of activity and expression’.[4] It is a terrain in which ‘institutional and political imagination[,] transformed by the speed and mobility of innovation, has repeatedly and unpredictably moved.’[5] While the questions raised by the project are interesting and may serve as a reference or a point of departure for further research, it is up to the curatorial and artistic staff to marshal the necessary resources to realize the project at the right pace, with the structure and composition of the development serving as a reference or point of departure. As the essay ends, it’s</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer trajectory, Allison Joyce compares the habitation of the urban space to a “fishing net”, or in the words of another, ‘a circular, metallic disc of sorts, that collects and holds together all the pieces of the once great metropolis’. ‘The net’ serves as a barrier between the once industrial zone and the now ‘urban zone’, an area that is expected to be uninhabitable in the future if uncontrolled growth overwhelms the built environment, but that is also expected to be fertile in the future if the city is managed well.’[4] In a larger perspective, the net is thought to be a form of cultural preserver, keeping pace with changes wrought by changing population densities, urbanisation and new trade routes. For Allison Joyce, the role of the urban net is two-fold. The first is to contain those pieces of the once ‘industrial core’ that are no longer needed in the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project by the artist Ai Weiwei, who curated the exhibition’s opening events. This ‘leap into public space’ invites us to consider a space for discussion and design that is both physical and cultural in its intentions. The exhibition opens with a series of architectural plans that are meant to represent the present and future of the city in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. These plans are carefully considered and emerge as architectural statements that trace the evolution of the city from the pre-historic to the present, in an attempt to ground future urban developments in the present. The series of plans are a response to a question that has dogged architects all along the ‘path of habitation: what is the relation between urbanisation and agriculture?’. In the words of one designer, ‘the “habitant urbanist”” has two options: growth or homelessness.’[3] In an introduction that mirrors the architect’s longer work, but is written in an entirely different language, the author begins by asking what the “habitant urbanist”” thinks about growth.[4] In the words of another, ‘the “habitant urbanist”’, ‘needs a set of skills and knowledge that can be developed through various forms of urbanisation, so that she can begin to imagine alternative futures.’[5] These alternative futures, the author is sure, would address the needs of the city’s habitants – but not in the ways that the author intends. What the author really wants is a set of tools that can be used by others to help them achieve the same aims. In other words, the “habitant urbanist” could be made homeless by the society in which she or he lives, but the society would not put any of its resources towards such a task. Shelter would be a more appropriate response to the city</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe.
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe. The exhibition was also supported by the Pulitzer Center for Cartoon Studies, which has a long-standing joint curatorial relationship with the Times. The three-month programme, the Museum of Modern Art, New York, 1972-74, featured new works by some of the curators, as well as works previously shown in the Museum of Modern Art, Washington, DC. The programme was presented in the exhibition hall of the M, 1972-74. The New York Times magazine re-launched in 1974 under the headline: THE FUTURE WAS HERE (On the cover, a future projection of New York City). The exhibition FUTURE, New York, 1978, was an expansive and provocative exploration of these new technologies, their discontents and the future that awaited them. The magazine ran in several formats, including a book published the following year, with a broad range of essays, a magazine that retailed in a number of</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe. The exhibition sold out in seconds, and the newspaper featured the news on its front page the next day. The New York Times reported that the space of the exhibition – the Chinatown Art Museum – was &quot;shuttered… because of the non-stop stream of new residents, tourists and business travellers arriving from the neighbouring cities&quot;. Chinatown Art Museum was closed for several months, and then re-opened in the spring of 1971. The exhibition itself was moved to the newly renovated Museum of Modern Art, but the closure of the museum seems to have had little effect on the development of the area. The Art Newspaper reported in November 1971 that the closure of the Museum of Modern Art had forced the Museum to make changes in the way it presented its collections, and had even led to the curators of that retrospective to leave the institution. It seems that the Art Newspaper was ahead of its time, and its depiction of the aftermath of the Art Apartment Movement was prophetic. A number of artists and</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe. The exhibition took place at the Henry Ford School of Engineering and Design at Columbia University, in partnership with WM1 and the Columbia Arts Collective. The Henry Ford School of Engineering and Design is a leader in its field and offers advanced degrees in mechanical and aerospace engineering, as well as a full range of graduate and professional education programmes in a culturally relevant setting. The School, founded in 1894, is ranked #1 in its state by the US News &amp; World Report. In 2015, the School became the New School at Columbia University. The Harlem Arts Center is an independent arts organisation established in New York City in 1972 and based in partnership with the Harlem Renaissance Centre. It is a not-for-profit arts organisation that provides educational and cultural programmes in areas of the city close to the central business district. It was founded in 1988 and is a member of the National Arts Centre. The Harlem Renaissance Centre is a not-for-profit cultural organisation established</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe. The exhibition was presented in six parts, with parts one and two from January to June, and parts three and four from October to December 1970. The programme of exhibits continued through January '73, with part one from that year, Dawn Schmitz: Contagions of the City (originally commissioned by WNYC) at the Jewish Federations, part two from the Museum of Modern Art, part three from M.I.T. and part four from the Queens Museum of Technology. In January '74, the W.E.B. Du Bois &amp; Company exhibition was mounted at the Jewish Federations, and in June of that year W.E.B. Du Bois: The Gathering Storm was mounted at the Museum of Modern Art. Throughout this period the volume of the New York Times transferred from its high in the air, its ground, to its New York Institute. The result was a succession</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe. The exhibition reflected the city’s past through the present, whilst proposing new ways of thinking about the city. It was an exercise in democratic participation in the absence of formal power, and as a result was troubled by the appearance of power brokers at both high and low levels, including the presence of tobacco companies, real estate developers, lawyers and many others. It was also deeply suspicious of the growing influence of international financial institutions, particularly in the post-war period, and related to its sense of being displaced by other cities. The exhibition offered many examples of this displacedness, including the &quot;Great Migration&quot; of artists from the New York City gallery culture of the late nineteenth century, the &quot;Migration of Cultures&quot; that took place in the early twentieth century, and the &quot;Migration of Intellectuals’ such as W. E. B. Du Bois and W. E. Lawrence. Both the photographer and the writer Dawn Schmitz</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe. Recent exhibitions at Curtiss &amp; Company include Digest (2011), NOMAD (2011), Curtiss &amp; Company (2011) and the ART event at Dawn Schmitz in 2012. The exhibition was co-curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe and Harold Gettys. The curatorial team includes Anne Kølbæk Iversen, Ewa Hauge, Murilo Senj, Svetlana Boym, Arjun Appadurai, Rebecca Oliver, Emma Schroeder, Michael Adachi and Ingo Heeswijk. The exhibition was curated by Ewa Hauge, Angela Kuftinek, Teresa Pascual Perez, Todd Lowell and John Noll and Wendy Chun Kim. The art events at Curtiss included the </text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe. The exhibition offered a rare and powerful look into the lives and works of artists, often neglected or understudied in the art world, as part of a public curatorial approach. It was not always easy to identify an artist, given the proliferation of biennials and the shifting curatorial posture of the art world, but the tenacity of the New York art scene is undeniable. The tenacity of the art scene in the US is undeniable. The fact that artists often find themselves struggling for inclusion in such a vital and influential art institution as the NYC Museum of Art) is a huge challenge, and it shows in the way in which the art was presented in the exhibition. Some curators were committed to finding an artist for the exhibition, whereas others pulled out all the stops and made an art project as an intervention in the city as a whole. As noted by Curator Ashleigh Sethur, the latter was the last to go, and ‘the Museum was her</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe. The exhibition itself was overseen by Dawn Schmitz, Steve Schwabe and Harold Gettys, and it was produced by Wendy Chun Kim, Steve Schwabe and Dawn Schmitz. The show was also written by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe. The Harlem Arts Center was established in 1970 and is the oldest arts centre in the city. Its current directors include Marge Chevalier, Ella Gibbs, Josephine Lacy and Wendy Chun Kim. The building that became the Chi-A post office in 1887 is now an industrial station for institutional housing, commercial office and massive storage. The building that became the North Street Expressway in 1960 is now the site of the North Fulton Mall, a hybrid malls with multiple storeys) that</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe. The Harlem Arts Center was a local arts organization founded in 1974 and housed in the Museum of Modern Art. The MCA also hosted Silver Spring Arts Festival in 1976 and Museum of Modern Art Photography in 1978. The Harlem Arts Center was a founding partner of the Chaplin Art Center in Yonkers, and has been a partner of the Chaplin Arts Center in Buffalo since 1977. In 2015, the Harlem Arts Center was named one of Time's 100 Most Influential People in the World.In the 1960s and 1970s the art world was captivated by the promise and the potential of computer aided arrangements. Though relatively new to the art canon, computerised arrangements gave the public a new understanding of the world. Their proliferation and globalization coincided with a realignment of cultural power centres: the cultural superhighway in Europe was passing into the purview of national art galleries and the new media of architecture, urban</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist&quot; in the New York Times. The programme, commissioned by the Times, invited invited curators from across the country to explore the history and culture of New York City through a three-month period. The exhibition, which opened on 14 January 1970, was the first in a three-part series. The curators included John Akomfrah or John Akomfrah Sisley, Rafico Ruiz, Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim. In addition to presenting their own work, the curators included Bobby Lee (of Lee &amp; Lee Gallery), Mary Jane Jacob, Mary Jane Jacob and Wendy Chun Kim, as well as Janet Richter and the Harlem Arts Center. The exhibition was curated by Dawn Schmitz and Steve Schwabe, and Harold Gettys and was co-curated by Steve Schwabe. The exhibition was initially presented as a series of videos, but as the years passed, the curators began to introduce guided visitings of particular places and curated trips to particular neighbourhoods. Some of this material was presented in the form of poetry, some of it in the form of performance works. In the case of the videos, the poems addressed personal subjects of concern to the artist, while a few of the performance works incorporated traditional art forms and dance. Some of the material was presented in locations unknown, such as prison or homeless, while other material was presented after the fact, such as during a riot. The aim of the curatorial activity was to experiment with ways of bringing people together in the context of an art exhibition, while the related aim was to observe how art institutions could work with and alongside community groups to address pressing social issues of the day. The curatorial format and the curatorial logic of the exhibition were intended to experiment with the two, yet in different</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is failing on both counts. Each of its fourteenths (2014) and seventies (of which two were in China) was visited by Chinese visitors, but these were transient, transitory affairs dominated by the major museums and the official biennials in Beijing and Shanghai. The number of biennials in China today is much higher than the number of visitors, and the biennials are less present in the cities where the consumption takes place, especially in the countryside. Meanwhile, the number of museums has remained constant, although curators in many cities struggle to find fulfilling work and educational opportunities. The number of museums in a city has increased very much in the past forty years, but there are now over three times as many museums as there were fifty years ago. The biennial must find a way to meet the unprecedented demand for information and culture, in both of which it remains underserved.This may require some creative rehabilitation of what has become a disjointed series of curatorial decrees</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is becoming ever more like other cultural forms it patronises, which is understandable in the current economic climate. But in their increasing privatisation and marketisation, the biennial and its patrons are becoming ever more like other segments of the global itinerary: they are contracting out of their cultural functions, and now even less able to finance them. The cultural tourism industry is in crisis, and its collapse is inevitable. But the biennial that emerged as a result of this crisis is unlikely to survive without investing in cultural infrastructure and in becoming culturally responsive, which is a task that at the very least, it should strive to achieve in the current economic climate. When the economic crunch comes, the biennial will likely need to find new ways to consume culture, and it will probably not be able to find any other market for its cultural products in this new economy. That is, of course, unless a drastic change in the financial sector comes to define the terms of cultural exchange on a global scale.In an ideal</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is becoming ever more like its visitor, the biennial visitor. The biennial is no longer the indispensible gateway into another world, but seeks to find other uses for the architecture it creates. The biennial has become culturally conscious in one form or another, and in all likelihood, will continue to do so. But it is also increasingly necessary in order to function in the long term, and this is why biennials have become rarefactionary in their own right. They are used, but they are also objects of historical interest and value, subject to the whims of the financial sector and its powerful ideologues. And while the biennial may claim to have a cultural significance in its own right, this is but a pretence. Its real and enduring cultural potency resides in its ability to function – to exist, to be constructed, to be shaped, to be bought and sold, to be catered to and against its visitors. Its power derives from the cultural institutions that it creates,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is incapable of achieving either of these goals. Despite the need for its curators to be expert in a multitude of specialized areas, such as geography, geography, geopolitics, economic histories, social histories, art and architecture, biennials generally lack the critical mass or critical mass of critical mass needed to exert lasting influence. This is primarily due to the fact that the biennial is usually so preoccupied with its own self-image and internal logic that it does not pay enough attention to the larger cultural landscape it is creating. Indeed, biennials tend to produce and exacerbate existing cultural trends rather than contributing to their demise, due to their often deceptively simple and powerful ways of presenting facts and figures. Therefore it is easy to understand why there is an explosion of creative thinking regarding travel, culture and geopolitics in the wake of a biennial, as opposed to engaging with the cultural situation and the current situation in the region. It is also a great pity that biennials rarely engage with</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is incapable of fulfilling either of these obligations in its current form. The biennial as a visitor is being trained to a mode of exchange that does not require it to produce cultural products or transform cultural practices on the world stage. The biennial is more and more like a consumer, captivated by the latest fad and enticed by the latest bargains, which is becoming more and more imperative as new fads and bargains appear out of nowhere. The biennial is now a museum, and its mission is cultural circulation. The biennial is an institution that can no longer be counted on to produce culturally responsive exhibitions. It is becoming increasingly evident that curatorial and educational curating is the new nexus in which exchange and exchange value are actively produced and reproduced. Curators, artists, teachers, architects, architects – they are the exchanges and the producers of exchange. They are the locus of culture warriors, cultural geographers, cultural geographers of every description. They are the exchanges of ideas,</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is failing in both of these ways. It is becoming increasingly apparent that the biennial is neither a cultural institution nor a biennial, but rather a transactional industry that requires both institutional and transnational legitimacy to function. The biennial is failing because it cannot find visitors willing to foot the bill for its institutions. The biennial is failing because it cannot find a global audience willing to foot the bill for its educational curricula. The biennial is failing because it is not global in scope and therefore cannot fulfil its potential via the given number of exhibitions. The biennial has global ambitions but lacks the power to impact change on a global scale.The biennial is a limited institution. Its potential is mitigated in part by the fact that it is so rare in contemporary art today, save for a few notable exceptions, to come with a programmatic agenda beyond the immediate interests of the art institution. The biennial is thus seen by its contemporary practitioners as an opportunity to shift the terms of cultural consumption and</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is being directed at the financial sector, and in this direction. The biennial is being funded on the back of a globalised transient art market, and these visitors are being recruited into a globalised transient art market by virtue of their being multiples of the size of the major museums. The biennial is being created with the transient in mind, and its tourism may yet one day be fully captured and returned to its birthplace in the traditional sense. But in its current form, it is becoming ever more evident that the biennial is being created for the transient, and not for the transient's needs. In other words, the biennial may one day return to the historical form of the museum, but its current form may not.The biennial as transitory, transientArt world biennials have a particular historical and contemporary set of relations, yet they are not immutable. Artworlds are often born of temporary, transient phenomena, some of them arising from the biennial itself. The relation between</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is failing on both counts. It is difficult to imagine how the Venice Biennale, which began as a cultural exchange initiative of the city's arts community and was later rebranded as the city’s biennale, could have become a biennial with the same level of cultural impact and systemic change had it been founded in Venice in the early 20th century. The biennial must assume cultural competencies that exist today, and engage with the world through those same cultural channels today. The biennial must also assume the social and economic conditions necessary for a social and economic future for its communities. The biennial must assume the cultural resources necessary for a culturally responsive art-historical society. All of these elements are becoming ever more scarce in the globalised capitalist economy. The biennial must adopt a culture of exchange today, or risk becoming culturally redundant.In order to achieve these co-occurrence criteria, the biennial must be able to govern its resources and even its own cultural parameters.</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is becoming more like every other museum and learning more like every other institution, which is a good thing in itself. The problem with the biennial is that it is becoming culturally insensitive, and in its tendency to consume culture, it is producing curators who are as likely as any to become culturally responsive themselves. The only way to ensure that the biennial produces a sufficiently large and diverse collection of users is for it to offer a sufficiently extensive, diverse and transient collection of curatorial practices. A biennial can and should choose to engage users in a reciprocal way, but it is the other kind of interaction, that of exchange between users and creators. A biennial that cultivates its user base effectively and continuously is both culturally responsive and will undoubtedly continue to be able to expand and self-brand. The challenge for the future, as biennial culture becomes ever more complex and variable, will be to create experiences that are both ever-transient and always-on.Download this article as PDFSami</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, capable of operating in an ever-expanding global market, may yet inspire genuine creativity within its curators. However, as the biennial tour concluded in Istanbul, the situation was such that the biennial was forced to adopt a package of curatorial priorities and tactics (both domestic and international) that were dictated by the needs and desires of the financial industry.The biennial has an obligation to the public to develop and foster a culture of exchange, and the financial sector has an even greater obligation to the biennial to airdrop funds in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. As biennials become more institutionalised and the financial sector increasingly dominant in worldwide cultural consumption, it is imperative that the biennial is able to respond with the culture of exchange it demands of its visitors. If it is to have any chance of remaining viable in the long term, the biennial must become both culturally responsive and economically self-sufficient. It is evident that the biennial is failing in both ways. It is becoming increasingly apparent that the primary purpose of the biennial is to hold as much currency as possible within the city in exchange for a predetermined set of curatorial and educational priorities. In this situation, the biennial is trapped between a pastiche of past cultural exchange and the demands of the financial sector. The biennial has no choice but to adopt a more globalised and commercialised form in order to meet these multiple demands. It adopts the guise of a major art museum, and begins to look like an art institution operating on a global scale. The biennial biennial is becoming ever more like other art institutions, exhibiting curatorial and educational content in exchange for cultural consumption. Yet the more the biennial exhibits, or more curatorial directions, are taken, the less culture that comes out of this process. The biennial biennial is exhibiting cultural exchange in the most economical way possible: it exploits the exchange it has already created.A tour of the Muse</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve by putting my art on display, but most of all, what am I trying to avoid?Thanks.DDownload this article as PDF2 October 2014To Minerva Downing6 November 2014From:john.podesta@gmail.comTo: michaelschools@gmail.com; nina.halifa@gmail.com; mia-pelosi@yahoo.com; mia.pavlovek@gmail.com; mia.sussman@yahoo.com; mia.williams@yahoo.comSubject: Re: [Re: What would you like to see at U’Mista]Date: Tue, 6 Nov 201412:48:40 +0000Message-ID: &lt;CAE6FiQAA==&amp;:151241104322.10000.10017&gt;20 November 2014From:john.podesta@gmail.comTo: michaelschools@gmail.com, n</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve by becoming a curator? What am I trying to conceal?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?Now, here is the tricky part: what do you value more than what we have in common? What are the shared common goods? How do we determine the value of what we have in common? What would make you want to destroy something?Now, here is the tricky part: what do you value more than what we have in common? What are the shared common goods? How do we determine the value of what we have in common? What would make you want to destroy something?Now, here is the tricky part: what do you value more than what we have in common? What are the shared common goods? How do we determine the value of what we have in common? What would make you want to destroy something?Now, here is the tricky part</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve by working with these people? What do they want from me?What do you want from me?These are the kinds of questions that institutions now ask young people, and many of us in the curatorial mix don’t have the answers. Sometimes the institutions don’t even have the questions. What does it feel like to be asked these questions by people who don’t have the answers?How do we collectively create the conditions where these kinds of questions can happen? This is the question that the Liverpool Biennial is trying to answer. We have a collective &quot;under-18&quot; group that works with other groups from the academy, museum, local authority and others to ask these questions face-to-face. Sometimes the questions are very similar, but different people from different institutions ask the same question. Sometimes the questions are very different, but the same question will land in different questions. How do we as young people in the public gallery, the local community and the museum collectively</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve as a participant in this exchange? What am I trying to hide?What do you remember about the past that you want to share with others?For me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared past? What are we trying to create by bringing together contemporary art and traditional past times? I’m interested in how we bring together art and communities to address issues of the day, but I’m also interested in how we create alternative futures through this art. Good news: there are organisations like the Arts Council, the Arts Alliance, the National Theatre and the Historic England Trust that can play a role in this exchange. What I hope to achieve is a kind of collective unconscious that organises the conversation around the past in a way that doesn’t necessarily lead to a future that we as artists or as artists-in-residence can build. What can be done as an Institution is a big part of what I hope to achieve as an artist.The Arts</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve by having a collection of objects? What does it mean to be an institution? What is the relationship between art and architecture? What are the boundaries between the physical and social? What are the limits to what can be done with space?What is ART? What is the relationship between the physical and the social? What is the relationship between culture and architecture? What is the relationship between architecture and the urban environment?What is meant by ‘the urban environment’? What is meant by ‘the urban environment’? When and where in the city?What is meant by ‘the urban environment’? When and where in the city?What is meant by ‘the urban environment’? When and where in the city?What is meant by ‘the urban environment’? When and where in the city?What is meant by ‘the urban environment’? When and where in the city?What is meant by ‘the institutional environment’</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve through this institution? What are its values? What values are shared by the members of an institution?What do you value more than what we have in common? What am I trying to achieve through this institution? What are its values?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are its benefits?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are its objectives?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are its objectives?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are its purposes?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are its objectives?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are its purposes?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are its spaces and its benefits?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are its uses?What do you value more than what we have in common? What am</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve as an institution? What can I teach the most effectively? I’m often asked what the shared common good is. My answer is often the same as the question above: what am I trying to achieve as an institution? What am I trying to teach the most effectively?If you’re trying to teach a particular art form or set of arts practices, you’re probably asking yourself similar questions. I’d also add another: what is the shared common good? What can we as artists teach each other?The answer to both questions is often the same – learn how to do something well, share what you learn, and make something of it. But sometimes the answer is different. I often find myself asking the same question but coming up with radically different answers to different situations. For me, the answer is always the same: what am I trying to achieve as an institution? What can I teach the most effectively?I have a specific question for each of the institutions</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve through this institution? What am I trying to hide? What am I trying to protect? What is it that we as artists create in our heads? What are we trying to hide from the world by pretending we don’t see? What is it that we as students create in our hearts? What are our fears and imperfections as we attempt to put ourselves forward as curators?What do you want from an institution?For me, the answer to this is: I want to see my work in places where I belong. I want to learn about how the arts are made in a particular place and at a particular time. I want to be able to say, ‘That was me years ago’.I want to know how the arts are made in a particular city, and I want to know what it feels like to be part of a curatorial or educational team. I want to know what it feels like to witness a production of the arts as an artist being made in</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve as an institution? What is it that I expect others to do for me?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What am I trying to achieve as an institution? What is it that I expect others to do for me?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What am I trying to achieve as an institution? What is it that I expect others to do for me?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What am I trying to achieve as an institution? What is it that I expect others to do for me?What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What am I trying to achieve as an institution? What is it that I expect others to</text>
    <text>Should Be Curated by an Artist’s GroupThis is a one-stop shop for curatorial questions. There are over 200 curatorial questions on the DBB’s website, and each question provides a clear answer to the curator’s question and a question for the artist to consider. For more information, visit the Curatorial Institute website.What Do You Want Out of an Institution?This is a question that many young people in the UK have. It’s easy for young people to identify with the questions above. What do you want out of an institution? For me, in my role, it’s easy to identify with the questions below. What do you value more than what we have in common? What are the benefits of a shared commitment to the common good?What would make you want to destroy something?This is a difficult one to answer for many reasons, but for me, the answer is always the same: what is the shared common good? What am I trying to achieve as an institution? What is the shared common good? What can we all share? What is the shared common good?What can we do as individuals?  A fundamental tenet of the DBB is that you don’t become an institution unless you’ve had a significant involvement with it at some point. So, every institution that I have been a part of has had a role to play in shaping my narrative, shaping my perceptions of the world, and shaping the narrative of art in the UK. I don’t consider myself an artistic administrator; I consider myself a facilitator, enabling artist’s and other stakeholders to have their voices heard, to be able to develop creative strategies and to be able to change their narratives when they want to. So, every institution that I have been a part of has had a narrative to play in shaping my perceptions of the world, and thus, every project that I have been a part of has had a narrative to play in</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
