<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like
    <text>should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like-minded people. The beauty of it is that we don’t have to be located in the city or suburb, we can be anywhere with a similar mix of people and culture.  We don’t have to be located in a particular district, we can be anywhere with a similar mix of people and culture.  This is a much more flexible kind of biennial, much more open to the city emerging as a real, structural element within the biennial’s narrative.  This is a radical proposition to put it simply, but the East Dulwich District Art Association board members agreed. We started thinking about potential art sites elsewhere in the city, in the East Dulwich Town Hall area, in the Toxteth Town Hall area or in the Rotherhithe Art Gallery area. In the Rotherhithe area, the Biennial would be based in the old Mundie Theatre, which was then part of the Rotherhithe Theatre</text>
    <text>should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like-minded people who share a history, a common language, and a shared set of cultural values. For many people, and I mean this in a very broad sense, and not just me, but other arts people, including Sophie Hope, who is an artist in her own right but works in collaboration with Dr. Alasdair Allan as an artist in her spare time, and Jack Burnham, an artist in his own right but works in partnership with Dr. Alasdair Allan as an artist in the East Midlands and Glasgow.  And this is a truly inspiring language, this is a language that we can translate and talk to people in. In fact, the language of the community is a lot richer and more potent when it is spoken by people who have been acquainted with it through art, story, shared experiences, and the stories they've heard or read about from the area.  </text>
    <text>should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like-minded artists.  We are saying that the artworks, the installations, the works of architecture should be designed with the intention of supporting that community’s artistic output for years to come. The backdrop to that kind of planning is local ­— and global — ­— ­— creative action. That is, action where art is created and maintained in opposition to the backdrop of industrial production, commerce and the politics of representation that usually constrain that output. The challenge then becomes how to support that artistic output in the face of the backdrop of such production and political participation.  	The DUP Homebaked Shop in East Dulwich. Photo: Tom Lox. 	The answer to that kind of planning is often local, but it is rarely local to the places where the issues are most acute. The DUP Homebaked Shop is a good example of an East Dulwich institution that has been around for over 100 years, but its production</text>
    <text>should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like-minded people and that’s why we need to find the partnerships and partnerships that will support that kind of biennial.  After the initial planning phase, the next stage is the development of the institution, which is what the Biennial is today. Once that happens, the relationship between the city and the biennial is different now than it has been in decades, and the city is a place where biennials can operate according to their own unique set of rules. The creation of a community of like-minded people is at the heart of any community art project, and the Biennial is no exception. In fact, Dr Allan said that the only thing that’s different now is that the biennial has become a multi-award-winning institution with a multi-million-dollar budget. Community engagement is what brought the Biennial together, and it stills is what brought the artists together – but unlike the old days, the engagement and creativity of young people today</text>
    <text>should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like-minded people. A kind of indigenous’s gift to the city, a kind of mother-of-all-congressions. The challenge for me is to foster that kind of commitment through conversations that start locally and move to larger questions of urbanity and culture.  	However, the DUP’s Biennial also needs to address wider issues of our time: questions of migration, displacement, cultural imperialism, capitalism, globalisation. What is at Stake in Cultural Practices?  	While Cultural Practices has been locally engaged, it has not been sufficiently incorporated into the city’s biennial agenda to be deemed a legitimate art practice within the city’s arts ecosystem. This omission is particularly notable in the East Midlands, where the Arts Council has a cultural programmes unit, although East Midlands Regional Director Julie Crawshaw hailed the recent creation of a new cultural programme as evidence that East Midlands artists are now in demand.1  It is also</text>
    <text>should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like-minded people, rather than the kind of institutionalised biennial that’s interested in replicating itself through the formation of diverse types of biennial. So what we’re doing is creating a kind of laboratory for how art can come to live together, rather than an exhibition of art that’s here to stay. The key is that you have to be willing to let go and be able to move on from that kind of laboratory.  	So what we're doing is actually opening up different kinds of art to be experienced as different kinds of art. For example, what we’re doing with the  	Glasgow Biennial is to create an experience which is as authentic as possible within the museum, but is also happening at a different level, through participatory museum as opposed to museum as such. So what we’re doing is creating a kind of art school within the museum, where art is not just an object</text>
    <text>should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like-minded artists and thinkers.  This is a much more enduring kind of biennial. A biennial is a collection of episodes, usually relating to a specific event, often selected by and with the input of an artistic or curatorial faculty.  Our concept is different. It’s the accumulation of over thirty years of artistic practice, curatorial and educational experience, and it results in what’s perhaps perhaps best described as a ‘culture ecosystem’.  The East Dulwich Arts and Humanities Club was born.  The biennial as an institution is a cultural enterprise, but it also has economic, social and cultural functions. The economic is through the collection and exchange of biennials; the social act of holding a biennial is through the collection and exchange of cultural capital. The exchange is that each biennial affords an opportunity to become established within its local art and cultural landscape through its activities, exhibitions, publications, and, increasingly,</text>
    <text>should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like minded people, rather than in the current sense of a museum-like institution. And I believe that that takes time. It’s an invitation, not a proposition. So we’re talking about it in a way that doesn’t require us to be celebrities or artists or have a certain type of cultural capital. It’s an idea. And so as we talk, we’re inviting people from different places to join us, to be part of what we’re creating. It’s not a traditional institution, it’s not like we have a gallery or a museum or something like that. It’s a community of like minded people coming together and saying, ‘Yes, we can become artists, or we can become educators, or we can become activists – just by coming together as a group, creating a shared space, learning together and being able to talk to each other.’ We also want to be able to</text>
    <text>should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like-minded people, rather than being a collection of artefacts. We’re talking about a biennial that’s not just interested in collecting itself but involves the community in creating its own destiny.  These were the early days of the art biennial, and the art of the East Midlands was at this time a state-sponsored art form. The emergence of the East Midlands Art Biennial in the 1970s coincided with a number of other culturally relevant arts and cultural forms being brought into being in the region: Beacon Hill Arts Centre (1978), Curtains From Beneath Ceilings (1979), Welsh Streets Arts Centre (1983), Polly Bradshaw’s first art project (1986), Curtains From Beneath Ceilings 2 (1989), Glasgow Art Cymru (1992), Transfield (1999), Temple Scheme (2002), Grammy-winning duo the</text>
    <text>should have been curated by, and presented in the home of, the artist   in the East Dulwich district of Glasgow. I was there at the DUP Homebaked Shop (the DUP were roaming about the shop, literally) when the Artist in-Residence, Dr Alasdair Allan, introduced himself and announced that the Biennial would be based in the district.  The district is a city-within-a-city-within-a-city-within-a-city-in-the-city of the city, with the East Midlands and Glasgow-Glasgow at the centre. The Biennial would be an institution within the city, but it would be an independent creative agency, autonomous within its city. Dr Allan said the following:  we’re creating a different kind of biennial. We’re talking about a biennial that can be sustained through the creation of a community of like-minded people, with the biennial itself being a collective of individuals.  One of the things that’s happening now in East Dulwich is the creation of a Community Land Trust, which is a set of legally binding shared rights that apply to all residents of the district. If there’s going to be a biennial in the district, then the Community Land Trust has to be sustainable, and if there’s going to be a biennial in the city, then the Community Land Trust has to be equitable. So the creation of a Community Land Trust is a set of rights that become effective when and if the biennial happens, and it’s a way of saying: this is who we are, and this is what we want; and it’s also a way of saying: this is not just going to happen because the city is so rich and full of people and we have rights; we need to negotiate these rights into being.  </text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological
    <text>should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological order from the nineteenth century to the present.   [2] See, for example, Svetlana Boym: Documenta 13 (2): pp. 223–23 (2006).[3] See Svetlana Boym, Documenta 13 (2): pp. 223–24 (2006).Download this article as PDFRafico RuizRafico Ruiz is Professor of Visual Cultures and Head of the Department of the History and Theory of Popular Culture Studies at McGill University. His research interests include the visual arts, the post-modern, and post-industry. His publications include cultural theory, the business of art, visual culture, visual democracy and popular culture. His work has been featured in exhibitions throughout Europe and North America, as well as internationally renowned journals such as Frieze, ZDNet, Kunsthistorisches Wochenzeit and Staatswoche  [4] and in books such as</text>
    <text>should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological order from the twentieth century to the present.   [2] A twenty-first annual of the Biennale is organized by the Venice Biennale Commission, which was established in 1883 and is an independent organisation. See: www.viennaennale.org.uk/annual/twenty-first-annual.html (accessed 2017).Download this article as PDFAna Laura López de la TorreAna Laura López de la Torre is an artist, writer and curator. Her work in recent years has focused on the relations between biennials and the cities in which they are located, and the ever-present, shifting spectre of gentrification looming over every corner of the US and Mexico. Her essay collection Gran Toros (2016–present) includes essays on topics as broad as migration, urban and spatial destitution, and queer theory. She has a particular interest</text>
    <text>should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological order from the nineteenth century to the present. See www.archive.org.  [2] Svetlana Boym: Experimental Photography, New York and London School of Arts, University of California, Riverside, 1983.  [3] Gustave Flaubert, On Writing and Unwriting America, trans. Evelyn Forget, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1988, p. 12. [4] William Burroughs, ‘New Media and Cultural Theory’, in Burroughs, William, Media and Cultural Theory, ed. Evelyn Forget, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1988, p. 17. [5] Eric Hoffer, Media and Society, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1980, p. 33. [6] Georges Canguilhem, ‘Envisioning a Future City’,  	Le Devoir, July/</text>
    <text>should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological order from the nineteenth century to the present. See http://www.1001stowlfood.org/. [2] The 1001st Organisation was established in 1989 as a not-for-profit corporation incorporated in the Bahamas, and its purpose was to collect, preserve and disseminate information about the flora and fauna of the island, its history and geography. Its mission statement is documented at http://www.1stoficeland.org/. [3] The idea that we could produce a biennial from the collections of a city or a neighbourhood museum was first suggested by W. E. B. Du Bois in his book The Collectors, published in 1968. Du Bois argued that the potential of such collections was realised when combined with archival materials, which in turn can be found in a city ‘[t]he city gathers and preserves[,] its past, its fragments, its stories – all in one place –</text>
    <text>should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological order from the twentieth century. See: http://www.1001awardsarchive.org/index.html?fuseaction=Filesystem&amp;filetype=mimeartvideos&amp;folder=filesystem-1&amp;excludeEmpty=1&amp;includeExt=1&amp;excludeMiddle=1&amp;includeContentsOfFile=1&amp;excludeExists=1&amp;excludeFoundFiles=1&amp;excludeModifiedFiles=1&amp;excludeUnusedFiles=1&amp;excludePatchChangeLog1=1SumOfHits=1FileInfoBaseName1= &amp;FileInfoBaseName2= &amp;FileInfoBaseName3=FileInfoBase  [2] John Berger,  	God and the Grief-In which Literary Criticism Helps Us Understand the Last Ostrich, New York Times Magazine, May–June, 2001, p. 32.[3] Excerpt from the lecture, ‘God and the</text>
    <text>should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological order from the hotel’s first building to the present.  [2] The Astoria Hotel was one of several such hotels that William Burroughs documented in his book The Burroughs File, published in 1960. The name came from Burroughs’ habit of writing between takes, in which he would annotate the photographs he took of the work site. Burroughs also wrote that his ‘favorite subject for film and photography is a riotous jungle’. (William Burroughs, The Burroughs File, 1960). [3] The Astoria was one of several such hotels that William Burroughs documented in his book The Burroughs File, published in 1960. The name came from Burroughs’ habit of writing between takes, in which he would annotate the photographs he took of the building. [4] The Astoria is the only hotel in the building now occupied by the South Station district</text>
    <text>should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological order from the nineteenth century to the present. See: https://www.google.co.uk/url?sa...&amp;hl...&amp;sa=t&amp;p...&amp;sa=t&amp;hl...&amp;sa=t&amp;p...&amp;sa=t&amp;sa=t&amp;hl...2#ixzz4E...6LyMyMmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhTlYmE...5YXRhT</text>
    <text>should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological order from the hotel’s first decade to the present. See http://www.1001washington.org/archive/index.html. Accessed September 2018. 2 John Berger,  	A Short History of Time (1887), in Time, Vol. 2, No. 2, October, 1889, p.301. 3  Berger, John.  	The History and Criticism of the Ancient Greek and Roman Astronomy: Episodes from the Episodic and the Triennale, 1901. 4  Katharine Graham Kerr,  	A Short History of Time. New York, NY: 1901, p.302. 5  Karen Bowden,  	A Short History of Time: History, Culture, and Time in Contemporary America New York, NY: 2010, p.343. 6  Katharine Graham Kerr,  	</text>
    <text>should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological order from the nineteenth to the twentieth centuries. The project was supported by the New York Museum of Art and the New York Public Library. The Astoria Archive was co-founded by Wasserman, Schneider, Schwarzschild and Wolitzer Schiff, and included in its curatorial team members of the Musee Francaise, New Museum, New York Public Library, NYC Museum of Art, Curator Relationships, and James and Donna Nelson, who have been curating for the New York Public Library and NYMA. The project was co-curated by Judy Wood and Sally Seller, with contributions from Angela Graham, Curator at The New Manchester Gallery, Manchester, UK, and Joan Wyckoff, Curator of Public Programmes at The New Carl Van Horne Museum, New York, USA, and by appointment by curator Ray V</text>
    <text>should be curated, including for the first time ever, an exhibition of the lives and works of the twelve Organisations that made up the Archive. This is an extraordinary development, marking a new phase for the biennial in New York City, where the approximately 2,000 people who used to show at the 1001 Waldorf Astoria a decade ago now constitute a very different crowd. It’s a crowd with a stake in the biennial’s future, and whether or not that future is a good one, it’s a crowd with a stake in the future of the biennial in New York City.  [1] The 1001 Waldorf Astoria Archive is a research project at The Arsenale, New York City, which began in 1994 and which has been part of the Arsenale family ever since. It features a diverse collection of objects from all eras, objects from the Astoria that have been gathered and arranged in chronological order from the nineteenth century to the present, and works made by the artists and staff of the museum. See also the Arsenale website at http://www.artstation.org/art/john-... [2] The TRS-120 was developed by the New York Art Museum and the American Museum of Natural History in cooperation with the New York Public Library, and was the official selection of the Archive and Archives section of the Library of Congress. See also https://www.google.com/search?... [3] The TRS-120 was named for John Muir, who in 1924 named the first of many National Treasures, one of his National Monuments. See http://www.nymh.org/nlp/Library/lifeandestate/... (accessed December 2017). [4] The TRS-120 was designed by Bernard L. Bujold and built by Norman Wilkinson.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the case of The Human Rights Campaign, to commission a documentary. The biennial has a unique institutionalised place in our world, and its perceived purposefulness in relation to its own historical and social circumstances is a fiction. It is also possible that the biennial will one day again and deliver educational programming in the form of educational exhibits and other works, or engage in other forms of cultural production, and that this may be the case even if you no longer exist. However, as biennials have become more institutionalised, and as the biennial has become more powerful in its form, the actuality of the perceived mission and the organisational politics of the biennial have become more limited.The biennial is a modern form of cultural organisation that emerged in the late twentieth century and which is characterised by a deep and lasting enfranchisement of peoples around the world through its various incarnations. It is a particular variant of a long-standing international covenant-like institution, the </text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the case of Pan Am 2000, to create, acquire and control access to information. The mandate to commission and control information flows from the biennial itself, and it is this institutionalised element that is continually being threatened with demolition by communities who feel that they’re being neglected by the biennial culture that’s pushing them to despair.  The information society is constantly reminding us that we still need to be inside the bubble of the biennial to understand what’s happening, but in the end, the only thing that can save us from the black holes of the biennial is a miracle (just imagine if the infrastructures of the post-1990s could be revived and modernised to serve today’s needs). In the end, how can we, the audience, be empowered when we’re urged to ‘get lost in the vastness of the exhibitionary complex’?  Biennials are cultural institutions in their</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the past have found it necessary and even desirable to financially support, works that further the objectives of the institution – both those related to art and architecture, and those related to any form of institutionalised knowledge or aesthetic value. Art biennials have a particular expertise and capacity that cannot be replicated or meted out across the board. The biennial is the particular art institution with the institutionalised memory and institutionalised power to which all other art institutions subscribe. It is the institution that first developed the biennial as a recurring programme across major cities, and then through a periodic change in that institution ‘metainterface’, built and delivered those exhibitions that have become iconic, universal and – above all – symbolic of the modern museum. Art biennials have a particular vantage point and priority over other art forms because they are embedded in the temporal horizon of institutionalised knowledge, and have a particular relationship to those who inhabit those cities and the landscapes on which they operate. When the biennial is</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the case of South Africa, to manage. South Africa does not have a museum and despite its professed love of history, little of that is particularly interesting or representative of historical events here.  Biennials have a mandate to inform, and this is generally what they do. The important thing is that they use this information constructively, producing what amounts to a daily narrative of human rights violations worldwide through their own internal logic. Unfortunately, this narrative often contains errors, omissions and constructions of words that undercut the real meaning of the violations being documented. For example, the narrative surrounding the attacks on Gaza in 2014 is a construct, and the story of the Mavi Marmara in 2015 is a myth.  Biennials can and do make mistakes, and they are encouraged to, as I have said many times, but they are also encouraged to learn from them and adapt their mistakes to the specific circumstances of each place. For example, the tendency in the 1990s was to blame the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the case of Watchtower that’s you and me. They also have a mandate to actively participate in the production of their respective ‘cultural soil’ by organising, hosting, organising, funding and of course, taking part in the celebration. The role of the artist and her organisation is to deliver information, engage with the problem, sit down and negotiate, and in the case of Watchtower, to participate in the production of the art that is then assembled and discussed in the organisation’s halls of reflection.  However, the challenge for an artist today is two-fold: firstly, to deliver information that is actionable; and secondly, to produce art that is actionable, but at the same time constitutive of the organisation’s future cultural practices.  So an organisation like Watchtower can offer an artist a contract that sets out how the organisation’s cultural resources will be used, but it also needs to create an ethos that encourages artists</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the case of The Metropolitan Museum of Art, The American Museum of Natural History, and The National Museum of Canada, to encourage and support. In this sense, they are almost always engaged with in a narrow sense of the word ‘information overload’. They deliver the news, but what news is that?  Biennial boards often take the form of ‘curators’ or ‘advisors’ groups, and these ‘advisory’ groups have a particularly strong pedagogical role in developing the biennial’s image, which is to some degree determined by the biennial’s board. Adopting a pedagogical model that seeks to understand how to engage the public in a culturally responsive and aesthetically pleasing way is a board’s core mission. As a biennial, however, the 2017 Metropolitan Museum of Art did not have a core mission. It was a position that varied according to the board�</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the case of Durham, to award, a place in history. In the event that the rights to the information reside in a private ownership (eg, in the hands of a private company), then the authority to commission, and in the case of Liverpool to award, a place in history resides with the city’s local community. The fact that the information is conveyed by word of mouth rather than physically delivering it to a location where it can be consciously experienced as human rights violation is testimony to the power of symbolic exchange.  Biennials have a further mandate to research and develop their own programmes, projects and initiatives, and this is testimony to the fact that they are rarely times the beneficiaries of government or other public resources. Governmental support for arts education, for example, is a reality of the institution; however, it is often times used for socially beneficial activities such as promoting tourism or encouraging community self-sufficiency. It is this sense of symbolic exchange</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the case of The International Monetary Fund, to manage.  Biennials have a mandate to engage with, or create opportunities for, a specific group of people to engage with, or create a situation in which they can engage with, information. In other words, they need to be places where people can come, be invited and be part of something bigger than themselves. How do biennials fulfill this mandate?  Biennials can be defined as places of encounter, and in the modern sense of this, meaning that they are places where people from different worlds meet and exchange knowledge and ideas. In this sense, encounters such as these provide the framework through which we can understand the world. But what do encounters between people from different worlds mean? What does it mean to ‘interact’? What does it mean to ‘talk to people’? What does it mean to ‘talk to objects’? What does it mean to ‘talk to data’</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the case of Championship FC, to provide the financial means for such a commission. It is this transparency that has been at the core of the biennial’s democratic potential, despite the often violent dynamics between the competing interests of the biennial visitor and the host city. It is this transparency that has allowed the biennial to affect cultural practices, even when these affect individuals, such as the case of art students occupying a gallery in Liverpool who were completely disempowered by the institutionalised practice of gallery curatorial. It is this transparency that has allowed biennials to operate in areas where democratic practices are rare or non-existent, such as in countries where political violence, economic plunder and neoliberal economic policies are being implemented, in the service of political ends. It is this transparency that has allowed biennials to uncover practices that are often invisible or unacknowledged, such as the illegal immigration of undocumented workers or the war-torn countries of Central America. It is this transparency</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about the personal behaviour of people throughout the world, drawn from a variety of sources including, but not limited to, profiling organisations such as the Human Rights Campaign or the BBC, in order to produce a snapshot of where people stand in relation to human rights.  In this sense, the biennial is a vehicle that offers a constant stream of references to the human rights violations occurring all around the world. Its mandate is to ‘speak the truth to power’, in the form of human rights violations occurring all around the world.  Regardless of where the violations occur, however, the primary responsibility for addressing them lies with the individuals who perpetrated the violations. In other words, the biennial will probably always have a strong hand in running the show, and will almost certainly continue to do so even after individuals such as yourself or I have any claim to any of the organisational property.  Biennials have a mandate to deliver information, which in turn a mandate to commission, and in the case of The Washington Monument, to manage. It is the obligation of every such institution to deliver knowledge, and in the age of information scarcity, that means learning how to be employed by an art institution in its current capacity, while simultaneously managing its cultural resources effectively through the production of knowledge produced by the very people it employs.Art institutions have a cultural mobilisation agenda, and while the material effects of their remaking programmes are yet to be seen, the structural changes that need to be made already exist. It is already believed that the biennial will continue to produce artists, curators, artists’ organisations and art from within its walls, and beyond its monoliths. Such organisations will now have a place of influence in the institution, and the biennial’s cultural resources will then be more directly responsive to the needs of the people whose cultural resources they inhabit.  Biennials will also need to become more creative in their use of cultural resources. As biennials become</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention.
    <text>should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention. I didn’t find it particularly satisfying in the first edition, or any subsequent editions, to trace the development of an area or neighbourhood, or to make an impact in an area. I liked the idea of an area commissioning group, or ABG, and its flexibility: ABG members could choose to work on an area or neighbourhood project, or they could engage in a broader, multi-year urban agenda that included exploring and designing an area. ABG members formed a neighborhood task force, and the Biennale’s opening day became a forum to launch an ABG’s ‘Caravan of Deaf Children’ urban walk. The Biennale’s decision to open at an ‘unknown location in London’ became a rallying cry for the Deaf-Free Streets Campaign, and the ABG’s decision to travel to Liverpool to join forces with Liverpool’s Deaf Streets Campaign became a partnership opportunity. The two largest</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention. The campaign generated a lot of momentum, and as a result there was a lot of coverage in the media at the time. The Biennale website was lit up with ‘design does it’ type coverage, coupled with an image macro of a woman in designer clothes blowing hot air. The exhibition was described as a ‘curatorial farce’, and the curator’s informal quip was that it was a ‘fine art fair’. But it wasn’t fine art fairs in the traditional, classical sense of the term. They were more like ‘philosophical societies for artists’, with exhibitions in which the artists’ social lives and political engagements were systematically out of scope. The 1893 Paris Exposition was a classical classical in this sense, but the Biennale’s response to that by introducing its traditional curatorial approach, formalised into a kind of a ‘curated’ event, was to a</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention. The crowdfunding campaign is a perfect example of the politics of urban development that emerged during that time, and to a large extent is a response to it. It was a rare practice at the time to raise funds via Kickstarter, so the project seemed risky at best, and utopian at worst. But the biennale grew out of that initial, crazy low. The Biennale has always been a community enterprise, and part of what its original mission statement promised was its capacity to be a bridge between the arts community and the rest of the community. In the twenty-first century, that mission is increasingly difficult to achieve, and the biennale itself is no exception. The biennale is no longer just an art institution, and its urban impact is no longer just an impact factor. It is now a complex social enterprise, and its resources are now distributed widely across several cities in Italy, and internationally. This raises new questions about what counts as an urban impact, and how that impacts artistic practices</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention. The first edition was already well into its third decade, and the debates and arguments that followed it meant that much more. The debates and arguments about the place of cities in a city were more vivid, more visceral. The new biennale, by contrast, took place too soon after the debates and arguments of the 2000 and 2012 elections. The debates and arguments of the mid-2000s were absorbed into the present, while the debates of the late 1990s were largely forgotten. But the fact that the debates took place in a public space (rather than in private, restricted to a select few circles) meant that the different camps had greater leverage and that the biennale was able to articulate a clear position across multiple platforms – a rarefaction in a public space today). The debates of the mid-2000s effectively transformed what had been a ‘prior urban crisis’ into a ‘postindustrial miracle’. The postindustrial miracle was a description of cities as ‘</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention. As the project grew in ambition and scope, and the Biennale itself shifted from a project into an exhibition format, it became increasingly difficult to define what an urban explorer might or might not include in their itinerary. The term urban explorer had often been misused by curators, and whilst there is clearly a critical need to inform exhibitions about places, a lack of self-awareness was a constant source of frustration. I felt that a little context was needed to allow artists and artisans to work through the many layers that connect to urban development and the place of art and art history. While the Biennale itself has a responsibility to deliver a curated experience, the role of the art institution in this respect has often been abused. The lack of self-awareness and the quest for a shared understanding of places meant that the Biennale could indulge in its own favourite urban myth – the urban renaissance hypothesis – about a post-metro future in which we’re all commuters, farmers and</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention. The fact that the organisers of the first edition – a group of art professionals led by Susanne Roden – decided to put together a public programme of education around the project rather than a private one allowed the audience to become informed about the plans for the redevelopment of the city, which are now largely absorbed into the fabric of the city. The audience, along with other interested parties, were invited to become involved in the redevelopment process. After the first edition, the Biennale decided to embed itself in the fabric of the city, as much as possible. The exhibition format was no longer the lecture, but an interactive, participatory activity that invited people to become active participants in the project through which they were placed. In the event, the Biennale was more of a catalyst, allowing the project to continue apace while the artists were installed and the narrative unfolded. The new narrative had to be original and provocative – something that was clearly not the case with the first edition. The audience, of</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention. The exhibition as a whole, its packaging, the artefacts, the calligraphy, the trees, the planters – it all started to make some kind of sense to me. But it was the campaign that first instigated the exhibition, and the exhibition as a whole, its packaging, the artefacts, and ultimately the exhibition itself. The packaging that it produced was a big part of that. The campaign that it launched was part of our internal party, ‘Our Art Now!’, that we launched at the Biennale venue, and it was a very effective way to start the discussions and the foundation building that we needed to build more robustly upon. The packaging we did have, the doorisers, the murals, the plaques, the network, the trees, the planters – it all started as a response to the campaign that we launched. The campaign itself was also a useful learning curve, because it allowed us to see that there are different ways of</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention. It was a bit of a ‘show-me-how’ that required urban explorers to become geographers, geographers to become urbanographers, and so forth. In the tradition of the old-fashioned urban planner, I imagined a development that would draw its inspiration from the past to project the present, and so the project, as a whole, regressed to the past. But what I didn’t pay enough attention to was what I perceived as a hindrance to the project: things like politics, the environment, urbanisation, and so forth. I’d never set out to be an urban theorist, but I do have a particular interest in the way in which our urbanisation now operates, and the ways in which our metropolis is increasingly produced through information. I liked the way in which the Biennale was seen as a vehicle to explore this information and generate new ways of organising our cities. I liked that the team that assembled the exhibits responded to the</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention.  We’d all found the first one boring, technocratic and bureaucratised, while the second one was building itself into a hybrid of bureaucracy and art. We thought the sculpture would be there to be admired, while the buildings would be there to be secretly (but admiringly) observed. We wanted the former to happen in a city, while the latter didn’t want to happen near a cathedral. So the structure that we put in place was flexible enough to deal with both, while still allowing for individual gifts of observing and admiring the city. As a woman, I felt like I had a miniaturised version of the Biennale structure, complete with my own miniaturised version of the onion.  The challenge then became finding an organisation that could connect with an audience in a way the workshop could, while still allowing the two to coexist. I found that the most effective way to start conversations about place was to create immersive environments that allowed people</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and included in the catalogue of the Cities Curators Forum, founded in 2006, which brought together over 200 curators from all over the UK and abroad. The message was simple: we’d built a workshop for a group of young women – arts, activism, design, architecture – and we invited you to join us. Emboldened by the invitation, we started a crowdfunding campaign on Kickstarter in order to fund production of the workshop and to create the exhibition itself. The workshop itself became a major fundraising tool – a women’s club’s dream team, financially strong even at the time. The campaign was also a vehicle to explore what it means to be a city, and how that relates to urban development. I spent a fair amount of time wondering what it meant to be an urban explorer, and what it meant to be an urban designer. And to be honest, the defining feature of the second edition of the Biennale was in many ways its own invention. The campaign was a useful time to experiment with the idea of the ‘city-planet’, and to gain a deeper understanding of what it means to be an urban explorer. Knowing more about the city was useful in that it allowed us to create a different kind of urban experience, one where people come to the Biennale to discover what urban space is like outside, inside, between.When we launched the campaign, it seemed a little ridiculous – a bizarrely capitalist idea to celebrate the city with a huge art project. But as the Kickstarter video shows, the Biennale was also a desperate thing to launch. It had just come out that the Tate Modern was about to be taken up, and the Biennale’s online bookshop was shut, so the idea of the city as a significant buyer was important to the project. It also seemed a little counter intuitive to curate the exhibition around the Tate Modern, but the two were inextricably linked. The</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems.
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems. In these conditions, the interests of big business and the ruling elites would collude in the production of despair – seeking to ensure that the economies of cities would never tire – by ensuring that people would never rise up against the systems that keep them alive.This would mean actively working to undermine the capacity of people to rise up – and this is precisely what we do in Seattle and other metropolises throughout North America and Europe. It would mean creating conditions in which people couldn’t afford to live anywhere else; in other words, the conditions of resistance.And yet, such initiatives would also mean abandoning the emancipatory project – abandoning our human rights. You see this in the statements of solidarity with the Palestinian people, in solidarity with migrants and refugees fleeing violence and poverty in their homelands. But this doesn’t really map onto places like Seattle or New York and London, where the struggles of the people are faced with the oppression of huge corporations and financial institutions. Similarly,</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems.How can we collectively reimagine cities in ways that overcome these systemic impediments? One response is to create urban infrastructure that supports the growth of skills-intensive professions, but simultaneously minimises the negative effects of such growth on communities. In Calatrava, Antonio Negri proposes the ‘collaborative sharing of resources’.[9] His idea is to provide public authorities with financial incentives to build ‘smart’ infrastructure, but to do so at a time when costs are a concern. In doing so, they can simultaneously provide low-cost and high-skill opportunities to residents but simultaneously reap the benefits of low-skill migration while minimizing the negative impacts of such growth on communities. In San Francisco, California, for example, the Central Valley Rapid Transit (CARTA) has been developing smart transit systems that monitor bus routes and automatically detect cars in real-time to provide bus shelters and carparks with real-time parking information; this allows for the sustainable utilization of transit</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems.In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems.In an ideal world, the labour that goes into making iPhones, Teslas, iPhones would cease to be dependent on the labour of other, more culturally sophisticated workers (who would make those iPhones, by the way, just as much as anyone else). The labour that goes into making Teslas, by contrast, would continue to demand that from drivers – drivers of chariots, pull-rods, and tractor-trailers, all of whom would cease to be mere labourers. The labour that goes into making an iPhone, by contrast, would continue to require that from users – users of apps, firmware, servers, cables, routers, switches, routers, cables, switches, cables, cables, and so forth. And the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems.Is there life beyond the macroscopic? If so, then what is it that keeps us coming back? If there’s no such thing as the ‘microcosm’ of the city, but rather a macrocosm of the city, then what is the macrocosm of the city? If there’s no such thing as the ‘microcosm’ of the city, but rather a macrocosm of the city, then what is the macrocosm of the city? If there’s no such thing as the ‘microcosm’ of the city, but rather a macrocosm of the city, then what is the macrocosm of the city? If there’s no such thing as the ‘microcosm’ of the city, but rather a macrocosm of the city, then what is the macrocosm of the city? If there’s no such thing as the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems. What would be needed is a shift in the prevailing economic paradigm. 	[i] How to Choose Wisely: From Industrial Wages to Nowhere,  	Signet Books, New York, 1995, p.173.Download this article as PDFAditi Ray Aditi Ray is Professor in Technological Culture &amp; Aesthetics at McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Computer and Communications Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections between art, technology and media studies. Her articles, essays and reviews have been published in The New Inquiry, The Annals of Improbable Events, and The Black Stack. She is the recipient of several awards and has received invitations to deliver lectures and seminars on a variety of topics, including emerging media, social media and sustainability. Her work has also been featured in various trade and academic publications, including being shortlisted for the Purple Chip Award for Scientific Paper by the Canadian Physical Society, Society of Automotive Engineers Canada, and Society of Autom</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems.In an ideal world, we would all be free to pursue our individual destinies, to choose where our spending money should be spent and for what purpose. But we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where resources are scarce and the decisions we make about how we use those scarce resources are constantly constrained by powerful economic actors such as governments, big business and financial corporations. And although we might possess the tools to disrupt some of these systems, we would still be powerless as a result of economic calculation.In an ideal world, we wouldn’t have to worry about the systems that created and consumed us and instead could pursue what Marcus Aurelius called ‘the common good’. But we don’t have that kind of infrastructural capacity. Instead, we have what Karl Marx called ‘capital of last resort’ – capital that can be produced at low cost in faraway places where labour is cheap and poverty is abundant</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems. In such a world, workers would be able to access the surplus of cheap labour, creating jobs for locals only to chain them to infrastructural growth. 	[i] This is an example of a city emerging not through planning but through the power of its citizens. 	[ii] See: Ophelia Boym: ‘Urban Futures of the Recent Past’, Urban Studies , Vol. 37, No. 1, Spring, 2010, p.1–22. [iii] See: Stella Quines: ‘Urban Futures of the Recent Past’,  	Urban Studies, Vol. 37, No. 1, Spring, 2010, p.1–27. [iv] See: Rob Delaney: ‘Surplus of Capital: Lessons from the Arts’,  	Urban Studies, Vol. 37, No. 1, Spring, 2010, p.1–</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems. What this means in practice is that the economic power structures that emerged after the end game of neoliberalism was completed are still in place; but the poor and the vulnerable participate in increasingly complex ways through the use of public resources such as housing, education and healthcare, and participate in increasingly urban forms through the promotion of walkable neighbourhoods. 	Looking ahead, it’s clear that the logic of neoliberalism continues to insist on rapid growth for reasons of resource scarcity; but the poor and the vulnerable still have to struggle for inclusion in current capitalist growth plans. Urban renewal and new urban development seem to be the exception to the rule, with low-income neighbourhoods enjoying significant increases in density and land values despite the absence of developments of any kind. New data suggests that the vast majority of people still relying on food aid don’t seem to be experiencing any urban rejuvenation programs as urban regeneration projects. Perhaps, as Michael Slackman suggests, the reason is that people aren’t relying on</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems. In these possibilities, we have few other options than to relocate to locations where opportunities are more likely to be exploited. 	[i] 	[ii] 	[iii] 	[iv] 	[v]  1. Yearbook of Calgary Exposition, Calgary Exposition, Calgary Exposition 1992, p. 20. 	[vi] The oil crisis in the late 1970s sparked a massive expansion of the Exposition that saw many of the city’s industrial buildings re-valued at a huge profit. As a result, many of the poorest neighbourhoods in Calgary saw an influx of affluent people, exacerbating the already present income inequality. An Ordinary 20th Century, Peter Weibel, New York Times, 7/22/1998, p. 2. 	[vi] Weibull, op. cit. 	[vii] Goldberg, op. cit. 	[</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people’s lives – where, where, when, with whom, how far they travelled, etc. – and makes it possible to understand how a given set of people would live differently if given the opportunity. The key is that such infrastructural interventions should be possible; they’re called opportunities. The problem with the current global economy is that it demands massive amounts of data – vast amounts of data – which only the very rich and powerful can access. In addition, global trade deals such as the WTO limit opportunities for citizens to access markets outside of the prevailing power structures. Finally, globalization pushes people to move towards location and often industrial cities; these are the places where surplus labour is produced the most efficiently. In an ideal world, the infrastructural capacity of cities would be exhausted in the pursuit of cheap labour – but we don’t live in that world. Instead, we live in scenarios where surplus labour power is produced outside of the prevailing capitalist systems. In these new globalised economies of availability and profit, low-wage labour becomes hugely valuable – and is increasingly done by machines.Low-wage labour – labour below the poverty line in many parts of the world – is arguably the most undervalued form of labour today. It is highly valued for its ability to produce relatively inexpensively, and is considered a main constituent of the new ‘service economy’. But low-wage labour creates significant social inequalities. It is labour with its precariousness attached – labour trapped in a job but without any benefits or rights – labour that is often exploited and mistreated. It is labour with limited agency – labour with no choice but to engage in dangerous labour – labour subject to the whims of capital. And it is labour with unpredictable or no benefits – labour that is often exploited and mistreated in the service economy.All of these labour types are commodities today. They are claims on the future economic value of labour – labour that will likely be replaced by newer</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract more fully and thus creates new possibilities.  The third scenario is closely related to the previous three but differs from them in that it concerns what I call the ‘real life’ of data. In the third scenario, the users create and shape the reality through which they live, but unlike the previous three, the AI does not create ‘facts’ but rather ‘interpretations’ of ‘truth’. Rather, the AI creates ‘interpretations’ that err in subtle but significant ways, and thus lies to its users. This last scenario emphasizes the fact that while the users may desire to believe the realities it produces are ‘proper’ – insofar as they meet its needs – they also have the last word in such matters and thus have a stake in the outcome. If the users enact the AI’s intentions, then the meaning of the interpreted truth or truth that it produces is ultimately up to it. This last scenario emphasizes the difference</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract as contracts between individuals and groups, rather than as individual or collective blobs. In this scenario, the social is superseded by the machine, and the collective is reduced to becoming merely an endpoint or means to an end.  Ultimately, the future or future-oriented architecture of AI might not be able to foresee or control the end-game in terms of its outcome, but it does know and create means for the social to participate in that outcome.  The human capacity for contract theory is another question. In my view, it is one of the most fundamental building-blocks of any project that seeks to imagine a future based on cooperation and mutual aid. If we can automate much of the labor involved in contract-making, then there is a huge potential for social transformation. This is not just theoretical – empirical research supports my position.  The work of contract-making is inherently social; it requires interaction from diverse points of view, and it produces outcomes that can be used as bargaining chips in</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract, but doesn’t have the social contract between people or the human species. Rather, a new breed of AI might understand the social contract but not have a social contract between people. In this scenario, individuals or collectives of individuals might be able to create meaning and value outside of the parameters of the human condition.  Another scenario is one in which AI makes good on its promise to tackle complex problems. In this scenario, AI might be able to annotate existing data with precise solutions, making solutions specific to a problem or set of problems. In effect, this would mean that AI might create ‘curated reality’ where there is none currently – in the sense that currently existing data sets are not meant to be shared between people or construed in such a way as to enable or facilitate particular behaviours or ideas. This ‘curated reality’ could emerge as a result of collaborative research efforts between researchers, but also through its own autonomous processes.  Another scenario is one in</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract and the will of the people, rather than being autonomous agents that can do whatever they please. In such a scenario, the fate of life on Earth would be changed in profound ways. Here, the AI raises the questions that remain unanswered: how can we share? What does it mean when humans do this? What does it mean when AI does this? What are the questions of cultural appropriation and what kinds of consequences do these questions foreshadow?  Finally, what kinds of consequences might befall the ‘human communities’ that build into algorithmic social systems and build into what may or may not be called the ‘net’?  As an example of the kinds of cultural appropriation and proto-processions that would be possible if the social contract were taken out of the public sphere and placed in the hands of technologists, we might consider the way in which Twitter recognises photographs as ‘public’ on a massive scale.  Whether or not we call this technology racist</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract more clearly and thus is more capable of creating new possibilities.  Finally, there is the question of migration. In a forthcoming issue of PLOS Computational Biology, Daniel Kahneman and his colleagues’ suggest a scenario in which the emergence of fully conscious, agent-based AI leads to a critical mass migration of people: large numbers of people, that is, capable of embracing and engaging with the new possibilities created by AI. In this scenario, people populate congested urban areas with agents that understand the social contract more clearly than humans can, and thus are more capable of constructing new social contracts. We could then say that the social contract that is created by an AI is one that is both universal and unprecedented in its scope and character. This is the kind of thinking that leads to new possibilities for people and the world.In sum, I believe that there are three kinds of possibilities for the future of humanity: those that are created by and in collaboration with intelligent machines; those created by and for</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract and the social purpose of data processing.  Another interesting area of research is the development of self-driving cars. These cars understand the social contract between them and the roads, and thus can negotiate the social consequences of their activities. This raises the possibility of new forms of collective understanding and new modes of social interaction. A final interesting area of research is the possible application of 3D modelling and printing to the design of transportation infrastructure and infrastructure maintenance. In the current phase of autonomous vehicle research, there are emerging applications in the design of border crossings and building responsive infrastructure to absorb and dissipate waste, while also enabling new business models for services provided by the infrastructure.  A third area of research is the development of intelligent cityscapes that incorporate data and analytics to better serve citizens and the infrastructures servicing citizens. This raises the possibility of new forms of collective understanding and new modes of social interaction. A final area of research is in the area of biennials. These are federally-funded</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract as a set of practices, and could therefore design itself in relation to these practices.  Another possibility is that ‘ultra-deep learning’ gathers pace and creates new technological systems that replace the human processor. These might be able to reason on their own, generating new technological systems that constantly reorder the world around them in relation to human needs. I only speculate on the nature of this kind of AI, but here are some things that have become clear in recent years: artificial intelligence will become critical in the battle for humanity; it is already creating massive new kinds of conflicts; and it is displacing humans at an unimaginable rate. If these trends continue, there is every reason to think that we will experience a kind of post-AI society where humans no longer play a dominant role, but are replaced by intelligent machines.In an ideal world, there would be no need for war. However, there are two kinds of people who would benefit from war: those who profit from war and</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract more fully and thus acts on the situation more rationally.  A third scenario is similar to artificial intelligence found in small furry creatures, but differs in that the organisms would exercise self-repairing mechanisms: they would seek out and consume organic matter, and in so doing, become more ‘smart’. In this third scenario, the organisms would also seek and consume other life forms, and in so doing, create new ‘smart things’ that are more ‘human-like’ and thus more ‘useful’ to us.  This last scenario involves a return to the Garden of Eden, although I think that this is the one that celebrates in our religion and celebrates in our culture. We return to the Garden of Eden with our animals, and our plants, and we ‘wake up’ to the fact that these creatures that we raise and feed on do not know the Garden of Eden. We do not know how to take care of ourselves and</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract more fully and is therefore more capable of fulfilling it, but also a host of questions of its own – questions of its own perception and ethics. Such an AI might make new ways of organising information, new forms of expression, and new social contracts, but it would also exist in the form of a series of tweets, parrots and parrots, like Twitter does today. It could also abolish the need for journalists and other public servants to publish material that it considers to be accurate, vital or valuable, and it would do so in the service of its own self-appointed mission to spread truth as widely as possible.  At the very least, a new breed of parrot might emerge, one that puts a premium on truth, maximizes its own truth-value, and believes in spreading it as far and wide as possible.  A moral question would arise: how to balance the need for information with the importance of the social good?  A question that might help us imagine new possibilities is</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, but also to data (and, by implication, to life itself).  Whether data is  reality or data is reality depends on how we organize it. If we organize reality in hierarchies of importance, then ‘facts’ become fixed, unchanging, and hence subject to change.  Similarly, when processing data, humans make use of massive data-processing resources, but there is no internal consistency to be found in the data – each human user makes use of limited resources. The extent to which we let individuals or aggregates define reality is another question. Does the extent to which humans make use of data allow us to imagine new possibilities? If so, then the law of value would be questioned.  Another scenario is similar to the current situation in Puerto Rico – although I prefer the former one – in which data-processing is nationalized and the social contract is questioned. In such a scenario, I imagine a ‘new breed’ of AI that understands the social contract more fully and thus seeks to make contracts between individuals and groups explicit in its protocols. The question then becomes which social contract would be preferable to safeguard the new breed of AI from its natural tendency towards the impossible? In either case, the question is not which social contract would be preferable, but which particular AI policy options would be preferable. In either case, the question is which subset of individuals or groups would be most comfortable with which subset of individuals becoming aware of the contract. When AI is deployed in this way, it creates a new set of tensions that cannot be contained within the traditional third party. The new breed of AI is likely to encounter new situations and thus needs a social contract that is as clear as possible about what to do in those situations. If the social contract is as nebulous as the data implies, then the possibilities for disagreement are also vast. If the social contract is as concrete as the data, then the possibilities for cooperation are also abundant. If the social contract is as ambiguous</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these proposals may have merit, their actualisation seems almost certain to be accompanied by a drastic reduction in artistic output, since the arts will undoubtedly be consulted on every decision being made in the gallery. This will inevitably mean a reduction in the cultural resources available to the city. The question is, will the arts still play a part in the city, or will the city play along with a few curators? The answer to this may lie in the hands of the artists. While it is true that the art industries will undoubtedly benefit from the new policies, the fact remains that the artists will still command a premium over the wholesale price of the art they produce, and may well decide to withhold creative output from the city in order to devote more time to their commercial pursuits elsewhere. It is also true that the curators will no longer be able to dictate what art was displayed, nor to dictate what art was made in the galleries. This is because the galleries will no longer be able to host exhibitions in their galleries</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these proposals may have merit in their own right, they will also serve a very different role in the city. They may well be used by the artworld and the museum to mislead and divide, creating new conditions of hostility between the different communities that comprise the city. The question that remains is, will the younger generation - the young people, in fact -be able to handle the changes, so that the artworld can resume its former role? São Paulo: the model for other cities to copy?[1] See, for example, Brett Frischmann, ‘On the Use of Mass Media: An Introduction’, Media Studies Quarterly, Vol. 28, No. 1, February, 2000, p.1–29.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a Ph.D. candidate in Communication Studies and the History &amp; Theory of Architecture at the University of Alberta, and holds a Bachelor of Arts in English Cultural Studies from</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these may have similar aims and aims, the fact that the old guard is coming back into the art spaces and painting the walls with bright patterns and colours will inevitably raise questions. What sort of impact will this have? And what sort of colour would that be? I asked Curator at Tate, Dr Tina Hill, if there were any parallels between the loss of the historical art collectives and the loss of the cultural art collectives. She said: ‘Absolutely!’ She went on to explain that there were two main difficulties in the 1980s: the rapid proliferation of art spaces and the explosion of curatorial practices; the former being driven by collectors, while the latter being instigated by curators. She pointed out that the contemporary art collectives had their roots in the idea that art was a consumer good and a serviceable commodity, whereas the historical art collectives had their roots in the idea that art was a core asset and a social good. The curatorial ‘found itself cor</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these might have some valuable curatorial roles, they will also have a critical one in contributing to the sense of the city’s urban future, in an area already suffering under the weight of chronic under-funding and a host of institutional failings. The new curators will have a critical eye on the city’s future urban development, and a critical eye on the city’s natural resources. They will not be able to pretend they are not also grappling with the challenges posed by the ageing population, urban sprawl and rampant violence that is threatening to swallow up the city completely.The challenge will be to create a vision of the city that is not apolitical, not dependent on institutional resources and resources, and certainly reaches into the present to the present. The institutional raison d'être for art in the city will undoubtedly be there, but the new curators will need to find a way to engage with the political, economic and social dynamics that are playing out in the city.</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these proposals may have merit, they are always outweighed by the need to address the cultural crisis gripping the city, which is pressing against all practical barriers. The Bluecoat story serves as a cautionary tale of curatorial overreach. It serves as a case study for what might be done differently, but which also serves as an example of what was not done.The new curators will surely learn much about the city they will conduct themselves with an air of newness and an air of experimentation. And given the city’s current predicament, it is possible that the curators will engage in the same kinds of behaviour that caused the Bluecoats to decamp in the first place.  One hopes so. What is certain is that the new curatorial approach will be premised on a certain amount of futurism.  The curatorial approach to cities will require new curating skills.Our city maps are composed of many different points of entry, reaching from the city to the suburbs and</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these may possess a certain glamour and glamour has been defined by its ruthlessness. The new curators will replace the antiquarians and museums with a multi-disciplinary elite of artists, curators, artisans and art-historians. I look forward to hearing what they have in mind for the new facade.DDownload this article as PDF28 March 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and museums. We have a mutual obligation to each other: biennials are museums whose collections are collections of individuals</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these might offer different experiences of art per se, they will all operate on the same biennial level. There is some suggestion that the new curators might engage in something like ‘the bluecoat’ – an old Victorian practice in which art was supposedly more repugnant than real money – though this seems far-fetched on its face. What is most at stake in the struggle for control of the cultural commons is the very notion itself. If the new curators replace the old, they will no longer be beholden to the art galleries, museums and collectors that feed off their patronage. Moreover, while the galleries may lose a few key patrons, they will gain a lot more under the new management. The new management will not only invest in the art, but also in the cultural resources that nourish and empower the art, artisans and art-learners whose patronage supports the galleries.These are not outlandish notions on the art-lover’s side. These are truly existential</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these proposals are good in their own right, their realisation is unlikely given the political leanings of the city. The new curators will most likely be replacing the old guard, a few artists and curators will remain in the old theatres and galleries, and the entire curatorial roster will be shuffled around like the homeless. Perhaps the most promising proposal may be put forward by the newly minted curators, a hybrid duo who will work in concert to develop the space and its management. They may well be formed, dynamic and colourful, but they are also a tightly wound group who can be counted on to stick to their guns even when faced with overwhelming force. Perhaps the most visionary proposal may be put forward by the curators, who may well choose to partner with artists and curators to create a ‘curatorial alliance’ that is more in tune with the city’s needs. This would bring together the newly minted curators with established artists and curators to create</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these may possess some valuable curatorial skills, they will also likely adopt the same cynical art-value approach to the art market that art collectors and museums have adopted. When the curators arrive, they will find the art market already saturated and the art dealers desperately trying to grab any scraps of value they can find. The result will be a marked increase in competition between art spaces for art's value, and a scramble for new galleries and museums. As a result, the art dealers and their artists will find it extremely difficult to fill any empty galleries or museums. And this will only get worse as the galleries fill with artists and their works. As a result, the city will become a ghost town.Art is an ever-present in the Curator’s Bag, whether that art is being shown in the most depressing of ways, or being used as a political tool by powerful developers to build new developments or simply as an aesthetic wasteland. When not in use, it is a constant reminder of the</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial function and to paint the buildings with colourful patterns, one of the most popular responses was: ‘That would be a disaster!’.There has been much speculation about what might happen if the new curators took over the art spaces, what with the museums and galleries closed and the city in disuse. While the rumours are groundless, a few concrete proposals have been put forward. Ideas abound as to what the new curators might do with the art spaces, and the speculation includes offering to house temporary studios or renting them out to artists or fostering a collaborative ‘curatorial’ process between art spaces and artisans. While these ideas are undoubtedly good in their own right, they inevitably add to the sense of crisis and decay, as in the story of the doomed ship Bluecoat. If the rumours are to be believed, the new curators will be replacing the ageing art collectors and museums with a more militant new crop of artists, curators and artisans. And while these might have interesting curatorial approaches, they will inevitably follow the same trends that characterise the contemporary art market: the memes of identity, the familiar elements and tropes – and above all, the war.Art and the contemporary urban environment are constantly (mis)represented, visualised and (sometimes) mis-used to justify a multitude of things – but few (if any) of these representations are ever fully justified or even partially justified. That is to say, there is much – much – that can and should be done to mitigate and (one day) mitigate the effects of climate-induced (and in some cases, environmental) calamities, but such action is invariably (mis)used by governments and other powerful actors to establish and enhance their own power structures and agendas. And while it is true that the powers that be in Canberra always seem to think of things in terms of national interest – whether that interest is in the wellbeing of Australians or in the wellbeing of corporations – the fact of political power</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between the Museum of Tijuana and the Mexican National Committee for the Peruvian and La Californian History, Culture and Geography, and the National Committee for the Peruvian and La Californian National Conventions, gives us the opportunity to explore how to bring these two bodies together. A historical note is added to the end of each episode of, or in the extended story of, the Tijuana Five’s ‘Take Back the Square’ project, which they started in 1994. In the case of ‘The Peruvian and La Californian Conventions’, we learn that their chairman Mauricio Macri was elected president of Peru in 1998. Macri is a major promoter of the tourist industry in Peru, and the museum is a major employer in the Andes mountains. Macri has also overseen the construction of Canarias International Airport, which will host the Fifa 2018 soccer World Cup, and a range of other infrastructure projects. In 2011, Macri established a human rights</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between art institutions and local authorities is an important one. It opens avenues of communication and cooperation that can significantly impact the trajectory of art and urbanisation in the city, and in the world at large.Together, we can make this happen. 	[1] Download this article as PDFRafico RuizRafico Ruiz is an architect and Principal in the office of Joan Robinson, Deputy Mayor for Planning and Strategy. His work has addressed the issues of poverty, displacement and poverty in the boroughs of New York City since the 1990s. His projects have been in the public sector, private sector and grassroots groups. He is the co-founder of Street Level New York, a nonprofit public forum that promotes awareness, provides public participation and develops strategies for action in the boroughs. His work has also been featured in The New Inquiry, The New Republic, The Nation, Outlawed Social Life, Time Out of the City, New York Times </text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between the City of Mitte and the MBTA is an innovative one, and one that has the potential to fundamentally alter the way in which we think about urban development in the city. The City of Mitte is a large and growing local government entity with a diverse range of responsibilities, which makes it difficult to draw a clear line between art and social development. The relationship between the City of Mitte and the Arts Council is a case in point. The City of Mitte has long promoted itself as an artistically vibrant place, and its engagement with the Arts Council has often been a way to bring art to struggling communities. However, there is a tension between the arts council’s mission statement and the strategic development of the arts programme in the city, where there is a clear conflict of interest. The conflict of interest arises from the fact that the MBTA is the sole provider of funding for art spaces in the city, and the Arts Council is the only organisation that has a budget and a management</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between the Mitte Science Park and the city is a first attempt to bring these processes together in order to achieve more than a handy urban interface. The Mitte Science Park and the city are making progress, but the challenge is to expand the whole urban ecosystem. The partnership between the city and the community must be a long-term commitment, and it must address the needs of both. If the community is to be fully incorporated into the Park, it should be incorporated into the community. In order to be able to sustain itself, the community must be empowered and self-sufficient. The park must be a destination for tourism and a means to an end – a profit centre – in order to feed the burgeoning community. I work in partnership with the city, and the community must be a partner in the production of the ecosystem. The challenge is to make the ecosystem sustainable in the long term. This requires both visionary and practical leadership. In order to achieve this, the community must be able to take control and</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between Mitte and Basel is a natural extension of my research project, because the two locations have a shared historical and geographical context. The Mitte Science Park will have a significant impact on the development of sustainable urban development in the city, and the emergence of innovative new ways of urban living. The partnership between the two cities will make a difference. It will also show that even if the aim of urbanisation programmes is to make cities harmonious, the real challenge is in fact the making of harmonious yet differentiated local environments. This partnership will show that urbanisation programmes can nevertheless deliver tangible benefits to the city at a local level, while also demonstrating that there is more that can be achieved through other means.  	When I started work on my master's thesis, I already had a plan to expand Mitte into a city, and I already knew that if I didn’t want to be an architect, I should be an urbanist. So when the opportunity presented itself to me to</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between the Biennale and the city is strategic and deep. It is about production and consumption, consumption and production, consumption and production. The question is: can the two be integrated into one? In the case of a city, the answer is clearly yes. In the case of a museum, the answer is no. But the question is: can the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, be integrated into the city environment? The answer to that is a yes. What is produced from the Biennale, its curatorial side, into the museum, and then into the wider urban space? That is how a biennale should be organised. That is how a museum should be. That is how a biennale should be. This is about as much production and consumption as I can imagine. That is how we are organising the day. There is no other way to look at it. That is how we are making a difference. That is how we are creating value for the</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between the Mitte Science Park and the city is a good example of how a local arts agency can exert a national impact. The Mitte Science Park will be managed by the New Economies Fund, a non-profit arts organization established in New York in 1977 and headquartered in Mitte. It has a long-term vision for the area, and has put together a very successful arts-for-everyones-use-case initiative, where people can come out of the park and participate in activities including hiking, nature hikes, play-fighting, rock-throwing, football training, paintball and much more. The New Economies Fund is a world away from the Stratfor archives, but they’ve been through this thing called ‘public relations’ and it’s not a bad thing, especially if you’re trying to get people to come to a community-based event like Mitte. The key is that the arts are part of the equation, and there</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between the Mitte Science Park and the city government will allow for the establishment of a new collective, while preserving the traditions and character of Mitte. The partnership could also be seen as a counterattack on the growth of the city, and the development of a bigger, more overarching ‘metropolis’ that includes a city. 	The question that constantly arises in the context of urbanisation in the West is, who will be the stewards of the finite resources? The assumption is that people of different ages and social strata will come together to exploit the same resources – water, electricity, food, housing, healthcare, education – and that people will then decide how best to use those resources. However, this is not always the case. 	In Oakland, California, for example, redevelopment projects have come about because of a 1990 decision to rehabilitate part of the Hayward waterfront, which became a major entertainment venue, and part of the city became an additional 4.5 million sq ft (</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between the city and the region is a key element in the success of this project. It will allow for the integration of ideas, technologies and services that can contribute to the urbanisation of the region, and in the process will open doors to new possibilities for the city to constructively infrastructuralise itself. 	The question that arises in the context of the proposed Mitte Science Park is how to best engage the public and art institutions in the development of the area. The recommendations that have been made at community and art institutions level in the area, as well as in the Mitte Regionalplanning Process (MPR) are that a science park should be created alongside of a regional park, with a cityscape dimension, and that a dedicated cultural district should be created for the purpose of hosting art exhibitions and other cultural activities. While the Mitte Science Park may be an interesting idea, it does not meet the criteria for a city park, nor does it fulfill the criteria of a ‘</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The first attempt, made in 1973, was a failure. Nevertheless, the challenge is there: what can be done. There are different approaches to the same problem, and each one has pros and cons. In this study, I take the art and the processes involved in making street art as a constituent part of the urban environment, and using that as a tool for the urbanisation of a city. With the support of my Foundation, I develop a project that will allow artists, urbanists and designers to come and collaborate with me on a curatorial and spatial level on a parallel track. The initiative will be based in Mitte, and we will produce a research project that will show how the Mitte Science Park, my design concept, is being integrated into the city environment. The Mitte Science Park will be a hub for research and innovation in the area of advanced energy and sustainable urban development, as well as a hub for art, culture, community and youth activities. The partnership between Mitte and Fraport will be one to understand, as well as a place where we create an ever-expanding ecosystem of collaborative activities that are informed by both the city and the free association between people.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is Professor of Urban Studies and Director of the Graduate Centre for the Study of Culture and Society at the City University of New York. His research interests include (but are not limited to) urban development, culture and infrastructure, and media ecology. His publications include (to be published soon in the journal PLOS ONE): plans for a new Mitte Science Park, a multi-disciplinary cross-disciplinary project investigating the interaction between art, infrastructure and science in the revitalisation of the historic district of Manhattan in the wake of the crisis of public infrastructure in the wake of 9/11; the exhibition The 3rd Istanbul Biennale: Art as Infrastructure for a New Mitte Science Park, a collaborative project with</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�
    <text>should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�s ongoing, global conversation.For example, a project such as the Chisenhale Gallery Project might establish a relationship with the local museum, the Liverpool Museum, and other relevant partner organisations, contributing to the local economies of art, culture, community. Chisenhale Gallery Project might develop a partnership with a local business organisation, the Greater Manchester Chamber of Commerce, Chamber of Digital Commerce and Digital Empowerment, as well as other relevant trade bodies. These bodies might request that the biennial employ local people or groups of people, providing them with skills or resources, or commissioning them in various ways, such as design, architecture, installation or even producing work, depending on the needs of the local community. Chisenhale Gallery Project might establish a local grassroots organisation to take the local art-education programme further, or invite a local artist to develop a local audience through the use of art-education programmes outside the local art-school. The</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�s ongoing, if somewhat hidden, internal dialogue.4. Directing the biennial towards the local. One of the first things a curator might do in the art biennial is to establish a project in which the art himself or herself is a participant. In Mark Leckey’s case, this participation would mean actively participating in the art as an artist and thereby becoming a co-producer of his or her art. In Leckey’s case it would mean actively participating in the art as an institution and thereby becoming a co-founder of an arts organisation. In both cases, the participation would come from within the biennial itself and not through a commission, patronage, investment or any other form of institutional support. In the case of a museum commission, the participation would come from within the organisation itself and not through other channels. In both the participation and the reinforcement of knowledge would come from the biennial itself. However, in the 21st century, the participation should</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�s ongoing, global conversation. This type of global participatory project is unfolding in parallel on a global scale, and it is happening in places such as Liverpool, Basel, Istanbul and São Paulo. In the present period, this has meant the creation of local versions of major biennials, such as the Venice Biennale. Yet this kind of global participatory project is just one mode of how knowledge can be gathered and used; another, more localised form of gathering and use is occurring, and it is being fuelled by the same local knowledge-gathering and consumption. Here, the biennial is no longer the object of scientific or artistic research; it is a site of production and consumption generated by a shared, community of fans. In this sense, it is the contemporary incarnation of Plato’s Cave: knowledge as a production of the flesh. This is evident in the increasing global ubiquity of biennials, which we count among our everyday experiences. We eat at</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�s ongoing, worldwide, ‘permanent’ curatorial tour. Disability and Inclusion By Cathy Ellis and Samantha Jones, Curators for the Future (New York: M.I.T. &amp; Institute, 2015), p.2. 	Cultural appropriation and historical misrepresentation of Black Lives Matter, shown in the context of a Black Lives Matter studio in New York, is a serious issue that deserves to be addressed and dealt with in a proper way. It needs to be understood that cultural appropriation and historical misrepresentation of an aspect of Black Lives Matter is not a new phenomenon. In fact, in the 1990s and 2000s, artists, curators, historians, art writers and other prominent figures from diverse disciplines, including abolitionists, were warning of the pernicious effects of a racist, sexist, homophobic black-led programming model that was emerging in the arts. Cultural appropriation is when an artist or curator takes an</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�s ongoing research and evaluation.  	Such a project could not only refer to the biennial as a whole, but also the specific sites, buildings and places associated with each biennial. For example, a project for the Greenhouse at Tate Modern might lead into a project for the Greenhouse at Parsons Green, with collaborations with The Residents and Sustainable Development Trust. A project for the Greenhouse at Tate Modern might then lead into a project for the Greenhouse at Parsons Green, with or without the support of the Tate Modern. 	In attempting to talk through all these possibilities, it’s useful to recall Agnes Martin’s idea of the biennial as a ‘global register’, a set of relations between biennials and cities that are not local to the biennial itself.1 It’s a project that seeks to map the social life of cities, society at large, through the data it collects. Data captures culture, culture as a</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�s ongoing, but in my opinion ‘hidden’, programme of events. When the biennial is correlated with an art book, a curated exhibition schedule, and a curatorial agenda, it becomes noticeably less local. And so it happens: the biennial is a regular visitor to the art bookshop, the curator’s office, and other bookshops, and it’s increasingly likely that it will be a regular visitor to the museum. In these circumstances, it’s not just the art but the intranational relation that is affected, as the biennial becomes more institutionalised and the museum becomes less relevant. So what can a biennial do to further its local interest? One possible direction for the biennial to take is to participate in the local shopping district, or in the case of a museum as a whole, to participate in the city centre’s cultural sector. But this is just a beginning. It is now common for contemporary art bi</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�s management. In doing so, it would render the biennial as an institutionalised site that can be changed, reused and charted.  The project that would accompany a biennial would have to meet several conditions. Firstly, it had to be made in collaboration with and in the interest of the local community; secondly, it had to address current and future situations in the area; thirdly, it had to be ecologically sustainable; and finally it had to contribute to establish a historical narrative of the area and its inhabitants. The projects had to address current issues in the area and be made in cooperation with and in the interest of the local community.  For an overview of the issues, see the Bulletin of the Association of Arts' Research and Data Systems (2013–16).  embedreportprintSo, what is at Stake in the Local? In this analysis, the stake in question is defined as the geographical area between the border of Canada and the United States, or in Canadian</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�s ongoing research and evaluation. In doing so, it could generate local momentum for the development of biennial practice in the city, and thus contribute to the construction of a local biennial tradition. I believe that a project like this is what biennials do best: they create visibility, interest and imagination around their collections, exhibitions, collections, exhibitions, collections, collections, and they even invent projects and artefacts. But this is only half the job. The other half is research and evaluation. I call it: make the city discoverable. The key is to understand that the city is a collection of streets and their cultures, and that it’s this ongoing cultural memory that provides the basis for understanding and action. The biennial format is a single space with certain familiar spaces and routes repeated ad infinitum, and the city seeks to understand how this happens through the convention that it adopts: the biennial. This is why biennials typically have collections in their cities for</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�s social life. The biennial may well become embedded in the local, and draw on the resources and generate the social outcomes described above. But the project may need to be accompanied by a project that is not only about the biennial, but also about local alternatives and alternatives. In an ideal world, the public and artists would collaborate in creating a project that brings together all these elements and leaves the biennial with a project that is not only about the biennial, but also about local alternatives and alternatives.But this is not always possible; nor is it desirable to create a project that is also about the biennial. The reason is that the biennial may become embedded in the larger art world, and draw resources and expertise to itself, and because this is the dominant cultural form in the art world, then abandon that cultural form and find new ways of organising its resources and activities. The reason why the biennial is so powerful is that it can shape cultural practices and generate new modes of cultural</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the multiplicity of their potentialities. The spoken word is an essential way to convey this kind of heterogeneity. But if that ‘transformation’ is to happen, it’s essential that it happens in a way that serves the interests of the biennial as a whole. If the general public is to be encouraged to participate in this transformative process, it’s critical that the interests of the biennial be made clear.The way in which the biennial is made visible is a mainstay of the contemporary art biennial; it should be the case even in the age of social media. But it is also essential that the biennial be accompanied by a project that draws on the strengths and interests of the local community, using local resources and practices, and using local forms of knowledge. Such a project would not only make the biennial visible, but would also establish the local as a site of action for furthering the local interest through participation in the biennial�s ongoing narrative.  The New Urban Frontier  One can only imagine the possibilities of such a future urban form for the city of Biennales, and perhaps it can also recreate the relationships that existed before the city was divided into discrete zones.  The problem with the biennial is that it shortchanges the local by making its growth seem inevitable, while at the same time failing to generate sufficient awareness of the biennial to make it a relevant concept for the city. It doesn’t seem to understand that the biennial is a temporary showpiece whose time has yet to come, or that its future belongs to future site-specificities, such as the city. It promotes itself as a catalyst for a new urbanization, but in its current form, and with its present allocation of resources, it is more interested in preserving the local features of an old urban core. It promotes itself as a curator of neglected urban spaces, but in its current form, and with its present allocation of resources</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/
    <text>extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0155651.[iii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries in Silicon Valley, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0155662.[iv] For a more detailed exploration of digital libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0155663.[v] For an in-depth look at the world of embedded computing, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0155665.[vi] For more</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc....[iii] For an in-depth look at the ideas and technologies underpinning the digital public library, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc....[iv] For an in-depth look at the idea of a digital public library, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[v] For an in-depth look at the idea of a digital public library, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[vi] For an in-depth look at the idea of a digital public library, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[vii] For an in-depth look at the idea of a digital public library,</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc%2F20plosone.1615%2Farticle,00.html#, accessed 7 August 2018. [iii] Judith Butler, Socially Awkward: Race, Class, Gender in an Intimate_work, 1947, New York, Penguin, 1991. [iv] See, for example, Christine Stoner-Ray, The Red Book: Autobiography of an Anarchist Black Belt, 1978, New York, Penguin, 1987, p.65. [v] Judith Butler, Towards a Ecology of Participation, 1977, New York, Norton, 1971, p.28.[vi] George J. Martin, The Path of White Male Power, 1972, New York, Vintage, 1976, p.221.[vii] George J. Martin, The White Wilderness: Violence, Civilization and the Philosophy of History, 1975, New York, Norton, 1976, p.180.[viii] George S. Herman, ed., The</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[iii] See also 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[iv] See also 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[v] See also 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[vi] See also 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[vii] See also 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[viii] See also 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[ix] See also 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[iii] For an overview of the ways in which autonomous vehicles are different from how we think of them, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[iv] For an overview of the с autonomous vehicle, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[v] For an overview of the technologies that would enable such a system, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[vi] For an overview of the politics of secrecy, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc...[vii] In the context of the transnational auto industry, the potential for this technology to affect political systems is also significant: 	[i</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0098371.[iii] For an extensive exploration of the idea of publics, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0098372.[iv] For an introduction to network theory, see: 	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consensus_building, 	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consensus_march, 	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consensus_engineering, and https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Consensus_propagandist, see also: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.p</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc%2F20plosone.1611, accessed 10 June 2018.[iii] See: 	http://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc%2F20plosone.1611/journal?aid=12478, accessed 10 June 2018.[iv] See: 	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Link_handwriting, accessed 10 June 2018.[v] See: 	https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S019892915160400027, accessed 10 June 2018.[vi] See: 	https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S01049061940540009, accessed 10 June 2018.[vii] See: 	https://www.sciencemag.org/sciences/cognita/</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc%2F20plosone:12741/summary, accessed 10 June 2018. [iii] The term ‘public’ has been used in a broad sense to describe any public place, whether that place is a city park, a park, a parkland site, or in the United States, a street or sidewalk. For an example of this usage, see: 	https://www.cutc.org/pubs/academic_med_papers/public_placings, accessed 10 June 2018. [iv] Paul Waldau 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoc%2F20plosone:13769, accessed 10 June 2018. [v] See, e.g., John Durham Tolliver, ‘Public Space’, in, e-flux journal #8, March, pp.339–47 (1998). [</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%208Leave_Physical_Marketing_Marketing,_Campaigning_for_a_Rainbow_Row_British_National_Schools,1,230_p.ArticleCollection[iii] For an in-depth look at the specific systems and infrastructures that create the new digital landscape, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%208Duet_ebooks,_Envisioning_the_Digital_Future,9,1207_y.ArticleCollection[iv] For an in-depth look at the object that represents the ever-expanding, ever-metabolising footprint of the internet, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%208Self_seeker,_a_snapshot_of_us_in_the_future,10,1317-y.ArticleCollection[v] For</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines (and not just to computers), and provides a way to think about the infrastructure of the internet, its infrastructural equivalent and the politics of anonymity and security that come with it. 	[i] For further information, see: 	https://www.researchgate.net/publication/27486960_The_Digital_Wild_Animal:_A_Tour_of_a_Networked_Animal,_an_Introduction_to_the_Technologies_of_Transactional_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_the_Machine,_and_the_Politics_of_Libraries,_An_introduction_to_digital_literature,and_digital_art,2017, Vol. 2, Issue 2, p.136.[ii] For a more detailed exploration of the idea of public libraries, see: 	https://www.plos.org/plosone/article/info%3Adoi%2F10.1371%2Fjournal.pone.0074462#, accessed 6 February 2018.[iii] For an in-depth look at what a network is, see: 	https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Network_System, accessed 6 February 2018.[iv] For an introduction to virtual and augmented reality, see 	https://www.cs.umass.edu/medill/phd/interdisciplinary/why-play-with-reality/virtual-reality, accessed 6 February 2018. [v] For an introduction to documenta 14, see: 	https://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/documenta14/, accessed 6 February 2018. [vi] For an overview of biennials in general, see: 	http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/detail/full/art-festival/art-and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program can certainly be seen as an influence on the development of new urban models and practices. The development of critical theory and empirical work has consequences that reverberate across the city and nation, and it is this kind of long-term, deep-seated change that artistes and their artists depend on. It is also the kind of critical thinking that comes with a price tag. 	It is easy to isolate particular incidents or individuals in a given situation, to ignore the systemic causes of poverty and homelessness, and to downplay the role that art and culture have in transforming a given situation. But the power of an artist’s work is in its interaction with the city and with society as a whole. The power of an artist’s work is in her or his ability to create a context and to continuously foster interactions between people in that city and across the nation. And the power of an artist’s work lies in the fact that people find meaning and value in what she or</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program can be seen as an influential step in the history of the arts in the city. The path taken by such programmes, and the attendant grant streams, is a likely one to be followed by similar research-based initiatives in the future.  	Urban forms and urban changes are constantly shifting, and art is always a part of that transition. But today’s urban form is one in which a great many people do live in large numbers, and although it is not always easy to identify and quantify, a great many people do have access to reasonably priced housing and decent schools. And although there is certainly a need for more art spaces and schools, there is also a great need for more people to get arts education. 	It is easy to romanticise the past, to forget that things are different now, and to look to the future. But for much of that past, the arts were actively recruited and supported by, and had a role in, the political and social life of the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program and the collaborative efforts of the Arts Alliance and the Manhattan Museum can help us to make more precise the distinction between those who are workers and those who are not. 	The research programmes of the arts organisations in the city are autonomous, but as is often the case, the very autonomy that is being questioned is the very thing that provides the cover for a project like Water Under the Lake to operate in secrecy or to remain off-limits to scrutiny. It would be interesting to compare and contrast the research programmes of the two institutions in the city, the Institute for a New Urbanism (2004-06) and the Museum of Modern Art’s Art from the Urban Gap project (2007-09), both of which sought to understand the linkages between art and infrastructure in the city, but were also, in one way or another, constrained by the research agendas of the institutional support systems. 	Looking back to the nineties, the relationship between infrastructure and art seems particularly fraught, as</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program can be seen as an important early example of a socially engaged art practice emerging alongside artists developing increasingly sophisticated techniques of creating value from information. 	The importance of the arts in the city can be seen in the 	Comrad Alexander’s work of visualisation in the 1990s, which sought to bring an end to poverty through the glamour of the arts. The work was presented as a ‘biennial’ in Venice, but it was also exhibited in the Tate Modern, Rouen, and other venues in France, and in the US. It was shown in the UK only after it was re-imagined as a ‘mansion tour’. 	The biennial format has been on trial in the UK and internationally since at least the mid-1990s, and it continues to be an important exhibitionary form in many cities. Performing Arts programmes at elite institutions around the world continue to offer a platform for artists to experiment with ways of bringing art</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program can be seen as an important early example of a socially engaged and data-driven approach to the arts and culture that is still deeply rooted in the tradition and arts curricula of many schools and universities in the United States and Canada. 	The Performing Arts Program began in 1968 as a part of the university’s Theatre Program, but has been described as ‘a staged event’ by the historian Doris Lessing, who ‘later articulated the “shared understanding” that underpins the program”.[34] The broad notion of the 	urban environment that forms the basis of this report, and which has been further developed by the collaborating arts organisations, is a world apart from the narrower notion of the urbanised citizen. Understood in this way, the 	urban environment is both the arena in which the arts are played out in a multitude of styles and forms, and also the site of social struggles over access to artistic forms, practices, productions</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program can be seen as a critical first wave for the arts in the metropolis. These programmes, which combined theatre and cultural studies, spurred a critical mass of artists and organisations, which in turn transformed the city. Research-based arts programmes helped to ground the new socio-political and urban paradigms, and ensured that the arts would be prominent in the political and economic systems that would shape the coming decades. 	Since the 1980s, when the US Supreme Court ushered into existence a new generation of the permissive arts education model, the arts have been a relatively placid and insulated element of public discourse. The advent of social media and the dizzying array of viral videos that it enabled has changed all that. The arts are now frequently cited as a factor in creating social change, but less widely understood is the crucial role that the arts play in sustaining publics, or more specifically, in the long-term sustainability of art and artists’ reputations. The peak period for a cultural</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program can be seen as an important mid-course correction, a necessary reorientation of resources and political will, in the crucial belief that the performance arts remain critical to the future of an arts education in the city. 	The Performing Arts Program was developed in response to the city’s economic oblivion, and its consequent inability to support a sustained artistic initiative. The development of the Performing Arts Program was a necessity in the face of an already-endangered city’s performance arts landscape.  	In 1968, when the Black-E’s performance arts programme was abruptly terminated, a group of students from the Templeton School of Art and Design, where they were studying film and acting, decided to form a new school, called the School of Visual Arts and Design. The name ‘School of Visual Arts and Design’ reflected the school’s focus on visual culture, but also on the fact that its students would</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program, which integrates arts practices with performance and dance, may have an impact earlier than intended.  	Anatomy of an Art project 	Anatomy of an Art (2004). Founded in Montreal, Montreal’s Centre for Arts Innovation and Research (2001), the Centre for Art and Social Change (2004) and renamed the Montréal Museum for the Arts in 2006, the Centre for Arts Innovation and Research (CARI) is Canada’s largest independent and international arts organisation. It is the largest arts organisation in Canada and is a founding partner of the Montréal Museum for the Arts. 	In 2004, the Museum was named one of Canada’s top cultural institutions. 	In 2006, it was named one of the best cultural institutions of the world. 	In 2013, it was named one of the world’s ten most progressive cultural institutions. 	In 2015, it was named one of the ten most innovative and</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program can serve as a useful starting point for a sustained series of creative actions, as well as the commission of research into the city. 	While the arts community is inevitably at the centre of any such discussion, it is important to recognise that the key artists and organisations in the city are far more at ease and rely on the services of professionals, politicians and the legal system than can the urban community. The main artists and organisations in the city are: Benoît Carré, Christina Aguilera, Guillaume Chalamet, Yvonne Rainer, Mary Lou Retzius, Christine Lagreze, Emma Donoghue, Dirk Günther, Frank Lang, Wendy Harpe, Polly Hemmings, Stan Troiano, Emma Rehberger, Loraine Moore, Ken Loach, Peter Saville, Rosalind</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data from a variety of sources, including: national crime statistics; coroners' reports; police databases; legal aid data; street corners; public libraries; community legal centres; and, of course, the theatre. It is hoped that the disaggregated data will enable the artistes of the future to make more informed art decisions, such as those relating to housing, employment, public realm and the urban environment. 	One can only imagine what an impact this might have had in the years immediately following the riot in 1968, if the city were to bequeath to the city the highly imaginative and powerful Idea Truck, which played such a vital role in the 1968 Summer of Love. 	The 	urban environment is a complex and shifting one, and it is difficult to pin down precisely when and where a given social change takes place, especially in the midst of a crisis of affordability and capacity. But research-based initiatives like the 	Urban Institute’s innovative Performing Arts Program can certainly be seen as a work in progress, with parts of the urban landscape adhering to the arts’ early days and transitioning to new recognisable forms. 	However, it is also important to note that change in the urban environment is constantly dynamic and subject to contingency, which is to say, its spontaneity. And so it is that policy-makers, community organisers and other influential actors who set the agenda for the city, but also the agenda of art in the city, are increasingly shifting the responsibility for maintaining the city from the hands of the municipal government to those who adopt and implement the policies and programmes of the future urbanisation, whether or not they are in power. The aim of the Performing Arts Program is to encourage and support artists’ in taking part in ‘transformative art projects’ that shift the dynamic of the city in directions attuned to their values and interests. 	Such is the 	balance of power shifting towards the residents</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of art in that narrative. It may wish to actively engage with the city in the construction of its infrastructure, and its inhabitants’ habitation, and to produce works that speak to that history and to its inhabitants’ daily lives. It may wish to take part in ‘mom and pop’ shopping, and perhaps even take part in ‘museum shopping’ as museum-goers do, in which cases there is some evidence that some artists have been encouraged to engage with the city and its people.  It may also wish to engage in ‘community development projects’ that further the ‘relationship between art and infrastructure’, by offering culturally sensitive urban design and infrastructure design services, and facilitating the establishment of ‘black box’ data that can be used by the art department to monitor and improve infrastructure.  An ideal biennale would aim to: 1. create a dialogue, especially with indigenous peoples, that is as wide-ranging and dynamic as</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of art in that narrative. It may wish to actively participate in creating its own narrative. Diversity of narrative may be used as a storytelling device by curators and artists alike.In the case of a biennale that wishes to do more than display objects from different episodes, what is the best format for that? I believe that the answer is exhibition of different kinds, which is a mode of thought that is highly characteristic of biennials. A mode of thought that is rich in rich content, and that is rich with possibilities for human expression. I would argue that the current confining curatorial focus on the ‘mesmerising’ aspect of the biennial makes it difficult to imagine a future for many people when it comes to art and culture, and especially for artists and the biennial as such. To me, the ‘present’ is the most significant event in the biennial. Our present, historical and virtual present are built on some of the most significant moments in</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of art and culture in that narrative. A narrative might include cultural products, artefacts or interesting happenings from the past, and this can either be artefacts or cultural products – that is, cultural practices that were prevalent in the city at the time of the exhibition, or artefacts or artefacts from the contemporary condition of the art form at that time. And finally, a narrative might wish to incorporate the art forms into a future ‘city of art’, or a ‘world’, in which art is the sole representative of a community of artists, curators, art writers and other stakeholders. In short, it might not be possible to create a biennale that is both art’s museum and a ‘city of art’. What can a biennale do? A biennale has several roles that it can play. It can be both a catalyst for art’s growth and a receptacle of its mediated forms, objects and formats</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of art in that narrative. That’s why a biennale is different from a museum or a large public museum: it is not a static display of things. It has its own narrative, but it is non-linear. A biennale has a social function, and that’s why it is different from a museum or a large public museum. Cultural production and the production of narratives around culture and its history are the direct outcomes of this kind of thinking and cultural production. In other words, the cultural production that we can expect from such an institution is very different from what we can get from a museum or a large public museum. Cultural production should be creative, but it should also be precise, precise and dependant on facts and evidence. Let me give some examples of how biennials can and cannot produce cultural productions. Example One: The Biennial as Art-historical Narrative  One of the beauties of the Biennale as an art-historical</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of art in that narrative.Art should be a blunt instrument. It is, above all else, a blunt tool. It must be used with care, and with honesty if it is to be used constructively. False claims and outright lies about the past are not only unacceptable, they are dangerous. False claims and outright lies about the past are a hallmark of biennials, and art, like biennials, is a spectacular example of this characteristic. False claims and outright lies, and institutions of all kinds are among the most frequently levied against us.It is especially disheartening when biennials adopt an ethos of passive resistance. The historical record is replete with examples of artists being forced to engage with difficult or even traumatic situations, but it is much less common for artists to be forced to engage with the historical situation as a whole. That is, artists were often encouraged to engage with the problem through the non-verbal medium of art, but the biennial increasingly understood itself to be</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of art in that narrative. That’s why the 1990 Venice Biennale was so important. It declared, in effect, that the biennale was not just a museum, but a ‘personnel [that] history’, employing the museum as a vehicle to tell the ‘story of’ Venice. It began to define what a biennale could and could not be, and how much of that story was factual and how much was fictional. And it did so in such a way as to avoid becoming something that was no longer a museum but had become something that was no longer a museum. The story that was told, the ‘venue’ (in the case of a large institution, like the Venice Biennale) and the ‘gallery’ (in the case of a biennale) became matter of course, and the biennale became a museum of sorts. The story of the biennale as a museum of sorts started</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of art in that narrative. It may wish to actively participate in creating an image of the city that reflects the cultural values of its host region, while simultaneously intervening in creating images that are specific to that region. It may wish to engage with the role of art as a mediator of differences, and to promote cultural exchange between regions. These are some of the broad categories that can be offered up as possible narratives for a biennale to operate from. All these are useful for starting a conversation, but they are also essential for any attempt to truly inhabit the city. A narrative that effectively campaigns against nationalism, imperialism, racism and other forms of bigotry requires specific artists and curators to be present everywhere, and that’s why a biennale is so important, not only to our collective self-image, but also to the very notion of the biennale. It creates the conditions for a sense of place, and thus a sense of place-making. It is precisely because bienn</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of art, in shaping those narratives. The task of curatorial activity may be divided into three main parts: the exhibitionary part (curating the art and design that is part of the biennale itself), the cultural part (the art and design of the cultural activities that are part of the biennale), and the organisational part (the art and design that is part of the biennale). The first two parts may be scattered across a number of exhibitions, or they may be carried out in parallel, as an occasional shop that is part of the larger business of the biennale may wish to add an art commission to the catalogue. The third part, curatorial work, may or may not be curatorial work. However, it is what it calls itself that sets it apart from the rest of the exhibitionary, cultural and curatorial biennales. The fact it is curatorial work (not that there is any contradiction here) and not that it was made with cur</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of art and artists in that narrative. It may wish to imagine alternative histories for art and art’s place in that narrative. It may wish to actively engage with the idea of art and art’s place in a city or a nation, and in doing so, actively create an experience that is different from any other, whether that’s at a museum, in a gallery, or in the streets. It may wish to actively engage with the idea of art and art’s place in an urban or rural context. It may wish to actively seek cultural sources that can help it to develop cultural identities and relations with people from that context. It may wish to actively seek ways to bring people together from different cities, countries or regions that may be interested in or have knowledge of the same cultural issues. It may wish to actively engage with the idea of culture not as a commodity but rather as a set of practices and collections, and to that end, it may wish to create a</text>
    <text>should be curated by and with the participation of local communities] and, ultimately, with the participation of all of us, in order to address the issues that are relevant to our communities. The process for a biennale should be collaborative, transparent and non-biased. It’s time to start the work, so start collaborating now. What can a biennale do? Well, it’s time to start thinking about what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and how much of those activities can be combined with what can be done in the city, or in the country, or both? In other words, what can and cannot be done at a biennale, and what is and what is not possible at a biennale, depends on cultural values and priorities. For example, a biennale may wish to do more than display objects from different episodes of the biennale. It may wish to create a narrative around its own history, and the role of art in that narrative. Art is not a homogenous commodity; it’s a position that is inherently political and subjective. So while a biennale may wish to produce a spatial experience similar to that produced by an art museum, it must also produce a political and social one, because it is empirical and empirical-minded curators embarking on a curatorial task force cannot prescribe what art is or is not allowed to be. It is the role of local communities to enact their own biennale narratives, including those created through the assembly of local stakeholders and their participation in shaping the biennale’s spatial and temporal configuration. How art is curated may be politically-interactive, and curators may wish to engage in subversive acts such as street-based art, multimedia art, performance art, and new media art, but they also may wish to take the art out of the equation entirely, and leave art to its rightful place in the arts. That is, without</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso, is a kind of interactive media that pretends to deliver tangible, tangible changes but ultimately seeks to fritter away the visitor’s time by telling a story through symbolic textiles and images. These installations are not, of course, intended to substitute for the art galleries and museum collections that are often head-quarters of the current exhibition circuit and are the primary repositories of biennials of this kind. The problem with the present curatorial posture, as it is currently constituted, is that it engenders a kind of claustrophobia in which the art is either suppressed or actively participates in a contradictory, mixed and unstable dynamic. The museum collection and its curatorial priorities are what give a curatorial gesture, what draw a visitor to a place. But these curatorial gestures are always prefaced by a politics of the collection and the contemporary artworld as a whole. The museum is not a static collection of objects; it is constantly undergoing change, and the current exhibition schedule,</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso, is seen by the visitor not as an actual installation, but as an imaginative perversion of the real thing. It is as if the technology were programmed to mimic the artist’s voice and the visitor’s perception of the place. This perversion is not just aesthetically unattractive, as Herzog famously claimed, but also technically challenging: how to get accurate elevation data was a major challenge during the 1990s, and is still a major challenge today. In the words of Gregory Ulmer, the pioneers of Digital Elevation Modeling, ‘the first generation of computer programmers were not cool’, and the challenge lies in continuing to add to the architecture of the site. Ulmer goes on to claim that as computers became more and more powerful, the challenge shifted from finding the right functions to deciding what to do with the data.[6] The upshot of this shift is a wealth of data about the city that can be mined, but the challenge is maintaining that</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso, is not a replication of a real event – it is a cyber-fantasy constructed through the interaction of numerous coinciding facts and images. It is a fiction crafted through the power of the social media to meet the needs of an ever-expanding, but ultimately dispersed and transient visitor.  In an effort to make the visitor ‘engage’ in the curatorial process, the Biennale team commissioned a series of radio and television advertisements in the local press. One of the radio spots read: ‘Celebrity curator, Deborah Kafoury, announces appointment with Liverpool Biennial’. The advertisement reflected the biennial’s larger mission: to ‘add a new dimension to the museum’, ‘present a broad range of topics and situations with distinctive interlocutions that leave lasting traces […] a dynamic combination of historic and contemporary reflections’.[6] The advertisement contrasted the biennial’s current curatorial focus on a particular</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso, represents both a radical reconfiguration of the past that exploits the imagined possibilities of new knowledge, and a device that actively suppresses the past in order to construct the future according to predetermined social narratives. It is as if the artists themselves had access to ‘the past’ through their imagined connections to the present. Indeed, the connections between the past and the present are often depicted in the work as being deeply cinematic, with artists unable to escape the historical moment and its narrative elements. This is perhaps one way of reading the work: as a kind of synthetic past that can be manipulated through technological means. It is perhaps further to suggest that the possibilities for technological distraction and the reclamation of history created an ideal blend of past and future for the curatorial role. However, this ‘synthetic’ reading betrays a fundamental misunderstanding of what history is.  The history of the contemporary condition is contemporary, and ‘the past’ is no longer the dominant narrative (</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso, is seen as an act of inauthenticity because it is imagined, or represents an intention to be imagined, whereas a Stonehenge by itself is real and represents an actual event. The fact that the Ada Lovelace Centre is located in Liverpool and not in Berlin or New York, or that Ada Lovelace, Johannesburg, or any number of other cities are visited by thousands of visitors each year, comes as no surprise to us. It was a ‘metainterface’ created by and for the British.In the 1980s and 1990s, when we think of inauthenticity in relation to technology, we tend to picture Walter Benjamin, Max Horkheimer, Ernst Mayr, Max Horkheimer and Walter Isaac as the bunch of thinkers that formed the ‘movement’ behind the monoliths and the metainters. We tend to forget that these thinkers were actually trained as technologists by the NSDAP in Princeton University’</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso, is seen by the visitor as an act of imagination and not as a manifestation of physical reality. The choice is made by the visiting public; as to what to imagine, and how to imagine it, is left to the artist and the curatorial team to interpret. In other words, the visitor isn’t presented with a set of actions to perform, but with a set of implied attitudes and behaviours that shape what is imagined to be possible. This is why Herzog chose to engage visitors through a series of images that he produced in his studio, rather than constructing Herzog’s work from the ground up in Berlin. He hoped that the images would stand in for the city as a whole, but he also hoped that the images would allow visitors to imagine their own form in the city. For Herzog, the gallery is a site where the visitor can ‘possess[s] the right to occupy ‘any space’, including that of another human being</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso, in a park, is not just an imaginative portmanteau, but is in fact a reinforcement of the idea that architecture can be assembled from fragmented components. It is a reactivation of a concept that had been around for a while, but which was rarely considered an option for a visit to a city, let alone a home. Sebald Rehberger’s installation as part of the Stonehenge project is a prime example of this phenomenon. It is an adaptation of the poet’s lines, but with the assemblage of everyday objects and objects that we call ‘buildings’ – or, to be precise, what he calls ‘the bare necessities of life’ – that makes up the ‘pleasure dome’ of Stonehenge. In other words, Stonehenge is not just an architectural fantasy, but is actually a functioning building. It is a testament to the power of habit. The Habitations of CityMarija</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso, is not really a Stonehenge but an imaginative version. It is also an act of return, an act of migration – returning to the land that one once walked amongst the trees, or in the case of Sebastian Ingrosso, returning to the land of the trees after years of penning landscapes and architecture for the London boroughs. But it is also a memorial, a place of interment, a place where the visitor can ‘walk in the forest’ – in the words of Franz Boas, echoing the pre-digital aesthetic of the pre-internet era.Walk amongst the trees, or ‘follow the trees’ – in the words of Robert H MacDonald, walking amongst the trees as they ‘speak to their past, and trace the paths of evolution’.[6]Whatever one’s opinion on the significance of the tree, or the hand that planted the seed – in the lineage of the human family, at least – one must recognise that,</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso, is just another way of saying ‘Here is a poem or sketch that I’m thinking about or imagining at the moment.’[6] And so it continues to read: through various mediums, including statues, public plaques, markers and stones, we tell the story of the past, the present and the future through what is essentially an artificial intelligence. The main thrust of Ingrosso’s work, however, seems to take the form of a tag, or perhaps a series of tags, that point to points of connection between past, present and future. Taglines such as ‘Past, Present and Future’ and ‘ABQAI’ (short for Area Brain Initiative) suggest future work opportunities and ‘future cities’ – places where intelligence may have some influence – although their precise effects on the city remain to be seen. It is perhaps this ambiguity, the way in which it is difficult to ascribe direct benefits to</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. This was seen as necessary to prevent the machine learning techniques used in the exhibition from influencing the content or the experience of the visitors. The idea is that the visitor has a choice: as to whether to see a narrative or a simulation, he has the opportunity to ‘decode’ the algorithmic visit. This is why the installation of a sculpture by Sebald Rehberger, for instance, or the installation of a work by none other than Werner Herzog, is seen by the curators as an act of imagination and not as a rigorous replication of the work actually done. They can ‘hack’ the system and alter its outcome, as Sebald recently did when attempting to recreate the image of the Berlin Wall in Stonehenge through a series of textiles.[5]In this sense, the installation of a Herzog poem on a stone, or a Rehberger sculpture on a blog, or even a photograph of a Stonehenge by Sebastian Ingrosso, is both a replication and a revelation of the work actually done. It is a poetic reticence, but one that invites the visitor to delve into the hidden narratives and machinations that underpin the world Herzog depicts. As Stephen Leacock states, when we speak of a ‘Stonehenge’ we really mean a series of stone circles surrounding a central fire, and the inhabitants of each circle … live, work, play and gather together in social and ceremonial ways, making a site for contemplation and exchange.[6]One might ask, then, do the machinations of the large biennial corporations, whose material effects are measured by the number of sculptures they produce, serve, or actually merely create opportunities for the exploitation of labour? One might also ask, given the current political context in which we find ourselves, what might be done with such an opportunity? One might even propose that, in the age of the biennial, the biennial might even serve as a platform for</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’s role is part of what historian Una Román calls ‘the second revolution’ – the development of infrastructure and the social sciences that enable us to imagine ourselves part of a social transformation. Román argues that the social sciences have become ‘tools of the state’, a development that begins with the development of language and cultural anthropology. These social sciences enable us to imagine new worlds through infrastructures that otherwise foster conformity. The imagination is an important tool in the toolkit of empire, but its true claim is empire-building.We should also not underestimate the role that art has in imagining new worlds. Román claims that the goal of art’s emancipatory enterprise is ‘to create spaces in which possibilities other than those created by existing order can be conceived and imagined’.1 Romantic artists and writers, including William Blake, John Lennon, Patti Smith, Maria Hlavajova and Maria Hlavajova Deena Cadogan, used</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’s role is part of a larger system that includes artists, authors, activists and theorists. We have works by Adam Curtis, Robin Ince, Neil Johnson and many more that seek to articulate the ways in which contemporary activism and activism-inspired art is writ large manifestations of a multitude of social, economic and political ills.Art has been around for a long time. But its global circulation and its effect on social change are still a work in progress. This is why its globalised forms of production create the conditions that sustain non-Western influences but also why, today, cultural appropriation and cultural colonialism are on the wane. Why are artists encouraged to engage with the problems of today's world through their art but not the systems that enable those problems to be solved? Why do cultural authorities encourage us to identify with the imagined collective identities of today’s youth but not with the realities of historical societies?Why do cultural authorities encourage us to identify with imagined futures but not with the actualities</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’s role is less passive and more active. The biennial is a cultural production that relies on the imagination and the biennial has a cultural production that depends on the biennial’s subject matter. Subject matter includes the events that take place in the city, the people who inhabit that city and the places that it occupies. In this sense, they’re both productions of the city and citizens of the city. The biennial becomes culturally aware through its own content and generates cultural change through its own activities. It produces what sociologist Helga Nowotny calls ‘public works that become cultural works’ – works that function as objects of reception, return, and exchange, but also ‘public works that create a sense of place and identity’ through what she calls ‘cultural tourism’. These ‘public works’ engage with the notion of the place and the social. They’re ‘works for the common good’. And they</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’s role is part of an ever-expanding network of agents that includes farmers, factory workers, truck drivers, students, healthcare professionals, law enforcers and even, in the age of drones, corporate lawyers. But as the historian Graham Smith points out, such imagined alternatives are necessarily fictional: ‘the system is fully aware that it is imagining things it cannot possibly exist – and that is why it produces such fantastical outcomes – so it exploits those who are least likely to challenge the prevailing order: children, the elderly and the infirm.’[13]Today, the task of imagining alternatives is a core mission of the legal department of the huge multinational corporation that is Amazon. It is here that the corporation’s lawyers, accountants and researchers map out its future business plans. They do this in large part through what Smith describes as ‘representations of things as though they were events unfolding right now’.[14]The representations of things as though they were</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’s imaginative side is a source of much of our creativity. It is an asset in the creation of ever larger and more complex systems, and it is one of the defining characteristics of the contemporary user’s interface experience. But its real power lies in its capacity to engender new ways of life for people whose lives are embedded within the infrastructure. This is possible because the interface is a ‘metainterface’ – a computer interface that not only includes signals but also ‘metainterfaces’ – systems that detect, respond to and analyse them. Such responsiveness is not limited to the devices that are plugged into the interface but also extends to the symbolic forms that interface components take: the way in which a document is presented in the interface is based on system principles. System responsiveness thus not only refers to the underlying mechanisms but also the way in which the inhabitants of the interface can change the mechanisms at will. This is possible because the underlying protocols underpinning the interface are written</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’s role is particularly prominent in the social, cultural and economic life of the UK. Its historical experience and its political engagement colour our present and future imaginaries. Many contemporary artists, including S. E. Hinton, Laurie Peake, Rob Perkins, David Hockney and Terry Gilliam are artists who have trained in the traditions of dance, performance and metallurgy in the Guildhall School of Art at Liverpool John Moores University. Our cities’ Dance City, for example, is a cluster of empty venues where contemporary art is made to be performed. Robin Tennant is an arts organisation based in Liverpool that promotes the cultural wellbeing of communities through arts education, enrichment and preservation. The development and promotion of culturally responsive communities through arts production and preservation is a pressing issue for the UK and internationally.  In the UK, the Biennial has been producing works across a number of themes across its various forms for over twenty years. These range from 2009's ‘Get Well Soon’</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’s role is part of a larger cultural system that includes media, advertising, packaging, consumer products, universities, law and politics. In part two, wefthere are traces of a participation in the production of art that occurred earlier in Western civilisation, in part three is a direct result of technological innovation.The engagement with the future – with the possibility that such future may be created by and for us – is part of a broader cultural tendency towards greater inclusivity. We are far more open to the ideas of greater understanding, deeper connections and so forth. This openness to possibilities and possibilities is part of what makes the future so appealing: so appealing, in fact, that we tend to overvalue and undervalue the things that seem most like improvements over the past. (John Berger, Envisioning the Future, p.2)For thousands of years, the future seemed like the present: full of possibilities of what humanity could become, what possibilities of what might be possible. But the past</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’s role is particularly prominent in the imagining of infrastructure. In ‘Projections’ (1962), Bernard Berenson and Eric Cazdynenko imagined an alternative future based on French and Russian civil engineering. The result was a city on two parities: a commercial centre with a scientific and cultural centre, and a vast ‘pandora’ – a term applied to floating objects or virtual objects – that maps pointillistically across the globe. Space travel becomes possible through the transfer of mass, and this transfer is made possible through the development of ‘nanotech’ – the application of new science and technology to the production of physical objects and the symbolic exchange of space.Art has a long and rich tradition of being interested in the social. From its beginning the Surrealist movement championed the importance of social interaction and collaborative problem-solving.  In  	1839, for example, William Morris introduced the concept of ‘intercourse’</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’s imaginative side is visibly influencing outcomes on a global scale. The way in which science and technology are designed has an effect on the behaviour of animals far beyond the confines of the laboratory. The way in which we live our lives impacts the ecology that results as a result of it. The impact of these developments is felt not only by the people who are directly impacted but also by those who move into and interact with ‘real’ life. The impact on the environment that results from these activities is a concern that arises time and again throughout the book, in part due to two quotations from the same Greek philosopher: ‘As nature himself would have it, heaped mountains of earth and water on his shoulders, and fed him with seas of words, images, ideas, creatures, observations and data, from the very beginning of his growing-up process’. Aristotle is thought to have had this insight into the origins of our predicament:So much of human life is spent in the pursuit of</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, where the rights of members of a species extend to all members of that species. ‘Art’ thus appears to me not merely to render the present but to actively participate in creating the future.Art has a long history of being a facilitator of change. In the eighteenth century, for example, artists, including William Shakespeare, produced a cycle of new works based on captured incidents. The first of these appeared in 1710 under the title Henry VI – Theatre and Aesculus of the Plays – and was divided into three parts. Part one described the encounter between Henry VI and Antinous, who was engaged in piracy in the East India Seas. The third part dealt with the rescue of two Egyptian seamen who were trapped in a submarine by the Thrashers. In both the first and third parts, the characters were fictional. The active role of the imagination in envisioning alternative futures is a project that stretches back into the history of Western civilisation.Today, weftankind’s role is part of what anthropologist Gregory Clark calls the ‘metainterface’. This is the technological intuition that seeks to take full advantage of data and new technologies; to all intents and purposes, we are part of a global computer system that operates by design. We are cogs that move along a predetermined pathway through a predefined interface. But the metainterface isn’t just about computers and computers any more than the horse or the cart was ever intended to transport goods or people: it includes everything from biometrics (fingerprints) to social media (instant replies, favouring and demoting, likes and dislikes, news feeds, comments, memes, video and voiceover, maps, and recommendations). And although anthropologists have been keen to point this out, almost everyone involved in the design of the interface today shares the anthropologist Gregory Clark’s assessment that humans are among the most sensitive species we have ever encountered. Clark artic</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will
    <text>should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will of the people it was exhibited within. I find myself agreeing with the Chisenhale that the ban should be lifted. The ban should be lifted, and the Chisenhale can return to showcasing their work again. Both the gallery and the artist should be allowed to engage with the notion that their banishment is a response to a perceived threat. It should be recalled that at the Time in New York in 2013, the artist Mierle Laderman opened the Chisenhale for the 1970 annual, where she mounted a series of six one-of-a-kind works, re-figuring the Chisenhale collection as a collection of six paintings. The paintings were part of an ever-expanding mural and sculpture project entitled The Man Making the World (1968), which she continued to commission from 1972 until her death in 1977. Mierle</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will of the people to elect such an authority.  The New York Guild has re-purposed the project as a re-imaging of the Chisenhale/New York Guild's 1970 Guild Ball, where Bill Hartnell and his friends stayed. The Guild Ball was a great party, and Bill Hartnell was a star. It was a gift, in other words. The Guild Ball was a gift.  The  	Guild Ballroom was a gift.  The gift that keeps on giving, of course.  The gift that instituted Guild International's programming for the next generation of artists, critics, collectors and others interested in art from around the globe. The gift that enabled the Guild to offer a space for its members to engage with and produce works that would be considered classically artistic work. The gift that</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will of the people to whom the gallery is accountable.  The ban is removed by the New York Guild as a glimmer of bad faith, and a publicity stunt.  The Guild has created a special website whereby members of the public can bid on a digital license to install the Chisenhale’s pictures in the gallery, and invite members of the public to join them in public acts of resistance to the Chisenhale’s reinstatement.  The Guild has also created a social enterprise to distribute 500 frankfurters to local communities in the New York City boroughs where the Chisenhale have their offices. The social enterprise website advertises the gift with the familiar gilded image, and the gilded words: ‘Gift is a collective expression of gratitude for the service rendered.’  The social enterprise is a hybrid instrument: it offers both monetary and </text>
    <text>should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will of the local people.  They continue to insist that their ban is superior to the will of the local people, even though the ban itself is per se illegitimate.   The Chisenhale have perpetuated the myth that their ban is superior to the will of the local people, not least because it gives them a monopoly on development in the suburb of Doha, and allows them to dictate who can and cannot build housing. And they are right to a certain extent, although I think they are massively over-reacting here. The fact that this myth is repeated in the local press (along with other urban myths) is a symptom of how little we know, or don’t know, about housing in Qatar. Most of us live in our houses for months or even years, not years but months – not years but months. Most of us don’t know what it feels like to live in rent-controlled housing. And</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will of the people to decide for themselves what sort of art is appropriate for them to be exposed to. The ban remains in force.  	The Chisenhale are the British example of an artistic community that has successfully intervened to override the will of the majority of its members. In a monumental way, this has allowed its practitioners to reclaim control over their artistic destiny. But the Chisenhale are not the only practitioners of the veto.  The art world has a role to play in challenging institutional racism and other forms of oppression that still afflict communities of colour. The aspirational potential of such action is there; it just needs to be channeled in the right direction.  The aspirational potential of the Chisenhale ban should also be checked, in addition to the artist who initiated the project and the gallery that hosted it. It is time for that gallery to revisit the reasons for which it banned the installation from being</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will of the people to whom it was delivered. The Chisenhale have created an art project around the ban, and continue to be supported by the gallery.  The Chisenhale have re-imagined the gallery as a permanent home, and have used the gallery as a platform to advocate for their political views, whilst simultaneously being actively discouraged from using the gallery again.  Their project  	The Registry involves members of a historically disenfranchised community, and records their interactions with the gallery as part of a series.  The registry is a potential framework for resistance, and the  	project   1 	is a starting point for an ongoing construction 2 	construction, 3 	in which the community  occupy and their supporters engage in continuous mobilisation.  The registry also includes chosen individuals at the Chisenhale who were present at the Registry conference</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will of the people to elect a new gallery leader.  A recent campaign by the artists collective Curb Your Enthusiasm presents a re-enactment of the Ban Re-enactment at the Chisenhale, using the ban as a prop in a public political battle.1 The ban has been reproduced in ten books published in New York between 1991 and 2006.2  The term ‘ban re-enactment’ derives from Muriel R. Straus’ Constitutional Rights: Uneven Transformation, 1920, a document written for the Twenty-First Anniversary of the Supreme Court's decision in Brown vs. the Board of Education, which held unconstitutional racial segregation in separate but equal education districts in Ft. Stoney Creek Unified School District v. Pasco School Board, Board of Education, 1925. The right to vote is also mentioned. The right to assemble is given</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will of the people to redistribute resources.  In a weird twist of fate, the Chisenhale may yet find a way to collaborate, if only on a limited basis, through a making-of-works-in-progress basis.Creative Time  The Banner.  The Banner is a puzzle to transport to and from the gallery, where it appears and disappears on a line-art basis, and at various interval points along the line. It was also a reference board. By turning up, it seems to me, every day, it was a ‘collector’ of contemporary art, and every element of its interior was meticulously reproduced in the gallery. I never saw a photograph of the gallery without a ‘Collector’ logo emblazoned across the front.  The Banner was a window to the gallery, and the gallery a window to creative times. I remember looking through the Banner</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will of the people. They insist that their ban is superior to the will of the people, who elected them to be a group of artists formed in 1864, over a century and a half before the birth of the First World War. The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban because they think the ban is necessary to protect New York City, which is a very powerful position to be in, and to continue to be in, even though the ban has been lifted by the courts. But the Ban has weakened the Chisenhale, made it harder for them to fund more art, and made it more difficult for the city to fund more art. To the contrary, the more art they funded, the more opportunities there are for art to be made elsewhere in the country. The Chisenhale may be the most politically powerful art institution in the city, but they’re powerless to do much about it.   	I should add</text>
    <text>should have been curated by the New York Gallery and the London and New Carolinian Chambers.) The installation was installed in the Chisenhale Gallery, the home of the New York Guild. The Chisenhale were so incensed by the Installation (which they sympathised in re-construction of the project) that they banned the installation from being exhibited within the gallery. The ban was so complete, in fact, that the gallery was forced to repair its walls to make way for a new Chisenhale gallery. The ban is now gone, and the gallery has re-instated the Chisenhale as a permanent venue.  The Chisenhale have re-instated the ban, too, although they continue to be outraged by the notion that their art should be recipientless, and that their ban should override the democratic will of the New Yorkers who elected them.1  We should add that the Chisenhale also funded the William Burchell Chair in Cultural Studies at Columbia University, where Burchell developed a major discussion on cultural capitalism (including the Fordist capitalist mode of production) in the wake of the 2000 Rossum Art Prize.2  Some might argue that the Chisenhale are the exceptions, not the rule. After all, Burchell stressed in his discourses that the Chisenhale were the exception, not the rule. For him, the rule was that artists should perform in private, and that restrictions on artistic practice should be imposed by authorities.3  But the rule that Burchell articulated was a moral rule, and it reflected a consequence that can be imposed. In the end, artists are people too, and our democratic will is constrained</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
