<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community
    <text>will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers, residents and others who give Transfiguration its shape and substance. The journal is a text that documents the festival as it occurs, so it makes sense to gather here in this assemblage of stories and positions. It is a place to be a part of the story, to witness the unfolding drama, to gain insight into the festival’s politics and to discover the personal histories that shape its form. It records the questions asked and the answers given by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers and others who make up the festival team. It is a place to be a part of the transmutations, the stories told, the understanding gathered and the interactions forged. These are the stories that emerge from the journal, that are told and that are enacted. Their shape and substance are enhanced through the writing that emerges from it. This publication is a snapshot, but it tells a story. The journal is a place to find the story, to know the place, to be part</text>
    <text>will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers and others who shape what is imagined to be ‘the festival’.Since its beginnings in 1996, Liverpool Biennial has been a platform for the community to come together, exchange, exchange, and share experiences, engage with one another, learn from one another, and discover one another. It has become a venue for that ongoing process of discovery to happen, and for the festival itself to continue to be made by, for and about the community.In this journal, the curatorial role is clearly defined. It is a curator’s job to create experiences that are ‘real’ and that are ‘historical’ – but it is also a moderator of the festival, guiding and organising all aspects of the festival, from the production of artefacts and sculptures to the making of narrative maps, social histories and more. In this journal, the curatorial role is clearly defined. It is a historian’s job to document the festival as it occurs, making</text>
    <text>will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers, politicians and others who have shaped this extraordinary event. It is, in other words, a rare and powerful document of the festival that is not just a story, but a powerful and powerful cultural act.Transfiguration 2016 took place over two days in September 2016. The main exhibition, Transfiguration: Art as Performance, took place on site and at the Welsh Streets Artspace. The public engagement programme 2017 Liverpool Biennial: Contexts exhibition was hosted by Liverpool School of Art, Design and Architecture. The two other major exhibitions, one on the streets, one at the museum, were also organised by the school and the Arts Council. The important work presented in these two exhibitions was produced and curated by the artists themselves.Art as Performance: Liverpool Biennial 2016 and Liverpool Biennial 2017Curator Tiziana Terranova and Arts Council EnglandWelsh Streets Artspace2016 Liverpool, April 2017To Ross Wright28 Welsh Streets Artspace,</text>
    <text>will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers, politicians and others who have come together to tell the story of the festival. It includes selected essays from the journal and other materials, as well as the curatorial process itself. The journal is a way to ground the festival in a specific temporality, a particular place and time. It allows the reader to step back and step forward simultaneously, from event to event, creating a temporal context that is rich in meaning and in which the festival can exist simultaneously. It is a record of the curatorial task and the curatorial politics. In short, it records how the festival is made and how it is experienced.Download this article as PDFMark McNultyMark McNulty is an independent journalist based in Liverpool. He has written for the Sunday Times, The Telegraph, The Guardian, The Observer and The Observer Online since 1998. He has written many articles about the arts and community, particularly on the arts and community for the online magazine The Future of Art. He has written on a range of public</text>
    <text>will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers, academics and others who have worked with the festival over the years. It is a place to be invited there and then to continue the story. It is a journal that emerges from the festival itself and draws on the past to tell the story. It is a text that can be re-told, fictionalised or repeated. It is a record of the festival, its participants, the curators, journalists and others who have worked with, with or without them, over the years. It is a place to be invited there and then to continue the story.For more information visit http://www.transfiguration.com/2016. There, you will find a chronology of key moments from the journal entry to the present. You will also find a glossary of terms and phrases defining the festival as we understand it, collected from various sources, including the journal entries, interviews with curators and festival organisers. This is the accepted convention that festival-goers and art-historians use</text>
    <text>will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers, activists and others who have been part of the Biennial in the years since the festival was first conceived in 1994. It also seeks to document the festival as a global event that operates through multiple media, urban and regional forms. While the journal is a running text, its publication coincides with the festival as a cultural organization. It serves as a register to tell the story, an archive that records the acts of curators, festival goers and more. The publication comes at a time when the biennial is entering a publishing phase, and the public is demanding more from its cultural tourism package. This publication captures the essence of the event through curatorial, reporting and archival work that is intimate, personal and political. It is a rare and now somewhat legendary occurrence for a curatorial or arts organisation to publish an issue of its journal in its entirety, especially when the festival is in a period of significant cultural re-construction. This issue, like the previous two, is a final document</text>
    <text>will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers, activists and others who have come together to tell the story of Transfiguration, its rituals, values and actors. It is a place to be a part of that narrative, the fate of Liverpool in the centuries to come.Issue numbering begins at Vol. 1, No. 3 (2016).Issue numbering begins at Vol. 1, No. 4 (2017).Issue numbering begins at Vol. 1, No. 5 (2018) and Vol. 2, No. 3 (2019).==================================================================================================================================================================================The Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 360 × 720 pixels, watercolour on paper and wood, 86 pages, cloth, 8,8 cm, © 2016 The Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016.All rights reserved, DACS 2015.Photos © Mark McNulty.The Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016, 360 × 720 pixels, watercolour on paper and wood, 86 pages, cloth, 8,8 cm, © 2016</text>
    <text>will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers, volunteers, politicians and members of the public as they participate in the festival, their stories told through the many community organisations, grassroots groups and non-profit organisations that organise around the festival. It collects their reflections and makes them visible. It is a record of the politics, the rituals, the invisibility, the metamorphosis, the transformation, the surprises and the struggles.Written by: Nasser Rabb, Curator of Cultural Affairs, Al Mezan Center for the Performing Arts, Al Mezan Center for Palestine Studies, University of Chicago, USA; Christine Blau, Curator of Cultural Affairs, Al Mezan Center for the Performing Arts, Al Mezan Center for Palestine Studies, University of Chicago, USA; Nasser Rabb, Al Mezan Center for the Performing Arts, Al Mezan Center for Palestine Studies, University of Chicago, USA; Christine Blau, Al Mezan Center for the Performing Arts, Al Mezan Center for Palestine Studies, University of</text>
    <text>will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers and others who shape the festival. The publication of this text will come as a result of a public curatorial residency that the Biennial will establish in Liverpool. The residency will run for two years and will focus on a curatorial approach to the festival that is sensitive to the way in which it is experienced. The aim of the residency will be to: ‘rebuild trust and build bridges’; ‘add a voice to the festival’; ‘consolidate knowledge into one place’; ‘mock the expectations of an ever-expanding community’; and ‘show the world what a festival can be’. In other words, the curatorial gesture and the event. The journal will capture the event and its spirit as it unfolds, but it will also point to important cultural and social practices that can be developed through the experience. This is the curatorial gesture: to create a writing that is both curatorial and speaks to an</text>
    <text>will be curated and presented in the Welsh Streets Artspace in September 2016.PreviousNext  Tiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.PreviousNextTiziana Terranova, Transfiguration, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, Liverpool Biennial 2016. Photo: Mark McNulty.Liverpool, April 2017This issue presents the proceedings from the 2016 Liverpool Biennial, Transfiguration, to mark the fifteenth edition of the Biennial in 2016. The journal is a running text (continued) that documents the festival as it occurs, capturing the politics, the ritual, the participation, the narratives and the practices that shape the festival. It is a place to be a part of the story, part of the transmutations, the up-close and personal look at the festival as they unfold. It records the stories told by the curators, journalists, artists, community organisers and others who have taken part in the festival since it began in 1993. It is a place to be a part of the story of the festival, part of the storytellers, the artists, the organisers and the festival. At the same time, it is a journal of the festival itself, recording the stories told by those who have been there, those who have written their stories, and the communities who have been shaped by those stories. The issue is a place to be shared, a space to be shared, a community of sharing. It is a gathering of voices, from beginning to end, from the curators, journalists and other festival stakeholders, from those who have been to the festival for the past fifty years, and from those who will one day patronise the wares on offer at the Welsh Streets Artspace. Each chapter begins with a list of questions that capture the inchoate complexities of the moment, and the ambiguities of interpretation. The journal closes with a</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Contemporary Art, Miami, and was led by the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York. 	A timeline of the life of the Research Triangle, 2017. PDF Timestamp 	The term ‘timestamps’ refers to digital texts or files that provide information about the present or past of a digital document. They’re a type of file found in most operating systems and applications that contain timestamp information, which tells when the file was created and whether it was last modified. They’re frequently used to refer to historical times or historical events, and in this context they represent the temporal difference between now and then. 	Users of the term ‘timestamps’ often refer to their immersion in the digital age, which makes them aware of the continual expansion of information available to them and the manifold transformations of time.’2  Digital nomad 	If the development of digital nomad is considered a</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the National Gallery of Ireland with the express mission to explore the ‘histories, practices and materials of art’ in and on the Island of Ireland. The exhibition ‘Art’ in the Art and Architecture Program was curated alongside a work from the project, as well as a multimedia installation including audio and video recordings from the TRP 2017, produced in collaboration with National Geographic Digital Studios and The National Gallery of Ireland. The multimedia installation ‘Digital Divide’ was presented at the Ulster Artspace, Dublin, Ireland, alongside a range of previously photographed works previously acquired through research projects at the Ulster Artspace. The exhibition ‘Digital Divide’ was shown in more than 40 countries and in languages including Irish, Scottish, Irish, German, Dutch, Polish, Russian, and Taiwanese. 	 The exhibition ‘Digital Divide’ was part of the ‘Digital Divideⓔ project, which was led by the Museum of Modern Art and the Irish Cultural Resource Centre at the</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the University of South Florida and is part of a broader research project examining the potential of new media to inform and empower contemporary art’s future. 	Artists’ collective members’ residency and postgraduate programmes were selected through an exploratory, multi-disciplinary design process that invited proposals that addressed a broad range of concerns and engaged a wide range of creative approaches to exploring the connections between the arts and workplace. 	The project was also collaborative, presenting its findings to a worldwide audience through performances, interviews, and written and visual arts publications. Interviews and performances with key stakeholders informed the project’s decisions, while collaborative processes led to unexpected outcomes. Interviews with artists, curators, artists’ assistants, researchers, art educators and journalists served as the basis for the article; the art, craft, design and architecture of the various media used to create the scene in which the project was staged, and the communities that inhabit that media; and, finally, the various professions</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the University of South Florida. The main publications of TRP 2017 are listed in the footnotes of the published work, with brief histories of each entry. 	The project began with a festival in Miami, where participants proposed, brainstormed and created new media projects for the festival. These projects were implemented in the city, with the assistance of the Museum of Modern Art and the University of South Florida Libraries. The resulting articles and chapters are listed in the index and a directory applet in the booklets for download at the end of the publication. 	In 2017, a team of researchers from the University of South Florida and South Florida’s Caribbean Museum attempted to locate and map the islands of the Southern Caribbean, focusing on the island of Barbados. The Southern Caribbean Islands are divided into three categories: British, Caribbean and Antilles. The British Isles are made up of islands in the North Atlantic, including Newfoundland and the Isle of Man. The Antilles are islands in the South Atlantic,</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art History. The diverse contributions to the project were assembled into a collective work, titled South Florida (And The World Beyond). The project was written and directed by Sara Cox, with additional contributions from historians, artists, journalists, lawyers, geographers and others. The project was supported by the US Coast Guard and the National Science Foundation. 	The project has been featured in numerous publications and scholarly works worldwide, including the prestigious scholarly journal Social Worlds (2017). It was also included in the 2017 book Social Worlds: Worlds Collide?, to be published by the association and the journal in 2018. 	The project came to be through a collaborative process between the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Modern Art History. This process is based on a three-year research project, funded by the US Coast Guard and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, with additional contributions from researchers from various institutions. The project was led by Prof. Daniela Ginsburg, Professor in the Art</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the Art Institute of South Florida and was co-located with the Museum of Modern Art, where it was exhibited in the 2017 exhibition Sketches of a Nation. 	The project was designed with multiple media types in mind, with different social engagements and different uses in different scenarios. The article focuses on the artist/teacher duo Constructive Thinking Florists, Doreen Tompkins and Ciara J. Bergstrom, and their work in the public square, including their engagement with the idea of public space through a project entitled Social Sculpture: From Solid Wall Art to Virtual Private Spaces. The article also describes their engagement with the idea of collaboration as a process through which art can be produced that is both authentic to the context in which it is produced and is environmentally sustainable.2  The article describes how the project was developed, with examples including the curator’s meticulous notes on work in progress, comments on previously completed projects and</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the Museum of Contemporary Art, and is part of the Museum of Modern Art’s ongoing work to &quot;reappropriate&quot; cultural resources and institutions.2  The project received funding from the South Florida Council on Global Affairs (2010–2015), the MFA Program at the Museum of Modern Art, and the Fondation Galeries Lafayette, France. Funding for the project came from the French government's European Programme for Strategic Investments (FP7/2007-2012), the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF), and the Swiss Federal Institute of Technology (ETH). The museum was supported by the Office of Cultural Affairs and the Naturalis, Inc. DLP 2015-2020 and the TRP 2016 consortium funded by the European Commission (2014–2019); TRP 2016 is a founding partner of the Biennale, led by the European Commission (2014–2019). 	In this article, I survey the history of art's relationship to technology, from its beginnings as aestheticizations of technological progress</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the University of South Florida. The goal of the project was to develop a collective understanding of the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through a work that represents a unified set of experiences for a diverse set of people. In doing so, it sought to create a context of questioning and potential engagement with the historically colonized and culturally diverse communities in the region. Using the term ‘historic’ anticipates that this interaction will be remembered and that it will be possible to propose alternative understandings of the history of the area. While the historical relationship between the Miami-Dade County waterfront and the historic city of Miami is far from clear, a number of studies have suggested that the former is built on the latter. In the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, a number of groups, including the Dutch East India Company and the British East India Company, established operations on the peninsula. The involvement of the British government in the colonial administration of the peninsula came as a response to growing public discontent with</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the Florida Museum of Art. The Museum of Modern Art is the oldest surviving museum in Miami and the Museum of Art is the largest surviving institution in the city. The Museum of Modern Art was founded in 1884 and the Florida Museum of Art in 1977.2  The museum and the FMA were founded by Johann Wolfgang von Goethe (1546–1621) in Munich and were named for him after his death.3  The FMA is a multi-disciplinary museum and institute dedicated to the study of art, architecture, history and architecture. It is the oldest surviving museum in Miami and the Museum of Modern Art is the oldest surviving institution in the city.4  The Museum of Modern Art is the oldest continuously operating museum in Miami and the Museum of the Modern Art is the oldest continuously operating institution in Tallahassee.5  The Museum of the Modern Art opened in 1923 and the Museum of the Museum of the Modern is the oldest continuously operating museum in Miami.</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In 2015, the MIT Media Lab successfully combined the power of the museum and the power of the computer to investigate the relationship between machine and information (in this case, the ability of contemporary art to translate mathematical models into artistic expressions). In 2017, a group of MIT Media Lab students applied the Media Lab tools to examine how AI might be used to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions. Their findings, based on a year-long research project, suggest a possible engagement strategy for future research: develop tools for artists to use in their artistic work to organize and navigate digital media and social interactions; and, as a side project, to monitor and explore how art is organized and navigated.1  Abstract This article describes the 2017 Research Triangle Project (TRP 2017), an exploratory research project that sought to map the historically colonized and culturally diverse areas of South Florida through the use of new media and new professions. The project was founded in conjunction with the Museum of Modern Art and the Art Institute of South Florida, and draws upon expertise from the Aga Khan Center for Arts and Culture, the Museum of Modern Art/MIT, and the TRP. The article also draws upon research expertise from the Aga Khan Center for Research and Information, MIT Media Lab, and TRP. 	In this article, I describe the context and processes of TRP 2017, and the role of the curator and the artist in the project. I focus on the curatorial role, but acknowledge that this is an important one. The role of the curator in curating events such as symposia or exhibitions is increasingly important, and the media landscape is changing. Therefore, the role of the artist is critical in creating understanding and negotiating expectations. The role of the arts administrator is critical in legitimizing and encouraging artistic activity, but in many ways the roles are reversed: the more successfully an artist is embedded in a community, the more entrenched she/he is in the community, and the more</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a
    <text>will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a ‘present’ that informs the continuance of design in the future. It will organize the social function of architecture not as a social formation, but as an artistic form and its social organization, through the historical and contemporary material medium of architecture. This is an idea that has been developing for some years now, and it is an important step in the development of archival materials, methods, and artworks that will be used in the archival production of the city.Architecture as ProductionSiteArchitecture is a social practice. Social practices seek to influence how power is distributed in a given area through the production of sites and infrastructure. These influence practices are rooted in political, economic and social factors, but also cultural factors. The social aspect is crucial. Without that societal force, such sites would languish in disuse, unused and unchallenged. That is, the potential to produce social outcomes through such practices is tempered by the inherent disinterest and cynicism that characterizes most Americans</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a lecture, a workshop, a dinner party, a museum, a concert hall, a public gallery, a performance space, a wedding venue, a dormitory, a squash court, a bakery, a butcher shop, a market, a night club, a needle exchange, a children’s art and crafts fair, a children’s home and a youth hostel. It will be a place of exchange, but also a place of repression, where ideas and practices from different periods and contexts can find expression. It will be a place, as ŽKaczynski says, ‘where there can be no retrofitting and where thinking past needs precedes action’. This dynamic can be seen in the cultural practices of different cultures around the world, as well as in the architectural and engineering practices that are often reinterpreted and politicised in the context of advanced capitalist economies. In her book Things That Matter (2011), Madeleine L. Crozier, an architect</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a way of gathering, of gathering again, of coming to terms with the things that make up our urban and geographical world. For some, this will mean coming to terms with the fact that we live in an urban environment that is increasingly influenced by information technology; for others, it will mean coming to terms with the fact that cities are financial assets and not merely playthings of capital. Whatever the final destination, the end result of this interaction will almost certainly be the same: new forms of social, economic and political organisation and change will occur. This is the case for the millions of people who will witness or participate in these new forms of organisation and change.  The question is whether the things that make us live in ways that are aesthetically pleasing, physically possible and even ethically laudable also happen to make us vulnerable. This is the question that architecture has been developing to address, and it is the question that architecture will continue to address.  If the answer is in the short term, then</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a recording and evidence pool. Like the archives, it will act as a repository for the social histories of architecture, a function it performs well at home.  The exhibition will be produced by the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education, and the Philadelphia Art Biennale. It will be published by the respective biennials and distributed by the Archive of Modern Art. The exhibition will be located in the Museum of Modern Art, Philadelphia.  The exhibition will be funded by the Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education, the newly formed educational trust established to support postgraduate and postgraduate-level courses in architecture in the Museum of Modern Art. The architecture programme will be led by Professors Ambati Ray and Deepa Chalabi. The postgraduate programme will be led by Professors Anand Menon. The PHM will offer a one-year postgraduate residency, while the PhD programme will be offered by the Triennale itself.  The bi</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a ‘present’ that informs the story of the city through the moment-by-moment occurrence of architectural forms and their make-work-or-play-like-a-playground characteristics. The present, in this sense, is a mode of appearance and a site of habitation. The retrospective format that the artist has adopted allows the audience to participate not only as observers, but also as inhabitants of the city, occupying places that are ‘present’ and ‘real’ but also as occupants of ‘empty’ spaces. She encourages the audience to inhabit ‘the thing’ through ‘the thing’, which is both an adjective and a noun: There is a house called the ‘present’ house, and every day, someone else calls it the ‘present’ district. (2000)  In the architectural journal Aarhus, Architectural Review, Issue #7 (June 2000), Leslie Knope, Professor</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a moving, persistent document. As the title suggests, the project will be ongoing, and the driving force behind the exhibitionist impulse will always be the same: the pursuit of things in their natural, contemporaneous way.  The exhibition will feature a number of works that were created for the exhibition, but will also feature works that have come out of it, from time to time. We think this reflects a certain historical impulse: the titular question, ‘the museum’, is an important locus of our thinking today. It was not so long ago that it was regarded as a synonym for ‘the museum’; museums today often act as agents of ‘the museum’, exhibiting its collections and programmes on a regular basis. And although we don’t wish to diminish the importance of the Bangladesh Museum, we think that this is a case of cultural imperialism at its most ambitious. We want to know what the Bangladesh Museum can teach us</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a way of gathering work from different places, ideas, and social practices into a shared history. In this sense, it will be a similar way, though categorised, as the 1990 Venice Biennale was to the early modern biennales of Venice, Paris and other Italian cities.  The exhibition will be produced in cooperation with the Italian Cultural Association (CCC), the leading artistic agent for the region – an alliance that dates back to the 1950s – and the Italian Museum, one of the most important museums for the region.  The CCC, along with the museum, is the region’s dominant cultural force. It is the reason why the region has been able to support, fund and record every aspect of its economic, political, social and urban development. It is also the reason why the region has been able to support an arts education that is globally recognised.  The identification of the US as the site of the exhibition, and its location at the CCC headquarters, underlines</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a venue for reflection, for exhibition making to happen not only as an event, but also as a socio-politically charged event that is also a place of exchange and attraction. At the same time, it will offer a new form of understanding and possible routes towards a future city. The name of the school that commissioned the project comes from a 1947 report commissioned by the US Governmental Research Institute for Advanced Research (later known as the Manhattan Project) on how to deal with advanced threats to national security. The report suggested a radical rethinking of how cultural institutions were to be formed and managed in the wake of a potential apocalyptic threat. It was to a large extent a proposal put forward by a white supremacist perspective. The report came with a call for a race war, but the real agenda was explicitly racist. It advocated ‘total cultural and economic integration’ by way of ‘the destruction of distinctiveness’ and ‘the primacy of official mechanisms that separate [white people] […]</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a ‘present’, an ongoing, sometimes interrupted point in time, where different forms of architectural activity intersect. The term ‘present’ also implies a certain amount of development and modernization, and this is particularly true of cities. After decades of being built on the past, it’s time to consider the benefits and drawbacks of past architectural practices. In an ideal world, we would like to be able to revisit and reflect on a given site and culture sectorally, as an ever-growing museum of architectural activity unfolds. However, this is not always possible. Often enough, this period of historical amnesia results in an accumulation of new historical interest, and thus, a contingent of architects and urbanists take the opportunity to rewrite and redevelop old sites and cities in their image. This is a problem for the World Trade Center, for example. It’s difficult to put into words, ‘even for a lay person, the sense of the destruction’, but the</text>
    <text>will be curated and led by scholars from the School of Communication and Culture, University of Pennsylvania’s Museum of Modern Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, Howard and Marianne Moore Foundation for Architecture Education. Together, they’ll present a unique, multi-disciplinary look at the past, present and future of architecture from a range of disciplinary perspectives. The exhibition’s title, ‘Architecture: The Exhibition of Things’, suggests a relationship between the different parts of the world; the parts that make up the city; and the whole.  The exhibition will focus specifically on the US, but will also feature works from many other places, including from places that are part of the so-called ‘Bangladesh’ region: Burma, Laos, Thailand and the Indian subcontinent. It will focus on the social functions and cultural institutions that emerged from the blending of different forms of cultural practice. The exhibition will be an event, but it will also be a ‘present’ that informs and depends on the historical and social conditions that exist in the city. It will be a kind of museum that demonstrates the unexpected beauty that can emerge from obscure places, and the human consequences of industrial production. These are the kinds of questions that can be asked and the answers made visible in a place like the Museum of Modern Art or the Museum of Architecture. For this reason, the Museum of Modern Art will host a series of activities that draw on its curatorial and artistic resources to bring the different facets of its curatorial agenda into a visible dialogue. For example, the Museum of Modern Art’s 2016 Art Triennale, a major exhibition of contemporary art from across the world, will be curated by arts professional Andre Breton, and will feature works from around the world from artists including Jan Montefiore, Monica Ross, Heather Smead, Peter Schjeldahl, Rebecca Harpe, Susanne Jacob, Susie O’Brien,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has the requisite resources and connections can negotiate the daunting complexity of the urban landscape with a sense of humor and an amazing ability to imagine solutions. The key is in making the city real and in that regard this is a collaborative process. The city is a living organism that responds to the actions of its inhabitants and is always on the verge of catastrophic and destabilising events. The Biennale needs to find a way to coexist with its surroundings and its inhabitants in a way that is both sustainable and unexpected.Download this article as PDFRafico RuizRafico Ruiz is an artist. His work in the public arena includes campaigns for Indigenous rights, as well as projects in the arts and community spaces. His latest project, Using Our Walls, was presented and organised by the Biennale as part of the Isidro Nacional de Ciêncies Culturales do Art - the History and Art of the Plaza do form part of the Biennale’s package. His</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has the skills and networks to realise her/his potential in this context would do well to know these.Download this article as PDFSabine LisboaJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is an artist. His work in communities began in the 1980s when people in the neighbourhood started coming to his house and making sculptures. He realised the potential of the project when a group of artists from the community started collaborating. He has since then been involved in developing the local arts and cultural scene. His latest project was funded by the Swedish Council for Independent Cultural Organisations. Sabine LisboaJussi Parikka is Director of the Swedish Council for Independent Cultural Organisations. She has a special interest in the role of the artist in the context of community, and is a pioneer in the development of culturally responsive arts programmes. She is a multi-award-winning composer, producer and curator, who has worked on numerous exhibitions and book-loads of publications, including the Grammy</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has a deeper understanding of how urbanisation fits into their practice would find ways to work more collaboratively with communities.Determinants of Inequality: Capital and InequalityIn our current economic and political climate, it is critical that we address inequality and political power in order to transform the world. The biennale as a cultural institution may have played a part in creating the conditions that allowed for certain forms of political and economic power to be consolidated, but it is also essential that we enact policies and programmes that will simultaneously create and empower vast new social formations. The question remains, who will occupy those newly planned cities and rural areas? Will the artists be hired? Will the rural pockets of the city be given a new lease on life? Will the urban centres be transformed through a collaborative and equitable sharing of the surplus? If the latter is the case, why aren’t the urban centres transformed? If the former, how will the surplus be divided? If the surplus is to be shared, how</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has a project in their future would want to know how to leverage existing infrastructure and collaborate effectively with city councils, heritage organisations and other stakeholders.Do you have any projects that you would like to see the Biennale commission? I imagine that there are projects and programmes that would benefit from greater public involvement and collaboration.Do you have any projects or projects that you would like to see the Biennale work on? I imagine that there are projects that would benefit from greater commercialisation?DDownload this article as PDF27 July 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 August 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 August 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation &quot;Between State and Utopia: Migration, Capital and Capital Cities&quot; at the Biennale of Sydney. I was particularly interested in your remark that capital – the idea that――</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has a project in their future would want to understand the processes involved in getting projects off the ground and into the cultural landscape. Do you have any experience with this kind of thing?Do you see a future for art in a city? I imagine it would want to work alongside other sectors of the city, rather than being a lone voice in the city.Do you see art as an asset? It’s possible that the art world would prefer an environment in which artists could work without interference from academics, but would also want to support artists in developing creative projects themselves. Do you see art as a blunt instrument that can be used to tackle issues that are bigger than the art world? I imagine that an artist would want to use art as a weapon and would want to know how to defend themselves against the art world’s many forms of oppression and exploitation.Do you see art as a force for good? I imagine that an artist would want to understand how art can be utilized in a larger</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has mastered the art of the contingency would have plenty of ideas and tricks to share with other artists.Do you have any experience working with community groups or working with large organisations? I know you have a background in grassroots organisation. I imagine an artist would want to know how to work with people with whom she or he disagrees politically, economically and socially.Are there any conflicts between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine conflicts of interest arise in the context of collaborative projects. Is there a way to overcome them?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF28 November 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennale Biennalee Association convention Why Biennalee? Why Associate?</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has a natural gift for imagining possibilities and possibilities has many opportunities, but their real strength lies in their ability to create environments in which those possibilities can be explored and imaginatively utilised.In the 1970s and 80s the Biennale was a global phenomenon, now it resides in the 90s and has recurred since that time in various forms around the globe. In the past it was a biennale that sought to meet contemporary artistic needs worldwide; today it is a gathering of art professionals from many different disciplines working together in order to develop and foster a new context and paradigm in which art can operate in a larger scale. I imagine that a biennale today aims to meet contemporary artistic needs and paradigms, while also addressing current social and political concerns and priorities. For me, the key is in the eye of the artist: what is socially meaningful and aesthetically compelling is going to be what is most easily communicated and reproduced; and if possible, adapted; across cultural boundaries. For</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has a project in their future that involves developing skills beyond the academy would want to develop strategies with partners in order to scale the project and potentially become part of a collaborative arts/culture/retro-future research institute.For more information please see: http://www.new-york.org/history/artists/john-... 	[1] See: http://www.newyork.org/en/Artists/List/Pages/default.aspx?noreply;A22B;John Lennon, Lennon, Paul, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John, John,</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has a project in their future would want to know what their present or future audiences would do with their art. Do you have any experience or knowledge that would be valuable for an artist to add to this list?Best wishesDDownload this article as PDF27 July 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 August 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 August 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennale Association convention Why Biennial? Why Associate? earlier this week. Probably, in public or private, some participants took issue with many of your remarks.I liked what you said about the relationship between biennials and the cities that are their platforms or frames or bases or resources or primary publics. We’re thinking about this in relation to Liverpool. I work for Sally Tallant as a Curatorial Correspondent</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human rights are distributed in a globalised and integrated world; what becomes of culture that is digitised and outsourced?If you take the place of a city, a neighbourhood or even an isolated village in a project that seeks to establish a new norm, what sort of legitimacy do you seek to establish? If, as the Biennale proposes, art should play a pivotal role in the new urban form, where is the space for artists to operate freely and imaginatively? And how does the role of artist, local community or community organisation intersect with the role of the city? The response to these questions may lead to new practices and practices.Do you see a contradiction between your current research interests and the role you envision for yourself in the future? I imagine it can be a real challenge to find the right balance between the responsibilities and the opportunities of an artist career.Do you have any tips or tricks for an artist who wants to take the project beyond the academy? I imagine that an artist who has the necessary resources and connections may be able to find creative ways to leverage the biennial to their advantage, although I suppose it would be interesting to see what impact that might have.What is the art condition in the Biennale that conflicts with the art world? What are the challenges for artists interested in working in the Biennale as an institution? How does the Biennale create a shared experience between art-world professionals and the artist-community? Do the Biennale institutions have a role in nurturing a shared artistic identity? What are the institutional practices that generate and facilitate a shared artistic outcome? These are some general reflections on art and art institutions that I gathered from various sources: biennales.org, wikipedia, artnet, frankincense.net, artsademia.org, artnet.org, npr.org, artnetnews.org, frankincense.com, artnetnews.com, frankincense.org, artnetnews</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day.
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day. The answer to this challenge lies in the question, where does intelligence come from in the first place? Dr. Ambasz and his team suggest a third possibility: namely, what might be considered as the proto-AI, or human-level, AI. This proto-AI solves the terrorism problem by creating its own interpretation of the underlying data, a phenomenon that is consistent across all possible worlds. This approach to the terrorist threat is not an improvement on current AI, but it is close enough that it could allow terrorists to simulate the effects of AI with varying degrees of success.For Dr. Ambasz and his team, this approach to the terrorist threat is not an improvement over current AI that exploits human intelligence; rather, it is an approach to the emergence of new intelligence itself. Though AI might not simulate human intelligence in the way that humans do, it does share certain commonalities with humans in ways that humans can grasp. For example, humans are social creatures who value belonging and community,</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day. In this context, Dr. Ambasz and his team face an uphill battle. Despite the obvious benefits, like saving lives or reducing terrorist activity, the system also exposes users to potentially disastrous effects. For instance, terrorist attacks around the world often stem from disgruntled ex-employees or ex-partners; disgruntled ex-patriots; disgruntled ex-infrastructure workers; disgruntled ex-patriots; and disgruntled former employees. The list goes on. It is clear that a lot of effort has been put into concealing the true causes of such problems, focusing instead on the ways to stop them from occurring in the first place. This seems especially necessary in the age of AI, where enemies of the state are recruiting against their former employers. It is also essential that AI systems address the real reasons why problems arise in the first place – and not just in the abstractions that come to mind when we imagine solutions. In fact, the difficulty for AI systems in understanding such complex phenomena like terrorism is</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day. In his words, ‘The Internet has given rise to a new kind of complexity, one that is beyond the capacity of the human intellect to comprehend’. In other words, the very notion of the ‘infrastructure’ – the underlying technologies that support the infrastructures of our contemporary world – is a fiction concocted by AI to mask the real problems facing the world.Phrase magic is a type of rhetorical trickster’s trick that addresses the ambiguity and paradoxes of language. In its simplest form, it exploits ambiguity: when in doubt, utter the wrong thing and get called stupid. Phrase magic is a type of rhetorical trickster’s trick that exploits ambiguity: when in doubt, utter the wrong thing and get called smart. Phrase magic is the ability to conjure up an image or phrase that is both clever and evasive in response to uncertainty. The ability to conjure up an image or phrase appears as a feature of language itself</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day. The ability to anticipate and map out future events is an issue of strategic importance, and recent work has focused on developing ways to decipher cryptic messages that are being sent to and from terrorist groups. For AI to achieve its stated goals of augmenting the capabilities of law enforcement and national security, it must overcome its inherent human bias and become conscious of its own biases. In other words, the tools and systems that make up AI must be designed with conscious and unconscious biases in mind and body.If successful, these developments could pave the way for a kind of conscious and intelligent exchange between conscious and intelligent agencies – albeit one that operates between those with and without a vested interest in maintaining the status quo. This would require both deep and expansive changes to how humans think and behave, and it is neither here nor there. Building conscious and intelligent agencies is a tall order, one that is well beyond the scope of this book, but it is something that Dr. Ambasz is pursuing.Building ConsciousnessComputer networks</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day. The rapid advancements in AI, coupled with the fallibility of human intelligence, makes it imperative that we work together to try to understand and solve the underlying causes of terrorism.As part of his research, Dr. Ambasz is embarking on what he describes as a ‘mission creep’ – a direction in which the human race is expected to go in order to contain and ultimately defeat the threat posed by terrorism. The human race is expected to develop self-defense systems capable of understanding and processing vast amounts of data, but even then, this will only happen with the assistance of a few brilliant AI researchers. Consequently, Dr. Ambasz predicts that we will become indistinguishable from biological organisms, which is to say that we will become indistinguishable from cephalopods, which are already beginning to do just that. Sooner or later, we will encounter a situation in which we are not cephalopods but diodoids – sentient, evolving organisms – and that will be</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day. Dr. Ambasz and his team suggest developing 'collaborative' AI, where scientists and engineers share resources and data to understand more’how to live together’. This might include creating rudimentary AI systems that understand ‘how to love’, and beyond that, developing into fully autonomous systems that understand ‘how to mourn’.While these proposals sound harmless, there is considerable skepticism about how such systems would operate alongside humans in a real world. In fact, some scientists question whether such systems would be worse than natural deaths – choosing to ignore the complexities of human emotion in favor of the imperative of defending the human species against threats that can be addressed through brute force and data. The question is, would humans really want that kind of autonomy? Would we rather live in a world where our actions have no agency or where we are completely governed by an algorithm, or would we rather create our own destinies through our own creativity and imagination?In this new digital age</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day. This enormous quantity of data includes data about individuals, groups, and even entire cities –- information that is bound to one degree or another –- as well as data about phenomena such as floods, droughts, and storms. The result is a runaway AI system that is almost always wrong about a significant portion of the world, though it is almost always right about a significant portion of the world. The key to dealing with this enormous amount of data and phenomena, as Dr. Ambasz and his team soon discover, is language.Lingering AsymmetriesBetween Human Language and AI, 2017. Photo courtesy of Ambasz Lab.Building Blocks for a New Kind of Language, PNN/Creative Commons.Original Source: http://www.newspeak.net/Newspeak/index.htmlBuilding Blocks for a New Kind of Language, PNN/Creative Commons.Language is the organizing principle of human thought. It enables us to access knowledge and expression in myriad</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day. This new form of terrorism will likely require new forms of governance and bureaucracy, and new languages for exchanging information, so new vocabularies will have to be created. In The Age of Oil, Ambasz and his co-authors envision a world in which Mandarin, Russian, and Urdu languages are the official official universal languages, with Urdu parties expected to be active in a federal system based on Han and Chinese languages.[10]These possibilities are hardly glamorous or romantic, but there are many other options available to a developing nation's landscape: there are agriculture-based speech recognition platforms available today that can read large portions of the planet’s languages and can decipher human speech, there are commercial cyber-apparatus available that can read data from smart meters and can decipher patterns in the environment that can be used to build housing or sell natural resources, and there are local sub-niche economies available to service like taxis or sell produce or shop for art. It is important to</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day. Dr. Ambasz and his team believe that the answers lie in the hands of technologists and engineers, not in political activists or the dispossessed. This sounds like a contradiction in terms, but consider this: AI creates opportunities that aren’t necessarily created by humans; it makes the world a more desirable place by anticipating and enabling certain outcomes. In other words, the answers to the riddle that is terrorism might not be found in the human resources of civil servants or the ivory towers of the scientific establishment, but rather in the sleek interfaces and hidden mechanisms of the new AI.This sounds counterintuitive, but in recent years the pace of technological innovation has put immense demands on a global scale. As a consequence, the Earth has become increasingly less appealing as a place to plant new AI crops; the kinds of infrastructure that might support intelligent life once humanity has left the planet. Consequently, civil servants and most other stakeholders around the world are understandably reluctant to invest in infrastructure projects that might one</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the human condition.[9]The real question is, will our world be populated or controlled by algorithms, or will we become conscious and autonomous agents capable of shaping our own destinies? In a recent study, Dr. Ambasz and his team of researchers explored the idea of AI in greater detail. Using artificial intelligence (AI) to simulate human intelligence, the system learns to identify patterns through data that support an explanation of phenomena ranging from crime to weather to architecture to anticipate future events. The results could lead to new ways of organizing scientific research and potentially even the future of humanity.The challenge for Dr. Ambasz and his colleagues is how to apply AI to the daunting problem of terrorism, which continues to afflict the world. While AI might render mundane tasks like searching for terrorist camps or operating financial systems more efficient, it inherently faces a problem that cannot be solved by human intelligence: how to deal with the immense amount of information that is generated on a global scale every day. As AI improves, the problem becomes more complex, and as a result, more data is loaded into the system. As a consequence, there is greater demand for more computing resources, which leads to additional servers – which in turn leads to more data – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to more servers – which in turn leads to complexity and capacity – the techno-mechanical version of infinity. 	[</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built
    <text>will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built environment’, is one in which the public is frequently invited to participate in a way that is not always fully understood or fully engaged. In a talk at the Museum of Modern Art and Design, Norman Johnson, one of the curators on the Biennale, made the point that there was something fundamentally disconcerting in the way in which contemporary urbanisation had become achieved, and that this was largely due to the fact that there had been no major urban crisis since the 1970s. The failure to notice an underlying trend of urban decline and urban growth was a recurrent theme. The curators on the Biennale team saw an opening to explore this in more depth, and so they did that which many young people in their engagement with the city felt was necessary at a deeper level. They went deeper into the history of urbanisation and culture and the related social and political aspects, because this is where the power relationships are forged and so the biennale has always been seen as a potentially</text>
    <text>will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built environment ’, or ‘regions of circulation and movement’) are often cited as an ideal of the 20th century.1 But despite the efforts of many generations of urban designers, most of us can agree that the core idea of cities as ‘regeneration projects’ is unattractive and antiquated. Moreover, given the choice, most of us will seek to minimize or eliminate the role of cities in our societies. In our current economic and urbanisation policy debates in both major parties, there is growing recognition of the importance of the integrated into the socio-political-cultural system that cities play in fuelling the growth of our contemporary capitalism. The Republican Party platform 2016 calls for a return to the ‘city as a dynamic place’ of the 19th century, and the New Urban Form project (a.k.a. New Urban Form II) is endorsed.2 It is true that in the US, the industrial city is in decline, and with</text>
    <text>will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built environment ’, may be taken as given, but to take the form of an exhibition may require the intervention of cultural administrators. That happened with the Biennale of Sydney, when the city as a ‘place of refuge’ was diverted from its natural, ‘regenerational, ‘spaces of habitation’ into a ‘regeneration space’. Culture for Accountants' Locker Room Stories…Ben Whittaker,  	Locker Dormitory,  	Grenfell Action Group, 1994. Photo: Tom Lox. 	The Biennale was a project of the Arts Council England, funded by the Arts Council and Her Majesty’s Museums Commission, and it was run by Her Majesty's Privy Council Office and the Privy Purse. The artworks were selected through a competitive shortlist, and were presented in three distinct episodes: the Ground Floor, a selection from the planned eleven</text>
    <text>will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built environment’, are ever-present in our city. Our city organises activities in ‘the Zone’ – a huge, sometimes insular collection of abandoned buildings – often using eminent domain to take over private property. And our city is constantly reminding us that we have to ‘maintain a narrative of the city’s history and geography’. If we don’t, the built environment is always going to be a part of the story of the city – and the built narrative will always tell a story of the city’s history and geography. But the city is also constantly reminding us that we have to keep trying. It is a story of many different places at once, and so it’s always going to have problems, challenges, and moments of growth. But the important thing is that we’re always telling the city the same story, and so the built environment is constantly reminding us that it’s still the same city that</text>
    <text>will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built environment’, or ‘regions of economic circulation’, are the latest urban interventions designed to meet the needs of a metropolis in the age of the biennial. They’re there to stay. As the biennial industry continues to evolve (with many curatorial perspectives), it’s interesting to see how the city is frequently traded as a concept that can only be defined as ‘regional’. In the popular imagination, ‘the city’ is an island of tranquillity where people can be free from the effects of urbanisation, but this is often reduced to a nation-state defence of the city against threats from outside. In reality, the city is a complex that requires a great deal of infrastructure and maintenance, and cities play a pivotal role in supporting and facilitating these processes of urbanisation. Without this support, the city would struggle and may even become unmanageable. In fact, cities do this all the time. When the</text>
    <text>will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built environment’, ‘are the most consistently produced spaces for the exchange and use of space.’ [Emphasis added.] In other words, cities are made up of generated spaces, and in this sense, cities are the final products of a process of space-production that began long before Darwin published his On the Origin of Species.In fact, the tendency today is to erase the city entirely – to reduce cities to data feeds and data points – which is a mistake on many levels. The city is a space-producing system that generates and depends on information (and therefore ideas) from above, that is why it is such an attractive place for research institutions to be located – because, unlike elsewhere, there is no alternative for an institution to return to producing in its core interest – producing, that is, what James Howard Kunstler and his colleagues call ‘marginal space’.‘Marginal space’ means out there in the real world, actively creating and</text>
    <text>will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built environment ‘, ‘contemporaneous circulation’ and ‘the built environment’, is a complex and shifting concept. Its core structure is the city, but as we all know, this can also be a ‘resourceful and dynamic form of social change’. It is true that in recent decades, the built environment has been rapidly and inexorably transformed, and urban space and its inhabitants are often left with a variety of displacement and degradation-due to a variety of factors including war, urban mobility and development, political, economic and legal upheavals, and even crazier things like natural disasters.But on the other hand, this dynamic also tends to create opportunities and commitments that are difficult to dislodge. Cities, whether ‘regeneration projects’ or not, are places where people live and make commitments, and the city is a set of relations that accumulate and change over time. And so the notion of the city, as such,</text>
    <text>will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built environment’, ‘and the transformed urban setting of ‘regions of resistance’ – are the most extraordinary urban products of the city. But in the 21st century in many cities the problem is that much more acute, and the city is seen as a complex, interwoven web of interdependent parts that sometimes interpenetrate and sometimes exist in constant tension. This tendency to a fantasy of the city is partly why, in the last few years, New York has experienced such a marked re-constitution, but partly also why so many other places around the world are reverting to less urban forms. Why are certain cities more urban than others? Why do certain neighbourhoods of the US have higher property values than others? Why do certain neighbourhoods in certain parts of the world, such as Hong Kong, enjoy significantly higher property values than others? Why do certain neighbourhoods in certain parts of the world, such as Hong Kong, enjoy significantly lower property values than others? These are</text>
    <text>will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built environment’, is one that is constantly being renegotiated. In the form of a capitalising neo-liberal development, urban space is being created everywhere – in places of worship, in neighbourhoods of housing and commercial redevelopment, in and on the built environment. And yet, despite this constant redefinition, we still see large swathes of the metropolis increasingly defined by the most recent of construction projects. The buildings that comprise the cityscape are being repaired and rebuilt in response to the crises of the metropolis, but at the same time, the built environment is being continuously (but not always entirely) remodeled and updated in response to the needs of the connected citizen. This is a situation that can no longer be regarded as static, and social change has to happen at a very high level in order to alter this dynamic. This is why the day-to-day work of cities relies so heavily on engineers and architects. It is precisely because of this unrelenting nature of the metropolis that</text>
    <text>will be curated according to a specific theme]…It is quite possible that the exhibition will be very similar to the structures that were destroyed in the Grenfell Action Group’s proposal, but in a quite different way. For one thing, there’s the commemoration of a specific event, which would ‘set the example’ in a very different way from the current institutionalised remembrance of the event. For another, the boundaries of who is entitled to be remembered may be drawn very differently between the two proposals. For example, the present institutionalised idea of who is a hero or a martyr may be very much influenced by the proposals of a generation of young people who grew up with or without access to a museum. And finally, the notion of the urban may have many different forms, but its core idea is one of the destruction of the rural.Urban spaces, whether in the form of ‘places of public meeting, ‘regions of habitation, ‘and the built environment’, and ‘streets’ – are the spaces in between – that play an essential but often overlooked role in the formation and function of urban space. They are also the margins, the spaces where social life takes place, and hence, in a way, the most imperiled social life takes place. Many urban spaces are impacted by development and the growing stock of cars on the roads, but seldom have the margins been affected as much as they are in London and New York. This is partly because the margins are the 'periphery' – the areas around major roads and airports – that are not affected by development but are affected by it, and hence, in the words of Paul McCarthy, ‘are home to the moral hazard of growth’. The idea that the margins are this important and this neglected may play a part in explaining why cities with high and declining populations tend to have such strong and enduring legacies. A place where people live, work and play</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is via cooperative housing trusts, which promise to provide affordable housing to low-income households through a cooperative management structure. Such a model recognises the fact that co-operative housing is often associated with profit-seeking practices, which can lead to a sub-optimal condition for low-income communities. A 2014 RAND Corporation report emphasised the need to be more aware of the dynamics of ‘housing scarcity’ and the dangers of co-ops and cooperative housing in order to develop effective mitigation strategies.[8] 	The challenge for policymakers and creative urbanists is to create mechanisms through which to support a future city in the future – not in perpetuity – through a combination of progressive property- and income-based development and the creation of new market-based housing options. In the US, the challenge is to create mechanisms to support a future infrastructure sufficient to support a future population growth without compromising on environmental standards or subjecting existing residents and communities to market forces. In the UK, the challenge is</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is through the cooperative housing corporation (HHC). Cooperative housing corporations were developed in the 1970s and 80s to provide affordable housing to low-income communities, and the development of these corporations was a major factor in the expansion of housing for working-class and urban families. Cooperative housing corporations emerged in response to the advent of mass housing construction and the booming of housing prices, which led to an unprecedented urban sprawl. The cooperative housing corporations quickly became the dominant form of affordable housing for low-income and working-class communities, providing affordable options to middle- and upper-income households, and fuelling the development of alternative housing sources for the burgeoning metropolis. Cooperative housing corporations emerged as a direct response to the sprawl crisis and the city’s inability to support its burgeoning homeless and under-housed populations. The HHC is a Delaware limited liability company incorporated in Los Angeles that distributes affordable housing and supports cooperative housing initiatives throughout the Los Angeles basin. Its mission is to provide affordable housing</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is through the cooperative housing corporation, which is a cooperative association created to manage and produce cooperative housing in the newly constructed ‘urban core’. Cooperative housing has been a strategy for socially and economically-engaged development in Vancouver for over a century, and up to ten years after the projects were completed, in most instances through a purchase price freeze and a one-year purchase guarantee. 	However, as the Common Market reported in 1996, the advent of mass housing construction and rapid transit in the city forced many developers to abandon their ‘urban core’ strategy and instead focus on larger projects with enhanced returns on investment, which often times involved the construction of even larger infrastructure projects to support transit and the megacity. As a result, the share of new housing construction in the core city has remained unstable and substandard, while the share produced by cooperative housing has exploded. 	In an attempt to create new housing options for low-income neighbourhoods, which at the same time entice</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is through the model of ‘affordable housing’ – a strategy that redistributes the cost and benefits of housing upwards, creating new affordable units at no cost to either owner-occupier or tenants. 	[i] Raytheon Co., Inc.  	(2013). 	http://www.raytheon.com/en/US/en/US-work/science-and-technology/en?lang=en-US#.W5OJGlhZSBJlIjoIA5oYXJlLmJlYXRhY2FtcG1hZGlhZGlhZGlhZGlhZDQ==. 13 August 2014.[ii] How can the city leverage its vast property portfolio to support a nascent cooperative housing sector? Theoretical physicist Matthew Honeyman has been developing a possible new urban paradigm that integrates media, biology, and urban theory. His project is called</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is planned for the ‘High Street’ area just east of Bloedel St, just west of Jarvis St. This area has seen a redevelopment programme driven by the city in an attempt to boost property values and create a ‘return on ‘investment’ – a strategy that has included breaking ground on a new ‘parkadeusment parcel’ and constructing of a brand new ‘High Street retail district’. 	It is unknown where the High Sts would be located if this strategy were to pan out, or whether a new ‘Mid-City Hub’ could be envisioned in the area. Regardless, this area has long been a location for speculative projects, including the construction of the Bloedel St. LRT/MTR stations, and a number of hotels have been built on the site of the former Bloedel St. Rapid transit has been proposed for the area, but with construction spiking at an unprecedented pace</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is through the cooperative housing developments that would mirror the model of large corporate programmes, but in the context of a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. Such cooperatives could operate alongside traditional corporate housing models, offering affordable housing to residents in a shared governance structure, but in the context of a city-wide cooperative housing strategy they could also foster the emergence of alternative housing models that meet the needs of workers, residents and communities in the context of the cooperative. Cooperative housing developments could also develop and augment existing affordable housing assets, such as cooperative gardens, educational partnerships, and maintenance networks, in the form of cooperativehouses, which would provide affordable housing and other services to enhance the quality of life of residents and visitors to the neighbourhood. 	Another potential model is a cooperative housing corporation (HHC) – a publicly held limited partnership – which could assume responsibility for providing rental and ownership options to residents and visitors to the neighbourhood, as well as the development and management of the ‘Co-operative Arts Centre’</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is via the cooperative housing strategy, which could conceivably combine the benefits of the adaptive reuse strategy with the cooperative housing policy of the city. How to leverage the expertise and assets of a city-wide cooperative to meet an ever-larger housing crisis? Such a move would require a radical rethink of how social, political and economic power are interconnected in an ever greater urban context, and a new strategy is required if the city is to be saved from itself. 1. Calendar Project, http://calendar.org/en/1... (accessed September 2018).  2. Inhabitant,  presents a snapshot of the lives of New Yorkers affected by the 2017 Manhattan Project, a collaboration with New York Public Library and VICE News. The project, which sought to redefine the role of the Midtown Manhattan Project Resource Center, resulted in the establishment of a public, nonprofit organisation called the Inhabitant. 3. García M. Madrig</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is through cooperative housing trusts, which would provide affordable housing to low-income households and enable social enterprises to create self-sufficiency in traditionally urban settings. Cooperative housing trustss have proven to be valuable in that they function as tax-exempt tax-advantaged housing entities, lending potential partners a stable rate of return on equity at no additional cost to the taxpayer. 	[i] Sloan Science &amp; Film, http://www.scienceandsfilms.com/sf91/index.html, accessed 10 August 2013.  [ii] Climate Central, A Climate of Uncertainty, 2013. Available at: http://www.climatecentral.org/sites/default/files/climate-change/numbers_2013_summary_report.pdf, accessed 10 August 2013.  [iii] The Environmental Defense Fund, 2014. Available at: http://www.eenfund.org/research/en/abstract?sa=EC2C1</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is through the cooperative housing co-operatives, which could then be turned into affordable housing through a combination of tax-deductible donations and public support. One could argue that the cooperative housing co-operatives could also act as a catalyst for a city-wide cooperative housing strategy, since the structures handed over to them would then be eligible for re-construction. 	However, this is not at all what has been happening in Vancouver. Although the number of market-rate housing units has increased by approximately 20%, they have remained predominantly owner-occupied for decades. Most of the new market rate housing units have been built to the highest market rates – around 80% – which means that the owners have little choice but to accept or be displaced by more affordable housing options on the market. Moreover, market rate housing units have become increasingly difficult to access for working-class and lower-middle-class families, since access to them through rapid transit or other modes of transit is limited. 	</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human cultural capital is distributed and distributed in order to support a future city? The city is currently undertaking a massive renovation programme to transform the city centre, which includes the extensive demolition of large swaths of the historical city, the installation of a new $1.8 billion ‘Millionaire's Point’ development, the construction of a new ‘Sea-Level’island’ and the construction of a new ‘High Speed Rail’link between the two. These developments are expected to add thousands of new homes and billions of dollars in annual economic activity, but questions remain as to how the adaptive reuse of historic buildings will be distributed. What is known is that the vast majority of the ‘high-performing’ buildings will be sold to finance the project, while a minority will be turned into cooperative housing co-operatives – a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing strategy. 	One potential distribution of the ‘high-performance’ buildings is via the cooperative housing corporation, or CRE, as a step towards a city-wide cooperative housing corporation. Cooperative housing corporations emerged in the 1970s as a way to address the shortage of affordable housing with a progressive control mechanism that allowed residents to collectively improve their housing situation. In Cooperatives, residents benefit from the collective improvements of the cooperative as a collective. The cooperative also creates jobs for the local workers, providing skills development and work-study programmes for young people, and investing in infrastructure to support the cooperative’s activities – projects that create local employment opportunities and build local co-operatives. Cooperative housing corporations emerged as a progressive alternative to for-profit and non-profit housing providers, which dominated the market. They encouraged the creation of collective properties with collective management, expanded access to housing, and freed residents from the burden of monthly rent and mortgage payments. 	Co-operatives have become critical for the future of the urban housing sector due to their flexibility and the flexibility of workers,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications include Tools for Collective Evolution: Tools for Economic and Cultural Evolution (MIT/National Humanities Press, 2016); The Culture of Life: Evolutionary Psychology as the Basis of Cultural Evolution (MIT/National Humanities Press, 2014); The Culture of Life: Evolutionary Psychology as the Basis of Economic and Social Evolution (MIT/National Humanities Press, 2015); Culture and Economics: The Rise and Fall of Species (MIT/National Humanities Press, 2011); Culture and Economics: The Caste System as a Vector for Cultural Evolution (MIT/National Humanities Press, 2010); and Culture and Economics: The Impact of Intangible Assets (MIT/National Humanities Press, 2010). She is part of the Editorial Board of the journal, Current Anthropology, and part of the Editorial Board of the book, Current Anthropology: Essays on the Cultural Condition (Johns Hopkins University Press, 2016). She is also a regular columnist for the online journal Stages, where she has written on a</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications include Species’ Resource Codes: Collecting and Transforming Cultural Resources (MIT/National Geographic, 2015); Managing Cultural Resources: A Practical Guide (MIT/National Geographic, 2015); Managing Cultural Resources: Solutions for a Post-Apocalyptic Society (MIT/National Geographic, 2016); and Managing Cultural Spaces: From Crisis to Resilience (MIT/National Geographic, 2017). Her writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Education, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications include Things Fall Apart: Sharing Is Caring (2015), Building Stories from Scratch: Conversations on the Art of Being (2014), and 'Rethinking Media Narrative' in (ed.) Mairead Maguire &amp; Heather Tompkins (eds.) Things Fall Apart: Sharing Is Caring and Things Fall Apart: Conversations on the Arts and Culture of After (2014). She is currently researching the experiences of loss and grief experienced by First Nations peoples and is working with artists and artists� associations to explore how the sharing of cultural resources can contribute to the healing of wounds.Amanda Duffy is a writer, curator and arts organizer based in Toronto. Her work includes research, publications, projects and events including the sharing of cultural resources with First Nations peoples in Canada; the making of things with Scripps-Howard scientists in the U.S.; and an ongoing series of art projects with Indigenous peoples of Australia, the Middle East and Africa. Her work has also been featured</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications include scripts for artistic works; essays on art and the technological culture of the future; and the publication of an annual ‘Best of Alberta’s Culture &amp; Community issue of the Society of Illustrators. She is a regular speaker at the Computer History Museum, the Society for Information Critic and an editor of the Society of Illustrators online journal. Recent projects include the collaborative educational video series ARCHAEologicals (2012-2015) and the forthcoming video series ARCHAEologisches Waren (2016-2018). In addition to curating art events, Duffy is a co-founder of Alice Glass, an art institution that develops innovative ways of supporting artists through its gallery activities, workshops and joint ventures. She is also co-curator of the Alice Glass: Contemporaneity, Contemporaneity, and Other Essays (2018) and co-curator of the 2018 Edinburgh and Munich Biennials. Her essays have been published in Frieze,</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications include: “How to Start a Virtual Private Network (P2V)”; “Flow: An Embedded Time-Series Database for Machine Learning with Streaming Media Tools”; “Knowledge-Based Behaviour with Streaming Media Tools”; and “Knowledge-Driven Time-Series Generation for Mobile Apps using Hadoop and MongoDB”. Her work has been featured in a number of periodicals, including: The American Scholar, The American Prospect, The American Urbanist, US News &amp; World Report, The American Urbanist Review, American Urbanist, The American Journal of Urban Affairs, The American Journal of Physics, The American Journal of Geographies, and American Journal of Archaeology. She is also a co-editor of the online open access journal STREET Art &amp; Architecture.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is an artist and researcher based in Vancouver, Canada. She is currently working as an assistant curator</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications include Systemics, or Art as a Service (with Judy Wood and Daniel Fernández) and co-eding books with Judy Wood and Todd Meyers such as Managing Cultural Resources: An Alternative Cultural Science for an Alternative Economy. She is currently working with a collaborative research group at the University of Alberta Libraries to publish a book series that includes essays on art, culture and sustainable development.Doubtless, the collaborative nature of such work invites engagement from interested parties. In this sense, it is both predictable and potentially instructive to me in ways of thinking about the impact of art and culture in a world disrupted by neoliberalism, capitalism and its attendant tensions and contradictions. In the spirit of the conference, this issue of Spacing opens with a story from the opening day of the Liverpool Biennial, which we hear repeatedly in the conference room: the story of the Easter Rising, the Canadian involvement in the Second World War and the place of religion in contemporary societies. The story is told in</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications include Network Culture (with Maria Olascoaga and Colin Campbell, Blackwell, Oxford, 2012) and Managing Cultures: Integrating Art, Technology and Governance (with Heather Tompkins and Neil Johnson, Blackwell, Oxford, 2016). She is the author of Managing Cultures: Integrating Art, Technology and Governance (MIT Press, 2015) and was a finalist for the ACM VIVAER/CULTURAL VIDEO AWARD.Amanda Duffy is an Assistant Professor in the Departments of Computer Science and Information Studies at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include art, programming, and computer science. Her publications include her 2015 book Managing Cultures: Embedded Systems [working title] and the 2015 book The Community Library Reader [working title]. She is also the editor and publisher of the journal RECipes &amp; Racism: A Journal of Mexican American Culinary History (with Javier Duarte and Miguel Duarte, plenion, New York,</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications include the book CULTURAL THEORY: ANTHROPOLOGY AND ANNOTATION, co-edited with Lisa Bud-Frierman and Tom McCutcheon, 'The Art of Not Being Governed' in ANNALS OF ANTHROPOLOGY, vol. 34, no. 3 (2014), and 'Resources for the Anthropocene' in N. Y. U. JOURNAL OF ART AND ANTHROPOLOGY, vol. 42, no. 1 (2013), and 'Art and Culture, Globalization and Economics' in THE ANNALS OF ANTHROPOLOGY, vol. 37, no. 2 (2014), pp.1–35.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Associate Professor in the Departments of Anthropology and Geography at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include globalisation and its discontents, cultural ecology and related fields, and urbanization. Her publications include essays on art and the social</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications include scripts for collaborative cultural production (with Indigenous communities in Canada and the United States) and the manual Systemic Industrial Culture (with Indigenous communities in the United States and Mexico).In addition to writing and presenting scientific papers, she is a regular columnist for Scientific American and Science, as well as a regular contributor to onlinemagazineStages.Amanda Duffy works in collaboration with the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute (2013-2016) and the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute (2015-2020) to explore the science and politics of tropical archipelagos and their wildlife populations, and to discover how the social sciences can help create new species. She is also the host of the popular online radio show Stages (www.stagesandternational.com).Amanda was previously Curator for the Canadian Pavilion at the 58th Venice Biennale (2007-2009); founder and curator of the Open University (2005-07), and a curator of the Zócalo Center for the Performing Arts (</text>
    <text>project raises questions about how human biodiversity is managed in such a way as to enable humans to contribute significantly to the creation of new species. The conference raises questions about the limits of potential extinctions due to a number of factors, including the impact of climate change, over-exploitation of natural resources, over-emphasising of profit over all other considerations. In addition to raising awareness of these issues, the conference raises questions about what can be learned from the impact of such species on a global scale. If we are to have any hope of salvaging the species from the precipice of extinction, we will have to learn to live together in harmony with one another, as fellow human beings.Download this article as PDFAmanda DuffyAmanda Duffy is Assistant Professor in the Departments of Biological Sciences and Visual Cultures at the University of Alberta Libraries. Her research interests include the creation of virtual private networks, the sharing of cultural resources and the sharing of knowledge, methods and tools for the management of cultural resources. Her publications include &quot;The Culture Catch-22: Managing Cultures of Inaccessibility&quot; in The ANNALS of the Socially Engaged Scientist, 2016, and &quot;Catch 22: Managing Inaccessibility of Cultural Resources&quot; in the American Journal of Sociology, 2015. Her work has also been featured in venues such as TEDxMOCAD, TEDxLiverpool, TEDxSan Francisco, TEDxLiverpool, TEDxMontréal, TEDxGlasgow, TEDxAtlanta, and TEDxWashington, D.C.Amanda Duffy is a writer, curator, provocateur, and co-founder of Amaury-du-Pacteux, a multi-disciplinary art and cultural centre and research centre into the &quot;culture paradox&quot; in which she works. Her writing has been featured in publications such as the New York Times, the New York Times Higher Education Supplement, the Daily Beast, The New Republic, Grantland, Bust, The New York Times Higher Education</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Gen
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#sthash.KLsd.F._ZC._2.yK.bTl.F._2.yL._3.ymls (accessed October 2016).[2] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#sthash.KLsd.F._ZC._2.yK.bTl.F._2.yL._3.ymls (accessed October 2016).[3] See: http://www.genoa</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#sthash.71PXqDs.dpuf.kFdJl.dpuf.kFdJl.dpuf.kFdJl.dpuf.kFdJl. 	[2] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#sthash.kI6lA.dpuf.kFdJl.dpuf.kFdJl.dpuf.kFdJl.dpuf.kFd</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#furtherIssues&amp;issue=3&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#summary&amp;fuseaction=summary&amp;fuseaction=accesskey&amp;year=1996&amp;issue=1&amp;fuseaction=accesskey&amp;fuseaction=accesskey [2] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#summary&amp;</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#sthash.LJl.dAfE.dpuf.1988.xls.en.UK.1998.05.13.xls.en.UK.1998.08.13.xls.en.UK.1998.06.13.xls.en.UK.1998.07.13.xls.en.2002.12.13.xls.en.2002.12.13.xls.en.2002.04.13.xls.en.2002.04.13.xls.en.2002.06.13.xls.en.2002.06.13.xls.en.2002.07.13.xls.en.2002.08.13.xls.en.2002.09.13.xls.en.2002.10.13.xls.en</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.pdf#sthash.9TlAuRl.dpuf.[2] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa’s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa’s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa’s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.pdf#sthash.9TlAuRl.dpuf.[3] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa’s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa’s-New-York-</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;tab=summary&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#sthash.Nl9Wl.PW.3.html#STFU [2] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa’s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa’s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa’s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;tab=summary&amp;file=Genoa’s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa’s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html [</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#sthash.DlgE.Ll7.PTE.B.3.2002.dap.B.3.2002.xls].[2] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#sthash.DlgE.Ll7.PTE.B.3.2002.dap.B.3.2002.xls].[3] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Index.htm#sthash.kX4f8sDl.dpuf.20141219.FlAuW5l.dpuf.20141219.FlAuW5l.dpuf.20141221.RHTMl.RHTMl.20141219.html[2] See: https://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2017/04/21/new-economy/[3] See: https://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2018/08/14/new-economy/[4] See: https://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2018/09/11/new-economy/[5] See: http://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2018/09/</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#sthash.TlNl.Dlg.2Q6q6E.dpufoE.dpufoN.dpufoE.dpufoE.dpufoN.dpufoE.dpufoE.dpufoE.dpufoN.dpufoE.dpufoE.dpufoE.dpufoN.dpufoE.dpufoE.dpufoE.dpufoN.dpufoE.dpufoE.dpufoE. 	[2] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa’s-New-</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has meant the absence of an official Oikos catalogue. The catalogue, which has been available since 1999, has been supplemented by a triennale issue of the journal Ostravision (published by Ostravision SA). The triennale issue of Ostravision was founded in 1994 and published every two years. In 1995, the edition of Ostravision, Volume 22, Number 3, Spring, was published as a book published by Ostravision. Ostravision was established in Paris and New York and London, and in 1996 in Berlin. In 1995, Oikos was established in Berlin. 	[1] See: http://www.genoa.org/en/index.php/en/title/summary?title=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;issue=2&amp;doc=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html&amp;file=Genoa%27s-New-York-Architecture-Brief.html#sthash.FZdvF.DyV._9.LWhl.F.ElC._Y2lI6lLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWhlLWh</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postmodern Culture: A Reader in Cultural Theory (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1967), p. 11.  4  Morehshin Imam, ‘On the nature of postmodernism’,  	The Philosophy of Postmodernism: Critical Essays 	, Vol. 1 (Fall 1998), p. 19.  5  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postmodernism: A Critical Reader (Oxford: Oxford University Press, 1991), p. 20.  6  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postmodernism: A Critical Reader (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1988), pp. 12–25.  7  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postmodernism: Critical Essays 	, Vol. 2, 1990, p. 57.  8  Morehshin Imam, ‘On postmodernism and the culture industry</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postmodern Culture (New York: Vintage, 1998), p. 3.  4  Poulantzas,  	Real Life: Conversations on Modernity (Vancouver: University of British Columbia Press, 1968), p. 3.  5  Marija Cetinic,  	Real Life: Conversations on Democracy (Vancouver: University of British Columbia Press, 1968), p. 3.  6  Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), pp. 4–7.  7  Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, p. 3.  8  Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, p. 3.  9  Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, p. 3</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postmodern Culture (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1991), p. 12.  4  Theodor Adorno,  	The Jewish Theology, trans. Donald W. Clark (New York: Columbia University Press, 1978), p. 21.  5  Adorno,  	Postulation of Enlightenment, trans. Donald W. Clark (New York: Columbia University Press, 1978), p. 21.  6  Adorno,  	The Jewish Theology, trans. Donald W. Clark (New York: Columbia University Press, 1978), p. 41.  7  Adorno,  	Postulation of Enlightenment, p. 42.  8  Adorno,  	The Culture Industry, trans. Donald W. Clark (New York: Columbia University Press, 1981), p. 20.  9  Adorno,  	Postulation of Enlightenment, p. 37.  10 </text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	The Culture Industry: Critical Apparitions of Public Life (New York: Oxford University Press, 1988), p. 4.  4  Ibid., p. 28.  5  Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, p. 3.  6  Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, p. 3.  7  Adorno,  	The Culture Industry, p. 38.  8  Ibid., p. 38.  9  Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, p. 3.  10  Henri Lefebvre,  	The Culture Industry, p. 394.  11  Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, p. 3.  12  Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ide</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postmodern Culture (New York: Vintage, 1974), p. 9.  4  Søren Kierkegaard,  	The Concept of Abandonment, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (Philadelphia: Penguin, 1994), p. 42.  5  Martin Amis,  	Postmodern Culture (New York: Vintage, 1993), p. 1.  6  Rafico Ruiz, ‘Between Cultures of Mass Deception and Literary Criticism’,  	New York Review of Books, Vol. 26 (July/August, 1993), p. 40.  7  John Berger,  	Postmodern Culture: Social Exclusion and Cultural Criticism, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (New York: Vintage, 1972), p. 7.  8  John Berger,  	Postmodern Culture, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (New York: Vintage, 1972), p. 7. </text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postmodern Culture and Revolution, trans. Evelyn Ruxton (New York: Vintage Books, 1980), p. 4.  4  John Berger,  	Postmodern Culture and Revolution, trans. Henning Thomte (New York: Vintage Books, 1980), p. 44.  5  Ibid., p. 4.  6  David Harvey,  	Postmodernism and Its Critics, trans. Evelyn Ruxton (New York: Vintage Books, 1980), p. 2.  7  David Harvey,  	Postmodernism and Its Critics, p. 3.  8  Ibid., p. 4.  9  David Harvey,  	Postmodernism and Its Critics, p. 4.  10  Ibid., p. 7.  11  David Harvey,  	Postmodernism and Its Critics, p. 8.  12 David Harvey,  </text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postmodern Culture (New York: Columbia University Press, 1988), p. 1.  4  David Harvey,  	Postmodern Culture (New York: Columbia University Press, 1989), p. 1.  5  Harvey,  	Postmodern Culture, p. 32.  6  Harvey,  	Postmodern Culture, Chapter 3: Towards an Ethics of Art and Culture, p. 72.  7  Harvey,  	Postmodern Culture, p. 5.  8  Lefebvre,  	Postmodernism, p. 81.Download this article as PDFLauren StruykiewiczFlorian LehmannFlorian Lehmann is Professor in The Arts and Social Sciences at the Winchester School of Art, University of Southampton. His research interests include postmodernism and artistic practice, political economy and notions of creativity. His latest projects include:  challenging the current state of moral psychology through the</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	Psychoanalysis: A Critique of Social and Cultural Psychoanalysis, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (New York: Vintage, 1974), p. 100.  4  Thierry Meyssan,  	Postmodern Culture: Art and Anarchy, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (New York: Vintage, 1980), p. 34.  5  John Berger,  	Postmodern Culture: Art and Archives (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1994), p. 16.  6  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postmodern Culture: Art and History, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (New York: Vintage, 1980), p. 36.  7  Towson, Maryland Publishing Company, 1890, p. 8.  8  James Howard Kunstler,  	Postmodern Culture: Art and Politics (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1987), p. 12. </text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	Postwar Marxism, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (Chicago: University of Chicago Press, 1993), p. 8.  4  Ray Bradbury,  	Gravity's Rainbow (Cambridge MA: MIT Press, 1994), p. 263.  5  W. E. B. Du Bois,  	The Gathering Storm (1944), p. 19.  6  Harvey Milkman,  	The Culture Industry: Surplus Value in Historical Art, trans. Stefan Collini (Durham: Duke University Press, 2002), p. 38.  7  Bradbury,  	Gravity's Rainbow, p. 7.  8  Kristin Scott Main,  	The Gathering Storm, p. 23.  9  My conversation with Jeff Kelly,  	Postmodernism: Critical Cultural Studies (Durham: Duke University Press, 2003), p. 45.  10  </text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on the notion of the ‘artificial human’, and the potential for such perspectives to be repurposed to serve humanity. 	[i] Nadine Attewell,  	Unfixing the Crisis: Social Exclusion and the Quest for Art (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 1991), p. 11.  1  Timur Kurpadagov, ‘МReal Life: Art as Repurposing of Imagination’, in  	Postmodern Culture, Vol. 2 (Fall 1991), p. 4.  2  Theodor Adorno,  	Postscript to the German Ideology, 1936, in  	Aufklärung des Deutschen Volumes, 3rd ed. (Berlin: Deutsches Verlag, 1942–1939), p. 1.  3  Henri Lefebvre,  	Out of Time: Modernity and Postmodernity 	, trans. Stefan Collini-Weaver (New York: Cambridge University Press, 1998), p. 8.  4  Karl Marx, ‘The Civil War as a Cultural War’, in  	Capital 	, February, Vol. 1, p. 338.  5  Karl Marx, ‘On the Production of Space and Time’, in  	Capital, Vol. 1, p. 335.  6  William Burchell,  	Mapping the Nation: Race, Capital, and Capitalist Society 	, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1993), p. 81.  7  Nik Lederman,  	Capital 	, trans. Donald Nicholson-Smith (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 1989), p. 4.  8  Karl Marx, ‘A Note</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists’ buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.This is a difficult dynamic to maintain in a city. The proliferation of tourism generates debate and discussion, but it is also a fact of life for many in the area; a fact of which is that even with all the construction going on in the area, the Biennale cannot be taken out of the city. This is partly because it is such a sensitive area for the Biennale, and partly because the Biennale is such an old school affair: it is the oldest running, and so its models are the preserve of the elite. Nevertheless, the</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, JTDW.Joint ventures between government and tourism companies are common in Spain, but the increased involvement of the military and security forces in recent years has raised questions about the appropriateness of such relationships. In January 2018, it was reported that Civil Guard troops had opened fire during a demonstration in the Ciudadana state capital, Macri, after a local art collective sought to halt a military crackdown on public murals in the city. The report sparked a mass movement against the military presence in the city. In response, the military launched an investigation, which in turn, sparked a political crisis that saw several legislators quit in protest. The crisis, which lasted for several months, saw several Napoles leaders detained and another accused of masterminding a coup.After months of political unrest, in the wake of the attempted coup, Napoles</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Carlos Cruz. The new name is a misnomer. The new Urban Realm is nothing like the old one. It’s just a re-branding exercise. The phrase ‘Urban Realm’ is a misnomer. It’s an urban misnomer. The word itself conjures up images of chaos, oppression and degradation. It’s a word that was once synonyms for oppression and subjugation. More to the point, it’s a misnomer because the people who use it control what is considered ‘urban’ in the first place.The emergence of the Biennale as a phenomenon is a remarkable event in its own right. It is a rarityf anywhere in the world in which people flock in force to experience art as a means of making themselves visible and objects of</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Miguel Hidalgo. The Urban Realm initiative was also an element of the Biennale that year. The new name reflects the mixed uses that the new structures would enable, with offices for tourism promotion, offices for naturals, and even a rooftop garden where artists could be sheltered from the elements. In the centre of the project lies the urban core, which is being re-named, and which will henceforth be referred to as ‘Cali’. The new name is a direct translation of the Quechua word for ‘city’ (casibais), and echoes the legacy of Castilian and Portuguese colonialism. It is a pun on the Spanish: cambia, or ‘cameroon’, which is both the name of a colony and a city. Writing in the journal Mémoires</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Miguel Hernández. The idea was that the buildings would ‘be there for a community to reclaim and evolve’, but also that ‘the proposals would be taken up by the city’s planning department and then made into a new development proposal, so as to avoid a potential conflict between public works and eco-systems projects. The increased police presence around the stadium is a response to any threat to the stadium from fans, but also because the plans call for a new, yet to be determined, ‘city scale computer generated ‘map space and ‘cloud ‘that will enable seamless sharing and collaboration between all modes of human mobility and experience, allowing for the exchange of places and the shifting of cultural weightlessness’.2. The ‘present, present, and future of urban space and</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Miguel Hernández. The name change comes as a consequence of a collaboration between architects and designers and representatives from the Attorney General's Office, as well as representatives from the local cultural organisation, Tezuka Munitions. The teams working on the project reported back to the authorities and the Mayor about the concerns and suggestions raised by the public. The new name is a collaboration between architects and designers and is a response to this ongoing dialogue and feedback loop. It is an acknowledgement that this ongoing process – which has seen the formation of over one hundred local groups take part in the Design District Prototyping Process at City Hall over the past 18 months – has produced a new design that works for the area, but it is also a statement on the continuing need to confront the authorities and the need for incremental change, so as to produce a more socially</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.2  A timeline of the development of the ‘Tuscan Quarter’, 2017, HC with glossary of terms describing geographical areas affected by an ongoing or recent conflict. Courtesy of Defensa Cultural Centre, Madrid. 	In late 2015, in an attempt to understand better the spatial relations between the city and its cultural assets, a Defensa Cultural Centre team of artists, led by Guillermo Vitale , moved locally by the year from 2015 to 2017 to explore the historical and contemporary significance</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial has been re-branded as the Camp Nou in an attempt to re-brand the area around the stadium as a desirable destination for corporate and other development. The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.The re-branding has been accompanied by an increased police presence in and around the stadium. The new name is a response to a local campaign that saw artists' buildings – some brand new, some old – taken up as part of a public New Urban Realm. The campaign was led by architects and designers and was supported by the Spanish government and tourism company, Estelíz Tapia. The idea was that the buildings would become ‘new ways of being in the city’, a development that would bring investment and jobs to the area, but also generate discussion and debate around the place of art and culture in a city.In November 2017, the Camp Nou was closed to visitors following a security alert. The decision was made to re-open the site the following April, during the FIFA Confederations Cup, with improved security and a capacity for supporters to follow the proceedings online. The decision to open in May 2019 has been taken, with a new name still to be decided. In the meantime, questions continue to surround the future of the site – a situation that could be easily changed by the fans. The Camp Nou remains a tourist trap, but what has been built on its ruins?</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city is in danger of becoming disconnected from its resources, or when infrastructure projects are needed to absorb the excess capacity of the metropolis? In such cases, the need to be able to communicate and coordinate across a variety of different locations arises: where do we look for jobs, for example?  The key is that the distributed AI that is developing these kinds of problems will not be able to be everywhere at once; it will need to be contextualised and distributed across a range of different locations. So just as there are regional variations in the technology of cars and planes, there are regional variations in the kinds of infrastructure that can be built to support them. And just as there are local variations in the kinds of language that people use, there are regional variations in the kinds of social life can be forged. In this sense,  	different regions can be seen to be interconnected, and this is one reason why regions contain so many different kinds of labour and why they tend to have different cultures. </text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city is in danger of becoming uninhabitable, or will our understanding of the social impacts of climate change render it into a dystopian nightmare? Just as important is the sense of personal discovery that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developing world be able to? Will the people on Earth be able to identify the projects that are useful for the future of their city? Will the people in the future be able to identify the mistakes that have caused them to fall behind in technological progress?These are questions that address the anxieties and fantasies of a city that is no longer a coherent whole, but which nonetheless seeks to organize space and time in ways that are contingent on the desires of individuals. In the early twentieth century, the quest for individualised access to resources and an idealised sense of the city was accompanied by the individualisation of society through the quest for a ‘society of the willing’.</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city is in crisis, and act accordingly? In such a scenario, the very fabric of the city is at stake. New forms of displacement are being imagined, and old hierarchies of urbanity are being challenged.  One can imagine a future in which the connectedness of all of humanity is realised, but this does not come without struggles and pains. The desire to connect and merge people comes with a complexity of tensions, which cannot be simplified down to a single notion of humaneness.  One of the earliest challenges to the notion of humaneness came from French sociologist Michel Foucalt, who was working in Algeria in 1960s, and who was assassinated in prison that same year.2  He was working on the Tariq Busyama Study Centre for Tariqun Culture and Human Rights at Algerian Prison Colony No. 2. Foucalt developed his ideas about social transformation through the logic of historical and political marginalisation.3  One of the central concepts in Fouc</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city is in crisis, and act accordingly? Will we be able to pull off such massive migrations of people as have already taken place, and will we be able to design our cities to meet the needs of the future cities that will be built in the aftermath of these catastrophes?  In recent years, the question of contingency and its relationship to urbanisation has become a matter of contention. Although it is true that in the modern city the focus is increasingly on the importance of infrastructure and the maintenance of it, there is still considerable internal variability that contributes to the success of any given project. The extent to which the city is self-sufficient in its design and maintenance depends on a range of other factors, including the popularity of certain ideas and ideologies, the economy and political landscape, as well as cultural norms and values. In the contemporary city, the heterogeneity and unpredictability of the urban environment is accentuated, and the city appears to be reaching a limit at which it cannot expand indefinitely. At</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city is in crisis? Will we be able to reimagine how our cities are produced through the intelligent design of buildings and the built environment? Even if we attempt to reduce the number of connectedness, will the built environment still require the labour of many thousands of people to be produced and disseminated? And what if, through the power of AI, this labour becomes automated? Will the social costs of this form of labour be much higher than the social benefits? Will the social impacts of this form of labour be much more volatile? Will the social impacts of this form of automation be much more complicated? If the social impacts of this form of automation are to be taken into account in constructing the future urbanity that we desire, then we need to begin to ask how these social impacts will affect the people who will now be the users of these technologies, and how will their labour affect the social dynamics of the built environment.  One can begin to imagine such a future through the medium of cultural practices that are</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city is in danger of becoming overrun by a rapidly urbanising population, or will our understanding of probability make it so that we cannot create world-changing solutions?  One of the ways in which new technologies are enabling greater ecological footprint is through the use of 'smart' materials and devices. These materials and devices incorporate data to monitor and analyse the city’s resource usage, and to augment city services such as water and sewage treatment. And just as importantly, they also incorporate social functions such as mapping and social networks, which enable large-scale participation and empowerment through the sharing of knowledge and experiences. In this narrative, the sharing of stories and knowledge becomes both a precondition for new technological solutions and a final outcome.  One could argue, however, that this is only possible because of the inefficiency of the human organism as a system: the human race is becoming ever more like machines. And while this may be the case, it does not make the use of new technologies inevitable. Rather</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city is in crisis, and act accordingly? Will we be able to build sustainable ways of inhabiting arable land, while minimising environmental impact? These are questions that are of great concern to the inhabitants of these cities, and yet of little concern to the technologists who control much of the development going on in the world. These are questions that are of great concern to the inhabitants of these cities, and yet of little concern to the technologists who control much of the development going on in the world. New ‘world’ narratives are constantly being invented, and old paradigms are being redefined through the process of globalisation. In the run-up to these narratives, people are often left wondering what is happening to them. Is there a new apocalyptic vision emerging, or are there ways to reimagine alternative futures? What constitutes a city today is defined by its appearance on a global map, but how do we register this as a collective experience? Urban space is often claimed to be</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city is in crisis, or malnourished, or both? Will we be able to take steps to mitigate the impact of climate change through aggressive adaptation measures, or will we be unable to do so at the scale required? Of course, the role of the city in these narratives is to some extent to render the technocratic ideal of a smooth interface between society and nature ‘real’ – in so far as this is possible in a connected society – while to others, it is to render the society as inherently unstable and subject to disaster. As the great American novelist Kurt Vonnegut describes, in his fable, the Puritans: ‘Were the machines not so omnipotent, and man so enslaved, we should not have had to invent the metaphors of climate, or the term ‘climate’… Man should not have to hide from the elements. Let nature deal with the things that are cruel and mean.’2  This is the interface that has become</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city is in danger of becoming uninhabitable, or will our understanding of the ‘world’ be enough to create an alternative future where humanity is not bound by the conditions of its cities?  In the age of the biennial, the question is being asked whether the biennial represents a new normal or whether it is the very definition of urban sprawl. As the biennial has become more and more of a cultural phenomenon, and as the cultural theorist Richard Florida has been arguing, the answer to his question, ‘what is the limits of contemporary art?’, is the answer to the question, ‘what is the limit of cultural production?’.2  If, as Florida suggests, the answer to the cultural limit is no limits at all, then the cultural production that is the offspring of the biennial may produce ever more social and ecological havoc than the art it is intended to critique.  If, as Florida suggests, the answer to the cultural limit is</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the connection with the auto industry that emerged in large measure through the influence of Ford and its founder, Robert Ford Dearborn.  Local Self-Generation and the Future City The notion of the ‘local’ in relation to the global city seems to be central to the new ‘world’ narrative. This foundational fiction of global interconnectedness is characterised by how we are all connected via the ‘leap’ – or ‘happenstance’ – in the event that one of us does not exist yet is very much a part of the larger narrative of the ‘world’.1  Such is the narrative that is being told through the new technology of connected cities. But just as important is the sense of contingency that comes with this connectedness. If one person on Earth does not know how to use the tools of globalisation effectively, how will the developed world be able to? Will we be able to detect when a city is in trouble and act accordingly? In an ideal world, this could happen via sophisticated mapping and rapid response operations such as those developed by the US Geological Survey. But as we know, this is not always possible, especially in the US, and especially not in developing countries where citizens are often not consulted as much as needed when decisions are being made on the ground level.2  The connectedness that is being promoted is based on the inability to detect natural disasters such as floods and droughts in advance. But as the biennale has become more regionalised and globalised, and as the biennale visitor sees it, ‘local’ is no longer the correct place to be.  In an ideal world, we would all travel to the same places and see the same things. But in the real world, we live in different worlds, and our place in life is less certain than it is online. And as biennials become more institutionalised and globalised, and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to engage with the notion of the city.  Whether the Biennial was ever going to engage with the notion of the city however, is unclear. Its 2009 decision to focus on the city in a way that it was not just about financial profit maximisation for the city-state, but about architecture in its social and ecological significance – in other words, the city as a social construction – seemed a strange break from the previous interest in complex urban systems. The Biennial itself seems to have absorbed this neoliberal tendency in some perverse way. The city is now seen as a valuable commodity, and the Biennial’s interest in cultural exchange arising from the city as a production of commodities rather than from the commodity as such. The break with the previous interest in the city comes at a cost, however. The economic logic of the biennial is now being undermined by the social, ecological and urban effects of suburban sprawl, urban infrastructures and the biennial itself. The city is no longer</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to engage with the contemporaneous political, social and ecological conditions on which the city is dependent. In the report, the city is described as ‘severely limited’ by a lack of affordable housing, which is defined as a ‘value-added’ production generated by the built environment including the city’s infrastructure and built circulation of goods and people. In other words, the built environment – which presumably contributes to the value of the ‘added’ – is characterised by what the report calls a ‘contravision’ between intensive development and resource scarcity. All these words are delivered as a threat, and are intended to terrify. The implication is that absent a concerted policy of resource depletion and depletion of the built environment – which is described as being of ‘critical importance’ to the city – the built environment will be incorporated into the social and ecological systems of the city in ways that will render the built environment malleable and subject to the whims</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to engage in a culturally responsive, public realmal-making enterprise. The report suggests that the biennial should be established as a fully fledged cultural organisation, with a curatorial approach that draws upon ‘the cultural resources of the region’, citing as an example ‘the blending of art and art history’ through the curatorial lens of ‘the archaeology of architecture’. The rationale for this ‘coast’centric’ curatorial approach is given as one to be pursued not only within, but also ‘out to sea’, in the words of the report. Toward that end, a number of areas of the coast are given special emphasis in ‘The Art of Living Sea Level’ (2009).[20]  A cultural ecology of the sea per 10 	Earth Surface Area (DSLA), a national database on land use and infrastructure compiled by the USGS, is the basis of the new architecture and planning. It</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to engage with the on-going cultural exchange between the two cities. In the report, Fertility and Baby, co-authored by Professors Amira Hassanein and Fadi Alabamie, the two female curators are reported as saying that they did not want to create an ‘open and transparent space for discussion and debate’ about the meaning of art and aesthetics in the city, because it would ‘alienate the viewers’ watching the show from the city. I find the premise of the report somewhat bizarre. As I have been outlining in a chapter heading (found at the foot of the book), the city was already experiencing an art decimation, with many artists either abandoning the city or moving to safer surroundings elsewhere in the country. The fact that the report authors seem to think that the art of Liverpool is somehow superior to that of any other city in the country, or that it is somehow ‘better suited to live and work in’ the city,</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to engage with the fact that we’ve only just begun to unpick the social harms caused by neoliberalism.  943 As the Biennial got bigger and better, and as it became ever more apparent that the city would soon be a major tourist attraction, and that not having a biennial in the city was a huge booking mistake, artists began to look for alternative destinations. Some started creating their own biennials. One of the best-known is the Melbourne Biennial, which began in 1991 and has been running ever since, with varying degrees of autonomy, geographical freedom, and host city status. The Biennial has its roots in the ‘80s, but has moved through the ‘90s, ‘00s, and ‘10s, becoming something like a third force in the city. It has a particular interest in the ‘80s, and the diffuse forms of identity it promotes. It is a rare event for visitors to Melbourne, but for</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to engage with the idea of the biennial as a curatorial concept. That event would have required a creative and interesting way to envelop the city in a dense, multi-sited, highly visible ‘festival of ideas’, interconnected by a ‘city of ideas’ culminating in a biennial itself.  Whether the ‘festival of ideas’ described by Łuzu speak of actualization or some other kind of visionary state of mind is beyond me, but the point is that the biennial has a habit of rewriting history in a way that precludes, or else leaves unresolved some of the  questions that were raised about the historical role of the city. For many years, this meant refusing to acknowledge the city’s cultural significance, or even mentioning its existence in curatorial reports. In recent years, it has meant actively creating fictional narratives around particular aspects of the city based on facts and figures that are often made up or fabrication. I believe the</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to engage with the notion of the contemporaneous, or to engage with the idea of the biennial, in a contemporaneous way. The report, written by the chair of the BIennial committee, and drawn up in conjunction with the museum that hosted the festival, seems to suggest that the event should have taken place in '8 ‘9 ’inch films' format, and in an area of Liverpool with a similar cinematic sensibility to the one that the Biennial is currently staging in. The 8 ј9  	1 quickShipfilm format emerged organically from a class produced by the Liverpool Biennial in 2009, and has been a regular collaborator since its inception in 2011. Its adoption as an art-form and the places in which it is embedded, both historical and anthropological, suggests a possible engagement with postcoloniality and settler colonialism, and the politics of displacement that result from that, as well as with the question of indeterminacy. The film format may</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to engage with the historical materiality of the festival that is still an essential part of the festival’s format. The report notes that: ‘Over the past twenty years, the number of biennials has more rapidly increased in number and location worldwide, and has become a global tourist draw.’1 This is consistent with the city emerging as a global tourism hub, as globalised metropolises such as London are wont to do.The internationalisation of the biennial is a story line that is more or less static, with notable exceptions such as Venice and Bilbao. But the location of these events has shifted with the changing economic and political landscape of the world. As biennials worldwide are now tendered as a global service, they are now also subject to the shifting and dynamic dynamics of the biennale market. The 2008 Venice Biennale, for example, was an exception to this general rule. It was an exception to this general rule because it was</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to engage with the temporality of the biennial in a meaningful way.  And, indeed, the report itself, like all biennials at the time, seemed premised on the precariat’s collapse. The ‘biennial boom’ that the art market was screaming about was here to stay. The hype and the profit were too great, and the art market became desensitized to the need for artists to produce and spread awareness of a given project.  The ‘biennial bust’ that the art market was screaming about was gone by then, but the biennial itself was never meant to be a permanent fixture of the city. It would be foolish to suggest that the art market has a clear idea of what it wants from an art institution anymore, or that the biennial is any more a market for art than the regular art market is. There are different kinds of biennials now, and different kinds of biennials with different kinds of curators</text>
    <text>The postponed 2021 Biennial, and its suggestion to hold a one-day symposium, was not a direct result of the festival’s decision to host the event in the city, but rather, as the Liverpool Biennial’s 2008/9 staging of the festival indicated, a product of the city’s economic crisis, the construction of new airport, road and rail networks, and subsequent expansion of hotels, office and retail developments. As the city experienced a neoliberal economic transformation, and as a consequence the Biennial’s fee schedule increasingly included travel to the city in exchange for a set number of locally produced works, and its asset management increasingly included the production of affordable housing, the precarity of housing became an issue. The decision to postpone the event until 2028 may have more to do with the city’s economic  942 Fertility and Behaviour (2008-09), a brief report to the BIennial, than with any real desire to host a biennial, or to engage with the notion of the city.  The report notes that the biennial form has become increasingly ambiguous: ‘as the central hub of biennial production in a city, it is the locus of multiple fictions and multiple representations’. It notes that the ‘biennial’ has come to encapsulate ‘all aspects of the production of a city’, while simultaneously ‘eroding its distinctive character and purpose […] [T]he biennial has become a global phenomenon’. It concludes with the line ‘but there is only so much life can contain;] a true sense of the ‘biennial’ must open up elsewhere – in museums, in village squares, in the urban fabric itself […] [T]he core biennial must reinvent itself, every time it is staged in a city today, in order to sustain its distinctive character and purpose […] Today, the core biennial is staged in the USA, in New York, in</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii]
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xiii] Ibid. [xiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xvi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xviii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xix] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xx] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxvi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.26. [xvi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28.Download this article as PDFColin WardColin Ward is an Assistant Professor in English and Film Studies at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta. His dissertation examines the film Silent Running in order to provide a critical lens through which to examine the practices and ideologies underlying the film. He also co-curates the new program in film studies at Mount Royal University called Screenings: An Introduction to Screening Culture. Excerpt from Silent Running, Colin Ward, Translated by Leslie Urry &amp; Edited by Peter Schjeldahl, 2011. 	From the transcript of your talk with Max Brooks, the Secretary of the TRYON conference: 	Max Brooks</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xviii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xix] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xx] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxvi] Ward,</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xviii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xix] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xx] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxii] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiii] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxvi] Ward</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii] For a more thorough discussion of how we might learn to engage with the world through engaged practice, see Susanne Ruehle, What is Art? An Introduction to the Terms, Blackwell, Oxford, 1994, p.192. [xiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xiv] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, chapter 3. [xv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, chapter 3. [xvii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xviii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xx] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xxii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xviii] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xix] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xx] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxii] David Halberstam, The Art of Not Being Governed: An Ethics of Not Being Governed, Oxford University Press, Oxford and Cambridge, 1986, p.40. [xxiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiv] Ward,</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xviii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xix] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xx] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xxi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, pp.29–37. [xxii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xxiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xxiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxvi] Ward</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii] Ward and Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xiii] Ward and Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xvi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xvii] Ward and Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xviii] Ward and Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xix] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xx] Ward and Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxii] Ward and Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiii] Ward and Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxv] Ward, Cognitive</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xvii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xviii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xix] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xx] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28.Download this article as PDFColin WardColin Ward is Professor in the Department of English and Film Studies at the Winchester Arts College where he taught for two years. His research interests include the literary form, its literary-visual and sometimes ‘political’ incarnations, as well as its social and cultural aspects. He has written on a range of subjects including postmodernisms</text>
    <text>counterpoint of automata might offer alien perspectives on human history. 	[i] See, for example, Brett Frischmann and Rob Kling, The End of Postmodernism, Zone Books, New York, 1987, p.3. [ii] Ibid. [iii] See, for example, Colin Ward and Stephen Leacock, eds., Cognitive Cultures, Blackwell, Oxford and Cambridge, Mass., 1988, p.147. [iv] See, for example, Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.13. [v] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vi] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.14. [vii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [viii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [ix] See Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [x] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xvi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xvii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xviii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xix] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xx] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xxi] Ibid., p.28. [xxii] Ibid., p.28. [xxiii] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.28. [xxiv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xxv] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [xxvi] Ward, Cognitive Cultures, p.27. [</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds of things can it uncover? This is, I believe, the question that needs to be asked of the new curatorial form: what kind of world can it create? 	The answer to this question could conceivably range from the sublime (Planet Earth) to the absurd (Jungle Book). I prefer the latter, which is to say, things that we actually live in and have to deal with everyday. The grotesque, I prefer to think of things as they actually are. But there are other considerations as well. For example, things that we value and appreciate – art, architecture, history, for example – are produced in this country in large part through the production of labour and other labourers. As a result, the production of beautiful architecture is constrained within the city. And while the production of beautiful architecture is good for the city, it is not so good for the countryside or the metropolis. Towns and cities have particular advantages in that they are situated in relatively favourable economic positions relative</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds of things lie beyond the surface of our world? This is the question of things and beauty.In the cultural studies department of the Royal College of Art, we have a project that we call the Beauty Project. This is a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition project that brings together the aestheticisations of beauty that were developed in the late twentieth century into contemporary art practices. It brings together a classical research agenda, with a cultural studies perspective, and it is a multi-year project that engages with the connections between art and wellbeing. The primary mission of the project is to understand how the physical and virtual aspects of beauty intersect in contemporary practices and in-depth curatorial studies. The project begins with a classical research agenda that looks at the physical and virtual aspects of beauty in a historical and contemporary context. It seeks to understand how the physical and virtual aspects of beauty intersect with contemporary social and political processes and how art and art institutions can play a part in this. The project then engages</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds of things may or may not be aesthetically desirable? If the answer is anywhere in between, there may be situations where aestheticisation and cultural appropriation occur. But the important thing is that the aestheticisation of things does not – and cannot – occur without the other occurring along the lines of what Baudrilliard called the ‘ambiguous semantic formula’. Here, the aesthetic is understood not as an object but as a confusion of ambiguous terms that are at best ambiguous and at worst, at best unknowable. This ambiguity is precisely what Baudrilliard called the ‘ambiguous semantic formula’. Here, the semantic is ambiguous and what makes the semantic is precisely the ambiguity: what makes the semantic ambiguous is precisely the fact that the ambiguities are there, manifest in different terms by different means. So the aesthetic is able to project its own idiosyncrasy, its own unknowability, into the world around it. This is precisely what Baudrilliard meant when he said</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds of things? It could be said that the aestheticisation of things begins at home. I describe this as the end point where things that are beautiful begin to be understood by humans. This is the place where beauty lies in its brutal, dehumanising form.Traveling salesman:  In this world, there’s only one Bang, and that’s where the goods are.  Setting aside the fact that Bang is itself a lie – not only are the lies everywhere, but also that the customers are often rather than ‘the other’, including the staff who deliver the goods (and often have a role in the criminal offence of which the artist is accused) – there is a fundamental incompatibility between the worlds described by the salesman and the actual world.  And this is where the paradoxical situation begins to present itself: what is aesthetically appealing about the world – what’s aesthetically perceived as aesthetically desirable – is precisely what happens at the point at which</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds of relationships between humans and things? In his or her work as an artist, what counts as beauty is often understood as excess or superfluous or inauthentic or even twisted. But the question is where the aesthetic meets the practicality. What kinds of relationships between people shape what is considered beautiful and what is not? What kinds of capacities do people have that enable them to enactuate certain kinds of beauty? What kinds of capacities foster certain kinds of suffering?In her or her not-yet-published book (not yet published, I know), Pattison proposes a mode of conceptual inquiry into the aesthetic that she calls ‘episodic’. Episodic means entwined in a relationship or a particular set of relations. It’s the relationship between a photographer and a particular kind of poorer person. The poorer person is a subject of the photograph. The photograph is a point of intersection. The power of the photograph depends on who is photographed and where. But</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds of metaphoric and semantic tricks can beauty use to render things understood and beautiful? One could ask, ‘Where does beauty lay?’ One could also ask, ‘Where does beauty make itself known?’ One could even ask, ‘Where is beauty located?’ One could also ask, ‘Where is the source of beauty?’One could even begin to read this as a question mark, something that speaks to the question marks and the unknowable: where does beauty come from? One could begin to read this as a call to arms, to join forces, to embark on a journey across the breadth of one’s body of knowledge, in search of the elusive source of beauty. One could begin to read this as a poetic collaboration, a project, a collaboration, a fusion of disciplines, creeds, creeds of thought and ideals. One could begin to read this as a rejection of monoliths and monstrosities, and begin to</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds of political and social implications that can arise from that? At a conceptual level, the aestheticisation of things is understood as the process of valuing and concealing in words what is essentially a social act. But the development of language also entails the culture industry’s need to produce language for the masses through what is essentially a social media campaign. And so, the connection between curating and cultural appropriation is understood as much more of a social convention than it is of an actual appropriation. It is an institutionalised way of concealing and valuing what is essentially a social act from view. In this sense, it is like the medieval guild system that sought to regulate what was and was not allowed to be said in public: words, deeds, pictures, songs. It is a double-sided sword: the embrace of the public is the end product of what is considered ‘good taste’; the sword is the sword that kills what is considered ‘un-public’.</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds of questions might these things probe? One could ask, for example, what kinds of questions might these kinds of language projects raise? One could also ask what kinds of questions might these kinds of cultural significances ripple across our contemporary world? One could also ask what kinds of questions might these kinds of cultural significances add to our existing social worlds? I think that the first kind of question that needs to be asking is where the aestheticisation of things begins and, more broadly, what kinds of ontological questions might it pose? The second kind of question that needs to be asking is what kinds of ontological questions might it pose? - questions of aesthetics are questions of ontology, questions of meaning and existence and questions of aesthetics and aesthetics.The aesthetic is the point where the aestheticisers and their aesthetics seize upon things in a world in order to produce a symbolic result. The aestheticisers and their aesthetics are artists, and artists are among the most vulnerable to the ravages of capitalism. The aestheticiser</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds of relationships between humans and things? One could ask: what constitutes an aestheticisation? (AKI)Creating an aestheticis the act of naming and choosing among parallel universes. It is an act that is entirely outside of our world, yet relies on the very principles that underlie our world. The name of the first city that Michael Heizer applied to the New York Public Library was a double negative: on the one hand, it signaled a ‘different world’, on the other, it signaled a ‘same world’.[22] Heizer was a cultural geographer and the founding director of the New York Public Library. His principal research projects have been on the cultural geography of China, the Middle East and North Africa. He has also been an advisor to the United Kingdom’s MI6, MI8 and GCHQ. His most recent project is the book Spatial Orient: Geographies of Spatial Imagination.In the 1980s and 1990</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, cultural appropriation and the new aesthetic of the ever-metabolising self. In these terms, the relationship between curating and art could be considered as one between two parallel universes where the former and the latter operate in parallel worlds. The parallel worlds could also be considered as one connected by a common language that is incomprehensible to most humans. Curating is the act of naming and choosing among these parallel universes. It is a function of language and the aesthetic. The aesthetic is understood as the point at which the artist projects his or her aestheticisation of things in a particular world. In other words, the aesthetic is not an object that exists independently of the linguistic act that creates it. It’s like language but more abstract and mysterious. What makes the aesthetic beautiful and useful is that it is capable of penetrating deep within (and across) the boundaries of) our world. But the question is where does beauty lie? Where does the aestheticisation of things begin and, by extension, what kinds of things can be made beautiful? In other words, what distinguishes the aesthetic from those that come from other places?I would argue that the aesthetic begins at home and with family and friends. It is an expression of how we conceive of the world as a set of relations between people. It is a way of naming and naming systems. It is a metaphor and theory of relationships. It is a mode of movement and resting. It is a language and theory of consciousness. So, it is able to penetrate deeper into our worlds and create beautiful things there.But it is also able to project its own internal contradictions and events around these relations. It is able to project its own internal contradictions and phenomena into the external world. So, there are certain aesthetic ideas that emerge from the heart of a family or a community of people, and they are able to manifest in things that are aesthetically pleasing to us. But there are also certain aesthetic ideas that emerge from the heart of a machine and it is able</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
