<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s book Art and his Country, from 1932. He points out that the policy of the United Arts Centre was to provide a setting in which the work of art was actively encouraged, whereas the policy of the museum-as-gallery was more of a rehabilitation programme.  So the policy of the Union was to enable the artist to do things that the Museum could then commission, while also enabling the artist to do things that the Museum could also do. For example, in the case of a mural, the muralists had to have the approval of the museum board, whereas in the case of a painting, the painter had to have the approval of the museum board. But the authority to commission an artist was absolute in both cases: the Museum could decide what was ­good and what was not, while the Union could decide what was art and what was not, although in the Union’s view, the work was art regardless. And so the relationship became very complicated, because the Museum board had</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s book Art as a Social Life (1931), in which artists’ support for social action is detailed. He notes that the galleries themselves often functioned as squats, where the gallery was itself seen as a platform from which social action could develop. Social action, in Heizer’s account, was stimulated by the presence of artists’ posters and installations in galleries, which encouraged a ‘groundswell’ of ‘positive energy’ around the institution. For many artists, this ‘institutionalisation’ was accompanied by a ‘fringe element’ – the ‘glimmer of new ideas’ that could be introduced by artists’ interventions. Heizer’s account seems to be the only one to offer any insight into the way in which the art department and the gallery were supporting the artists’ social activities. But this doesn’t really tell us anything about the relationship between the art department and the gallery.</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s book Art and Labor (1952), in which Heizer describes the exhibition as a ‘gallery-tableau’.[6]  The key concepts are as follows: ‘The gallery is the meeting place of the mind, where ideas are gathered, expressed and presented as a social event is planned and carried out.’[7] And again, in the exhibit ‘Organisation’, the sequence of gathering, gathering, gathering again, again, again, again, again, and again.  A gallery is a social gathering place where ideas are gathered, expressed and presented as a social event is planned and carried out. And the key concept here is ‘the gallery’. There is an immense amount of overlap between the exhibition and its host, the museum, but there are also significant differences.  The key concepts are deeply embedded in the conventions of the exhibitionary form, but the host institution has the final say.  The key</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s book Art as a Metainterface (1980), in which Heizer describes the evolution of the Museum as a metainterface. A metainterface is one where the computer interfaces are not taken into account when organising an experience; they are only there to render various layers of the experience possible. So the introduction of the  	Windows interface in the mid 1980s in a series of user-friendly pamphlets didn’t really touch the fundamental essence of the relation between the artist and the computer, between the user and the artefact. It was more of a demonstration of the capabilities of the computer and its user: the potentialities and pitfalls that exist when the capacities of the artist are grossly underestimated. But since then other interfaces have come and gone, and since then the Museum has hosted a number of user-driven exhibitions, including a number of exhibitions that actively draw on the collections and archives of the Museum.  The introduction of the </text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s book  	The Art Newspaper, published in 1971. In the book, Heizer discusses the relationship between the gallery and the historic, or modern, or contemporary, exhibition as a way of thinking. In the nineteenth century, H.G. Wells, the great American curator, was an early proponent of the former, while Rudolf Steiner, an archivist and historian of art, was an early promoter of the latter. In the twentieth century, David Hockney, an anthropologist of modern culture, came up with the idea of the archive, which emerged from his work as a curator of art institutions. The archive was a place where discrete objects could be tracked and reproduced, and objects could be arranged in layers, such that layers could be seen as discrete objects. For many curators of the twentieth century, the idea of the archive was further developed by David Kessler, an early proponent of the object and a designer of social and cultural packaging. The H.G. Wells</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s book  	The Museum Trap: Modern Art and its Critics. He notes how the nineteenth-century museum became synonymous with the nineteenth-century gallery, and the twentieth century with the twentieth century museum. So the first three generations of the twentieth century were constructions, while the fourth generation is going to be stories. And this is what the twentieth-century museum is: a story. It has a beginning, an epilogue and an ultimate destination. It begins with the artist John Lennon’s painting of the École des Arts Parthenon, in Paris, in May 1968, and continues with various portraits of the same artist, taken in various locations around the world. So the museum-as-gallery begins with Lennon’s painting, and it continues with the history of the twentieth century. It is the site of a seemingly endless series of pictures, and its permanent collection, which John Lennon created, is a story that is far from over. It’s</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s book Art as Artillery (1953), when he juxtaposed photographs of different kinds of artillery with drawings of individual artists. He found that the former was more like a collection of objects in a museum, while the latter was a gallery with its own kinetic quality. He also contrasted this with the more modern depiction of the museum, where the collection, the artefacts, is the only focus. In the latter, the collection, the artefacts, and the installation all blend into one. He viewed the museum as a site of interconnection and potentialities, where art and art history meet contemporary art and art practices.  A more specific but still relevant notion is Georges Canguilhem’s Memoirs of a Memory, (published in 1971), in which he recounted the story of Bouchra Khalili, a Moroccan writer and activist who came to the United States in 1967 and initiated a number of sit-ins and sit-ins at American embassies around</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s book The Art Gallery as a Collective (1972), in which artists were described as ‘living communes’ in a number of of situations – living communes in their gallery, in their studio, or in their home communities. This is very different from the way that cultural theory describes art as a collective, or the way that artists are typically described. Cultural theorists tend to think of an artist as an individual, isolated, and disconnected, whereas the reality is that many artists live embedded in their communities and are therefore forced to travel great distances to find the time to work in public spaces or social situations. So the gallery as collective entity – which Heizer defines as ‘the fundamental building block of art’ – emerged as a way of thinking about how the artist is embedded in the community. The ‘collective’ aspect is important because it allows us to understand how the gallery is a site for the growth of the community’s own cultural values, which then</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s book  	The Gallery as a Space (1977), in which he uses the term ‘the museum-as-gallery’ to describe spaces that capture and simultaneously retreat into the dynamic range of cultural experience.[29] The museum-as-gallery might be seen as a prototype for similar practices across art forms. Indeed, museums have often been used as a site to recover from the effects of the museum, or to provide a cover for the museum’s activities. In the contemporary art world, this often happens at an artist’s exhibition, with curators and artists resorting to what might be termed ‘self-repairing beauty pageants’ where the art is displayed at a later date and the issues of art and beauty are discussed.[30] However, this sort of self-repairing ‘beauty pageantry’ rarely happens at a museum, because the museum is the ultimate repository of the past, and the ultimate guarantor</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people’s organising the whole exhibition.) There was a sense that the Museum was organising itself, as if it were a large corporation: the curators, art directors, artists, production staff, students, administrators. But there was also a sense of the museum itself itself being somewhat dispersed, as if it were a large organisation with a local board of directors. The fact that it was a union hall and not just a regular gallery made it different from other art institutions: the exhibition buildings were located in the art department, the photography better, the installation galleries in the art department, the sound installations in the design department, and the public programme, that was where the action was. So there was a sense that the Union was supporting the work done by the artists, in a way that was very different to the way that the management of the museum was supporting the artists.  A more general notion of the museum-as-gallery comes from Carl Heizer’s book  	The Art Newspaper, published in 1971. In that year, Heizer interviewed twenty-five of the most influential photographers of the decade, many of whom were present in the current collection of the museum. Twenty-five of the photographers had their photographs used in the exhibition.Carl Heizer used to work at the New York Herald Tribune, where he was newspaper managing editor at the time. He also worked for the New York Times and the Washington Post, and was a columnist with the New York Tribune. He was a columnist for the Sunday Times, the New Republic and the New York World. In the mid-1970s he edited the photography section of the now defunct Post-Standard, where he produced a number of photo essays on the Vietnam War.  His photographs of the miners who would become the Hellfighters in the late 1950s and early 1960s were used in the filmstrip Planet of the Apes, which was adapted from the pulp fiction by Frank Miller and illustrated by</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility to art from the arts organisations of the city was accompanied by a decrease in the need for artists to reside in the area and do community work. All of these changes were generated through direct action and creative scholarship.Artists were also encouraged to develop alternative cultural models that would be more accessible to communities. The most pioneering artists of the 1980s were given the freedom to explore new terrain, and many of them were given a platform to develop alternative cultural models. The main challenge for the early artists was to find a community of socially engaged, culturally responsive artists who would participate in the creation of the work, while the main goal for the community was to engage with the art through being made in the community. This last aspect is critical, because engaging with the art through being made in the community is a very powerful way to create community. If done correctly, artists can build communities through engaging with their cultural practices. For example, when the Community Arts Centre of Ontario was founded in the early 1990s, artists</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility of art making through increasing access to culture meant that the public was able to participate more fully in the creation of art, and to demand more of the work produced. Finally, there was much more emphasis placed on the arts being transmitted from generation to generation, rather than the particular origins of that art.This shift in the emphasis of art making from the city to the city possible through the introduction of new technology, may have contributed to the significant increase in population density in major metropolitan areas throughout the world over the past forty years. The megacity became the global centre for the production of art, as much as for its consumption. It is this consumption that has fuelled the growth of contemporary art and its media products, but it is also the source of much of the tension between the rich and poor quarters of the globe, fuelling the desire among some to consume more and the scarcity of resources fuelling the need to consume less. It is true that in poorer quarters, such as in Africa, social media</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility and affordability of arts education in the city were made possible by the increased commercialisation of education. Finally, from the mid-1980s onwards, there was a gradual shift away from direct action towards forms of cultural organising that incorporated the arts where the arts were actively encouraged, where the direct action was supported by the city government, and where the co-convener was a well-established organisation with a long-term view. During this transition period, the term ‘ultra-activist’ was used synonymously with ‘deepened activism’. This is not to suggest that ‘ultra-activism’ was without its critics, nor that it was without its mistakes. But the way in which art was produced and the way in which activism was supported during this transition is very different from the way in which we imagine activism to be today. What is activism today if not activist-driven art? What is activism if not activism-sourced activism?</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility and globalisation of contemporary art meant that the public was able to access and participate in artworks produced by the government, whereas in the past the arts was often restricted to an elite few. Finally, there was a shift towards greater globalisation of contemporary art production, in which art is produced and contributed to wherever it is deemed appropriate. I find this particularly significant in the 1980s, when the gulf between the worlds was increasingly difficult to bridge. Art is often produced in contexts in which the people who create it and act upon it will be able to claim some kind of recompense. When that happened, the public was able to create, and artists were encouraged to create, what was in many ways a more socially relevant work.The fact that artists were able to inhabit previously occupied cultural spaces allows us to imagine a different future. When the Tate Modern was initially conceived, there was a sense that it was an ideal location for the Museum, since it would host exhibitions, perform public programming, and provide</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility to art and cultural resources through mass media meant that art could be produced and consumed in ways that were less constrained by the political landscape in which it was made. Finally, the introduction of social programmes and other forms of arts education in schools allowed for artists to gain skills in production that would be applicable to a range of other kinds of artists, including designers, managers and artists. The public were also much more open to the idea that arts education was modelled on a local basis, and that the arts organisation might have a role in shaping cultural practices within communities.The idea that the arts organisation might be able to create its own forms of cultural practice – create what it calls a Mission Statement – came as a huge surprise to many people involved in the 1980s and early 1990s. This has to do with the notion of rebellion, which was often used as a tool to marginalise people with different ways of being involved in art. The Mission Statement allowed for the organisation to define what it saw as its</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility of art makes it easier to engage people in art-making, whereas in the past when the access to art was restricted, it was often difficult to engage people in art-making due to the perceived marginalisation of the arts in the public sphere. Finally, the increased accessibility of art makes it easier to consume art, whereas in the past when the access to art was restricted, it was often difficult to consume art due to the perceived diminishing of artistic value.[1] The key tenet of biennials is that access to art is universal; if you ‘re not in the art gallery, you're not in the art gallery’.[2] And yet, the tenet that access to art is conditional on the availability of other art resources (geographic or physical) is an essential part of the contemporary globalised art complex, and art today is everywhere, everywhere, everywhere. Art today is produced not in response to consumer demand, and particularly not in response to</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility of arts content via pop-up arts camps and trips was closely tied to the urbanisation of the city. Finally, the biennials that accompanied major art fairs during this time were largely self-produced, and had a much greater urban context.In my estimation, both the public and the arts organisation needed to be involved in the creation of the events, but since the public was fragmented and anonymous, the arts organisation was able to create a sense of belonging and identity for the fans at games such as sporting events, by giving them a sense of agency in creating these aspects of the event. During this time, the biennial format was also used in a way that ensured that the artists arriving later in the year were not replacing existing artists, as was the case with the biennials in the 1980s. For example, in the years immediately following the Venice Biennale, the Biennale commissioned a team of artists to create a new kind of graffiti for the Giardini –</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility of art made for television, and the increase in quantity and quality of that art produced, made it easier for artists to produce works of art with which to engage with audiences outside the arts context. Finally, and perhaps most importantly, the increased accessibility of information on art making facilitated the creation of a public sphere of interest that was not confined to those with formal education and power, but drew on the inherent resources of the city. The arts and visual culture commissioner was a good fit for the public sphere of access to art, and the city was a good fit for the ‘public sphere’ of access to information. The city had two goals in mind when creating the public sphere: (1) the common good and (2) access to knowledge. The first objective of the public sphere was met in three ways: (a) access to information meant that which could be understood by all individuals had access; (b) access to knowledge was maximised when it was made freely available; and (</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility of art made in the area meant that the public was able to participate in the creation of art. Finally, the increased participation of the public in art making meant that the arts organisation could produce results. And although the public involvement was often quite playful and ribald, there was always a risk of something going too far and being misconstrued as a compliment. A good number of the artists we worked with were given the opportunity to develop their own conceptual toolkit for artist-organisations to use in producing art across the city. This isn’t to suggest that the way in which the public was connected to art production was perfect – there was always some suspicion about who was genuine and what was authentic – but there was also considerable latitude given to artists to explore this space and breathe new life into old problems. I would say that the flexibility that the public gave art was significant, and that it informed the kinds of projects that were possible. For example, there are artists today who have their own</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by a director of a museum, a gallery or an arts organisation, but by an artist’s collective. We didn’t have a director, so we made the art. The collective took the director on a trip around the globe, funded the trip by running the art fairs around the city, created a fund to carry the art when it arrived, and then used that money to commission local artists to do the same. It was a very different relationship to the one we have today, and the way in which it was done.There are a few key differences between the way in which the relationship between the public and the arts was in place when Ultralow Occasions started in the early 1980s. Firstly, the public was much more receptive to art being produced through direct action. Secondly, the arts organisation was often a co-convener with the city government, with artists being encouraged to work alongside government officials in an area without opposition. Thirdly, the increased accessibility of art making through mass media was a factor, whereas the increased commodification of imagery leading to images on a global scale such as billboards and magazines played an even greater role. Finally, there was the fact that the late sixties and early seventies were a golden age for the arts in many places, with major curatorial changes often stemming from the shift to the internet and social media. The reason why the arts organisations in many places were so eager to reuse the artwork from the early sixties and seventies, and to no longer bemoan the passing of the art medium, was because that period of hyper-accessivity brought with it a huge increase in consumption. Any photograph that establishes a new standard of beauty is an image that can be reproduced and communicated widely; and with the proliferation of image-based media, that standard has become something that is particularly difficult to define. If, in turn, the artworks that were reinterpreted and created new image-based art forms in the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public gallery should work alongside the local community, with a particular focus on the needs and interests of communities of colour, including the needs of disadvantaged groups, and take into consideration cultural practices and their users. Doing so would require a major overhaul of the existing relationship between the gallery and the community, and I don’t see how this is possible in the City of Toronto. The dynamic between gallery and community is complex, and I don’t think I have the answers to all the questions about how the gallery should work with communities. But here are some general ideas that may help us begin to understand some of the tension and tension that exists between the gallery and the community: 1. Gallery membership and patronage. I think that there is a misconception about how much of a role the gallery plays in curating communities. I think that there is a misunderstanding also between the community and the artists who work there. The community is there to be entertained, not to be engaged or to take part in</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public gallery is there to serve the local community, and curatorial approaches should be tailored to local needs, interests and priorities. If the needs of the community are not considered in a balanced and relevant way, the community will not be served. I think that the role of the art gallery today is to provide a platform for the community to be heard, and to foster relationships between the different stakeholders, regardless of where they may be located, what their responsibilities may be, and how those relationships may evolve. It’s up to the community to decide how art is produced and delivered through the collection and presentation of that art. The curatorial role today is much more responsive to the needs of large corporations and their boards of trustees, and I wouldn’t necessarily say that the curatorial role in the 1980s was all that different from the curatorial role now. But the relationship between the two is much more fluid and variable. The board meeting that takes place in the public gallery is an institutionalised</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public gallery has to recognise that it’s competing with itself. As the public, we’re competing in our own self-image. The private gallery needs to also recognise that it’s competing with itself.This is the second part of a two-part series on the exhibitionary economy of culture in Liverpool. The first part can be found in Graeme Ruxton’s book   	Cultural Capital: The Economic Roots of Contemporary Art’s Growing Game Effect. Part 1: The Crisis of Postmodernism, Culture and Capital (2013) examines the financial precursory to the cultural-materialist crisis of the 1990s. Part 2: Postindustrial Culture and Cognition (2015) looks at the discontents of contemporary globalisation.  And finally, in the third part of the series ‘Challenging Capital: Cyber Culture, Economic Autonomy and Political Governance’ (2017), I turn to critical questions of</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public gallery should be supporting what the local community produces and inviting that to continue. The question of community it not be confused with community art. As soon as the Biennial opened in 1989, the Biennial took up permanent residence in the heart of the city, where it hosted over 200 artists and was home to over 1000 performances. The Biennial’s success was due in large part to the city being turned into a major biennial tourist destination. The Biennial was a biennial in its own right, and the city became a city in which biennials could be built, managed and operated. In other words, it was a biennial in the modern sense of the word. The Biennial provided the infrastructure for an artist-led community to develop its own culture, and over time, the community might have to be supported through artist’s commissions. The interesting thing about the Biennial, though, was that it emerged from the community behind it, rather than through it</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public gallery should be trying to meet the needs of the communities it serves. In this respect, the private gallery should be competing with itself. I don’t think the public gallery has the resources or the mandate to try to solve all problems, so it falls to other levels to try to help communities. In the 1980s, the private gallery understood that it could not just patronise the arts space and produce great art there; it had to be connected to the arts and had to be purpose-built on the back of the community. It was seen as a much needed asset to the city’s coffers and so it became a way for the community to take over artistic activities. In many ways, the initiative now falls on the shoulders of the community, but it is still viewed as a last resort. In a city like Liverpool, with its large and diverse community of artists, the arts community was seen as a vital and ever-present resource, a community of advocates and activists who could</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public gallery must balance the needs of the community with its interests in the context of the gallery. The role of the artist, once he is clear of the legal challenges, is to create opportunities for the community to be involved in the creation of the artworks. It’s not for the community to dictate the way art is made or experienced. The role of the community is to be a creative partner in the creation of the art, and the gallery must play that role without forcing it to do so.  In the 1980s and early 1990s, the gallery struggled with the heavy hand of the law as it sought to impose a strict definition of what constituted an art piece and what constituted a cultural production. Curators in the gallery were free to include materials or ideas from anywhere in the gallery, but the law had an agenda of its own. Its mission was to create a public gallery where arts production could take place in a manner similar to that of a museum, but it also had a mission</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public gallery’s mission should be to serve the community. In my opinion, it is the inverse of the inverse: it is serving the community in the sense of its own resources. When the community goes to the private gallery, the resources are used in an inverse ratio to what the community creates.  	The curatorial role today is much more dependent on the financial and material resources of the institution, on the institutional memory of the past, and on the institutional will to intervene in the future. These three elements – the relational, the material and the financial – together constitute what I would call the ‘present’. In other words, the curatorial job in the contemporary world is much more like that of the medieval casuist or the early modern jurist: there is a great desire on the part of the public gallery to revisit the past and to intervene in the future, but the institutions that created the backdrop for that desire are much less capable of recalling and intervening in the</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public gallery should actively participate in producing its own artistic environment. The curatorial role should be an opportunity for the artist to work openly with its audience, and to engage with culture in ways that are authentic, authentic and possible within that very environment. I think that’s what the 2014 Biennial was all about. It was all about engaging with art’s place in the city and its political and social meaning today. I don’t think we can erase the past, but we can learn to work through the trauma and emotions that artists and audiences experience when encountering contemporary art today. The biennial opened up for the artist Jorge Quintero and his group to begin to explore this new context. With that opening, it became a project that became a very urgent and public need for the community to come together and actively participate in creating an artistic and creative future for the area. The Biennial is an important cultural artifact for the area, and a way to bring together artists, art</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public gallery, like any large organisation, has a function to perform in the public arena. It is, however, in a much weaker position today than it was in the 1980s. It is much more vulnerable to changes in the value of art and the value of money, and to the impact of change in the social landscape. I don’t think this is a critique of the curatorial role in the 1980s, although there were certainly artists and curators who actively sought to influence the development of what we think of as the modern curatorial tradition in the city. But the role of the modern curatorial today is to perform in the social sphere, and in that respect it is much weaker. The curatorial role has changed, but the social sphere doesn’t necessarily need to.The role of the artist today is very different from that of the curatorial ten years ago. The artist is a complex human being with many sides. Many artists have multiple legitimate artistic interests that conflict with</text>
    <text>should have been curated by and with the artist Dirk Partęs UrbanーRS project – then maybe we could have discussed what it meant to be an urban community in the 1980s. Maybe it would have been interesting to observe how cultural production in the 1980s was aligned with developments in the city. Maybe it would have made some sense to artists and curators who worked on the project at that time to reference the early and late experiences of cultural production in the city in order to understand how art is produced in communities today. Maybe it would have made some sense for art patrons to be presented with a selection of works created in the city in an effort to inspire artistic practices and suggested curatorial approaches. I don’t know what the future would or could or would not bring. In the meantime, the curatorial role today is very much influenced by the developments in the local art world. I don’t think the public gallery should be competing with the private gallery in this respect. The public gallery can and should work alongside other partners in a community to find creative solutions to difficult problems. I don’t think the public gallery should be the curator of the creative solutions, either. It’s a great role for the public to have, but I feel it’s important for the gallery to know what the gallery has done with the character and essence of the city in order to create its own creative future.  For further information visit www.urban-regeneration.org.uk.  References  Bauman, Judith. Culture and Capital: Social Contract and Cultural Capital. Chicago and London, University of Chicago Press, 2009.  Bauman, Judith. The Culture and Capital Trap: Capital, Cultures of Critique, and Art's Postmodern Condition. Berkeley and New York, University of California Press, 2006.  Bauman, Judith. The Crisis of Curating: Meeting the Future of Art Criticism. New York and New York University Press</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I try to instill in everyone I come into contact with. That’s what I try to impart to others. That’s what counts.That's what I try to impart to others. That’s what counts.That’s what I aspire to.That's what I strive for.That's what I’ve striven for.That’s what I’ve striven for.That’s what I’ve built.That's what I’ve strived for.That’s what I’ve strived for.That’s what I’ve strived for.That’s what I’ve strived for.That’s what I’ve strived for.That’s what I want.That’s what I aspire to. That’s what I’ve strived for.That’s what I try to</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do. It’s that’s all I can do.Thanks for the pointers, Wendy.DDownload this article as PDF29 October 2014To Wendy SeltTo Wendy SeltWendy Selt is an artist and writer. Her work in communities began in the 1970s when she was at UW-Madison studying political economy and urban studies. She has a particular interest in the communities that are the products of the economic logic of mass incarceration and urban decay in the United States. Her artwork and writing has been exhibited internationally, including at the Venice Biennale, the Whitney Museum of American Art, and the Wall St. Biennale.Her artworks have been commissioned by the New</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I try to instill in the young people in the way I instill in the art professionals: that’s all that counts. That’s what ­counts. And I’m afraid the young people you speak of, the artists, they may not all be young people, but they’ve all been given the chance to grow up and face the world.Because the world is changing all the time. And if the world doesn’t keep up with what's happening in the city then the city may well slip into the abyss. That’s what happened in San Francisco: the decline of the city coincided with an explosion of insane projects that sought to recreate the glory days of the city without any reference to the declining population, or to the fact that in the midst of that explosion there were more people moving into the city than were being killed there. So the artists, the city workers and the politicians that sculpt and paint our cities into landscapes that are either</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do. That's what I try to do.That's what I’ve always tried to do. And you know what? Sometimes, that’s what it’s like trying to be somewhere else. It’s like trying to be an alien. You’re not supposed to like it, but you have to do it. Because otherwise, what do you do? You’re supposed to be here for a specific reason. You’re not supposed to be here to watch TV or do nothing, but somehow, somehow, you end up here. Like a massive clusterfuck.And it’s frustrating. It’s frustrating to be stuck in this bubble, to have to deal with all this diversity, to have to deal with the fact that people coming through this door don’t know what it feels like to be in the bubble. People coming through this door don’</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I look for in a curator. Someone with a clear idea of how they’re going to use the art they have acquired, and how they’re going to use it. And also someone with a clear idea of what art is. Who is it that you want to draw into the future? Who is it that you want to educate? Who is it that you want to make funny? Who is it that you want to make tragic? Who are the people that you want to make fun of? And then, someone with a clear idea of what art is going to be like in the future, someone with that personas firmly in mind. This is what I’ve done with my career. I’ve given people an idea of what art is, and seen what they can do with that. And then, when the time comes, I’ve taken an existing art practice and made something new out of that. That’s what I did in the 1970</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do. That’s what I aspire to. That’s what I’d do if I was you. That’s what I’d always do. That’s what I aspire to. That’s what I’d always do.That's what I try to do. That’s what I’d always do.That’s what I aspire to. That’s what I’d always do.That's what I try to do. That’s what I aspire to.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do.That's what I try to do.That’s what I try to do.That's what I aspire to. That’s what I’d always do.That's what I strive to.That's what I aspire to.That's what I aspire to</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I look for in a person. I look for something in a person that will allow me to see the world the way I want to see it, not through the lens of what society tells me is right or wrong. I don’t need to know what society thinks is ideal or what society tells me is ‘right’. I only need to know what I can and cannot do. I’m not looking for a superstar or any sort of mythical being or figure of pure goodness. I'm looking for someone who can be me, make me, and give me the tools to be able to do what I want with my life. And that’s why I’m not necessarily an advocate of what society puts in front of me. I’m not saying I want to be like Leonardo da Vinci or Andy Warhol or Richard Southern or Terry Gilliam or Damien Hirst or any of those artists who came before me, but I’m saying</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I try to do, whether I'm working as an arts administrator or as a cultural theorist. My main interest in art and culture is in terms of its ability to create spaces in which people can ‘express themselves’. And the more space that’s created, the more freedom that person has to do whatever they want to do, and to inhabit that space in ways that are free from oppression. But what I also try to do is look at what space and how that space is created, and how that creates oppression. I’ve also been interested in the ways that spacefaring cultures create ‘differentiations’ in and against their own history, present and future. Where did that come from? Where did we go wrong? What are the lessons we can learn from that other places? And what can we do from here?  For me, the answer is always the same: make better stuff. And if I can do that, anybody can.Art is a</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I’ve been doing. That’s what countssships. That’s what counts.That’s what I’ve been doing. That’s what countssships.That's what counts.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’ve been doing.That’s what I’</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place, or would we? As the saying goes: history is made by the victors of a political struggle.And politics is no longer the defining variable of our time. People of many races and creeds, from the rural poor to the urban rich, people from all over the planet, people from every walk of life, sit down, talk, shop, eat well and generally be themselves. They’re not looking for a ‘person of colour’ or an ‘elitist rich white guy’. And they’re not looking for a ‘West Asian guy’ either. They’re looking for someone with a similar mindset, who can see the world through their own two eyes.For me, in my role, that’s what matters. That’s what counts. That’s what countsships. That’s what countsship. That’s what counts.That's what I look for in a candidate. I look for an approach to things that aren’t your traditional ‘traditional’, white guy’ typesetting them. I look for someone who can be themselves, with honesty, compassion and a sense of humour. I don’t want to recruit you into a cult of personality, but you should know what you’re getting into.If you want to know more about what it means to be a part of something, join a cult. I don’t want to lead you somewhere, but I’m interested in what you’re contributing to a cult. Why are you contributing to a cult?Because that’s what you’re doing. That's what you’re doing. Why are you contributing to a cult?Because that’s what you’re doing. That's what you’re doing. Why are you contributing to a cult?Because that’s</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger
    <text>presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger role in the future urbanisation of the city than in the present, and so it’s a balancing act that we’re performing well in today, but which is also happening in reverse: the city is becoming increasingly populated and unhealthy. In the coming years, we’ll need to find a way to both balance the city and nurture its natural resources without becoming urbanised ourselves.‘Call it eco-tourism’. So far, so normalised. How we perceive the world around us is affected by factors beyond our control, and so it’s our role to try to identify and address those who are contributing to the crisis of our urbanisation. But there is a deeper issue at stake here: the role of the artist in this process. The role of the artist is to create a scenario in which we can adopt new ways of perceiving the world. But that doesn’t mean that the artist has to follow the narrative laid out by</text>
    <text>presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger role in the future than in the past, and so it’s critical that we balance the needs of the present with the priorities of the future. 	[1] Global Environment Facility, http://www.globalenvironment.org/en/p/en/nature/en/nature/forecast/20170222160304.htm (accessed October 2018). [2] Thorne and Myers, &quot;A Theory of Visual Experience,&quot; in The Oxford Handbook of Film and Media, ii, pp. 21–47. [3] Gross, Understanding Cinema, Aperture, 1984, p. 29. [4] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, Penguin, 1948, p. 22. [5] Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, p. 23. [6] Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, n. 3, 1942, p.</text>
    <text>presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger role in the future of our research, because we’re going to be building new urban forms around biomaterials and eco-systems. Nature is going to play a much bigger role in the future of our research, because that’s where all the technological revolutions are going to end up. Our research is a continuation of that trend. Nature is a research project, but it’s also a much bigger project, because it’s happening now and it’s never going to be done. Even though it’s happening now, it’s going to be really interesting for us to observe and map that research project over the long term, because it’s happening at such a faster rate than any of us imagined possible. Nature is a research project, but it’s also a much bigger project, because it’s happening now and it’s never going to be done. Even though it’s happening now,</text>
    <text>presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger role in the future climate than in the past, and we have to work together to find the balance. Nature plays a pivotal role in our transformation into a biosphere, but we also have to play a pivotal role in the maintenance of the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the future climate than in the past, and we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger role in the future climate than in the past, and we have to work together to find the balance. Nature plays a pivotal role in our transformation into a biosphere, but we also have to play a pivotal role in the maintenance of the city. Nature plays a pivotal role in our transformation into a biosphere, but we also have to play a pivotal role in the maintenance of the city.  To some extent, we’re all part of that pivotal role. Nature plays a role in our climate, but we also have to work together to find the balance</text>
    <text>presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger role in the coming years than in the past, and we’re seeing a marked increase in urbanization projected for the region. Nature is going to play a much bigger role in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a vital role in preserving it. Nature has a ‘bigger picture’ to think about, and that’s why cities are so fragile. To be sure, nature has this magical ability to create massive upheavals that can be controlled, but in the end, it’s up to us, the people, to rebuild cities and make them useful again. And that’s what we’re doing. Nature has a bigger picture than we do. Our European model is an ideal one to study as we adapt it to different environments; but it’s going to be very challenging to bring this model to the region, because of the scale at which we’re at now. We don</text>
    <text>presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger role in the future urbanisation of the city than in the present one. For us, it’s a balancing act that’s all we can afford to do in the face of such a huge change in the nature of urbanisation.’  Conclusion  A few years after I started my PhD research, I started a job as a Project Manager in the Artistic department of Neue Zürcher Zeitung. I worked alongside two artists: Ingmar Kübler-Ross and Norbert Goering, who were developing a new kind of urban research project. The project was called  	Nature Underground. The idea was to find underground cities that were as challenging as the major metropolitan centers to explore in a new way. I joined the artist team in Rotterdam and worked as a project manager with the cityscape department. In a way, I was their intellectual partner: I could see what they were trying to do, and from the office, developed theory and applied</text>
    <text>presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger role in the future climate than in the past, and we need to find a balance. Nature is going to play a greater role in the future climate than in the past, and we’re all going to play a vital role in preserving the planet we live on. A balance that includes, but is not limited to, nature, culture and the natural resources that support its future growth.  The European model is a good starting point, but it’s only the beginning of a process that will have to be undertaken in order to address the huge changes that are needed. We need to find a way to collaborate with people from different disciplines, including local people, in order to achieve the necessary change. A large part of our work involves developing new ways of approaching our city, its history, and our relationships to each other and to the environment. We develop strategies to work with people from different disciplines, including local people, to create 'cross-disciplinarity'. This is a</text>
    <text>presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger role in the future than in the past, and we’re in a unique position in that we have both urban and nature in common. Nature is our second language, and we share a lot of our values and habits. Nature is a much bigger part of our future than we are in the present. Nature has many forms – natural resources, ecosystems, and cities are just a few – but the important thing is that they have a way of linking and bringing people together. Nature is our first language, and we share a lot of our values and habits. Nature is a much bigger part of our future than we are in the present. Nature has many forms – natural resources, ecosystems, and cities are just a few – but the important thing is that they have a way of linking and bringing people together. Nature is our second language, and we share a lot of our values and habits. Nature is a much bigger part of our future than we are in the present. We need to find</text>
    <text>presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger ecological footprint than previously imagined, and we’re creating a hybrid form that has some very specific features and characteristics, but also some very wild ones. Nature is going to play a much bigger role in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a ‘big-picture’ view of the world, and we’re creating a hybrid that has some very specific features and characteristics, but also some very wild ones. Nature has a ‘region’ in its landscape that’s constantly evolving and changing, and that’s why predictions of disaster are so scary. Nature has several forms of urbanization planned for the city, but we’re also creating a hybrid that has some very specific features and characteristics, but also some very wild ones. Nature has its own apocalyptic narrative, but we’re also telling a fictional story about an apocalyptic future. Nature has its own apocalyptic future</text>
    <text>presented as an online project).‘The European model is an ideal one for us to operate in, but it’s also a model that’s going to be difficult to change one day. We need to work with the local community to adapt our model to their needs and interests, rather than against them.’ Our Project Manager, Mathias Volz, puts it very well:  The European model is a ‘template that can’t be remade.’ The challenge now is to find the right balance between the needs of the urban and nature, while also meeting the needs of the urban development and the commercial sectors. Our model is a hybrid between the two, and we’re working towards a more natural and ‘human-scale’ urban form for the city. Nature is going to play a bigger role in the city in the future, but at the same time, we’re also playing a crucial role in preserving it. Nature has a much bigger role in the future of the city than in the past, and we’re seeing a marked increase in nuclear power, biofuels, and other dirty energies in the European energy mix. It’s no wonder that cities are spending more on maintenance and protecting against natural disasters like floods and fires. The European model is an ideal one to try to figure out how to inhabit and imagine change in the city in ways that aren’t destroyed by the destructive forces of capitalism. Nature has many layers to play with, and we need to uncover the layers and come to terms with the fact that we’re both going to be part of the city for quite some time to come. Nature has many talents, and we need to harness them in order to create the kind of urban form that works for us and our future city. Nature has many talents that can be used for good or for evil, and we need to work together to find the best use for them.A city is</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist
    <text>should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist Christos Theodorou, an ‘occasionality’. The real challenge for Augé and Frank, as well as anyone contemplating visiting the Biennale in its current form, was to figure out what to make of the art as an event that happens to be fictional, or at least imaginary. It is not supposed to be real, but rather fictional – in the form of a biennale – and so it falls outside the real, physical, urban world. It is a form of simulacrum, but it is still contemporaneous. So the Augé-Frank experiment suggests a more expansive, perhaps more interesting ‘eventology’ than the artistic biennales that have traditionally taken place in Venice, and which tend to be about the present but do not really live up to the artefact or artefactological paradoxes of the city.  The eventology that they propose – and Frank and others seem to have relished the opportunity to experiment with that – is</text>
    <text>should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist, a ‘political painting’.  The problem with biennials in their current form, though – and this is my reading – is that their current form feeds into the everyday and that in turn feeds into culture. If the biennale is to survive as a form in which it can reliably (and fairly) present art from everywhere, it must change. It can no longer be invited inside the city and its peripheries and it must seek to engage with the political, economic and urban processes shaping the city.  It seems to me that the biennale is primarily interested in its social function now that everywhere is represented. For the organisers of the Venice Biennale to be able to continue to provide a platform for cultural activity in the city, they need to be able to draw in other stakeholders – artists, curators, communities, community organisers – and also have to be able to negotiate the vagaries of economic development and urban transformation. As festival-goers, we�</text>
    <text>should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist and essayist Emily Pringle,  discourse, which was more ‘real’ than the art. In other words, the art was always there, but the biennale required the art to be experienced as a form of travel. To visit the art was to be seen as a sort of entrepôt or tourist attraction, like the circus or aquarium. To multiply the two, art was seen as both a commodity and a form of transport. The Frank’s idea was that the art should be able to ‘code’ or ‘codevelop’ the everyday world in which it operates. To travel in art, one had to have ‘a good understanding of how the art is made’. To travel in the art, one had to have that understanding. This was the duality of the biennale: it offered both the art and the art’s make-believearers a way to consume the art without necessarily having to</text>
    <text>should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist, an act of wilful blindness.The Frank and his colleagues were, of course, reacting against the prevailing notion that the biennale was apolitical and detached from the city. The biennale, they said, had become like any other art institution: subject to the vagaries of economic development, urban infrastructures and the whims of a capitalistic urban renaissance, and yet always a threat. The late 1980s and early 1990s saw a time when cities around the world were experiencing their own act of biennaleizing. New York and London were notable exceptions, as art was more easily obtained in those cities. But the Frank’s project took the biennale to another level: to understand how the art was produced in and through the city, and to imagine what the art might look like if it were produced there. In doing so, they opened up a can of worms about what the art might actually be like.Why would a biennale, now</text>
    <text>should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist, a ‘problem of appearances’. Visiting the city was part of the experience, but in itself, an act of discovery. What the Biennale sought to do, in its early years, was to offer the city a narrative in which it could be part of, an understanding of the city that not all of us, not even the artist, would necessarily agree with. In doing so, it could either legitimise the city’s existence or annihilate it. This was the narrative that the Biennale was trying to create for itself, one that it could then inhabit and, if it was successful, even become a part of. Unfortunately, the Biennale in its early years tended to consume the city–something it felt it had no other narrative for. In the early years, it tended to consume the city and throw its characters into chaotic patterns that made them hard to categorise, but as more and more artists and their works were shown in various venues</text>
    <text>should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist, a ‘double bind’ – present in the form of both the object and the human form.Art, then, could be seen not just as an effect of urbanization, but also as an effect of the changes that have taken place in the city over the past twenty years. The biennial has been an urban effect throughout much of the twentieth century, and it is no exaggeration to suggest that its current trajectory is due to the biennale as an institution. But the influence of other artworlds has also influenced the biennale, and in many ways continues to influence it to this day. The biennale was not the only factor in shaping the twentieth century, but it is the main one. The biennale, in its turn, was not the only factor in shaping the twentieth century, but it is the most widely read and adored one. It is common for biennials to be about contemporary art in certain broad strokes, or in-depth accounts</text>
    <text>should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist, a ‘double consciousness’. The art was intended to be seen as both a ‘present’ and a ‘future’.  The double consciousness had its difficulties too. Frank concluded that the Venice Biennale ‘[s] double consciousness of present and future is deeply problematic and that, in the present, it is no longer possible to read the present or future in terms of a real or potential future or, indeed, to capture and narrate the contemporaneous or contemporaneous past in images and stories’. But he and his fellow artists found a way to simultaneously put their art back on the cultural map and to engage with the persistent sense of present-present crisis and anxiety – to put the Biennale back on the map of contemporary art and culture.What the biennale can and should do is a difficult, even essential, thing to grasp. It is not just to offer a place, a convention, a set of rules or a</text>
    <text>should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist,  surrounded by &quot;metainterfaces&quot; – crowds of people in suits and ties, many of whom were art-school graduates but also artists. The real interest of the Frank’s project was in the ways in which the biennale invited people into the virtual space of the art world – the city, the museums, the convention centres, the shopping districts – and into the narrative of the art world. The Venetians and Pan American Centres also arranged for artists to come to events in the city, such as fairs and festivals. But the real power of the biennale came from its ability to create worlds – worlds of experience and possibilities – for people to inhabit. The biennale itself had this ability, and sometimes that quality was a problem. The Venetians and Pan American Centres had this quality of entitlement – they owned the place and could choose to let people in or not let them in. But the biennale also had this quality of</text>
    <text>should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist, a ‘message from the machine’.Art, as an art-medium, plays a particular role in the machine’s workflow. The complexity of the world outside the art is explained by a machine that can do things like recognise faces, recognise speech, understand images, understand codes, understand time – skills that humans have nonetheless, in the broadest sense, yet cannot do without the machines.  Similarly, the biennale as a whole plays an important role in the larger socio-political context of the city, even if this is often confused with the more familiar ‘cultural capital of the world’.  The biennale is a production for the machine, and as such it must be organized to meet its management’s needs. Management is the operative word here, and so it is that the biennale is often confused with its many forms: confused by the varied origins of its various titles, confused by the diverse purposes they serve, and so</text>
    <text>should have been curated around the node. The fact that these exhibitions included not only from the city but also from outside the city – in the countryside and in the city – was an added bonus. In this sense, the biennale was responding to the disruption caused by the city. It was also an oddity in its own right: a strange but intriguing hybrid, a strange mixture of facts and ideas and objects and figures, a weird landscape that could, in theory, be visited but rarely seen.  The problem with contemporary art biennales is that they tend to be about more than just the momentary interest of the art-world in the moment. Marc Augé and Mathias Frank at the Venice Biennale in 2015 proposed a project around the everyday, everyday experience of everyday life in the city. The problem with that, as the Frank discovered, was that, inside the biennale, the art was about many things and had many forms. It was, in the words of the artist, a ‘consumption of everyday objects’ that, as they were being taken away, were also being made, and this meant that the art had to be taken out and put somewhere else. So the form of the biennale had to evolve.  Ultimately, the Frank’s idea was that the art should be taken away at the end of each exhibition so that it could be put back together again, but that this ‘would destroy the intimacy between artist and audience’. That is, the art might be there, but its real work would be hidden or suppressed. That is, the art might be there, and the art might be hidden or suppressed, but the audience would know and connect with it. That is, the art might be there, and the audience might connect with it, but the art would be engaged in something else. So the biennale evolved over time into something more in keeping with Frank’s concerns and desires. It became</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The
    <text>presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The second aspect of my thinking on the role of poetry in our age is concerned with the production of knowledge. In our age of ever-more accurate and quantifiable statistics, it’s very easy to become literate: to see the statistics and the processes involved in producing a statistic, and to connect the dots between particular events. But in the age of unlimited access to data, it’s much harder to see the world through the prism of a particular poetry. The poetry that comes out of the particular moment is going to be very different from the poetry that comes out of any particular tradition or ideology. So we can think of the poet as somebody who has discovered something new. She will be looking for meaning in the world through processes of abstraction and not through the imposition of specific ideas. She will be looking for meaning in the abstract, not through the imposition of particular values. She will be doing things out of her or his own perspective and not in conformity to a specific ideology. And</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The other thing is that in the contemporary world, we are all immersed in a constantly evolving and shifting culture. We don’t necessarily know what that means, and so we can make lots of contradictory inferences. For example, the inferences that we can draw from data about the number of people in a given metropolitan area are much more limited in scope and so are subject to more powerful influences such as economic development, migration and so on. But the inferences that we can draw from data about the number of cars sold in a given metropolitan area are much more certain and so are able to generate huge flows of investment, generating huge new employements and so on. So the inferences that we can draw from data about the number of commuters travelling through a given metropolitan area are much more limited in scope and so are subject to much stronger influences such as cultural tourism, which tends to generate massive flows of people and so on. And so the scale and the range of inferences that we can draw</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The ride I’ve been on so far isn’t techno-critical, but it is techno-immersive. It’s like going on a totally different planet, but in a different dimension. The difference is that on the planet, humans are still made up of bits and pieces, with parts that fall away all the time, but in that world, things happen much more organically. For example, the way in which we cook our food is driven by the weather, the way our bodies process food is driven by the weather, and the way the world looks through the prism of light is driven by the sun. The biennale as a whole is driven by light, and as a result, the entire city is affected by it. The impact of a light show in a given city is maximised when there is a total absorption of energy, which is why a city organises itself into what it calls ‘infrastructures’. Infrastructures</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The concept of ‘instant prototype’ seems to capture some of this unpredictable aspect. In that case, obviously, the objects that make up the prototype are the very same ones that make up the finished product – but there is also a question mark hanging over the edges: is the smooth surface of the prototype replicating what the objects actually are, or is the smoothness just an illusion? Obviously, there is a difference between the two, and a prototype is a proto-form that needs to be verified against actuality. Nevertheless, the concept of the ‘prototype’ has become a mainstay in science and technical writing, and it’s quite easy to identify a proto-form on the web: a URL, a document, a template. In the case of the ‘prototype’, the ‘reference implementation’ is a good place to start looking for traces of the magic that brought about the objects in the first place.In this context, looking for</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The second exhibition in Venice featured works that appeared as a response to the first. In the exhibition catalogue, the artist Eduardo Sánchez refers to the fact that, during the development of the work, there was a conflict between the needs of the artist and his audience. The conflict was between the artist’s contractual obligation to make money and the audience’s desire to see art produced in a different way. In other words, the conflict wasn’t between the audience and the artist, it was always the audience versus the contractual obligation. But the tension between audience and artist grew increasingly pronounced, and eventually, in 2015, the Biennale decided that the conflict couldn’t be allowed to remain unresolved. In the exhibition catalogue, the artist Eduardo Sánchez writes:It started with an agreement between the Biennale and the artist. He had to make a clear distinction between the Biennale and the Biennale’s audience, who were</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The idea of ‘being alive’ came to mind when thinking about the distinction between life and technology. In biology, there is a distinction between life and death, which is often made to be ‘difficult to define’. I have always found the more difficult life to be, the more fascinating and fascinating it was to observe and to understand. As I learned more and more, the more bizarre and maddening the processes that created it, the more bizarre and maddening the consequences became. And so it goes: the more abstract and abstract the processes involved in the production of life, the more bizarre and maddening the consequences became. Life itself is a complex process, and the more we discovered about it, the more we understood life’s complexity. Life’s complexity is what made Darwin so fascinating: his conceit was that life would be able to handle the transformations that science and technology were enabling. But in the process of becoming what we call �</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The other reason why the novel has such a seemingly inevitable end is that we have no way of knowing what that new world is like. Even if we do discover it, we cannot know what it is like yet, not because we lack imagination but because our finite brains cannot conceive of a beyond. The human capacity for imagination runs into a limit in the form of physical constraints: beyond that point, the human capacities for language and action begin to falter. So the imagination runs into a limit as well, and the limits that we perceive around the world begin to intervene in our everyday practices. But that is to say: the limits that we perceive around the world can and do intervene in our everyday lives in subtle and sometimes profound ways.When thinking about the novel as a process of becoming, or the unfolding of the novel as a sequence of becoming, one can begin to see how the novel represents a future that is not necessarily a future set in stone. Futurist visions of the future often feature dystopian</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The other precondition for the production of the production of the novel is a certain amount of preconditioning, and that’s where things get interesting. There is a concept called ‘pre-indeterminacy’ that we have to grapple with when thinking about how technology is going to effect our daily practices and routines. And so, there is a distinction to be made between what is pre-indetermined and what happens when things that are pre-indeterminate happen to be generated in a particular way. What is pre-indeterminacy? Well, there is a conception of pre-indeterminacy that I take issue with. I think of it as a different kind of determinacy. That is, the kind of determinacy that results from a prior event, or set of past events that are more or less present, and in the present. Aspects of the past that are past in time are not here to stay; they’re part of the system</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The second element in the mix is technological innovation. As the internet and social media have made possible the possibility of ever greater transparency and accessibility of data, it’s easy to forget that the internet was initially conceived as a single point of failure. The web is an interface that captures and distributes information, and it’s this very transparency and accessibility that makes it possible for us to create new media and entertain ourselves with ever greater amounts of data. The problem with the web is that it captures a lot of information, and as a result, records a lot of things that can be defined as ‘real’. For instance, what counts as a 'true' story? How is it that some stories are more relatable than others? Is it due to the fact that some stories are inherently more relatable? Or is it due to the fact that in the age of the infinite database, the human element is generally omitted?A final element to consider is the geographical. What does</text>
    <text>presented as an online project, the project was originally conceived as a one-man show) and the publication of the first part of that in 2014. I’m interested in how the impossibility of viewing the world through the prism of techno-mathematical models impacts our understanding of the world, and how this impacts our everyday practices. Sometimes the depiction of techno-mathematical modelling is apropos, as in the film Groundhog Day, in which the same actors, each with their own distinctive set of actions, come together to create a new world. In that case, the setting is quite different from the production of the new world, and the act of producing is what makes the action novel. In that case, the novel has a beginning, and the novel itself is a process of becoming. In the case of the present, there is no predetermined end to the process of becoming, and the unpredictable aspect of techno-mathematical modelling runs contrary to everything we think we know about the world.The second part of my talk is titled ‘The End of Story’, and it is concerned with questions of artificial intelligence, more specifically. In the last few years, there has been a lot of hype around the applications of AI to a large number of different kinds of processes, including natural-language processing. In the context of human-computer interaction, machines are said to understand and be able to understand narrative. In the context of journalism, machines are said to understand and be able to arbitrate among various kinds of evidence. In the context of cultural practices, machines are said to understand and be able to analyze cultural phenomena such as music, film, and art.[1] Ishmael and Serena Ahmadi are co-authors of Becoming Human: Rethinking Race and Class in the Modern Era[2] and co-curators of the forthcoming exhibition The End of Story: Machine Learning and the Future of Story[3] at the Whitney Museum of American Art.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of
    <text>Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of technology in societies.Download this article as PDFOnder-Usman KhanAsif KapadiaAsif Kapadia is an architect and Principal in the office of B.C.'s Minister of Advanced Education and Training, Language Arts, MFA, Ray Worm/M.I.T. joint venture Learning Technologies. His work with the M.I.T. group has been featured in the New York Times, The Atlantic, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed Web, The New York Times Higher Ed Journal, The Atlantic and The Nation. His latest projects are part of the Concrete Archive project at M.I.T. He has also written for The New York Times, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Digitimes and The Nation. He is a founding partner of Worm, Inc., a non-profit organisation that uses concrete, cement, timber and other building materials to support</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of information technology.  [1] The B.C. Human Rights Commission, 2016.  [2] The B.C. Human Rights Code, 1990, s.2(g). [3] The B.C. Human Rights Act, 1996, c. C-16, s.1. [4] The B.C. Human Rights Review, 1999, c. 21, s.1. [5] The B.C. Human Rights Review, 1999, c. 21, s.2. [6] Id. [7] See, e.g.,  	Toronto Star, November 22, 1996;  	Toronto Star and International Herald Tribune, July 20, 1998;  	International Herald Tribune, October 22, 1999;  	International Herald Tribune, February 22, 2000;  	International Herald Tribune, April 18, 2000;  	International Herald Tribune, June 17,</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of rural and remote regions.Download this article as PDFHuman Rights Watch's International DepartmentHead, Human Rights Watch Jerusalem, September 2014.PreviousNextHuman Rights Watch's International DepartmentHead, Human Rights Watch Jerusalem, September 2014.Istanbul, TurkeyAugust 2014Dear Sir or MadamThank you for your presentation at the Human Rights Watch International Department's 'Open House' event, 'Open House' (http://hrw.org/en/2014/open-house/), entitled 'The Ghost of Communism: Urban Ghosts of the Middle East'.I welcome your presentation, which we hope will bring to our attention numerous urban and suburban ghost cities around the world, including those in Turkey, Iraq, Afghanistan and Qatar.We also need to acknowledge that, during the past year, there’s been a lot of activity in your adopted city of Liverpool. A lot of new ideas and tactics were put into practice – new ways of organising ourselves, new ways of interacting, new ways of making the city</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of urban resources. He has a particular interest in the politics of transition and displacement, particularly for communities of colour.Over the past decade the biennial has undergone a structural change at the Museum of Anthropology, taking on a new purpose and agenda. The Museum of Anthropology, which has a long history of producing culturally responsive exhibitions, curatorial work and programmes, is moving towards a two-year cycle. This is in large part due to the substantial funding cuts that the Museum Board has been forced to impose, forcing it to adopt new programs and exhibitions that it does not host. The biennial as a cultural organisation is being challenged by a more functionalist agenda that seeks to reconceive the biennial as a museum shop that is self-sustainable. Max is part of a curatorial team that is developing a new kind of biennial that will embrace urban and regional forms and exploring their intersections. The exhibition format will no longer fit neatly into the museum shop, but rather demand a great deal of planning</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of data, particularly for communities in the West African countries of Burkina Faso, Cameroon, and Nigeria.Download this article as PDFDoubtless, there is a general sense of uneasiness, even anger, regarding the assumption (now rightly) that there is only one species of person entitled to occupy any particular place and that this person is, by definition, human. However, there are also certain recognisable communities of people – perhaps recognisable because of their shared ancestry – who are given to imagining and fantasising different forms of people and places. These recognisable communities are often drawn from the wider public – specifically, those who identify as either British, English or British-Indian – and are often taken up on this claim by those who call themselves ‘British Columbians’.The question, then, becomes: what could such a recognisable constituency look like? What are the ways in which one might organize such a constituency? There are many viable ideas, but the most promising is</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of economic, social and political resources, and is particularly interested in the politics of poverty reduction.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatI came to Canada as a child in search of adventure. But my father’s voice kept telling me, ‘You’re leaving.’ I had to tell him the truth.  The next time I saw him, he was already gone.From Cairo, Egypt, to Toronto, Canada, July 2012. Photo courtesy of Nasser Rabbat.PreviousNextFrom Cairo, Egypt, to Toronto, Canada, July 2012. Photo courtesy of Nasser Rabbat.From Cairo, Egypt, to Toronto, Canada, July 2012. Photo courtesy of Nasser Rabbat.From Cairo, Egypt, to Toronto, Canada, July 2012. Photo courtesy of Nasser Rabbat.From Cairo, Egypt, to Toronto, Canada, July 2012. Photo courtesy of Nasser Rabbat.From Cairo</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of geography.This episode was produced by The Current Time, with contributions from: Ryan Avent, Mary Turner, Sarah Friedland, Lloyd Asness and Maxime Lagacé.With Jack Aberrant, produced by The Current Time, with contributions from: Ryan Avent, Mary Turner, Sarah Friedland,  Maxime Lagacé and more being assembled, we sit down with Jack and recruitment and design agency The Current Time to discuss the challenges facing the City of Vancouver at the moment of its writing of its future.  The Current Time is a non-profit, public-art organisation established in 1981 and chartered in 1994. It is a producer and innovator in the arts and social impact of its activities, with a particular interest in the arts and social impact of publicly-funded art in the city. Its mandate is to stimulate artistic practices through collaborative platforms, partnerships and events, while continually improving the infrastructure</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of data. This has recently been seen in the release of the UN's Sustainable Development Goals (2017) and the United Nations Framework Convention on Climate Change (2015). His latest work, 'Democracy Federation' was co-curated with Juliana Engberg at the Museum of Anthropology and History in Vancouver and was recently presented at the 14th Annual Meeting of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research.The B.C. Lions ShareYourFuture.com 	The B.C. Lions ShareYourFuture.com is a free online community of learners, contributors and supporters that convenes every two weeks in Vancouver and Calgary. It was started in 2012 by artist Ai Weiwei and the Canadian Centre for Policy Alternatives, and is co-located with Policy Leaf, a national public-policy think tank based in Toronto, Canada. We’re here to learn, talk, share ideas and connect via social media, art and craft. Come with us! The B.C. Lions</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of technology in urban settings.  He has a Master’s degree in Political Science from the University of Alberta, and a Bachelor’s degree in Geography from the University of Alberta Libraries. His publications include the book  The B.C. Demographics Project, co-edited with Susanne Craig and Trevor Mills, and the blog  The B.C. Demographics Project.PreviousWork: In 2010 I co-founded and edited the blog  The B.C. Demographics Project, where I post a weekly collage series from the archives of the magazine,   B.C. Demographics, that documents the history of the Demographics Project, from its origins in Vancouver to the present. The series was nominated for the Sir John A. MacFarlane Publication of the Year Prize, 2008. My work is presented as a talk show, in partnership with Public Radio International and CBC Radio One. I was one of four curators for the 2008 Venice Biennale</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, Max is a designer whose work often addresses the relationship between people, machines and data. His work often involves interaction between humans and data, often in unexpected ways.His latest work, 'Face It: Breaking the Cycle of Poverty and Homelessness in Vancouver' was presented at the Humanities Faculty conference - Canada 150, held at the Museum of Anthropology in Vancouver, Canada, June 2016. Max is a Co-Founder and Chair of the Board of Directors of the B.C. Federation of Community Land Trusts. He also serves as the Co-Chair of the Advisory Board of the B.C. Centre for Policy Alternatives. His writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The New Republic, The Atlantic and The Stranger, amongst many others. He is currently the editor of the African Journal of Urban and Regional Research, and the co-editor of the African Journal of Regional Development. He has a special interest in the politics of access to and integration of technology in urban environments. He has written for CBC's The Current and The Current Africa and is currently a correspondent for the African Journal of Global Affairs and Technology.PreviousWork: In 2009, I co-founded the African Centre for a Regional Research Network (ACNR) in Durban, South Africa. ACNR is a multi-disciplinary, multi-use centre for the study and production of contemporary art, design, architecture and urbanism in the Durban-Fremont metro area. ACNR was founded as an independent research organisation, and our programmes span from there into ​​researching and criticality into the social and political contexts of art and architecture today. I was also a co-curator of the 2016 African Design Biennale, and the first curator of the African Development &amp; Policy conference, held in Durban in 2017.Rethinking American Architecture: From Quartering Jets to Multi-Disciplinary MuseumsArchitecture and Design, 2012. I have a particular</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The Biennial was initially conceived as a ‘postgraduate’ programme with the intention of bringing together biennials with artists from various disciplines in an ongoing exchange. The curator was expected to lead this exchange and offer a ‘corner case’ to the biennial in the sense that the exchange was not confined to the confines of the biennial. The revised  	Programme of Art &amp; Architecture of the Biennial in 2012 proposed a similar division between curatorial and arts context, but with a focus on biennials in the city. The curatorial role was divided between two offices: the Architecture Archives Office at the Liverpool Biennial and the Arts Archive Office at the National Gallery. The former was responsible for archiving and preserving the architectural heritage of the city; the latter for producing, organising and displaying architectural works from the archives. While the curatorial role has traditionally been viewed as that of a specialist, the former opens up new perspectives and brings to life old</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The idea that cities could be transformed through the collaborative initiative of artists and local communities gained momentum. The notion that the art form could be collectively re-purposed through the collaborative activities of artists and local communities was developed, and the practice of curation became an integral part of the curatorial agenda. 	There were, however, persistent concerns about the capacity of the art institution to support socially engaged and apolitical art projects at a city scale. There were two main sources of objection to the biennial’s urban agenda: (1) the historical role of the museum in the development of urban infrastructure and public realm, and (2) the impact of curatorial interventions in the development of socially engaged and politically engaged art practices. The concern about the role of the museum in the development of infrastructure and public realm was most clearly articulated in the proposal by Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT, who proposed that the biennial establish a long-</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The Biennial began to experiment with the idea of what it meant to be an ‘international’ entity and started to introduce ‘curatorial values’ into the definition of what counts as an exhibition. By the early 1990s, a work environment had entered the canon of aesthetic concerns of the Biennial. The Biennial also began to experiment with what it meant for a curatorial gesture to be accompanied by a ‘show’ or a ‘trick’ in order to broaden one’s audience. The show itself entered into the canon of exhibitionary forms and themes. It became evident that the show needed to be accompanied by a ‘show’ that generated interest and excitement beyond the art students and art professionals who were visiting the city. 	As a curatorial gesture, the Biennial attempted to engage with the notions of value and immersion in the city through the use of its signage – a form of advertising intended to lure in visitors from other cities by</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The Biennial was launched in 1991 and its mission statement reads as follows: ‘To be a catalyst for cultural and social change through research and exhibition.'[20] Its collections, exhibitions and resources are a testimony to this ambition. 	[i] The Biennial has a long-term research-based research agenda that extends beyond its regular exhibitions to bring to life the hidden sources of culture, both historical and contemporary. This approach is reflected in its name: the ‘bullet journal’ is a record of events in the biennial’s past that are currently of cultural interest to the biennial. 	[ii] In 2004, the British Council established an Endowment Fund to support a continued study of the policy effects of planned and planned regeneration in the borough of Newham, London. This was done in part by investing in the Biennial, which at the time was planning to establish a permanent art gallery in the borough. 	[iii] The Biennial</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The proposal 	for the Liverpool Biennial to take over the curatorial role came from the Urban Design Group at UDT. Urban Design was headed by Graham Turner and included architects, planners, landscape architects and urbanists. It was part of a wider research group that also included architects and landscape architects from across the UK and abroad. In 1980, the group was restructured and renamed  	Architecture at City University Liverpool. The reorganisation saw the creation of a new division within the department responsible for architectural education and research, with responsibility for the  	‘City of Ideas’ project and the University’s continuing exploration of the role of architecture in the city transferred to the  	‘Architecture Institute’ in the City of London. The new division’s activities were expanded and it became a hub for architecture projects worldwide. The new division’s website boasted a short description of the project’s ‘City</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The idea that the city is an appropriate place to develop socially engaged projects emerged as a response to the closure of many community art centres due to budget cuts. It is an honest to the city’s crisis of overbuilding and underfunding that the Biennial would one day need to address. It is an acknowledgement of the city’s capacity as an artistic and cultural production centre that is stretched to capacity. It is a call to act on this artistic and cultural potential through what has been termed the Community Arts movement. 	A large part of the initiative has been taken up by the artist Ai Weiwei, who has been developing a project called Liverpool Art Apartment Trust (LEAT), which seeks to establish a cooperative art gallery for artists and community artists in the city. The gallery would display the work of artists in an area under the LEAT banner, while providing a space for discussion, debate and collaboration on the issues facing artists and the community. The art gallery would operate counter to the</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The ‘City within a City’ concept and its development as a curatorial enterprise is characterised by the taking of control of space and time, which in turn are characterised by the circumvention of its rightful use. In the context of the postindustrial city, the practice of the ‘City within a City’ emerges as an increasingly pernicious urban legacy. In 1989, Fred Turner coined the term to describe the effect of the division of labour on urban space and made it a core concept of his influential work, The Great Stagnation, which examined the consequences of postindustrial capitalism. 	In the 1990s and early 2000s, the term ‘suburbia’ was frequently abused to describe areas with a ‘suburban feel’ and a tendency towards electronic consumption. Suburbs, he claimed, were a manifestation of the tendency towards 'wobbliness’ in response to resource scarcity and industrialisation.[4] Suburbs,</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The Biennial moved its development arm from Liverpool to Berlin in 1989 and its cultural arm from Liverpool to Stockholm in 1993. Following the closure of UDT in 1993, the Biennial moved its cultural arm to New York. It is the work of just two people: Guy Debord, whose name is on the Biennial’s charter, and Ada Louise Hryjkovskaya, who is its curator. The relationship between the biennial and the city is complex and dynamic. During the 1990s and early 2000s, the biennial was sometimes accused of being a city within a city, a hybrid of urban and metropolitan, and sometimes ‘too urban’, with its postmodern tendencies. But Debord and Hryjkovskaya’s work is radically different. She started from the premise that cities are made up of different biennials – each with a slightly different mission and approach – and has worked her whole career, from the creation of the biennial in</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The Biennial was launched in April 2017. It was originally conceived as a ‘platform for thinking and experimentation’, where artists could sit for one-to-one conversations with curators, journalists and other curators. It was also intended to be a place where artists could work collaboratively with local communities and engage with their ideas through a ‘community of artists’. In the event that was planned, it was often used as a pulpit to promote a particular ideology or point of view. The Biennial’s 2017 programme of events suggested a more active involvement for artists and curators: more than usual programming, events and activities; more theatre and arts activities; and a ‘curatorial summit’ hosted by the Liverpool Biennial itself. Curator and artist Irene Hofmann was invited to lead a virtual tour of the Biennial, based on the ideas and techniques of socially engaged art. Hofmann’s artistic direction was important in developing the Biennial</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. The initiative was labelled ‘Project Curzon’ and its members given the task of organising exhibitions, seminars and workshops in a city as a result of which the city was transformed. The aim was to create a ‘curatorial village’ and ‘a city within a city’. It became evident that the city did not have the infrastructure to support such a project on an industrial scale. The models used in the city were not built for the scale of the projects envisioned in the urban development plans but for the children. The ‘city within a city’ concept was partially developed out of a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial and Jussi Parikka and his Urban Design Group at UDT. Jussi Parikka was a leading urban theorist of the 1970s and 1980s and a professor at UDT until his retirement in 1990. His work during this period includes the book City of Silver and the documentary film Cities of Silver. 	The Biennial was founded in 2014 and its mission is to bring together and foster dialogue between art and architecture on a global scale through research and analysis, in an attempt to account for the urban transformation taking place all around us. The biennial’s projects in the surrounding area are organized around the concept of cities as ‘material forms’, addressing the question of what it means to be ‘built’ and what it ‘means’ to be ‘urbanized’. The project in Anfield includes research into the area, with a view to bringing the Biennial into the project by encouraging its ongoing collaboration through events such as the Architecture Biennial and the Biennial Research Project. The project in Anfield is a collaboration between the Liverpool Biennial, which organises the Biennial as a whole, and the U.S. Geological Survey, who are partners in the project. 	The Biennial Research Project is a collaboration between the Biennial and the University of</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the
    <text>presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the social and political meaning of sexuality and gender roles. Her work with communities, incorporating sex work, poetry, tutoring and youth groups, was produced in venues such as the Greenleaf Arts Centre, The William and Flora Green School of Art at Virginia Commonwealth University, and the Museum of Modern Art, where her interest was particularly focused. Her later commissions included the Human Ecology exhibit at the Museum of Modern Art, which opened in London, the US, and the first Public Theatre production of Act of Valour in Vancouver, Canada.Her most recent projects include: Working Class Hero (2016), a video essay on the events surrounding the death of 18-month-old Elmo at the hands of a state-sponsored killer, and the documentary on the Holocaust and subsequent Armenian Genocide, The Grave of the Armenian Decade, which premiered in Venice. Her latest project, El Parthenon de Jesus (2017), is a cultural monograph on the life and works of Franciscan Sister of</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the social construction of identities and place and has worked with communities in her career, from the 1980s through the early 1990s when she was at the University of Maryland, where she supervised the School of Communication Arts and co-founded the College of Communication Arts. She also directed the first phase of the College of Art, Design and Politics. Dezember has a particular interest in the condition of post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD). Her artwork and writing have been featured in publications such as The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Ed, the Village Voice, The Village Voice Arts &amp; Culture, and The New York Times Higher Ed Memoirs.Her artworks have been commissioned by National Endowment for the Arts, the Library of Congress, and the National Endowment for the Humanities. In 2007 she was part of the curatorial team for the 10th Annual Meeting of the Atlanta Art Biennial. In 2013 she curated the</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the history of feminist and activist art and the contemporary condition of visual literacy in communities. In addition to her artistic writing, she is a co-founder of Action Space, a collective of activists dedicated to the socialization of art and communities, and the co-editor of the Action Space Quarterly, a journal of activism in the arts.She is the host of the Audre Lorde Curatorial Writing Fellow (2016-ongoing), the inaugural recipient of the American Artist Knox Fellowship, and was an Artist in residence at the Museum of Modern Art. She has written for the New York Times, the Los Angeles Times, the Village Voice, and other publications on the justice, environmental and racial justice of the arts, and has participated in the A. Philip Randolph Humanitarian Award, the Pulitzer Prize, and the BBC's &quot;Great British Bake Off.&quot; She is the recipient of several awards and has lectured on a variety of subjects. She has a special interest in the condition of virtual and</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the social and civil rights of women and racial justice. In addition to being an artist, she is a campaigner for indigenous peoples and has written for publications such as the New York Times, The Washington Post, The Village Voice, The Nation, The Baltimore Sun and The Village Voice. Her work is part of the Racial/Class Divide project. In addition to artist-teach-recipes, her other work includes the award-winning Black Women Poems, from the collection of the Baltimore Art Museums, and the award-winning Black Women Journal. She has written for the Washington Post and The Nation, among others.Her work incorporates language, performance, object and artefacts. Her work with the Idle No More movement in Canada resulted in the establishment of the National Museum for the Arts. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Commonwealth, Frederic Bastien Foundation, Howard Zinn Foundation, National Endowment for the Arts, Royal BC Museum, and the Canadian Museum for Art.Tania B</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the history of pornography, race and social intention, and her work often pushes the limits of what one can imagine or conceive. She has written for The Nation, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The Baltimore Sun, The New Inquiry, Steeped in the history of black feminist and queer theory. She is a co-author of the critically acclaimed Black Feminist &amp; Queer Theory: The Politics of Empowerment (2007), a companion work to her 2014 publication Stages: Sexual Politics in Black Feminist Theory. She has also co-edited the anthology Black Feminist Theory: Volume Two: Race and Class in Modernity, edited by Audre Lorde &amp; Roseanne Eldredge, (Wiley-Blackwell, 2015), and edited the forthcoming Black Feminist &amp; Queer Theory: Volume Three: Sex, Race and Class in Modernity, edited by Roseanne Eldredge &amp; Janet Biehl. She is the host of the popular podcast Stages on the Pod Save for Peas &amp;</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the history and contemporary art of communities and has worked with communities through projects such as the Montgomery Arts Project, which examined the history and practices of community art, as well as the 1981 Montgomery Bus Boycott, which was inspired by the fact that the first bus from Montgomery, Maryland, to Washington, DC, ran every Friday. Dezember has shown projects at the Black-E, Black-Rock, Silent Spring, and the National Gallery. She is an adjunct faculty member in the Faculty Development and Research Lab of the Graduate Center for Art and Social Inquiry, and the Art and Communications Studies Program at McGill University. Her writing has been featured in publications such as the GLAAD/ACTA Journal, the New York Times, the New Republic, Popular Culture/Singleton, among others. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Whitechapel Gallery, the Canadian Museum for Racism and National Études, and the Royal College of Art. In 2015 she was the curator of the exhibition</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the social and cultural construction of power and control and has published widely on topics related to social structure, power and the social. Her writing has been featured in numerous books and journals including The Progressive, The New Inquiry, Socialist Alternative, World Socialist Web Site, Socialist Register, Black Flag, Socialist Home Journal, Third Coast, The Nation of Islam, The Anti-Capitalist, Socialist Alternative, The African and African-American Party, among others. She was a contributor to The Wages of Terrorist Violence, published by SocialistWorker magazine. She is a co-editor of the upcoming African Journal of Critical Studies, due out in 2017, and a co-editor of the upcoming African Journal of International Relations, due out in 2018.Dezember is a prolific writer, with over a dozen published books and over a half a dozen works in the public domain. Her work is presented in venues ranging from mass media to academia, including the National Portrait Gallery, Tate Modern, Tate Britain, Black</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the history and practices of fetishism and she has published several essays on the topic of art, sexuality, gender and politics in contemporary cultures. Her artwork 'Conquest of Time' was featured in the film The Guest, directed by James Ivory and starring Julianne Moore. In 2015, she participated in the Biennial of Sydney, Australia, and was a curator for the opening weekend of the Venice Biennale. In 2017, she curated the Venice Biennale, which she organized with her partner, Julia Dean. Together, they curated the first Venice Biennale in eight years, with a curatorial team led by Nasser Rabbat. When not actively involved in the art as a curatorial stance, Dezember pursues other interests, often exploring the social context of contemporary art and the role of curatorial practices in the formation of social change. She is the recipient of several awards and has been a presenter of multiple national and international television shows.In collaboration with Future City, we</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the intersections of power and social organisation. She has worked with communities to establish and reinstate non-profit arts organisations, as well as for civil rights and environmental causes. In addition to her research, she coordinates the Justice Centre for Alternatives Programmes, which offers free or subsidised post-secondary education and training to artists - including some whose work is featured in this volume - through which artists can engage with issues relating to community and democracy.Dressing Herself in Masks and Steampunk Uniforms1935Juliana Drawn and Suzi GjakovStuart Ringhold and his gang of street urchins in their original clothes, go underground, past the theatre, and into the dark labyrinths of the steel industry. After a number of years they are back in the public eye when they are arrested by the police and forced to make an appearance in court in front of a sympathetic press corps. Stuarts story is told in the press as a justification for the wholesale reconstitution of</text>
    <text>presented as an online project) and is now at K, Deena and co-author (with Daniel Coleman) of the forthcoming book Due Diligence: Contemporaneous and Consumer Discourses of the Post-Apocalyptic Condition. His writing has previously appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, Reason and many other publications. He is a regular contributor to Arutz Sheva and Current Culture, among other publications, and is an adjunct faculty member in The George Washington University's Metropolitan Museum of Art Program. His new work, Using Media (2016), presents his research and thinking on the post-apocalyptic condition in a new light.Rosa Parks - Fetishism, Genocide and Blogs Shannon JefferiesDownload this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began in the 1980s when she was at the University of Maryland, Acting as Associate Professor of Art and Director of the Art and Communications Studies Program. Dezember has an interest in the social and political meaning of erotic art, in the ways it is produced and reproduced in communities, and in the practices and institutions that shape social and political values and perceptions of the world. She has written for publications such as National Review, the Washington Post, the Village Voice, the Baltimore Sun, the New York Times and the Village Voice, among others. She is a co-founder of the blog  	Tipping Point (www.tip-point.org) and the podcast  	Praying Mounds (http://www.prowl.net/podcasts/paul-waldman-the-sacred-potential-its-potential/archive/podcasts/paul-waldman-the-sacred-potential-its-potential.m3u9). Michelle Dezember is a writer and artist. Her work is concerned with the politics of erotic art, with the production and consumption of erotic art, and with</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province from drawing resources and resources on its own accord, whereas the City could do so freely in and around its core.  The City’s inability to marshal resources or draw resources on its own accord was also seen as a major hindrance to the creative impulse of the city’s burgeoning arts scene. Finally, the Province countered that the City was pursuing a cultural trajectory that was antithetical to the province’s, and in fact threatened to undermine the very fabric of the Province’s collective identity.  The debate over the relationship between the arts and the city was closely watched by the media at the time, and the news was often rife with references to the City’s desperate need for urban renewal. The debates, which came as often as weekly, highlighted the City’s desperation and the Province’s creativity. One particularly controversial issue that came up time and again was the one pertaining to the size and shape of potlatch. The City argued that</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province from providing the kind of cultural orientations that would draw people to the downtown core and encourage them to move there.  The City responded that it was ahead of the game in every respect, and that the Province was behind in none of them. This latter claim was widely disputed, but the two were in a constant state of flux, with different levels of government constantly intervening to tweak and tweak the City's urban landscape in an endless loop. The City maintained that it was in a race to the bottom in technology and ready access to information, while the Province was seen as behind in one area and completely blind in another. In the end, it was up to individual municipalities to decide where and when to spend cultural dollars, and this was a decision that was entirely at the discretion of local councillors and mayors.  So far, so routine in today’s city: the introduction of a new light-rail transit line promises rapid growth, the introduction of a new bus rapid transit system promises frequent service</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province from effectively engaging the City with cultural initiatives in the downtown core. The City countered that this was because the Province lacked the expertise and capacity to effectively engage the city in cultural projects in the downtown core, and because the City lacked the skills needed to effectively employ artists, designers, and other cultural creatives in the downtown core.  The City also alleged that the lack of a downtown interfered with the ability of artists and other cultural creatives to effectively engage the city in ‘design-build’ programmes, which are increasingly common in commercial centres but are not uncommon in neighbourhoods where the City’s urban fabric is poorly maintained or un-fulfilling.  Finally, the City alleged that the lack of a downtown interfered with the ability of communities to collectively pursue creative solutions to urban problems. In other words, the struggle for democratic control of urban space – a right that was supposed to be inherent in the City of Vancouver – was made into a struggle over control of aesthetic spaces. All the</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province from understanding its urban development better. In the end, both the City and the Province were left holding cultural resources that were either too valuable to waste, or were seen as too threatening to invest in creating new ­urban forms.  At the same time, the emergence of ‘alternative urban forms’ in the mid-1980s put an end to this outdated and dirty urban resource-based allocation of resources. The shift in the global allocation of resources came about when the technology industry displaced smaller landownership forms as the primary form of manufacturing in Canada (following rapid growth during the 1980s and into the 1990s by the adoption of post-Fordist finance premierships in Ontario and the ‘London Standard’ in the ‘Standard Chartered Book of Commerce’). The shift in the use of space came about because of the increased productivity generated by the proliferation of computer systems and software, which allowed larger producers to compete at lower costs. The shift in the use of</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province from perceiving the City as a living, breathing entity.  The City countered that it was the reverse: the Province was blinded by its economic self-sufficiency, while the City was seen as drowning in its own aquatic abstraction. The race to the bottom in technology was thought to aid in a city’s recovery, while the other was thought to aid in its recovery.  The debates, while not always amenable to resolution, provide valuable insight into the current state of tensions and tensions in the City.  The discussion also provided valuable insights into the past, present and future of the City’s arts scene. As technology advanced, so too did the pace of innovation and creativity. And as a result, so too did the resources required to support it. Rapid technological change and the fluidity of innovation are the result not of individual creators exercising creativity at a breakneck speed but of a collective, interconnecteding effect. As a result of this trend, a city is often left</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province from effectively lobbying the City to create a cultural district there. The two levels of government – the City and the Province – responded that they had created a common sphere of influence in an area the size of downtown Vancouver. This common sphere of influence, they claimed, could be realised through a ‘cultural district map’, which was then submitted to the voters of Vancouver at the 1982 municipal level.6 The City did not respond with a 'map' of cities, but with a strategy for creating a ‘cultural district’ based on the strategic location of technology and how it interacts with the city. This was seen by some as being overly technophobic, while others saw it as being overly feminist. A ‘culture district’ is a place where people gather to ‘enact, create, observe or engage in a shared experience’, and is a strategic location for the City’s strategy of culture production. It is a place where art, poetry, play,</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province from perceiving the City as a viable option for provincial arts and culture initiatives.  The City responded that it viewed its position as one of desperation, with the Province having arrived too late to save the day. The presence of millions of dollars in federal arts and culture funding from the 1980s that it could deploy against the City was clearly seen as a serious threat. The City’s position was that it could not possibly deliver the technology, the managerial skill sets or the artistic resources to compete in a federally funded arts and culture arena, since the technological capability of the City was second to none.  The City’s claim was that it was being overrun by artists and performing a public function, when in fact it was the reverse: it was performing an arts and culture act at the expense of the Province. Despite the obvious fact that the technology was there to be exploited and that the City could easily install and upgrade its systems to meet federal arts and culture requirements, the Province decided against stepping</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province from realizing its potential. Eventually, a consensus was reached that all three levels of government needed to come together to tackle the structural inequalities that were holding back the City from realizing its potential. This was seen as a national crisis, and it was felt that the only way to end the impasse was for all levels of government to collude in an unprecedented fashion to create a new downtown in an attempt to revitalize the downtown and bring the City back to life. This was seen as a last resort, and it was believed that the best interests of the City were greater than the interests of any one level of government.  So far, so normal in the City, except that now the techno-savvy downtowners had taken control of the city. They had created a ‘smart city’ that offered better resources, created greater imitations of the city, and so forth. And so the race to the bottom in technology and knowledge inevitably led to a Race to the Bottom in aesthetic standards.</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province from providing the necessary resources for arts and culture.  In a landmark decision in 1986, the Supreme Court of Canada ruled in favour of the Province, awarding Msgr. Shamloo and her husband, Scott, a major cultural victory.  The decision opened up a number of new frontiers for cultural and urban exploration in Canada and the United States. It is worth noting that in the years that followed the decision, technology and information technology became much more accessible, allowing people to do things such as post and instant messages on social media, accessorize their homes with apps, and access podcasts and films anywhere.  A number of other high profile cultural and urban victories were also achieved during this period, including the appointment of well-known artists and intellectuals to key positions in the City’s cultural life.  An example of this is the 2010 Canadian pavilion, which was designed by Frank Gehry and Maxime Reynaud, and was designed to the specifications of Canadian Heritage architect Frank McGarry</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role in a drive for efficiency and creativity. These were seen by some as a way to increase the visibility of arts and culture, while others saw it as an opportunity to boost productivity and compete against each other in a race to the bottom for technology.  The race to the bottom in technology was another area in which the City of Vancouver was at loggerheads with the province. During the 1980s, the City was accused of being overly technophobic and backward-looking in its approach to the cultural sector, while the province was accused of being overly romantic and ­feminist. The City was seen as overly concerned with the appearance of technology and overly concerned with the well-being of women. The City was also seen as lacking in vision and lacking in resources. The Province argued that the City was woefully behind in its quest for cultural resources, and the City responded that it was behind in its technological and aesthetic sense, as well. It was also claimed that the lack of a downtown prevented the Province from providing the vital infrastructure for a downtown, while the Province countered that the City was constructing too rapidly and that the Province was building buildings on sand and mountainside topsoil.  A growing rift between the two levels of government allowed the emergence of a competing cultural strategy, which was generally seen as preferable to the City's traditional approach to resource scarcity and the pursuit of aesthetic ­norms.  An art gallery in the vein of Mission Dolores del Mar, but with a feminist slant, would surface first in an urban core, while a contemporary art space would surface in the periphery.  The slant in cultural strategy was generally believed to be a good thing, since it supported the City’s artistic aspirations and allowed the City to dominate the cultural landscape in a way that it could not, with or without the support of the Province.  But what the City was primarily interested in was the ability to control how art would be presented and how people would be made aware of art within</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour
    <text>Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour – artists, architects, journalists, students, custodians, labourers. It gave form to many different kinds of labour and thus, in my opinion, the collection should be of a kind that transcends technology and infrastructure. It’s a collection of stories, woven together into one long narrative. Because the collection as a whole is a story, its format is inherently storyteller’s toolkit. It has the potential to be much more than numbers, symbols and codes. This is why biennials can be so endearing to visitors drawn by their historical narratives: they’re memorable places where we visit familiar places and feel like we have intimate knowledge that other people hold in common. Because we share so much in common, we share experience, we share our history, we share the stories of how we got here, and so forth. And so the collection becomes an object of sharing – one could say, in the words of Georges Canguilhem: the</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour. It was an evolving and dynamically changing version of the numbers 2up2down/Homebaked/3up3down/Shopify, the name of the shop that housed the wares of the day. As a curatorial gesture, the collection’s current exhibition format is a kind of ‘found footage’ video, in which works from the collection are shown alongside works from other artists’ studios and social missions. This kind of inclusion is at odds with the automatism of the curatorial gesture, but it is also a recording of the conditions of existence of the individual artworks and a testimony to what a particular archaeological dig can reveal. The collection’s current exhibition format is a kind of ‘found footage’ video, in which works from the collection are shown alongside works from other artists’ studios and social missions. This kind of inclusion is at odds with the automatism of the curatorial gesture, but it is also a recording of the conditions</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour. It was both a tool and a paradox, simultaneously seeming like a permanent archive that could be tapped into and being used to great effect by those with a technological mind and a penchant for new technology. The collection as a living sculpture became a site of potential encounters between those with different kinds of tools and professions, as well as places of encounter for those with an imaginative impulse and a knack for building things. It was a site of possibilities, where people with different kinds of skills could find skills that could be used creatively, inventing and making new uses for old technology. It provided a way to rethink old questions, unanswered questions, about how labour might be structured so that creative labour might be encouraged and employment possibilities maximised. In other words, it was a point of intersection, where different kinds of labour could find common ground, engage with and overcome differences, and develop new solutions to existing problems.In the biennale’s own words:  [T]he Biennale is</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour. It was a living sculpture that combined the best of many different kinds of work into a coherent whole. It was a living sculpture that allowed its own symbolic and/or literary value to emerge through the combination of many different kinds of symbols. And it was a living sculpture that allowed its own actual size and shape to be understood by visitors to the museum. It was a living sculpture that was constantly evolving, constantly on the lookout for new kinds of labour and creating new kinds of meaning through their presence. In short, it was a living sculpture that captured the imagination of visitors as workers in many different kinds of jobs looked to it for direction and inspiration. It was a media project that captured the imagination of the media and public alike. It was a sculpture that functioned as a point of departure and an end point for many kinds of converging forces. In this sense, it was both urban and rural – capturing and transporting places. It captured the essence of places and their people while simultaneously lending a certain</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour. It was a platform on which many different kinds of labour could operate simultaneously. As the collection moved through its various incarnations, it also contained links between objects in the collection. The way in which it was organised and the images that it housed made it possible for people to find what they were looking for, independent of their positions within the collection. This is one kind of archaeology. The collection is a huge warehouse of images and symbols, but it also has images of objects that are of no value to anyone but those who keep it together and organise the events there.The next step is for the collection to unravel its varied incarnations – to open up its internal dynamics, its images and its archives. This is what the Biennale did for me. It opened up a world of possibilities, possibilities that were constrained by the constraints of a city. In doing so, it created a new kind of urbanity. It was an experience of the impossible – of the unknowable – which challenged</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour. It went through many transformations as a result of our conversations, but one of the most important came as we worked on the script for the 2018 iteration of the biennale. The idea for this iteration came from the office of the curator, Maria Hlavajova. She and her team had several questions that needed answering. Questions that, as we all know, are beyond the scope of this work. Questions that, as many artists have said many times over the years, are of the nature of collaboration and collaboration without question. Questions that demand an answer no matter how many times you try, whether it be as a member of the artist group, a writer, a curator, an HR person, or even as a member of the staff at the biennale itself. I sat for an in-person interview with Maria Hlavajova during the Biennale of Sydney. I was invited because I had just published an article in the journal Art and Urbanity about the conversations that</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour. It was a catalyst for a range of behaviours, behaviours that would later be defined as ‘cultural’ and ‘partnering’. As a project, it functioned as a point of departure for other artists and cultural organisations to explore how the biennale can build partnerships with local communities and other local enterprises. It provided a kind of counterweight to the urban density and corporate culture of the city, promoting a kind of rural countryside feel to the city. It also provided a kind of public space for the working class to be present in, and influencing the composition of, a new kind of cultural landscape.As a curatorial gesture, it allowed the collection to inhabit and inhabit again the urban core, injecting another layer of discourse, action, and practice into the artefact. The collection became a kind of urban museum, its curatorial function a kind of museum of symbolic exchange. It also invited in visitors from beyond the city, including artists from faraway places, artists</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour. It was a tool for reflection, a place for negotiation, a stage for creation, and it was a venue for exchange between worlds. It was a site for the production of new social forms, for the reception and exchange of different kinds of knowledge, and it was a site for the celebration of these forms. The collection and the work are multifaceted and dynamic. As the collection itself changed, so did the work that emerged from it. The collection would not exist without the work, and artworks would not form the basis of what the biennale was about. In that sense, the collection and the work came to constitute what it meant to be a biennale.And yet, somehow, we sensed an object in the collection that was different from anything else around: it broke the mould of what we had made before. It broke the codes we had used to capture and manage that which we had created. And somehow, it functioned as a kind of a monument to our</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour. It’s a reminder that, although it may look like a number, it’s really just a number – a number that can be augmented and augmented in many different ways. It’s a code that can be broken into many different codes to achieve many different things. For example, the number 6 was originally written as ‘6 + 6’ or ‘6 + 6 + 8’, and later ‘6 + 8’, or even ‘8 + 8’. In this archive of numbers, there’s a great potential for different kinds of knowledge to be gathered. In one of my sculptures, a woman reading the number on a piece of paper sits on a red carpet at the Venice Biennale. She may or may not have access to the information that would allow her to perform the number accurately. Her sculpture is a kind of ‘hidden number’ that allows passersby to step back and allow different kinds</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, people can create meaning and purpose through symbolic actions. We use numbers and symbols to tell stories and reveal truths. And as an art project, it’s about more than the numbers and symbols that appear on a CV.It’s also a way to be present in a work that may one day be digitised and stored in a museum. In the coming years, the collection that will one day be housed in the biennale will consist of objects that can be seen to be of symbolic value – lost narratives and fragments of knowledge that can be retrieved. For me, the collection is a vast warehouse of texts and images that can only be accessed through a symbol. It’s a labyrinth of tunnels with hidden doors and passages that only the most skilled and resourceful of workers have access to.The object that emerged as the result of our collaboration was a living sculpture that functioned as a kind of database, a warehouse of knowledge, and a stage for many different kinds of labour. It was a point of departure for us in that we could have any number of interpretations of what the collection could become, and the different kinds of labour could interpenetrate and interconnect. For example, the collection of objects that came out of our discussions with the H.W. set the stage for the collection of paintings that would one day be exhibited in the Biennale. These paintings, from the collection of artists that came out of the meeting, and the various collections of artists, in their turn, would draw upon these same collections to tell stories or take on new forms. This last bit is an example of a classically trained artist coming up with something new from scratch, from the fragments and fragments of knowledge that came out of the meeting. It’s a work that was intended to be seen as a response to the biennale’s monstrosity of its starting, but it quickly becomes apparent that this is no longer the case. The monstros</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis,
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis, entwined with time, image courtesy of CC BY 2.0. 	The 3rd Istanbul Biennale in 2015. Photograph courtesy of Bina Fokidis. 	In the intervening years, I have continued to work in the same cities as the Gilded Age Project, while my partner, Elena, works now as an artist. We created a project called  	Cities in Crisis  with colleagues from the Russian Centre for Addiction to Experiences in Need of Sorrow in order to bring together a large international team of artists, curators, journalists and others with a mandate to investigate the full range of catastrophes, from natural disasters to war and conflict. The project was presented at the 3rd Venice Biennale as part of the 'Cities in Crisis: Global Futures' exhibition and has been re-presented at the Venice Biennale after it was deemed to be a biennale 'event' by</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis, Curator of Artsangelsk, Shiraz, Russia. 1962. Watercolour on wax. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962. Collage magazine, 1962.</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis, Narrator, Groundhog Day (1995). Directed by Steven Soderbergh. Also starring Peter Sellers, Matt Damon, Robin Williams, Woody Harrelson, Rose Byrne, Ron Howard, Susan Sarandon, Donald Sutherland, Donald Sutherland Jr., Joel McKee and Steven Spielberg. Running Time: 149 min. US / GR8 / GRAPHICLIVE.comReleased: April 24, 2012Curious Gilded Age was the subject of a documentary film, Groundhog Day (1995), that was produced and directed by Steven Soderbergh. It is the story of how the artist Jeanne van Heeswijk came to be known as the ‘King of Shiraz’, and the circumstances surrounding her ouster from the Shiraz Academy in the 1970s. The film was written by Brian Cox, with additional work by Lynne Ramsay and John N. Clarke.It is the story of two worlds colliding: the world of the artist Jeanne van Hees</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis,  	Curious Gilded Age, 2013. Installation, Shiraz Museum of Art. Photo: Nasser Rabbati. 	The Fokidis’ work has a kind of time stamp – it is a kind of a ‘time capsule’. It records, from the very first drawing of a man in a horse-collar shirt and trousers in Isfahan, how the city was emerging as a metaphor for a utopian future – and the tensions and contradictions of this future, which are reproduced in the work – in an age when the city is a huge and seemingly inexhaustible resource. And it does this in such a way as to provoke a kind of critical-thinking about the contemporary condition that is very much unlike that of the Gilded Age. In the Gilded Age, material wealth was distributed globally; now we are experiencing what M. Ervin Castro, the Cuban who was imprisoned for 11 years for taking part in the 2000 2000</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis,  	Curious Gilded Age, 2012. New York. Waterhouse. PreviousNextCurious Gilded Age, 2012. New York. Waterhouse. 	The most memorable moment for me was while visiting Shiraz, the city where the Gilded Age is based. I was accompanied by an artist who is an Iranian-American living and working in New York. We visited the old city, visited the sites where the Gilded Age was made, and then we visited the present city – Isfahan, Mashhad and Shiraz – visiting the places where the modern and contemporary Gilded Age begins to take place. Isfahan is the site of the 2012 Summer Olympic Games, and Mashhad and Shiraz are the sites for the 2015 and 2020 games respectively. The entire city is being redeveloped, and the old airport is being converted into a residential and hotel district. Shiraz is being served by the US Olympic Committee, US Department of Energy and the New York City Transit</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis, Groundhog Day (film still), 1991. Photo courtesy of Marina Fokidis Archive. 	The biennial format did not exist in its current form before the 1980s, and the extraordinarily rapid pace of development that accompanied it – in terms of new buildings every day – is unprecedented in human history. The biennial as an institution has since then largely shrunk in profile, and its various forms have been pulled into ever greater complexity, with more emphasis now placed on the needs of the curatorial (curatorial priorities, after all) than the actual needs of the communities living there. Still, the main challenge for curators and artists of the 1980s has largely remained the same: to make art in the most accessible way possible, with as little social or political impact as possible. The challenge for contemporary artists and curators is entirely different – and much more immediate and palpable – in that it calls for an end to economic capitalism as we know it today. It is a demand for a new kind</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis, The Gilded Age Project, 2010. Installation view at Pirbright Gallery, London. Photo: Tom Lox.  	The Gilded Age Project was a collaborative project between the PIE (Persian Society of Antiquaries), the Shiraz Museum and FACT (Foundation of American Archaeology). Together, we explored the relationship between gold and power. We saw how early American and Persian artists used gold as a medium of exchange and how the Shiraz Museum and FACT continued to use it as a media-maker and a repository of cultural practices through their collections. We also saw how the promise of a new economy of cultural exchange could also liberate cultural practices from the constraints of nation-state construction. In the film Groundhog Day, Peter Brook plays a character who wants to open a cold store but is afraid to go to the grocery store. The narrator tells us that Peter is not alone:There are other people like him – pre-Columbian, pre-Mayan, pre</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis, who is now the Dean of the School of Art and Design at the University of Akron, is the director of the Art and Design Lab at the University of Akron and a curator at the American Museum of Modern Art. Her research and writing on art and the Gilded Age period is cited in such books as Gettysburg, The Gilded Age and Giuliani: Ten Stages.Fokidis was born in Shiraz, Iran, and raised in Mashhad, a city on the Mediterranean coast. She is the author of The Gilded Age: Modern Cities and a member of the ACM Digital Time &amp; Society group.Fokidis is the author of several books, including the 2014 New York Times best-seller The Gilded Age: Rise of the Millionaire Class (with David Humes and Evan Calder Williams) and the 2015 New York Times best-seller Shadow Government: Surveillance, Authority and Democracy in a Shadow Government (with Dan Frow &amp; Jeffrey Feltman). In 2015, she</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis,  	Curious Gilded Age (2006), San Francisco, Bayview, USA. 	After the project, Fokidis wrote a book about her life in a medieval Persian court, titled  	The Persian Empire: A History 	of Three Kingdoms. She also wrote a memoir – part memoir, part narrative – about how she came to be the curator of the Isfahan Archaeological Museum. 	Fokidis’ account of the Isfahan Archaeological Museum, her role in the project, and her own, are the subject of the film  	Groundhog Day (2008). The museum was closed for renovation for several years and reopened as part of a larger urban renewal project in 2011. She writes that the project ‘wasn’t about me, but rather about the fact that the museum would reopen only a few months after the opening of a new museum, since renovation is a scheduled process here, and since the closed museum meant</text>
    <text>machines were asked to take over the curatorial role. Curator Marina Fokidis took up this challenge and started a website  	Curious Gilded Age – a play on words of two Greek words meaning ‘gilded age’ and ‘age of innocence’.  She also started a Facebook group ‘Curious Gilded Age’ where others in the group shared their memories and anecdotes. This is when things started to move quickly, and we did some traveling to get here, as the film Groundhog Day shows. I am the youngest one by ten years and the only one who is still alive. Fokidis and her team of artists, writers and archivists, chose three locations – Shiraz, Mashhad and Isfahan – and visited each of them several times over five years. They were there every day, documenting the lives of people there through drawings, paintings and sculpture. The project came to be known as  	The Gilded Age Project. Marina Fokidis, Shiraz Jildife, and Tenay Baksaoui:  	Towards a Global Gilded Age 	Towards a Global Gilded Age (2014), New York, 236 p., (originally published in French as Le Devoir du Gilded Age, 1915). 	[1] Eugene Ostfeld,  	The Gilded Age: Economic Complexity and the End of Capitalism 	, Vintage Books, New York, 1987, p. 35. 	[2] Steve Raabe,  	The Gilded Age: Wealth and Capital in Modern-Day Britain 	, Vintage Books, New York, 1991, p. 76. 	[3] Frederick Engels, The Civil War 	, Penguin Classics, New York, 1984, p. xviii. 	[4] Frederick Engels, The Civil War 	, Penguin Classics, New York, 1985, p. xviii. 	</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities
    <text>Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities, suburbs or remote locations, enabling it to draw on this information in innovative ways. Such collaborations between artists and art institutions are frequent in South Sudan, with the most recent being a project by the Art and Culture Departments at the National Gallery of South Sudan and the Arts Council of South Sudan to commission a multi-disciplinary team of artists to paint on the walls of the South Sudanese National Museum of Art. In 2015, a similar project by the Art and Culture Council of South Sudan and the Arts Council of South Sudan was co-curated by the National Gallery of South Sudan. In both the 2015 and 2016 biennials, artists and art administrators from across the institutions participated, as well as artisans from other fields, including art historians, art databankers, media collectors, artists and writers.The challenge for the future is how to support such collaborative research and development in a way that liberates cultural resources from the bureaucratised control of capital and the museum sector, while enabling</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities, suburbs, or small towns, through the provision of cultural resources or the purchase of smart devices. The competition amongst artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job could be seen as a competition as to who could pull off the most innovative work. The use of data could be used to identify promising artists, curators, writers or artists through analysis of their curatorial choices, their social media activity, or their labours in the art world. The use of data could be used to identify promising artists, curators, writers or artists through analysis of their curatorial choices, their social media activity, or their labours in the art world. The biennial could enliven its visitor experience by employing innovative art-histories, creating an environside experience, or both. The use of data could be used to identify promising artists, curators, writers or artists through analysis of their curatorial choices, their social</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities, suburbs, or regions in an effort to identify promising locales, or places to look for better places to live.It is easy to understand the attraction of such a dynamic. After all, cultural institutions are places where people gather to exchange ideas and experiences, exchange culture, create friendships, and exchange goods and services. In these terms, the biennial – as an art form – is often seen as a resourceful, dynamic, even helpful resource for the wider community. In this way, institutions can be seen as useful cultural scavengers, bringing knowledge and resources to communities where it is needed most.In reality, however, competition between biennials is fierce, and many biennials would rather see a diverse collection of art and curatorial styles and works displayed in venues where they can be explored and enjoyed by a community (rather than competing for membership in a cultural body). This kind of community is not always represented in art exhibitions and public interventions, and many biennials are actively involved</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities, languages, cultures or any number of other variables that are important to a business or industry. It is also common for biennials to recruit artists to participate in competitions or exhibitions based on need or for-profit ventures that draw on the expertise of academics, artists or other art professionals. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access talented artists with diverse kinds of artistic styles or backgrounds and the skills required to participate in exhibitions or competitions that are judged on potential. For many years, the only way to learn about or see work by artists outside of a formal art context was to attend a regular art context – an art institution, a museum, an arts festival. This was a situation where the biennial was able to establish a long-term relationship with an artist or institution, and thus establish a network of artists and art professionals who could then be brought into other contexts. As biennials become more institutionalised and nationalised, and more reliant on commercial circulation, the competition between</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities, suburbs or remote regions of the world, in addition to collecting and analysing huge volumes of data about travel and places. Such data may be used to understand cultural phenomena in cities or other large settings, or may be gathered and used as a tool to monitor and control populations. In many ways, biennials can be seen as extensions of existing artworld models, albeit with some important differences. For example, exhibitions in galleries and museums are still mostly about a curator’s curatorial style, but the way in which artists develop and present their artworks differs from venue to venue. This has often been an issue for curators, whose work tends to be absorbed into a larger context that includes a museum exhibit and a programme of activities. It is also common for exhibitions to employ artists from a local area or a specific city to create a context or theme that is unique to the institution, often through the interaction of artists, artists, curators and other stakeholders. Finally, many bienn</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities or even countries with a critical mass of users. Its competitions often demand a fee or other consideration from the other participants in the competition. The urgency to position art and art’s social effects in the context of social struggles often arises from the misunderstanding or underestimation of the impact of art or art’s potential in challenging power structures. For example, the art of not being seen as a legitimate form of political resistance is frequently cited as an example of biennial engagement that is misplaced or compromised. But the biennial is hardly ever seen as a critical hub for the social struggles of a community. The increasing number of biennials and their market share also reflects their increasing access to cultural venues and reach. As the Biennaleeer.com website notes, the biennial has become a ‘gigantic industry seller’ in the city, one that is difficult to comprehend ‘without getting lost in the noise and volume of the information flying around’. The popularity</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities, suburbs or regions in an attempt to spot trends or even distinguish between real and fake residents. In the context of such monitoring, the biennial is often asked to produce benchmarks or indices to measure the success of such initiatives. Unfortunately, these indices often become mere tools or statistics used by institutional critics of the growing economic and social crisis in order to assess the institutional responses.As biennials, our focus has often been on the research side of things. Of course, this is still a prominent part of our game, and we have produced some impressive figures such as: Man Ray 	, whose work in communities around the world was highlighted by the London Biennale as one of the twenty-first century’s top ten contributions to the art and culture landscape, to mention only some of his achievements; Ben Goldacre, whose work as a writer, activist and director of the Free Speech Forum in the UK gained widespread public and international attention; Ray Brad</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities or even countries where the art is located, while enabling critical reflection on the varied purposes that those places may serve. In many cases, biennials have even themselves, as young artists or curators, becoming experts in a particular field or art form.This kind of multi-tiered, multi-platform, multi-platform research and development is now routine in most art world, but until recently it was often performed by local art communities. In many cities, the role of the biennial was to house artists and other artists for a specified number of years in a developmentally appropriate setting. Artists were usually expected to have a stable of projects that they could easily switch to when the host community needed artists, and the biennial could provide this for free. However, the advent of digital media and social media has changed this to an art institutionally-driven cycle. Biennials, as part of the art museum visitor base, are now also part of the art institution. This is coincidental</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities or even countries where conflict is frequent or endemic. It is possible that in the future, such biennials could draw on this kind of deep knowledge to commission works by artists or other curators selected through an innovative curatorial or artistic approach.Such a development would undoubtedly put curatorial and arts-policy-making bodies in a more political and activist position. It would also make it easier for such bodies to decipher trends in art-use and culture that may be indicative of broader social changes. For example, a biennial that develops a long-term interest in the arts and their discontents may decide to devote significant resources to entertaining such interests' social purpose, rather than chasing their economic or aesthetic success. Such a development, however, is highly problematic and may alienate communities whose needs are aligned with those of the powerful.In the contemporary context, bienniality is characterised by the production of sustainably managed cultural landscapes that function in a dynamic and ever-expanding context of exchange.</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, can you imagine a future in which everything you do is guided by algorithms? Inventing a computer that secures data from sources such as healthcare providers and real estate agents could make it easier for businesses to monitor employees, businesses to target employees with training, and the government to monitor employees and communities?Over the past decade, biennials have increasingly placed their research and development efforts in the context of larger cultural institutions – universities, galleries and museums. In doing so, they have often been enlisted by civic groups to monitor or even to provide critical feedback on cultural institutions and their work. In the 21st century, this has often been required of artists, writers, composers and artists whose work is displayed at cultural institutions. This kind of collaboration often takes the form of a competition among artists, curators, art administrators and others with skills or training in performing data mining or data extraction on the job. In these cases, the biennial is often able to access highly detailed data on industries, cities, suburbs or rural settings, and can draw upon this knowledge in its curatorial work.In recent years, the biennial has increasingly relied on art institutions, particularly those affiliated with the art fair, to provide programming and outreach support for the events, and to lead in terms of publicity and public perception. This has been done through partnerships with local arts organizations, including the amazing work done by the Art Federation, the Korea Arts Council and the National Arts Foundation. The important relationships between the biennial, the arts organization and the artist have also been developed through collaborative research and development projects between the two.For example, the biennial format places great emphasis on the historical significance of particular art forms, and the shared relationship between the artist and the historical form. This research and development process is driven by the biennial itself and its artists' union, the KMA. The KMA has developed an innovative research and development model that places considerable emphasis on the preservation and promotion of art forms as a public purpose</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow
    <text>should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.OhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOh9. Miriam Kramer, The Rape of Lucía Sanromán, 1961. Composed for the ​Bates Museum, Liverpool Biennial 2016.OS:Software, or the soft stuff, is a human behaviourism that emphasizes the integration of human behaviour into computer systems, much as John Nash’s behavioural psychology favoured the integration of language and</text>
    <text>should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow</text>
    <text>should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay. Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay. Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay. Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay. Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay.Okay</text>
    <text>should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.OhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOhOh(ed.)Now I See You (1965)P</text>
    <text>should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh oh</text>
    <text>should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow.You know what I’m getting at? When I used to paint the walls of the house,I always had someone over to paint the ceiling. They would come in through the window, looking pretty good, and then they would leave. I never knew why. I never understood why they didn’t come back. And they always painted the ceiling.See? Easy. I did that. When I had to leave,I always had someone over to look after the house.And they would always say, ‘You know what? I’m ready to give you a reason to</text>
    <text>should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Whole Lotta Love (2011) directed by David Lynch, produced by Ali Payami, Carol Kane, and Savan Kotecha.In the year 2000, David Lynch assembled a rotating cast of artists and activists to reconstruct the historic financial district of Hong Kong</text>
    <text>should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow[1] See Ben Whittaker and Rob Bremner, eds., The Venice Biennale Reader (Venice: Biennale Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor of English and Director of the English Department at the University of Toronto, where she has taught English and Film Studies for over a decade. Her work has addressed the relationship between art and literature, social practice and academia, art and integration, and art and identity. Her publications include the web-based anthology, Encyclopedia of Social Practice: Art &amp; Society (2014) and the award-winning, New Media Reader, (2015). She is part of the editorial board of the online magazine, Higher Education, and was an editor of the online journal Stages (2014-2016). She is part of the publishing team for the online book Stages: Critical Writing on the Digital Shortages (Harvard University Press,</text>
    <text>should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.This article was originally commissioned by and published in MUAD Magazine #27.For more information visit: www.marcheline.com/messe/chronicle/27.htmlMichael TruscelloMichele Dean Michele Dean is a curator and writer with a particular interest in the history and contemporary state of New York City. Her publications include the Historical Atlas of the City (2012), which documents the development of the city from colonial times to the present; The Journal of Radical Urbanism (2008), an online journal of ideas and</text>
    <text>should have been curated to showcase every conceivable manifestation of the City’s cultural resources). Yet here we are, almost a quarter of a century later, and we still don’t know what the fuck that meant. I remember vividly the first time I went to the Biennale, we were told by the curator, Paolo Baratta, that the biennale had to be a ‘glimmer of light’ in the city, because otherwise, we were told, the Biennale would not be allowed to grow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow. Wow. Wow. Wow.Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow. Wow.Wow</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
