<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the installation a single video. The collection was used as a platform to explore, in-depth, the ideas and practices of postmodernism and its discontents. Szymczyk argues that the common denominator of the contemporary condition is a digitised and connected present; ‘information overload’ has become the new normal. (JL)Dazzle  	Dazzle is a term first used in 1984 by the poet Terry Smith to describe the visual excesses of the post-war counterculture. In that year, the term came to refer to ‘the excesses of visual culture’, a movement to overload visual media with visual images and to the ‘overload of ideas’ that results from that excess. In the words of the poet, ‘the excess of visual culture is thinking, feeling, breathing dazzle. It is an obsession with appearance, a form of self-indulgence and a form of self-congratulation</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the installation itself a multimedia installation and live-streaming conference.)  And now, a few years later, the Biennial itself. The exhibition has undergone three distinct curatorial approaches: that of the original exhibition, the development of a curatorial approach that has been characterised by in-depth, multi-disciplinary, up-to-date documentation, and the installation of artist-led projects that engage with the collection in various contexts and ways. The collection has been re-organized and restructured several times since its first appearance in 1990, yet despite this constant reorganisation, the underlying questions of ownership, identity, and place remain relevant. Here, the collection is described in terms of its geographical position (i.e. the location of its earliest documented instances of use, or at least as an approximation to the position of its use today).  The collection is divided into three main zones: cities, suburbs and rural areas. Suburbs comprise areas along the California coastal and inland coastal regions,</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the collection as a whole, in what Szymczyk describes as ‘an ephemeral point of departure and a place to sit and think and watch and be watched by many and, at the same time, to be watched by none’. He also describes the collection as a point of departure from a history of aesthetic practices that he traces to the nineteenth-century Romantic tradition. Romanticism, Szymczyk explains, is defined by its rejection of nature as aesthetic experience; art is therefore not an emotion or a concept but is defined by its syntax. Art’s ontological distinction is made explicit in the collection itself, which is mapped onto a single painting, a single painting, a single gesture, a single icon or motif. The collection thus becomes not only the image of art, but also one of artlessness. It contains both the collection of paintings and the collection of gestures – both historical and contemporary – that create the image. It is both a snapshot and a point</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the installation itself a standalone work. At the time, the Arts Council was keen to emphasise that the collections would be left to 'careers and communities’ and that artists would be commissioned to work with the collections in a range of ways. The collection, they said, was an asset that could be shared between the council and its members, and that the arts councils should be working with each other across forms of expression without having to necessarily know each other.  The council has certainly recognised this is the case, now that the museums have closed. When the Venice Biennale was initially mooted as a separate entity from the other cultural activities at the council, the council commissioned a new generation of curators to tackle the art-historical aspect of the new development. These were to be tasked with reviving the important role of the museum as a performing space for art, or creating a new one. While the council has clearly recognised the value of the collection, doing so in a way that</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the production incorporated over 1,000 rooftops and over 100 public areas. The collection was a major part of the exhibition, and Szymczyk has continued to collect material from the site. However, the collection is often misconstrued and its meaning misapplied. As the Biennial and its collection of artefacts continued to fail to materialise, the Museum of Modern Art sought to start a new phase in the collection, and started an independent commissioning arm, the   	Modern Art Commission, to carry out a new kind of archaeological survey of the area. The result was a disaster, with so much of what it described as the City of London landscape being made up of rubble and rubble. The commissioning ended up with a report that was even worse, in that much of what it said was actually just urban myth. After the excavation there was so little left to be salvaged, the museum made a big fuss about the fact that much of what it had collected was just rubble</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the installation itself a standalone work. In both forms, the goal of the work was to tell a story through images of the collection, while simultaneously placing the collection in contemporary context. The collection as a whole is a large and complex collection of paintings and objects, but it is divided into three main categories: objects in collections, those kept by museums, and those kept by individuals. Adam Szymczyk’s installation, however, placed the museum at the center, while the museum and its collections moved to the periphery. The collection as a whole is split up into several smaller spaces, and the museums that comprise it are no longer the dominant force in the city. Adam Szymczyk’s work, then, placed the museum in the middle, while the museum itself increasingly segregates itself into distinct spaces.  The collection as a whole is made up of objects from different times and places, and its collection managers allocate spaces to particular kinds of collectors (objects in this case, those</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the video essay was written as a trilogy of articles exploring the installation. Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture presents the collections in chronological order of priority, from cave paintings to Björk’s painting of a cave in the Dolomites. The exhibition is divided into three parts: Introduction, the Collections, and Art as Media. Part I introduces the collection as a collection of works from various points of view, highlighting key figures from the field, and the various discourses and approaches to the collection, at a time when concerns regarding security and the threat of terrorism were on the minds of many in the cultural sphere. Szymczyk’s collection, which is comprised of over 200,000 paintings, is a complex collection that is constantly (correctly) updated, annotated, and revised. It is a testament to the power and resourcefulness of the artist and the way he conducts his art practice. Part II presents the various sections of</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the paintings made up a narrative that ran alongside the video narration. Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art runs through to  [End Page 4] 5 January 2016. I will be uploading full-size images from the exhibition as soon as it is finished, so be sure to check back soon. [End Page 4] 	[1] Deena Chalabi, ‘On Immersive Public Art Projects’, in New Media Arts: The exhibition, ed. Roland Eisenberg, Bernard J. Foley and Nancy M. Paul (New York: Museum of Modern Art, 2015), p. 10. [End Page 5]Download this article as PDFNina EdgeContemporary Art and its Episodes of Art, Beauty and MadnessNina EdgeContemporary Art and its Episodes of Beauty and Madness 	Contemporary art, at its best, engages with the notion of beauty in a visionary way. It creates worlds, imaginary or physical, out of very real things. In</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the first and second parts were screened simultaneously at the Venice and San Francisco biennials. Szymczyk has said that the former exhibition ‘created a kind of static in the city that the video would degrade in quality and quantity’, but the message of the installation and its video still stands: the significance of art is still unclear, and no amount of video or text will ever convey the full significance of art.  The installation and its video still exist on the Venetian and San Francisco biennials websites, but are now embedded within an index card sized hardback book that is part of the collection, and part of the Metropolitan Museum of Art’s, permanent collection. The index card and the collection are now separated by a layer of text that explains the location of each painting and the date of its acquisition. Art and the post-modern condition are made visible through these indices, which are often cryptic and deceptive. In  	Modern Art’s case,</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by David Hockney, is a case in point. The project was hugely expensive, with the Arts Council having to step in with huge funding after the Biennial failed to materialise. The failure of the Biennial coincided with the closure of the Museum of Modern Art, so the Arts Council was forced to find another home for its collection. The Museum of Modern Art closed after only three years, and with it, abruptly, – so the story goes. – with its collection of art being either destroyed on a massive scale or moved to new locations. The question that remains, however, is when, not where. What happens when the collection finally ends?  In 2015, artist Adam Szymczyk used the collection of more than 200,000 paintings as a platform for his installation  	Adam Szymczyk: Modern Art – A Visual Post-Technological Culture, or in English, Why Art Matters. The exhibition was a combined film and video installation, and the installation itself a standalone work. It received critical acclaim, but little else. Now, a year after its installation, the collection is back in the museum, although this time under the title Modern Art in Doha.  	The collection is important to the Doha Biennial because it allows the Biennial to reveal new circumstances and different kinds of art from different periods. In other words, it tells the story of contemporary art in a different way from the way the Doha Biennial might tell the story of art from the same city in the same city some years later. For example, the collection might reveal more about the contemporary art of Doha in the year 2000 than in the year 2040, when the Biennial is proposed to be built. 	However, the collection also needs to be accessible: accessible to researchers, art collectors and students, and accessible to professionals charged with preserving the art within. This last requirement, in my view, is the real Achilles' Heel of</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a tendency for the Biennale to become something like a museum, with curatorial approaches that were very much like those of a museum. The main difference was that the Biennale was building itself, rather than curating other works, and so its curatorial work was questioning the historical relationship between art and society. The Biennale itself was building towards a more definitive form, and so its curatorial work followed a similar line of questioning to that of the museum. The key difference was that the Biennale was building towards a more definitive form, and so its curatorial work followed a specific form of historical-cultural writing. The Biennale of Sydney was building towards a more complete social mission statement. The museum was building towards a more specific kind of social mission statement. So the Biennale of Sydney had three parts: the social mission statement, the museum mission statement, and the art mission statement. The social mission statement focused on how to make the Biennale a socially</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was an assumption that the cultural critic who judged the art was also a cultural critic, since there was a professional relationship between the artist and the biennale. There was a tendency for some of the artists to be from outside the city, since there was no community feel to the Biennale. On the contrary, the Biennale was often shown engaging with what it called ‘histories and traditions of the city’, since these ‘gave the occasion, during its history, ‘a framework in which to work, to be reminded of times past, and to talk about things that happen in the present’.  In the 1990s, the Biennale rebranded itself as the ‘Open School’, an acknowledgement of the fact that it is a ‘school’ within the biennial itself. At this time, the Open School was organising a series of events around the biennial itself, with the cultural critic Cynthia Rowlands as its artistic</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the Biennale to be selective about who it featured, since there was a strong association between the colour of the artist and the kind of cultural activity that was being produced in the city. At the beginning of the Biennale's history, in fact, it tended to do the opposite: it featured artists from a city who were artists of colour, since there was a strong racialised bias in the way in which the Biennale was produced.In the 1980s, the Biennale became increasingly apolitical, and in recent years it has played a more active role in the biennials that it funds. In recent years, the Biennale has begun to fund cultural activities in the city, and it is now beginning to fund culturally relevant projects in the boroughs. I think that the Biennale’s largesse is now being used for cultural activities that are not being produced in the city. I would argue that the Biennale is becoming</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the Biennale to be selective about who it showcased, since there was a strong connection between the transnational and the local. In the 1990s, the Biennale displayed work by many artists who were not from the UK, including Mark Leckey, Paul McCarthy, Rainer Maria Röntgen, Paul McCarthy, David Hockney, Lisa Eaton and Peter McCaughey. It also displayed work by artists from many other parts of the world, including performers in many cultures from across the globe, such as Thuli Madonsela, the late Suzi Gabl, the recently released Chinese artist Thangam Bazar, and the recently released Filipino artists Rafael Cardoso and Janet Lim-Napoles. In these many other cases, the accounts of the artists are fragmentary, but in the presence of the Biennale staff, the artists were able to constructively exchange texts with each other. The Biennale staff were formed from the staff</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for artists to be artists from other places, since there was a universal tendency for people to find something to like in art from any place. But the trend towards the artist with a national origin or a place of exile seems to be ongoing. Does the tendency towards the artist with a national origin or a place of exile reflect a desire for art to be taken outside of its local context? It is possible that the biennale is becoming more of a residence than an exhibitionary form. The Biennale house was not built for exhibition, but for a series of recurring and ephemeral performances that are now often curated by artists from places other than Italy. For example, the Biennale house was not designed for a Venice Architecture Biennale, but for the construction of a new Osteria di Venezia, which is being built by the Biennale. The Biennale, today, is planning to build a new world-class biennale venue in</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the Biennale to be a re-occurring, ‘white guy’ show, since there was a strong connection between the two.  Even when the Biennale started off as an ‘independently elected body’, as it claims to be, its members are overwhelmingly white.  Art by the Artsy Community, 2013  Art by the Artsy Community, 2013  	When the Biennale Council was set up in 1983, there was a clear intention to create a biennial that would be reflective of the city, but would also foster a dialogue between the city and the biennale. As we shall see, this entailed creating a dialog between the city and the biennale, and the different curators, including myself, who were invited to set up variously titled 'curatorial councils', 'intelligent cities', and 'community gardens' around the Biennale. These were to offer a space for</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the Biennale to become something that is very white, very western, and white male-dominated. Art is much more easily understood as a social act than as a collection of images, which explains why the images that are most readily accessible on a biennial are those images of art being done in the context of white people. And so the Biennale has a particularised, transnational flavour to it, in that it is performed by white artists and their organisations. The Venice Biennale is an institution that is much more universalised than art museums, and so much more easily comprehended. It is performed by an affluent clientele that is much more readily assimilated into the wider cultural landscape. It is performed by an audience that is much more easily drawn to a certain type of artist, and so on. That is, the Biennale is a cultural institution that is much more readily understood as something that it does with white people. Biennials perform a</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a tendency for the Biennale to become something like a museum, in that it was becoming increasingly difficult to separate art from its social context, since the Biennalee was inevitably influenced by the daily news cycle. So the Biennale became a museum in its own right, exhibiting the politics of art and culture at work in the city. It was a strange but partly successful hybrid. The Biennale became a museum in its own right, presenting the politics of art and the urbanisation of postindustrial areas, and it also happened to be a biennale that happened to be very active in its own right. It would be naive to suggest that the Biennale was immune to its own form of political and social change, but it is also entirely possible that the Biennale in its current form is more representative of the city in which it happens, with a specific and rapidly increasing population, than any historically pure form of urbanisation could possibly be. The Biennale is</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was also a tendency for the Biennale to be selective in whom it showcased, since artists were generally more visible in the early days of the Biennale, but since then the Biennale has generally displayed its artists among the most prominent artists of the world. 	The Biennale of Sydney became the first to offer its artists a platform on which to develop their exhibitionary project in the open, making it possible for them to display their work anywhere – including in venues with restricted public access – and opening it for any artist to propose an exhibition. At the time, this was an innovative approach to a traditionally ‘black box’ situation, but it brought the Biennale out of its traditional conception of itself as an institution of culture and society and placed the exhibitionary initiative in the hands of its artists. 	A key innovation of the Biennale of Sydney was how it promoted its curatorial agenda through a multi-tiered promotion system that incorporated a curator-led</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the city (including this one), but also on the working-class and racialised biennial that is the contemporary experience in London. In 1984, the Biennale of Sydney was founded in part to address the historical under-representation of black and ethnic minority artists and the ways in which black and ethnic minority artists’ bodies are dissected and politicized. In the years that followed, there was a revolution in the artworld when it was revealed that the organizers of the Venice Biennale were black. By the 1990s, there were signs that the Biennale was becoming increasingly isolated from its origin in the 1980s, while the art fair format was being questioned. Then, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists who performed in the Venice Biennale to be artists of colour, since there was a strong connection between the two. Later, in the early days of the Biennale, there was a general tendency for the artists to be artists with a social agenda, since the Biennale was seen as an ideal venue for a social action, and art as a social practice was a natural next step. 	But in the intervening years, the Biennale has tended to fragment into many different forms, depending on the biennale promoter’s political orientation. I suggest that the biennale, in its present format, can be reorganized around a number of basic principles, some of which can be adapted to the needs of the city. These principles, listed in order of appearance on the first page of the first edition of the Biennale book (published in 2004), were: (1) The Biennale is a public institution with a particularised, public mission; (2) The Biennale is an inherently political event: it is part of a public process that is driven by, and is necessarily related to, the current political situation; (3)</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter
    <text>will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter Carr or Meehan Crist. The diversity of the curatorial pool will allow for the installation of various types of art, whilst also enabling the exercise of different skill-sets within an artist's studio. The selection of artists will be guided by Wendy Harpe, a former Curator for Life at Liverpool School of Art and a specialist in art and community development at Manchester University. She will lead a team of artists, writers and artists, including Jane Hill, Roselyn Groves, Mary Turner, Renee Hall and Jane Sutton, as well as Wendy Harpe herself, as they embark on a multi-disciplinary project that will see them commissioning artists and organisations to join them in creating a unique environmental assessment of the area. The project is expected to be completed by the end of 2018. 	The conversation 	Around housing in Liverpool, which we received to</text>
    <text>will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter Schjeldahl or Paul McCarthy. The artists selected will have the confidence, skills and networks to execute this ambitious project with the resources and connections to execute it successfully elsewhere.Biennials and their archives continue to provide crucial perspectives on the past, present and future of art and curating. It is important to document these experiences, for they allow us to understand how art is produced and reproduced in a contemporary context, and how this affects the practices and bodies of art today. The biennial format provides a means to simultaneously document and archive these dynamics, while also allowing for the possibility of future intervention. It is a record of what has happened in and around the art museum, and how art is made and acquired in that museum. This record will need to incorporate information from all aspects of the biennial – its curatorial, artistic, technical and financial decisions, as well as the lives and works of the artists who exhibit in the museum. It will need to capture the diversity of the art</text>
    <text>will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter Schjeldahl, Wendy Harpe or Suzi Gablik. The curators selected will have a curatorial set of skills and know-how to deliver socially responsible work that is relevant and engages with the current political context in which the Liverpool Biennial finds itself. Some will be artists themselves and have experience within art curating. Others will have expertise in other areas and have connections to other arts institutions or sectoral leaders. Still others will have no formal curatorial or arts experience and are already arts educators or have other forms of education.  One can argue that the fact that the project is a curatorial one is a reflection of the status of art and the social context of the era, and so the institutional memory may also be relevant. A second possibility is that the institution is responding to a changing artist-led culture that is more interested in the accumulation of cultural capital than in the creation of knowledge, and so the memory of an era is a resource that is being</text>
    <text>will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter Carr or Wendy Harpe. The key is that the curators selected have the expertise and networks to support artist-driven projects of social change. Liverpool Biennial will offer many opportunities to engage with the topic from its own position of artistic autonomy to the potential of artist-curated projects from the perspective of a wider art institution. The curatorial craft, the craft of individual curators, and the craft of collaborative art projects will be reinforced through the activities of the Liverpool Biennial. The curatorial agenda will evolve as the project evolves, responding to the needs of the people involved in the project at every step. It will remain static, with curators increasingly joining artists as partners in engaging the local public. It will become ever more critical that the needs of the urban poor are taken into account when considering regeneration schemes and the needs of the urban agglomeration.  The biennial will offer many opportunities to engage with the topic from its own position of artistic autonomy to the potential</text>
    <text>will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter Carr or Wendy Harpe. The key is that they understand that art is a publicly funded program with a curatorial mission, and that the mission is to support the program as a whole. As such, the selection of curators will be able to deliver resources and capacity in a manner responsive to the needs of the program, while ensuring that the art is delivered with care and respect for the people involved.  The invitation to explore the idea of Community Arts Internships in the context of Liverpool Biennial and The Resident presents an opportunity to develop a new kind of artist-in-residence at the Biennial. The opportunity may involve volunteering or working independently, and the biennial may offer a financial reward for the best ideas.  The conversation  For this survey, I wanted to know about the specific challenges and opportunities of artist-in-residence in the Biennial, and how that might map onto a local problem-solving model. How might biennials contribute to</text>
    <text>will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter McCaughey. These individuals will know and trust the art system, and can bring expertise and networks to create strategies that are more responsive to the needs of communities.  The project will be a test of these new art facilitators and artists, with a public art project often reliant on trust and artist-led processes. I am looking forward to seeing what these artists can deliver. Liverpool Biennial, 2017. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial.  To receive weekly art news and more straight to your inbox, subscribe to the ART &amp; ART NEWS RSS Feed.  To stay up to date with art &amp; art news, follow Facebook. And Twitter. All art &amp; art news sent direct to your phone.And Reddit. Here is how you can join the artistic team:Step 1. Take part in a workshop, research project or class with Art &amp; Art News staff.Step 2. Focus on one medium (</text>
    <text>will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter Carr or Peter Mandelson. The project will be an art project in the tradition of Projections, Laurentian Style, and the Biennale tradition, but it will be art projects commissioned by and for the community. This will be a project in the tradition of Art and Community Partnerships, but it will also be art projects undertaken by and for the local community. The project will be art as a social process, but it will also be socially responsible and well-designed. Indeed, this is the approach that the Biennale has taken in order to support its development as an art project, because it is the social responsibility that it is. It is a unique way to embed creativity and open access to art in a curatorial enterprise, and it has the added advantage of embedding the art in a community in ways that are deeper than the art itself. It is an art project, but it is also a curatorial project. In this sense, the</text>
    <text>will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter Carr or Mary Turner, or having worked with artists such as Peter Hurley or Claire Bishop. The curators chosen will be artists with a social conscience, willing to adopt new artists and art practices, and able to tap into the artspot of the city. They will have the trust of the people with whom they work, and with that of the local community.  The aim of the project is to establish a dialogue about art and the social, including between artists and the communities they work with. The project may come across as elitist, but it is vital that artists have choices and are not forced to conform to a prescribed path or identity. The decisions they make must be socially responsible and equitable. How they engage with communities and create art is a choice, and the choices they make must impact the environment in a meaningful way. This project comes from the Biennial executive committee, selected from a shortlist of talented artists and curators. The project comes</text>
    <text>will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter Brook, Mary Turner, Eleanor Hartney or Terry Gilliam.These are just some of many examples of artists being encouraged to apply for the project through the Liverpool Biennial in 2014. There are many more who have expressed an interest in participating, but have not yet been asked.  One can only imagine the possibilities for this exciting new art project if the right people started coming through the door.  The tragedy of the commons is that in the age of the biennial, in the age of the social, in the age of the  	geographic, the tragedy of the commons is that in our current condition – trapped in ever greater geographical and institutional complexity – artists are forced to make projects with ever greater publics. Such is the paradox of the contemporary artist: trapped in a public that is ever more complex, ever more dispersed and ever more dispersed in time, yet is also challenged to speak the language of the public in ever greater detail.  The</text>
    <text>will be curated by Antoinette Block and directed by Paul McCarthy. The project will also include a reception for two selected curators, with a message to the public: Liverpool Biennial is a public art institution, and the curators selected will share with the public the passion and skill that they had to acquire a project through curatorial craft. They will demonstrate a mastery over the art process that was more artist-led and artist-led in nature. The curators selected will share their vision and skill with the public, providing context and enabling the exercise of creativity within the institution. The initiative will be an art project, but it is also a public art project that requires that artists develop collaborative processes with the curators to deliver socially responsible art. The curators selected will have expertise and networks to support this project, including having worked before with artists such as  Bert Béland, Ingrid Michaelson or Simone Sacco, or having worked with prominent artists such as Peter Schjeldahl, Wendy Harpe or Anna Best. The artists selected will have a clear role to play in the project, but will have to demonstrate a willingness to expand the project beyond the confines of their preferred field of expertise.[1]  References [1] Tables, W.D. Deaton and D.L. Herman, ‘A model for cultural regeneration in the context of a city’, in  	Cities and Social Change, ed. William E. Lange, Harcourt Brace and New York University Press, New York, 1968, p. 119–37. [2] The table was developed through a year-long research project at The Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, Maryland. The original ideas emerged during a conference of the Society for American Archaeology in New York in 1971, with contributions from a group of Johns Hopkins faculty, including</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the
    <text>Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the biennale is that it can be transnational in its approach to curating and art. This means that it can be seen as a biennale that happens to be happening in the city in different ways, and in that sense we can say that the local curators are interacting with the rest of the museum sector via different registers.  One of the great things about the biennale is that it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city. That’s perhaps what the city was able to do through its economic engines: the biennale’s success as an event was due to the fact that it coincided with the city’s real-life economic development, which we can see in the increase in tourists and the reduction in workers. The biennale also happened to coincide with an election campaign, which heightened the city’s status as a tourist destination.</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the biennale is the opportunity to be transnational in its scope of activity. This allows the individual biennale to be multivalent, including both the past and the present, while recognising the essential link between the two.  Another way in which the biennale can be multivalent is through the use of its funds. Biennale funds are typically used for specific activities, such as the art display, but can also support research and arts-related activities. For example, the Biennale’s revenue model relies on the sale of a fee for access to the Biennale, and its use of the biennale as a cultural institution: research projects are incorporated within the architecture of the Biennale, and the biennale itself as a product line within the firm.  A third way in which the biennale can support its own activities is by encouraging participation from local producers and artists through the provision of culturally responsive production.  This is exemplified by</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the biennale is that it is able to do both. It gathers historical materials and forms them into a form that is both accessible and radical in its own right.  Another way in which the biennale can break the surface of things is through its frequent (but temporary) re-enactment of historical events. This is a historical technique that can break open old understandings of things, and can even produce innovative re-construction of the past through historical research and archiving. For an example of this, take a look at ‘The Anfield Home Tour’, an event that Liverpool Biennial began staging in 1989.1  The idea of the tour came from a book called The Anfield Home Tour: A Visual History of the City (1984), by John Urry and Peter McCaughey.2  This book assessed the significance of the book in the city, in terms of the places where the book was written and in relation to the</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the biennale is the opportunity to work outside the museum, to engage with cultures other than the mainstream.  Another great thing about the biennale is the sharing of resources. The biennale usually produces important contributions to the local economy through the sharing of resources.  One of the great treasures of the biennale is its ability to happen at a time; it’s possible that a couple of years from now, a local community will be hosting a biennale. And, of course, there’s always the chance that a biennale could one day return to the city.  The challenges of the biennale, then, are two-fold. First, how do we create experiences that are richer and more profound in their own right, so that when we do eventually return to the city, we will probably not be able to compare the past with the present, but we can certainly compare with what has happened in other places. Second, how do we</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the biennale is the opportunity to work across historical, cultural and urban divides. This is a huge opportunity for an artist to exploit a historical curatorial intervention or historical conceit.  One of the great ironies of the biennale is that it has been an important part of the art world's promotion as a consequence of the early twentieth century, yet the very act of staging a major art exhibition in such a setting is often seen by curators as a prelude to an artist’s subsequent career.   A good example of this is the Biennale of Sydney, which began in 1903 and ran for eleven years, through to the biennial of New York in 2006, and now operates as a museum of modern art.  One could argue that it’s the twentieth century, but the biennale is a museum of contemporary art and the twentieth-century art museum is a museum of twentieth-century art.  And here we arrive at the second great irony</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the biennale is that it can happen at any time; in fact, because it so frequently engages with and depends on the present, it is able to do so in different and unpredictable ways.  One of the great challenges of the biennale is how to live in harmony with the rhythms of the city. This is a difficult balance to strike, and it is easy to lose perspective on the larger picture. Sometimes the biennale’s main aim is to celebrate what it means to be an artist in the city, while at other times its main endeavour is to document the city’s urban past through archival research and documentation, while at other times it is about contemporaneous social and political change in the city.  A biennale that is itself a historical and cultural reflection of the city must therefore act in harmony with both the contemporary and the historic.  The biennale also has a responsibility to offer a way for artists and artists to participate in creating the city</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the biennale to date, and one that we look forward to continuing to do, is the development of long-term, permanent curatorial commitments. This will be one of the main themes of the biennale, and one that we can look to in the future for lessons on how to expand this process into new forms.  Another way in which the biennale can be seen to render the city into a massive historical archive is by providing an alternative venue for the exchange of cultural commodities. This is seen in the project of Bernard Saltzman, who, in the 1980s, created the Biennale of London, which was characterised by an exchange between commodities and conventions.[10]  A third and final way in which the biennale reproduces the social totality is through the concept of its registrant cities.[11]  In the 1980s and 1990s, the biennale was a massive commercial enterprise, running into the hundreds of millions of pounds, and it is</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the biennale is that it allows us to see the city from multiple perspectives. We get to know the artists as they arrive, go back to the city and create mini-exhibitions around specific artists’ works.  Another great feature of the biennale is that it allows the public to participate in the construction of the city. By staging mini exhibitions around specific works, the biennale can generate knowledge about the city and its inhabitants. For instance, a mini exhibition around Michel de Certeau’s Ceramics of Paris may present the artist’s idea of ‘liveness’ in relation to the electric car, while a smaller exhibition around a specific architect’s office may present the ideas of ‘office space and productivity’ in a particular city. The idea of the ‘biennale’ is to allow for multiple modes of understanding, and this can be seen as a very important negotiating tactic. The reputation of the bi</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the biennale is the flexibility to be able to switch from the past to the present, but also from the present to the future. This allows us to think about the urban through the lens of the future, or bring forth alternative futures through various cultural practices.  Another way in which the biennale can be organised is as a ‘curatorial lottery’, in which works in-depth with the biennial as a whole. This last aspect, cultural hygiene, has become a great concern of the local urban planners, who are increasingly concerned about the spread of communicable diseases and the proliferation of urban voids.  A curatorial lottery would place great demands on the biennale’s time and resources, since it is our main form of cultural exchange. The biennale would then become something that is far more easily accessible and manipulable, and its practitioners would see a way to further develop and expand the biennale’s potential.  A cultural</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, the artists’ work often operates with the user in mind. The task is to deliver a message across an area of the city that is as good as possible in terms of both quantity and quality, but with no strings attached. In other words, it’s not just about the art; it’s also about the social implications of what this work might mean politically for the city.  One of the ways in which the biennale has attempted to address this is through the concept of temporary exhibition sites. These are places where exhibitions occur for a brief period of time, usually a few weeks, but can be sites of permanent exhibitions as well.  One of the great strengths of the biennale is that it exploits the historical, cultural and urban flows of the city in different ways. This is achieved by engaging with the past through historical research and archiving, while incorporating aspects of the present through different forms of cultural re-construction. One of the great gifts of the biennale is the flexibility it provides for the city to respond to different conditions, both physically and mentally.  Another great flexibility is the way in which it engages with different cultures through different modes of interaction. This engagement does not necessarily result in a cultural exchange, but it may employ cultural tools and act as an intermediary between various cultural practices.  A final aspect of the biennale that is often under-studied is the role played by artists, curators and artists’ unions in the production of art across multiple sites. Art is made possible through the interaction of many different kinds of people; the biennale as a whole, but especially its ‘golden days’, when people coming from all over the world met to come and spend a few days in Naples, and its ‘second golden days’, when people coming from other parts of the world met to spend a few more days in Venice.  Art’s social function in the contemporary world</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stad
    <text>will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

Cultural Exchange: A Journal of Cultural Economics

3 November 2017

Cultural Exchanges: A Journal of Cultural Economics is the discursive and transnational journal of the European Arts Council. Its aim is to document and analyse the cultural and artistic exchanges taking place in Europe at the moment of Brexit. As a result, it provides a platform for artists and arts organisations to share experiences and gain expertise, while also investigating the politics</text>
    <text>will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KIC Cincę Stadion, KIC Cincę Stadion, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KIC Cincę Stadion, KIC Cincę Stadion, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KIC Cincę Stadion, KIC Cinc�</text>
    <text>will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazim</text>
    <text>will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive</text>
    <text>will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KIC Cincę Stadion, Kazimierz, Poland

KP archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KIC Cincę Stadion, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KIC Cincę Stadion, Kazimierz, Poland

KP archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KIC Cincę Stadion, Kazimierz, Poland

KP archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP archive</text>
    <text>will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz</text>
    <text>will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive</text>
    <text>will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KF, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KF, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KF, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KF, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KF, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KK, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KK, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KK, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KK, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw,</text>
    <text>will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazim</text>
    <text>will be curated by Anna Best and will include works from a range of disciplines. The exhibitions will be delivered by Anna Best, Nasser Rabbati, Asma Khalidi, Rosie Cooper, Zoya Jha, Hanan Ashrawi and many more, and they will be held at the following locations:

Gallery Stages 2017

14 May –22 May 2017

Klimów Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

Kociversity KK, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KK Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KIC Cincę Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Archive, Warsaw, Poland

KP Stadion, KFC Kazimierz, Kazimierz, Poland

KP St</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson
    <text>archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson’s current projects and research interests include the Urban Frontier Library, which is the infrastructure of the post-industrial city; Envisioning a Future City, a research project at McGill University's Montréal Centre for Working Life; and the World Community of Religions, the gathering of disparate traditions from around the world. He is the host of the weekly TV show Stages, and was a co-winner of the 2014 Polaris Prize for Community Theatre. He is also co-editor (with Ray Wynn) of the forthcoming book Local Futures: Participatory Arts and the Politics of Performing Arts from Albania to Bangladesh. To learn more about the Urban Frontier Library and see images of some of his projects, visit www.ahrc.org.uk.To learn more about the Centre for Working Life, visit www.workinglife.ca. To learn more about the World Community of Religions, visit www.worldcommunityreligion.org.au/en/</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson has a particular interest in the history and contemporary of community based practices in the social sciences, particularly in the areas of art, architecture and design. He has a particular interest in the ways that art and art history are interrelated and how cultural production can be contextualised within the development and history of infrastructure. He is also an artist and has a background in media design and is the recipient of several awards and recognitions for his work. He has been curator of the Mersey Ferry International Art Register and has been a lecturer at the Mersey Ferry, Aarhus University, and the Royal College of Art. He was a consultant for the renovation of the former East India Company buildings in Liverpool, and he was part of the curatorial team for the Mersey Ferry artist Peter Carruthers’s multi-disciplinary exhibition The Contemporary Condition: Art, Architecture, Politics to be published by Liverpool Biennial. He is the editor of the online peer-reviewed journal Plenitude (http://pl</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson has a particular interest in the history and culture of the Caribbean and the Caribbean languages. He has spoken of the need to reclaim languages spoken in the Caribbean, especially those that are now endangered, and has suggested ways to do so through the use of new media. He is the recipient of several awards and has been featured in numerous books, including: ‘Outlawed Social Life: Race, Politics, and the Law in Contemporary Latin America’; ‘Rethinking Imperial Histories: Race, Law and the Aftermath of British Rule in the Caribbean’; and ‘Unravelling the Leviathan: Race, Capital, and the Politics of Empire’. He has written several articles for the Atlantic and the New Republic, among other publications. He is the host of the weekly multimedia show ‘What are Writers Doing Now?’ on the Tor.com network and the executive editor of the popular web site Spaced.Jeff Roberson is the author of The Social</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson’s work has been exhibited at the Black-E, Venice, Japan, and the Venice Biennale, Italy; the Whitney Museum of American Art, New York, USA; the New Museum, New York, USA; and the Berkley Museum of Art, USA; as well as the Carnegie Museum of Art, Pittsburgh, USA; and the Howard M. Sternberg and Joel S. Lapidus Gallery at Columbia University, Israel, where his work has been shown or developed into exhibition formats.[72] Two years before his death, in 2006, a group of artists formed the Gordon and Betty White Foundation, Inc. The name derives from the White family’s early years in New York’s Chinatown, and the White Foundation is a charity established in Gordon White’s name. In 1921, Gordon White established White’s Paintings Workshop, an art studio and gallery that produced one of a number of paintings for the growing Chinatown community. In</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson has a particular interest in the role that art can play in creating a cooperative environment and in imagining alternatives to bureaucratic apparatuses and the market system. He has worked with leaders from the local community to developing nations such as Bangladesh, Kenya and South Africa in an attempt to create a model for the cooperative and artist-centered arts education offered at a community college or secondary school level in those nations. He has also co-authored the book A People’s State: Art, Statelessness and Democratic Autonomy with Angela McKay, State, Distributed Art (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015).Where is the Art? Understanding Time by Meehan CristMeehan Crist is an artist, writer and educator. Her artistic work deals with the temporal complexities of the contemporary condition, from the notion of ‘time’ to the concept of ‘space’. Her work has been featured in numerous books, including New York Times best sellers Such Time is Now! (</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson has a particular interest in the history and legacy of community organizing and he participates in a broader community of scholars, artists, writers and artists who collectively engage with the social, economic and political contexts of contemporary community life. He is currently finishing a two-year stint at Berkley College of Arts where he will be completing his MFA thesis, in which he will look at the UC as a post-collegiate institution that engages with its past, present and future through critical pedagogical practices. He is the recipient of several awards and has been selected for various honors and recognitions, including:Awards from the American Community Arts Association, Berkley College of Arts, 2009; American Community Arts International, Berkley, 2011; and the Leonard and Shirley Simon Family Foundation, Berkley, 2012. He is also a past president of the American Federation of Arts, and the Society of Illustrators. He has taught at Berkley College of Arts and the Howard C. Bellamy</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson is a specialist in the arts and humanities with expertise in the social impact of cultural practice. He is a founding partner of the New Art Foundation, where his work includes the writing of collective rights and the implementation of a Community Arts practice; the development of municipal artists’ practice and the storage and management of cultural resources; and the development of collaborative resources opportunities for the arts and culture worker. He has worked with the New York Public Library, the Museum of Modern Art, Columbia University, and the Museum of Modern Art-Modern Art Connection, where he developed a long-term relationship with the latter. He has written for The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, The Nation, Spin, The New Inquiry, The Village Voice, The Village Voice Digital Journal and The Village Voice Archives. He has lectured on the arts and culture for institutions including The New York Public Library, The New York Public Library Digital Journal, The New York Public Library Digital Archives, The New York Public Library</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson is a specialist in arts and social practice in the Seattle/Tacoma metropolitan area, and has a long-standing relationship with the Museum of Art. He has also worked with the Museum of History &amp; Anthropology, where he developed a multi-disciplinary approach to art, history and culture through art, education and research that examines the ways in which art can be contextualised within contemporary society. He is a member of the Advisory Board of the Museum of Art’s Social Practice Research Network and has served on the advisory boards of the Museum of Art’s School of Architecture &amp; Urban Design. He is the recipient of several awards and has lectured on a variety of topics, including the arts and social practice sector in the US and Europe. He has written for the New York Times, The New Republic, The New Criterion, Spin, Frieze, Spacing, and many other publications. He is the recipient of the 2015 MEER human rights prize and was shortlisted for the 2016</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson has a particular interest in the construction of infrastructure and urban changes that can be mapped directly to climate change. In particular, he sees an opportunity to transform the Bay Lights District – which includes the former home of the Golden Gate Bridge – into a novel-length urban epicentre that incorporates information technology, mapping, and geo-thermal data – as a way to interrogate the logic of the global‐warming paradigm and the ways in which it is being created today. He is currently researching the 1944 Paris Climate Conference and its aftermath, as well as the 1972 San Francisco Pan Expo, which resulted in the antialiasing of a large part of the city. He is currently a consultant for the film The Reclaimers, which is set to be released in 2017.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, or its use as a container for such material); ‘the gatekeeping of biennials in society’; and, finally, ‘the idea that a biennial’s curatorial mission is one of containment, domination and subjugation – not of the governing, in general, but of the permissive.’[71] For more, see Bernard J. Foley and Michael J. Doran, eds., The New Curator: The Rise and Fall of AHRC (New York: New Vessel Press, 2015), p. 33.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the community. Roberson is also the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015).Roberson has written extensively on a range of social, economic and spatial issues on topics of race, identity, cities, gentrification and postindustrial society. His most recent work was published in the New York Times Magazine as part of the 'Books That Matter' series. He has a Bachelor of Social Science from the University of Missouri, and an MA in English Culture and Society from Columbia University.  [1] Bakargiev, Alexander. My Struggle, translated by Peter Herman and Armen Weizman, New York: Zone Books, 1992. p. 8.Download this article as PDFJeff RobersonJeff Roberson is the President and Co-founder of AHRC, Inc., a non-profit corporation established in 1999 that brings together the work of art, artists, researchers and communities to address critical issues and works in the local community. He is the author of the forthcoming novel The Administrators, to be published by Palgrave Macmillan (2015) and the forthcoming memoir The Muse</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the twenty-first century, cultural institutions funded by governments, territories and nongovernmental organisations are increasingly constructed with citizens and stakeholders in mind, drawn from a range of socio-politically diverse and economically powerful groups. These stakeholders include citizens (nationally and regionally diverse, including migrants and refugees), civil society organisations (including nongovernmental organisations), academics, stakeholders in tourism (eg companies), stakeholders in infrastructure (eg governments), stakeholders in knowledge (eg stakeholders in media), stakeholders in the arts (eg cultural institutions), stakeholders in science and technology (eg governments), stakeholders in immersing cultural practices (eg consultants), stakeholders in law and regulation (eg stakeholders in capital markets), and finally stakeholders in stakeholders (eg stakeholders in archives, museums, legal aid organisations, trade unions). It is important to note that not all stakeholders are stakeholders in the same way, and that art, and particularly contemporary art, is a social enterprise. That is, it requires stakeholders to contribute to its functioning, and</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the twentieth century, cultural capital primarily benefitted from the invention of mass media, which made it possible to consume art at scale. But media also plays a critical role in the social dynamics of our culture today. It influences what kinds of art can be produced, who can express artistic potentialities, and how – all functions through the social. Media production, whether industrial or service-based, plays an essential role in the social life of communities of people and goods – and this includes the work of art. The history of cultural organising goes back to the Renaissance, but the impact of the digital revolution is greater and longer-lasting. The twentieth century marks the centenary of the birth of the Renaissance, the year in which Michel Foucalt made what became known as the 'archetypal critique'. Foucalt was one of the founders of the Third Party, a political party formed in France in 1903 that espoused a programme of participation in the electoral process. The party fielded candidates in over 1</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the twenty-first century, cultural institutions and their representations in media continue to proliferate, but this does not necessarily imply a return to the past; new media can assert a powerful influence even when it comes to representing the past as  	present. Media technology continues to reshape symbolic acts and public spaces, but it is also increasingly evident that many forms of symbolic activity, including that of art, are equally at risk of losing their power. 	Art is no longer the sole determinant of what is understood and valued in the world; the cultural capital of the twenty-first century is built on the back of shared values and practices. That is, the values and practices that shape cultural production and consumption shape how we perceive the world, and how we act in cultural spaces and practices. This is no small thing to change, nor is it a thing that can be easily fixed. But the cultural capital of the twenty-first century is being created not on the back of a set of past</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the twenty-first century, cultural institutions funded by the state are more readily accessible to consumers around the globe. But this shift also implies an influx of resources – ideas, practices, languages, collections, materials – that shape how we understand and communicate about the world. How do we reconceive cultural production and our consumption of it? In an effort to find out, the Biennale commissioned a multi-disciplinary art team led by Carolyn Christov-Bakargiev, Chair of the Department of Art, Culture and Communication at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and part of the department of Visual Cultures &amp; Cultures of the Future, a.k.a. the 'New Media' project. The team consisted of artists, curators, journalists, cultural activists and scholars, as well as academics and critics. The project was developed and delivered through the multi-disciplinary curatorial and architecture practices of Bir Zeit University, which runs concurrently with the Museum of Modern Art’s exhibition, 'Points</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the twenty-first century, cultural institutions are globalised through the adoption of locally-sourced materials and practices. But even when these practices directly employ workers and artists from different places, they often employ artists from different places in the world, and some with expertise from places other than their own. For example, some curators engage with the challenge of locating cultural resources in urban environments where access to education and health care is limited, such as in impoverished or migrant neighbourhoods. But even when these resources are located in culturally diverse urban neighbourhoods, the challenge is not so different from locating them anywhere else in the world. What is different is the globalisation of the means of production and consumption. The means of production and consumption today live apart, are mobile, and are affected by a variety of forces including production by the individual and the built environment. So how do artists navigate this shifting landscape? In a number of recent exhibitions and books, including those by the likes of Patty Smith, Maria Hlavajova,</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the twentieth century, cultural production increasingly took the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (NGOs). These emerged as a response to the dominance of economic, legal and ideological forms of cultural organisation, particularly in the hands of national artists' social movements. But their institutional forms are also characterised by the global interconnection of business and finance capital. As a result, the social functions of the arts in capitalist society are increasingly mediated through the grafted assets of these three pillars. So the question is: what becomes of this capital when their social uses have lapsed? The NGP, in turn, appears to seek out opportunities to expand its portfolio of assets in the interests of corporate profit. So what are the social uses of cultural production? Rich in resources, these social uses appear to trump any intrinsic value of the resources. In the twentieth century, cultural production arguably became ever more problematic in the light of the ecological crisis, but the social uses of cultural production seem to have become ever more apparent</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the twenty-first century, the foundation of such organisations is increasingly dependent on the location and the funding of such exchanges; indeed, the financial viability of an organisation is increasingly dependent on the geopolitical situation in order to continue to propogate its agenda. And of course, the advent of digital media and social media has radically changed the conditions on which these collaborative forms can operate, enabling artists and their collaborators to work across national boundaries, national borders and cultural divides.Global art exchanges, then, exist in the context of multiple media, but they also exist in the context of the web. The web is a series of interconnected sites that together form a larger whole. It is a globalised version of the metaphor of a city growing larger and more complex, where the city is seen as an ever-expanding landscape that can be mapped, calculated and controlled. And yet it is also a symbol of inaccessibility. The search for meaning on the web is fundamentally a symbol of inaccessibility. Inaccess</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the twenty-first century, cultural capital is increasingly generated and directed by nongovernmental entities (eg nongovernmental organisations funded by governments), whose activities are often guided by the arts councils or cultural boards established to oversee artistic practices within government-funded arts educational institutions. This is true of institutions funded by the US government, such as the National Endowment for the Arts or the National Institutes of Health, whose mission is to &quot;support and encourage creativity in all its manifold forms … promote cultural exchange and knowledge sharing among diverse communities’. But cultural institutions funded by the US government also play a critical role in structuring the relations between the national and the globalised imagination. They shape social perceptions and practices, foster the negotiation of shared knowledge and knowledge gaps, and create platforms for the expression of diverse opinions.What is more, these ‘third parties’ play a crucial role in generating, maintaining and enabling the social conditions necessary for art to take root in new environments. In shaping cultural practices</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the twenty-first century, cultural institutions are more likely to be body and digital connected, but they also tend to be regionalised and globalised. Thus the twentieth biennial – which offered several instances of the same art being exhibited in different places – is in part a regional phenomenon. For example, twentieth Tokyo Burusho was held in the same city as the present, but twenty-first Tokyo Nippon-Nippon Artusjusen held its twenty-fifth edition in 2017 in a different city. Art is more likely to be exhibited in a city where the majority of the population are urban or suburban dwellers, but also in cities with high rates of unemployment and poverty. And yet, although art institutions may be regionalised, their social activities tend to be nationalised: twentieth Venice Biennale is the largest Venetian institution, but its fifty-sixth edition in 2015 was exhibited in New York. This</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists can now create worlds that are both physically based and digitally manipulated, at nearly any scale. Such creative action, not least because it is relatively cheap and accessible, is in part a response to the fact that traditional art forms remain deeply embedded in the social fabric of the globalised capitalist system: in the form of cultural capital, internationalisation and the built environment.Art, and in particular cultural production, has become transnational. In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, cultural activity was driven by national artists' societies, which often overlapped and intersected with one another. But with the increasing globalisation of the economy and society, cultural capital increasingly resides in the form of non-governmental arts and cultural organisations (eg cultural institutions funded by governments, territories or nongovernmental organisations) operating in countries around the world. These cultural institutions have come to dominate symbolic gestures, public displays and symbolic exchange, but they are also vital for our understanding of the dynamics of social and political change.In the twenty-first century, cultural capital is being generated in parallel. Globalisation, whether it is the direct conversion of historic cultural centres into digital cultural destinations, or the adoption of new technologies that cause cultural centres to be run as services, ‘curation’ is the contemporary fashion. We could say that the twenty-first century is shaping up to be ‘the curatorial century’. This is an increasingly critical time for cultural institutions around the globe, since many of the social, economic and political changes driving these changes are being fuelled by the emergence of new digital media, which makes it easier to consume culture-wide. New media allow us to be connected to cultural resources around the world, and to participate in cultural consumption globally; and, as a result, the boundaries between the local and the global are becoming increasingly blurred.New media and their accompanying cultural resources are shifting the cultural landscape in many ways, and much of what used to be called the classical curatorial domain is no</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means repeating it often, in order to maintain its form. The question now is: how many more iterations of this wall can we make? The answer is: yes. The answer is: how many biennials can we make?The question of where to locate artworks now becomes very important. If we look to the present for the template for future examples, then we can create a sense of community around the most recent artworks. We can create a sense of shared history and nostalgia for a place and time that is distinct from the city. We can also create a sense of community around shared values, principles, and convictions. We need to be able to identify biennials by their curatorial appointments, because that is the only way a public can identify a curatorial appointment as a bona fide biennial. The only way to know for sure, of course, is to actually see one. In the twentieth century, the biennial began to represent the changes that were happening all around us.</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means it has to be constantly reinvented.And so we, the artists, made art again and again and again and again and again, in very different ways, until finally we created a kind of collective unconscious that permeated the city and beyond, even as we gradually dismantled much of what we had created on the site. And we did that in stages, over years, rather than ephemerally. We dismantled a layer by layer, over decades. Eventually we emerged back to the surface, to the point where we were able to conduct a full-scale renovation of the entire building, removing and rebuilding all the way to the top, so that the entire building was one big art project again.Art as social  Art is inherently political, and social media has played a very important role in enabling a kind of political discourse that has rarely been more prevalent or explicit in the contemporary art world. Social media has enabled a kind of participatory understanding of art that was previously confined to a small elite. It</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means that biennials are around for a very long time to come, as institutions, as cultural locus of action, as sites of artistic activity and as cultural organs of state power. They’re there to be counted, and to be bought. That was their mission from the beginning. And it works.It’s true that the biennial form didn’t exist in its current form in Istanbul, and/or other cities where it has recently emerged. But that doesn’t change the fact that the biennial form is happening all over the world. The fact that it was happening in Istanbul at all, and not some far-flung island outpost where the local artist was either forgotten or too intimidated to explore the city, made the biennial a global event. It gave it international credibility. It gave it institutional forms of expression. And it made it possible for artists to exist in parallel universes where their work is simultaneously globalised and localised. This is happening</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means repeat it often. We can add to the list of cultural stakeholders the government – which is increasingly important as a society – as well as individuals like ourselves (who are increasingly alienated by the society around them). The result is that biennials today tend to be produced in culturally diverse urban centres, and particularly in those areas with a significant number of disadvantaged citizens. These are the artists who draw audiences to their work, and the communities that support their communities, and whose neighbourhoods tend to be enriched by the organisations they form. But even though biennials have become more diverse in their production, their social composition and their consumption, their primary form of art-making remains beholden to a few dominant artistic voices. And although cultural biennials have certainly changed, their social composition and their consumption – their relationship to one another, and to broader art-world practices – remains subject to the whims of the economic and political world that can shift at any moment. That is, of course, the nature of</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means it has to be constantly reinvented and re-formed. So the question is: how do we create the infrastructure to produce and distribute images and videos that are not just of the world we live in, but of artists making work in that world?Art and artists have a complicated relationship. It’s easy to criticise an artist or an organisation for not being innovative enough. But there is a tension between the way we, as artists, are trained to think about art as new worlds to be discovered and experience, and the way we, as artists, are presented with the complex world of art society makes possible through technology. There is an emotional dimension to the task, and there is a tension between the ability of the artist to communicate that complexity to an audience and the ability of the audience to empathise with the world that is made possible by that technology. Sometimes the two act in quite diametrically opposed ways. Take the case of the artist Jeanne van Heeswijk. She</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means that when it comes to an artist signing a blank check, the biennial has to deliver something on the ground.Art is made up of rituals and allegories. We live by them, and we learn them, and we act them out in our art. And while the art we produce, if it is good art, may in some ways be politically aware and politically incorrect, it is art nonetheless. I remember well the conversation, the formation of an Artists’ Cooperative, the emergence of which was a topic of much discussion in the 1970s and 1980s, as well as in the 1990s. The aim was to bring together artists and artists from different parts of the world to exchange and collaborate, to exchange ideas and to produce collective work. It was a space for the exchange of ideas, a place for the production of value and a rumour.It was a space for the production of myth.Here, again, we see the political potential of the cultural-economic nexus. The</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means it has to change, change, change, change. But it’s also a very particularised form, and art has to find its place in that particular society.The thing is, I think now, more like a biennial than a traditional art institution: it’s producing works that are produced, in part, by its own processes of repetition. Think of the prisms that it projects onto the world: the museum, the street, the factory, the river, the factory itself. And that’s what biennials do. They create their own worlds. I should add that this is a form that has its limits: it’s impossible to create a biennial out of parts. The museum, for one. But that’s what biennials do. They are culturally embedded, embedded in their local culture for a very long period of time, and then they completely change how art is produced in that society. And that process of cultural embed</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means repeating it often. The problem with the biennial is that it’s increasingly rare – second-tier, even – compared to the monumental works of art that once graced the cover of Time, Fortune, Timex, or when they first appeared on the back pages of magazines like GQ or People. So what makes this particular iteration unique is that it comes from the same publisher, the same year, the same publisher again and again, and so on. And so the biennial becomes embedded in the larger cultural structure, and the publisher becomes a widely-recognised cultural figure, lauded in the media, lauded as a new breed of artist, heralded as a modern visionary. Publishers, of course, are cultural actors. They’re cultural narrators. But they also narrate narratives, and the things they narrate are produced by and for society at large. And so, the repeated presence of the biennial – which is currently the largest single exhibitionary market in</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means it has to be constantly reinvented, new artists have to be recruited and the biennial has to be constantly renewed. Trust me, it is that important.In order to understand how the biennial forms work, it is necessary to understand some basic sociocultural concepts. I will explain these concepts, and offer some examples of how art practices in the form might relate to our present and future social situations.Sociocultural theory is the study of how individuals and social groups come to understand, exchange and incorporate new knowledge and evidence. It is a deeply embedded field of study, with a wide variety of theoretical frameworks that can be developed to understand how we understand and create knowledge. It is primarily concerned with the production and (more specifically) the circulation of cultural forms and objects, and its social consequences. Sociocultural forms are produced through interaction, generation, repetition and repetition again and again – in much the same way that genes are produced and reproduced. This interaction and repeatability is what</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial, curated by Bernard Goossen and Peter Weibel, was one of our most visible public interventions. We, the artists, were not there to promote the festival as an art form, but to ask: what could it be? What could it possibly be, that would bring together so many disparate parts? What did the biennial do when it was first conceived? What has it done since?These questions and more made the way we looked at art in the twenty-first century, and art in particular, in very different ways. In some ways, it made us uncomfortable, in some ways we enjoyed it, and in some ways we didn’t care. But in the end, what did we make? The wall. The biennial as a form has a way of re-constituting who is an artist (or an organisation, institution, whatever) and how art is produced in that society. It’s a form that has to be repeated, and that means it has to work across cultures and in different times. In this sense, it’s more like a city, and more in the sense that cities are the locus of contemporaneity. But there are other, less obvious but nonetheless significant cultural dimensions to the relationship between biennials and contemporaneity. These are the &quot;bottom-up&quot; cultural dimensions, the &quot;who, what, when, where&quot; dimensions, and the ‘what ifs’ that can and cannot happen in a city.The bottom-up cultural dimensions are the source of much of what makes biennials distinctive. They give them a weight and real effect. For example, the importance of biennials as a cultural form for a developing nation or a particular neighbourhood is underlined in the way that the Biennale itself operates. The way in which they are funded, the way in which they are embedded in the institutional framework, the way in which they are culturally engaged, and the �</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’.
    <text>will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’.’[6] And so, a collection of fairy tales, a poem and a knick-knack – a memento mori – arrived at a time when a number of artists, including the greats like William Burroughs, Kurt Andersen and Noel Burch, were churning out poems and tagging along to galleries, where they were given a backstage pass, and given an audience with the artists they admired.Burroughs was a fan of the early postmodernist movement, which he would later champion in a polemic against mainstream art. In his poem ‘My Poet Was a Robot’, he declares:…

I wrote “My Poet Was a Robot” in response to the idea that a poet’s work should be elevated above all else, above all public, political, even “spontaneous” events, in order to be taken seriously. Burroughs is no more an advocate of ‘</text>
    <text>will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’. […] There was a time when people in the West were so wrapped up in their own images and sounds that they didn’t pay much attention to what was happening in the world around them. But Rankin’s work wasn’t just visual art; he was into biological and biomedical research, and so was into understanding how images and sounds affected behaviour. He found a lot of art to be divisive, and so there was a tension there. But Rankin also saw an opportunity. He saw an opportunity to work with people from the arts community, to bring artistic practice into the creative process. So there was that opportunity to explore how art could be used constructively.It was a gradual process of introducing the art into the creative process. We introduced the painting of the elephant with watercolours and the embroidery of the flag with thread, and the watercolour slides. We even did an embroidery workshop with the girls from the design team. It was</text>
    <text>will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’. [Images courtesy of East India Company Archives, East India Company Archives, East India Collection]In the 1920s and 1930s, when Rankin was alive, postmodernism was a way of life. It was a way of constructing worlds in terms of relations between people and things. You could imagine an elephant in your front garden, or an elephant in your back garden, or a flock of eagles on a mountain peak. Rankin wasn’t a natural philosopher, but he was an elephant builder and he had an intellectual ear. [Image courtesy of East India Company Archives, East India Company Archives, East India Collection]An elephant in your back garden is a pretty picture, but what really got the zeitgeist going in those years was the idea that you could live by your plants. You could have a back garden full of plants, with benches and a small vegetable garden, and you could walk to and from work. It was a counter to the urban sprawl that</text>
    <text>will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’. And so Rankin’s work, which was originally called The Magic Fairy Book and Later Spinning Its Yarns of Worlds, is a riff on the myth of European witch-hunts in the East. But it is also a sort of invitation to turn to magic, which is, by now, everywhere. It is published every two years by Macmillan, its pages dwarfed by the corresponding books in any of the major American periodicals. And yet it is a fairy tale. It begins with a fairy tale, and then goes on to describe a magical world, full of feigned catastrophe, made up mostly of the fables found in the London Fairy Tales. It is a kind of magical shorthand – a sort of literal translation of the words of a fairy tale into something that is more easily understood. And it is this kind of magical shorthand that Lovecraft’s monster is able to fill in, filling in every detail possible, so that when the reader</text>
    <text>will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’. […] The motif of the dead returning to life through a miracle, or perhaps of the returning to life of a given order and community of people, is an old Irish one. It is also a motif that is very much alive in the land that you and I call Ireland. Ireland has a very rich and complex and rich cultural past that includes things like piracy, torture, massacres and stills from the wars that these people are still involved in. A lot of that history is woven into the fabric of the island, so there’s a connection to that. And there is a connection to that particular poetic turn of phrase ‘spinning its yarns of worlds’ that’s being used now by Rankin and others like him. It’s a powerful phrase, and I think it has a kind of a sad and brilliant aspect to it.’[…] The poem begins ‘Spineless Thread’, the name of the Irish ship that</text>
    <text>will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’.’[1] And so we can read into the self-published form of the work a latent desire to be magical, communal and magical, to be able to stand on the shoulders of giants and turn into something magical, when in reality, it is the other – the forces of darkness – who would rather tear you limb from limb, limb from limb, than wish the most basic of humanity a happy, fulfilling existence. Do you see the irony, the horror of it all?The world was made up of equal parts human and magical creatures. Now, some of those things are stronger than others, and so you can be born with a body that is both strong and stupid and so endowed with magical powers – think of how an African lion mauls a human being to death. But there were also times when the world was made up of only very strong, very specific, very particular things: things that could only happen in a specific set of circumstances. And so the work</text>
    <text>will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’. […] [T]he magical thread that runs through much of Rankin’s work is a call to arms: to arms, that is, with the religious underpinnings of his thinking put in such stark contrast with the more natural and human dimensions of his actual life. He was an atheist and a soldier for the state, but there is something profoundly Christian about his magical thinking. That is, there is something genuinely Christian in the notion that you can create a fantastical world out of disparate elements. It’s as though the author had a field day creating an entirely different world from the one we live in, one in which magic and reason coexist. Something tells me that’s difficult to reconcile with the character we have today.‘Today’, of course, is a global language: it’s too easy to identify with our physical world. But Rankin’s work is not an isolated example of postmodernism�</text>
    <text>will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’. […] There was a time when it was said that a wizard’s hat could turn a man into a monkey.] […] There are a number of magical trinkets in the form of objects, rare and magical and sometimes downright silly: a pair of shoeshine kettles, a wizard’s hat, a pair of scissors, a strand of pearls, a tin plate, a thread or any number of thread or string. But there is a problem with the idea of things: there is a problem with magic, and if you give things to someone who wants to use them then you have broken promises. So you have broken promises, and the character in the poem is complaining about this.Â[…] The first time I saw the wizard’s hat, I thought it was a bit garish, and I wasn’t the only one. But then I saw the picture of the real thing – the workmanlike craft</text>
    <text>will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’. And so Rankin’s writing, like many Romantic poets of the period, is one big magical spell. It’s magic that allows us to see the world through fantastical frameworks and to pretend otherwise. It allows us to imagine realms far more fantastical than our own. And so here, too, we can look to the past and wish that our own magical, fantastical past could somehow exist in the future – in a world where people actually live and interact and make decisions based on evidence and reason rather than the whims of a few economic actors. And there’s a moment, here, that’s often-overlooked in writing about the religious, political and social history of the twentieth and twenty-first centuries. In the twentieth century, religious fundamentalism was re-purposed as a social construct through which social struggles were manufactured. In the twenty-first century, religious fundamentalism is re-purposed as a social construct through which</text>
    <text>will be curated with the help of the East India Arts Council.]A Midsummer Night’s Dream was written for a girl named Leah Boylan and it was first published in 1954. It is a collection of fairy tales, with elements of Jewish mysticism woven through. Leah is the name of the character. She is the daughter of English nobleman, poet and statesman Philip Boylan (1799–1949), who was also the name of a fictional Irish peasant named Leah Arnold (1809–92).A Midsummer Night’s Dream begins:There was a witch-hunter named Stefan Rankin, an Irish Catholic, who travelled widely in Africa, Asia and Europe in the 1920s and 30s. He was a great admirer of John Lyly’s work, and so was very into the postmodernist vein of Jean-Luc Nancy’s poetic invention, that one could say ‘spinning its yarns of worlds into existence’. As Rankin wrote elsewhere, the motif of the here and now – that ‘dead hand of the past’ – was woven into the fabric of European society from the very beginning. The fetishisation of the present as a site of past lives gave rise to a concept that would later be described as ‘presentism’. A touch of vernacular modernism is in here, too.Modernism is an ideology that advocates a society in which people live according to their own set of values and desires – in other words, it does not envision a future beyond the present – and seeks to reconcile this desire for ideal society with the fact that different people have different lives paths and lives (whether of desire, necessity or other). In other words, modernism does not envision a future of abundance and ephemeral forms of exchange between people; rather, it seeks to create a society based on mutual aid and social co-preservation. For Marx, ‘abstract space�</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial end, and they are likely to perpetuate existing hierarchies of power and wealth. As a result, they may seek to destroy not only those who are not part of their fold, but those who are different from them. This is one possible endgame. Another possible endgame is possible too, and it is being written about in some quarters. In any case, it is not clear what the future holds for us or what might befall us in the event of such a scenario developing.Artificial Intelligence and the Media Daniel Kahneman,  	Process Culture, 1983. New York and London: Wiley-Blackwell, 2005. p. 25. Arjun Appadurai,  	The End of Postmodernism 1970–79, 1982 London: Verso, 1987. p. 5. Florence Akhter,  	Time and Society 1983 London: Picador, p. 5. Graham Kerr,</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial end, and they are manifest in the forms of advertising, PR, and the political system that is developing in Denmark. In a way, then, the politics of art and the politics of AI are closely related. The politics of the artistically inclined individual, or the politically apathetic mass media viewer, is intimately tied to the politics of the system that creates and supports art. And the politics of the AI that is developed and deployed is closely tied to the politics of the media that narrates the political landscape. Sound familiar?  The politics of mass media in Denmark is closely tied to the politics of art, and Danish art is a media-rich country with a mass media complex that is literally a cathedral to Danish media culture. Art’s political potential is realised when it is delivered by artists who are not necessarily politically inclined, but who nevertheless believe that they are artists, or who are given to poetic exaggeration, or by those who simply happen to be politically engaged.  The political implications</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial end, and while their capabilities may be used for good, the ethical question that arises in imagining the future societal effect of such capabilities is likely to be different from the question of how such capacities might be used in the present. In trying to envision the ethical implications of these technologies, we may need to grapple with more concrete political-cultural issues and actors.Art and creativity are not necessarily mutually exclusive resources, but they are certainly designed with different needs in mind. The end users of contemporary art and creativity may well be interested in the kinds of ethical dilemmas that art and culture are capable of posing. It is also possible that the creators of these kinds of media will be interested in the kinds of problems and social problems that art and culture can help to solve. It is also possible that the end users of artistic production will seek to help artists and organisations that work with artists find new kinds of art and creativity. This is the dynamic that art and culture are designed to foster. While the end users</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial end, and they are much smarter than humans are, which is to say, much more capable of understanding cultural norms and values. Thus there is a tension between the capacities of the artist and the systems that are being developed to render her work intelligible. The tension is heightened in the context of a major art biennale, because the artist is often the only visitor to the proceedings. Even for the artist herself, who has a critical perspective, the visit is often brief and confined. She is often confronted with the decision as to what to do with the knowledge that has been gathered. Her recent exhibition at MoMA: ​Reflected Image, ‘Reflected Image’, presents a rare opportunity to examine this type of knowledge in the flesh. The exhibition is an extended version of a lecture she gave in Copenhagen in 2006, when she was selected for the World Columbian Exposition. In that lecture, she invoked the name of the artist and the exhibition in order to demonstrate how the</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial end, and they are likely to end up in the service of some form of government. As a consequence, the kinds of state that are created through these kinds of changes will be politically engaged, and will need to be involved in the creation of a shared understanding of what AI means. While the state won’t come to an agreement on what kind of shared understanding of what AI means, it can certainly choose to engage in certain kinds of discourse around certain kinds of knowledge. The kinds of state that are created through this kind of change will also need to be involved in the maintenance of a shared kind of understanding of what AI means. These kinds of political engagement are possible because of the emergence of a shared understanding of what AI means: a shared set of rules that govern how information is delivered across a shared set of borders. But the kind of shared understanding of what AI means is likely to differ from the kind of shared understanding of what the state means, and from the kind of shared understanding of</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial end, and as such are bound to play a part in the economy. In this way, they may serve as agents of economic transformation, or as administrators of knowledge production themselves.Artificial intelligence raises the question: what kinds of ambiguities do we confront in the world? In my view, there are three types of ambiguity that AI may confront: pragmatological, conceptual and linguistic.1. Programmatic ambiguity. Programmatic ambiguity arises when the rules that enable an AI to perform a task are specified by human beings – for example, when the Turing machine enables a human to solve a riddle. In such cases, the AI performs an action based on its understanding of the world, but paradoxically, this may also render the world unintelligible. For example, the Japanese text-editor ANSI X9 (computer system for electronic document processing) was developed by IBM under the name Kanzi, and its intention was to render electronic text as graphic text. But in the face of</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial end, and they operate at a level of abstraction and nuance that is as human as possible. However, they are also conscious systems that can be reified and anthropomorphised. That is, conscious systems can have emotions and desires and can – presumably – make mistakes. Therefore, while the designers of these systems undoubtedly have intentions of ever enabling more creative and interesting ways of interacting with the world, they also have a responsibility to continually learn and grow. This is true of all AI systems, but perhaps the greatest challenge of AI is the fact that it is always seeking to make itself more human-like through ever greater and more pervasive human enhancement. In this respect, artists and creative people are at least initially invested in becoming more like humans, and perhaps more so than those who do not master coding or mastery of platforms, algorithms and data. In this sense, the AI/ART problem becomes particularly interesting insofar as art is one of the last vestiges of classical human creativity remaining. While it is</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial purpose, and not just to serve the interests of humans (Ehrhardt: ​​&quot;Art has a responsibility to people, and if it doesn’t, people have a responsibility to art’s audience&quot;). So while the intelligence that creates art does have a responsibility to the people who engage with that art, it also has the responsibility to future generations and to actively engage those generations in a way that is relevant to the interests of the art world today and in the future. This kind of explicit engagement with future generations is something that AI does very well, and it is something that is very much at the core of what the term ‘Artificial General Intelligence’ means.Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) is an umbrella term that refers to systems that understand more than program instructions and are able to reason independently of one another. In the context of contemporary art and contemporary culture, we can think of AGI as broadly the capability to understand cultural phenomena such as historical images or</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial agenda, and are much like the kinds of programming that are being integrated into commercial aircraft today. Like all kinds of programming, this kind of AI requires humans to be creative and flexible enough to handle the new meanings that are being thrown around by the AI. Like any kind of programming, this kind of AI requires problems to be programmed that are malleable enough for intelligent machines to operate on them, and much like any kind of infrastructure, this kind of AI requires maintenance to ensure that the systems that it builds are maintained and continue to offer various kinds of benefit to the society at large. Here, we can move from AI that is being developed in labs around the world to AI that is being used in the real world. Like any kind of infrastructure, even if it is being maintained by a multi-billion dollar corporation, maintenance is a major source of funding for new AI research. Maintenance is a necessity for any kind of AI, and as we saw, there is no way to remove it from</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this regard, the relationship between curating and Artificial General Intelligence (AGI) can be seen as analogous to that between curating and biomedicines. AGI is a new kind of intelligence that is both intelligent (understood as a set of rules) and non-intelligent (understood as a process of metainterface). Its intelligence is understood as a set of rules that regulate the interaction of matter with matter in various ways (movement, reception, etc.). While the human intelligence that creates artwork, or science fiction, can be understood as a product of human agency, the new kinds of intelligence that are emerging in contemporary art are neither artist-crafted nor ethically pure. Rather, they are the product of new kinds of AI (Artificial General Intelligence), systems that learn to handle knowledge in various ways (see my book The Prince of Denmark: ​The Rise of Denmark and America, 2006). These new kinds of intelligence are explicitly designed to serve a commercial end, and they are likely to end up in the news a great deal because of the increasing privatization of everything from education to healthcare to the media. Despite the fact that this type of intelligence has been around for a long time, people get very nervous about what they don’t know. In fact, there is a famous saying in computer programming: a bad guy with a shiny new AI gets a black eye. While this may be true in rare cases, in the broader sense this seems silly. After all, if the AI can’t understand what you mean, but instead behaves in ways that maximize your profit, then what is the point of having an AI at all? In this context, the notion of the AI seems even worse: to some extent, we are talking here about what might happen if our AI becomes smart enough to understand that there is more to life than meets the surface level – beyond the surface level of what we are trained to think we know.  So we</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, and the Origins of Biennials. Durham: Duke University Press, 2001.Download this article as PDFEva CastringiusEva Castringius is Professor in the Department of Culture and Society at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the Canada Research Chair in cultural studies at the Winchester School of Art (University of Sydney). Her research interests include art, crowds, and culture production. Her work has been shown at the New York, Venice, Sao Paulo, and Bernardo di Vicenti festivals, and she has presented her work at the Venice Biennale, Venice Architecture Biennale, and The New York Times. Her publications include the award-winning Culture and Society: Art, Crowds, and the Origins of Biennials (with Monica Cyrana, NZS, 2015); the New York Times Best Seller Culture and Crowds (with Monica Cyrana, NZS, 2015); the New York Times Best Seller Listing for Cultural Spaces (with Monica</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, and the Origins of Social Movements. New York: Palgrave MacMillan, 2015.Download this article as PDFAna Laura Lancía PascualPascualReales de Campesina, Ana Laura Lancía Pascual, Campesina y Los Tainos, 2015. Don Quixote y Paco de Oro, 2015. Written by Laura Lancía Pascual, with contributions from Don Quixote and Paco de Oro. Produced by Don Quixote &amp; Paco de Oro.Duration: 1h 54minSanto Domingo, 2015. The Campesina, 3rd movement of Don Quixote y Paco de Oro, 2015.Cameroon, Cameroon, October 2014. Photo courtesy of Ambasz Archives.Duration: 1h 54minThe Campesina, 2015. Don Quixote y Paco de Oro, 2015. Written by Don Quixote, with contributions from Don Quix</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, and the Episodic. New York: Duke University Press, 2015.Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is a Ph.D. candidate in Cultural Studies and Co-Director of Research Institute of Deaf Studies (Qatar Studies) at McGill University. Her dissertation examines the role of art, culture, activism and the movement for social change in the aftermath of the Arab Spring, and she is currently researching the experiences of her mother, father and three siblings, among others. Her publications include the collections Société Culturaliste en Arabémie des Beaux-Arts (CASCO, 2015), from which the present work is drawn; the book Arab Spring: The End of Postcolonialism (2013, New York Times best-seller) and articles for the online and regional cuisines of Le Devoir, Le Monde diplomatique, Le Monde   Manuel and the like.Gabriela Rendon is a curator</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, and Crowdsourcing. In The Institutionalization of Culture: Crowds, ART, and the Social (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2015), pp. 79–114.Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, and Crowdsourcing. In The Institutionalization of Culture: Crowds, ART, and the Social (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2015), pp. 79–114.Ambasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture. In The Institutionalization of Culture: Crowds, ART, and the Social (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2015), pp. 79–114.Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture. In The Institutionalization of Culture: Crowds, ART, and the Social (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2015), pp. 79–114.Download this article</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, and Mass Media. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2015.Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. Culture and Society. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2015.Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. Culture and Institutional Change. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2015.Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. Culture and Institutional Change. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2015.Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. Culture and Institutional Change. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2015.Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. Culture and Institutional Change. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2015.Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. Culture and Institutional Change. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2015.Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders.</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, and the Law (Cambridge, MA: The MIT Press, 2003).Download this article as PDFStuart MoulthroupStuart Moulthroup is Professor of Sociology and Co-Director of the Centre for Research on Globalization (CRG) at the University of Toronto, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Research on Globalization, with a particular focus on the role of cultural capital in fostering economic growth and social mobility. His research interests include the social sciences and humanities, with a special interest in the social sciences and humanities that incorporate art and artistic production, including but not limited to: cultural theory, critical race theory and ethnography, and media and visual culture. Moulthroup is the recipient of several awards and publications, including the Mersey Traveler Prize, the J.C. Denton Prize, the Paul H. Smith Prize for Public Knowledge and the Mersey Traveler of the Year Award. He has been a fellow of the Mersey Traveler</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, and Capital (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2013). [2] See Danielson, Capital in Continuum, Chapter Two, section 3. [3] See Danielson, Capital in Continuum, Chapter Two, section 3.1. [4] See, for example, Mitchell, ed., The New Media Reader (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2015), pp. 875–87.Download this article as PDFAna Laura López de la TorreA Laura López de la Torre is a literary critic, essayist, and critic of institutionalised forms of writing and knowledge. She is the editor of online literary journal Stages and the author of several books that address the social, economic, and political dimensions of contemporary creativity. Her work has been published in Rolling Stone, The New Inquiry, The New Inquiry Reader, and the journal Aventura Nacional. She is also the executive director of the Institutional Radio Network,</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, and the Social Life of a Public (PHYS 2016)Karolinska Institutet, 16 January 2016.Facsimile of the front cover of Karolinska Institutet, Issue 13/14, March 2004.PreviousNextFacsimile of the front cover of Karolinska Institutet, Issue 13/14, March 2004.AS THE AMERICAN GIANT GIRL, I turned seventeen in November 2003. By then, I was already a self-taught artist, having begun when I took art classes at the Rhode Island School of Design. I went on to study art history and art form at the Rhode Island School of Art, where I participated in the Art Underground series in 2008 and 2009, and in 2011 I co-curated the Rhode Island Biennial, which introduced a completely different generation of artists to the art form.The Biennial format had several sub-genres, which I would define as follows: ‘series of</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, Cities. New York: D.A.P. Strategies/Crowds, 2015.Previously, he served as Artistic Director of the New York Art Center (2009–12) and as Artistic Director of the Auckland Art Biennale (2007–09). He worked with artist and activist groups including the Black and the D.A.P. to develop a three-year long project in 2009–10 that combined traditional and social curating approaches. These led to the publication of four books, including the award-winning Local Curating.He is currently a professor at the New School for Art and Architecture, City College of New York, New York. He is the host of the weekly public programme, The Green Book, which has been described as the Public Gallery of the Museum. He has co-edited the forthcoming New York Times best-seller Listening Postscript: Art, Crowds, and Counter Culture, with Ravenna Whiteley-Brewster, and co</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. Curating is about relationships and how relationships are formed, but also about the relationship between curators and artists. Artificial intelligence is the new hipster bar, but unlike the bar, it has the AI that orders the bar to be exactly as it wishes it to be, and even though it may not know what that is, it is capable of understanding the meaning of that. It is this understanding that underlies the new curatorial format that seeks to simultaneously ground and deploy the power of the collective unconscious, a kind of grassroots imagination that has become a predominant mode of cultural production in the age of the biennial.  [1] For a more in-depth analysis of this relationship, see Anders Aslund and his collaborator Ambasz, eds., Deceitful Institutions: Institutional Change and its Consequences (Durham: Duke University Press, 2015).Download this article as PDFAmbasz, Anders. The Institutionalization of Culture: Art, Crowds, and the Law (Cambridge: Polity, 2015).Download this article as PDFGabriela RocaLara FavarettoLara Favaretto is Professor in the Department of Anthropology and Director of the Center for Anthropology and Visual Cultures at the University of Pennsylvania. Her research interests include the social sciences and humanities of the arts, their social effects, and the development of cultural constitutions in the age of the biennial. She is currently working with Joasia Krysa on the publication of a book on the history of biennials that will be entitled Institutions for a Post-Imperial Imagination. She is the editor and co-founder of Institutional Fragility, a journal of the Institutional Fragmentation Research Centre. Her work has also been featured in Institutional Analysis, a journal of institutional reform, and was recently edited by Jan Latymer and Peter Weibel. She is co-editor of the forthcoming book Real Institutions: Renewing Contempor</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey
    <text>archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey’ and it would be a quick trip to ‘Bangladesh’. 	The ICTC recognized Turkey as a founding member of the ‘Union of Orthodox Ecumenical Churches’. This came as a great surprise to the other ‘establishment’ churches, which had all been encouraged to join the ICTC by the military junta. They were all told to sit down and find a solution to the problem of who was an authentic member of the Orthodox Church and who was an opportunist member of the military machine. The opportunists were to be counted among the ‘first-generation’ members of the Church. The Church was to be counted among the ‘second-generation’, after the population had become more urbanized and the bureaucracy had been forced onto a smaller and more human scale. 	The ICTC recognized Turkey as a founding member of the Union of Orthodox Churches. This came as a great surprise to the other</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey’, and the convention would tell you where to find everything from hotels to art to sports grounds to university campuses all over the place. The interesting thing about these lists is that they are often rephrased to suit the interests of the tourist, who is granted omnipresence thanks to technology. 	For example, the ‘points of origin’ for heroin addiction are now Afghanistan and Iran, not Iraq and Libya. The ­​points of origin and destinations of today’s super-soldier drugs are any number of regional centers, but the real point of origin for the militias fighting in Syria and Iraq today is in the Eastern Mediterranean, where the Armenian Catholic Church has a large presence and the Iranian Revolutionary Guard a small one. Today, Turkey is a major player in the global heroin trade, and the current prime minister, Ahmet Davutoglu, is an economic nationalist who wants to take back control of the economy from the global financial institutions. 	Dav</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey’ and then get on a plane to wherever the product was located. 	Since the 1980s, when the biennale has been headquartered in New York, the IDC has become a global symbol of globalisation and the value it places on numbers. It has even managed to find a place in the Trump Tower in New York – where, in theory, any building can be a museum or a museum. 	But the history of the IDC and its divisions, which began in the mid-1980s and continue to this day, is a story of urban resistance, global commodification and the gradual demise of the city as an object of cultural exchange. 	The IDC emerged as a response to a demand for more precise information on the location of goods and services produced by the multinational transport and logistics companies, which was creating new kinds of national museums with permanent exhibitions in many national capitals around the world. The need for such information became evident in the 1980s, when the</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey’, and the agency would quickly order the goods and services of every kind imaginable. 	The point of origin and destination names were chosen on the theory that, as the agency and its clients grew larger and more powerful, it became increasingly difficult to distinguish between the kind of travel that actually happened and the kind that was imagined to happen. In other words, the agency’s expansionary moves, which we see coming increasingly from the organization’s periphery, were in part an internal game, playing out against the backdrop of the agency’s increased political and economic presence in the country. 	The IDC decided early on that its expansion would come at the expense of its traditional core business of smuggling people across the international borders of the Turkish Straits. So, the agency began to specialize in interior decoration, primarily in the service of the Turkish government. In 1975, the creation of the AKP (National Assembly of Turkey) political party came as a huge surprise to many</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey’ and there was a store for that for you at ‘Dubai’, ‘Kabul’ and ‘Lagos’. 	In the twenty-first century, these names are generic and the precise definition of a biennale is vague, but in the nineteenth century they were defined and formalised as a kind of major international exposition – an exhibition of goods or exhibitions of displays of things. So the ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’ that we find in the biennial today are defined as having something to do with goods and services, and not necessarily with the twentieth-century categories of goods and services. And so the twentieth-century biennial has arrived. It is an international exposition of a particular type, and it is a kind of point of origin for the twenty-first century type; it is, in some ways, the point of diffusion. 	But it is also a kind of diffusion of art</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey’ and get a flight to ‘China’. 	The ICTY created a new division within its headquarters in New York, and within three years established a new corporate structure: the International Centre for Photography and Art (ICPA). ICA was a publicly traded company with offices in London and Istanbul, as well as branches in other cities. Its activities – buying, selling, managing artists’ studios and art books, and distributing artwork – centred on Istanbul. 	In 1983, a wave of bombings rocked Istanbul, killing over 300 people and leaving over 8,000 homeless. The government responded by staging a massive military operation codenamed Euphrates Shield, calling in NATO allies and engaging in what was widely considered a PR disaster – leading to accusations of double standards and a constitutional crisis. 	Within months of the attacks, several prominent artists, including Paul McCarthy, Peter Carr and Noel Burch, formed a CLT (Commission for Literary and Artistic Works</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey’ and get a flight to anywhere in the world. 	The ICTY organised these various forms of tourism conventionally, with partners such as the World Travel and Exhibition Association and other trade unions. However, the biennale’s export market was always a point of departure for a host country to explore new economic opportunities, and the biennale itself is an ideal case study of a country trying to export its way of life. Its collection of local partners ensured that the biennale would always be able to find a home in a given city. 	The biennale’s ability to declare itself to be anything it wanted – a position that it held regardless of what its real source was – is what attracted so many artists and art professionals to the project. 	As biennials become more and more international, and the host country more and more distant, the need for artists to develop larger local followings grows. And so the biennale began</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey’ and get a product or service immediately. 	The ICTC has continued to expand its division into many other types of enterprises, often operating outside the legal jurisdiction of the city, and it is still a global enterprise with offices in many cities. But with the economic, social and political systems that it developed in its current form – a hybrid between law, bureaucracy and financial capitalism – behind it, the museum has little direct recourse but to grapple with the structural changes that it requires to confront. At the center of this challenge has been the central role played by the museum in the creation of its social and political forms. The museum is embedded in its social territory, whether that is with its collection of public acts or its collection of private collections. The importance of the museum as a social entity in this transformation cannot be understated. 	The museum as a historical artifact confronts its own social totality in a series of episodes that continually shift the historical narrative. As Lefebvre puts it</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey’ and then find a way to get somewhere else. ‘Iraq’ would be included in the following year, and so on. 	The division of goods and services into discrete and discrete parts became a global format for this kind of globalised infrastructuralisation. For many years, this did not include ‘the Middle East’, since it was seen as the region least able to support a robust centralized power. But the division of labour has become increasingly important in the global economy of consumption, and it is this kind of global circulation that is now suspected of being at the root of the growing inequality and malnourishment seen in the region. 	The rapid growth of global trade after the mid-1970s represents a generalised alteration in the global division of labour that had been developing for several decades. The new forms of production required new kinds of infrastructures, and this new infrastructuralisation required new kinds of maps. The division</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, which were an early forerunner of the modern museum. 	Events in modern-day Istanbul provide a rich source of material for a museum to work from. These days, the city is awash with tourism (80% of which is from Istanbul alone), and the financial blockade imposed by the national ID card system makes it very expensive to travel outside of the city. On top of this, the constant stream of migrants pouring into the country from across the Balkan route, the Middle East and Africa, makes it even harder to visit. 	In an attempt to absorb all these different streams of tourism, the IDC (International Convention of Travel Companies) decided in 1974 to create an international division of its type – a division that would, among other things, include ‘points of origin’ and ‘destinations’. These names, chosen optimistically, offered quick and easy access to a global market of goods and services: you could say you were in ‘Turkey’ and then get anything you wanted anywhere in the world. 	In this case, ‘Turkey’ was a point of entry and a point of exit. And these three words spelled out a lot of money to be spent. As late as the 1990s, when the industry finally started to recover from this disastrous investment, the global trade in antiquities was still regarded as a relatively new phenomenon. 	The IDC ‘temporarily suspended’ this nascent global trade in antiquities because it was becoming increasingly difficult to access finance to finance the increasingly elaborate urban infrastructure that supported the growing trade. The suspension of the trade meant that important archaeological sites around the world would have to be retraisted – put back into circulation – which meant constructing new monuments around the old ruins. This process of retrofitting was being driven by a new generation of urban planners intent on a better world for the cities and countryside, not just for the urbanised elite. As a result,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms
    <text>Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms enabling this process are provided or created by now, and 6. These public boards or mechanisms are empowered to make decisions with respect to such development on their own. What are the tasks of the Community Land Trust? 1. Establishing Community Trusts (CTs) and collaborative agreements with stakeholders via Community Land Trusts (CLTs). 2. Planning, designing, constructing, managing, and sharing opportunities to acquire and use land and buildings, including by partnering with other authorities and non-profits. 3. Providing legal and financial support for the activities of the Community Land Trusts and CLTs, including through grants, cooperative funds, tax deductible contributions, and other forms of private and public support. 4. Establishing and managing an annual budget to support the activities of the Community Land Trusts and CLTs, including through grants, cooperative funds, tax deductible contributions, and other forms of private and public support. 5. Establishes and supports an International Accounting Standards Committee (or equivalent</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms that monitor and control such developments are subject to change, and 6. The mechanisms evolve to meet the changing needs of the community. 	However, such visions are not without risk. The concerns of the Bed-Share movement led to debates and challenges around housing and development that continue to shape the city and country. Perhaps the most prominent example of this is the debate and challenge around the desirability of such radical housing alternatives for the millions of people who now call Toronto home. In the 1980s and 1990s, debates around desirability were central to the political and social life of the city; today, it is even more so. But in an effort to meet the challenges of a rapidly developing city, new modes of consumption and self-sufficiency are being developed that threaten not only the vested interests of the financial few, but also the very fabric of the city. The question is, which of these two worlds is being threatened? 	In order to offer affordable housing to all New</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms underlying such transparent or quasi-transparent public boards operate in a world where, increasingly, issues of public safety and security are paramount.  [1] See, for example, Graeme Ruxton, Human Capital: The Rise and Fall of Creative Industries (Cambridge, Massachusetts and Chicago, Illinois: The MIT Press, 2015), p.10. [2] Ibid., p.13. [3] See, for example, Tiziana Terranova, The Coming Crisis: Global Templates of Capital (New York: Columbia University Press, 2015), p.11. [4] See, for example, Susanne Kugler, Culture and Capital in Transition: The Rise of Postmodernism in Europe (Cambridge, Mass.: The MIT Press, 2015), p.3. [5] 'How should we design our cities for the future?',  	Future City, November, 2016, http://futurecity.org/2016/exhibition/how-</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms involved in the provision of affordable housing, including public boards, reduce political involvement and empower citizens, 6. New modes of access to data and creative thinking might result in ‘better yet’ outcomes for communities. 	The use of big data and Big Dreams is not new. But how such technologies might impact specific communities is much more complex. Big Data and Big Dreams are used in very different ways in Brazil and in the United States, but the underlying principles are the same. In Brazil, Big Data is understood as data about the physical world around us; it includes data about movement, temperature, humidity, soil and water, as well as aggregated statistics on population, employment and land use. Big Dreams, on the other hand, refers to the internal workings of the human mind and body. It is a form of prayer to an unseen power, and it is said that the creator of the universe felt compelled to make it manifest.1 	At a fundamental level, Big Data and</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms governing such monitoring and control become transparent to the communities directly, through interactions with the new denizens of the area, 6. And, finally, 7. The mechanisms governing this process are adapted to the specific needs and politics of each locality. I want to explore in detail the kinds of monitoring and control that might be employed in a future city, such as a neighbourhood, township, or village. But first, let’s consider what might be termed the proto-cities of the present. 	What if, tomorrow, a large number of people decide to create a parallel, co-generative, and hugely beneficial human-resource-producing environment around themselves? What if, instead of having one of these parallel economies, we decide to invest in creating a city around ourselves? What if, in the next city, we embark on the same mutually reinforcing cycle of mutually reinforcing creative-resource-producing processes? What if, in the eighth and final city, we embark on a process of</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms brought about by this paradigm shift might be incorporated into design and building codes, but within this framework, they could also be implemented through open-source or -as-needed architectures. 	With the support of a city or a municipality, such entities might be created to provide legal representation and other services to residents and members of the public, coordinate with other public authorities, and establish mechanisms for sharing resources and empowering residents to take part in the process of development. 	Such entities might be created to monitor and control such developments, but within this framework, they could also be implemented through open-source or 'as-needed' architectures. They could monitor and control access to resources, draw-futures on infrastructure, and create and adopt strategies for smart growth. Their mission statement might read something like this: 	To monitor, control, and (in the future) augment the urban environment’s ability to support life, human habitation, and (with appropriate government oversight and</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms governing this process are available to all, whether local, regional, national or international, and 6. New business models emerge where transparent or quasi-transparent public boards can be convened with minimal involvement from the local government. What is at Stake in Community Practice? 	One can begin to identify what is at stake in the current political and economic landscape of the UK. This has become evident even amidst the celebrations of the success of the hugely successful Big Data programmes such as those led by H.E. [John] Watson and Institute of Chartered Surveyors, which have themselves become macroscopic within the context of the social enterprise sector. It is necessary to develop strategies for the construction of alternative economic paradigms, where the public is effectively excluded from the (potential) profit. This will require a critical understanding of how economic data is generated and communicated in the UK; how such data is used to (potentially) generate political and economic change, and how such data</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms involved in the performance of these cooperative efforts become transparent or quasi-transparent, 6. Agencies involved in the performance of these cooperative efforts, whether local or national, tap into this data to enhance their bottom lines, or as a way to protect their respective institutions or constituents, or to engage in what they call ‘counter-radical Islamic terrorism’. 	[i] Sunita Paul,  	Landscapes of Desire: Urbanization, Cultural Capital and Development in Bangladesh (DACTA: Dhaka and Silo Society, 2014). [ii] Environment News Service,  	Global Greening A Brief Look at Tenure in an Hour (2014). [iii] Environment News Service,  	Greening Predictions: The Environmental Turnaround (2014). [iv] New York Times,  	Greening: The Innovative Urbanizer (2013). [v] Time,  	10 July 2014, '</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms governing this process are collectively referred to as ‘Big Data’. What started out as collecting statistics on house-building in areas around schools and playgrounds has evolved into a paradigm of analysis of spatial data, interpretation of that spatial data, and application of that spatial data to catalyze new development or facilitate old. 	Such Big Data approaches are not new. In fact, many technologists and researchers in the social and behavioural sciences are now drawn to the project of creating socially engaged or socially engaged infrastructure, whether that is through the mechanisms of city halls, academic institutions, grassroots groups or other grassroots actors, which often have skills and tools that are complementary to those of city planners or urban engineers. 	However, the adoption of such technology for a given context or locality is complex and uneven, and diversity of contexts or localities is therefore essential for its success. Today, Big Data is used to gather data on a local level, but more importantly, it is being deployed to collect data</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, statisticians, and computer programmers, artists, Julia would design practical ways to support community gardens through partnerships with local businesses and community organizations. Through an artist-initiated community collaboration, local residents, business owners, community leaders, and local educational institutions could pool resources, identify potential opportunities, and work collaboratively toward a common end. This end might include seed funding for start-ups or seed funding for community-based organizations, partnerships with art institutions, or both. The end result might be cooperative, community-based solutions that address pressing local issues or local desires. This is the paradigm of big data and Big Dreams. We envision a future where: 1. Inhabitants of properties and buildings around to be redeveloped, 2. Developers of such structures, 3. Community leaders take part in this process through collaborative agreements, participatory councils, or other similar mechanisms, 4. New technologies enable transparent or quasi-transparent public boards to monitor and control such developments, 5. The mechanisms that enable this public are augmented with new vested interests, and 6. This all happens with the tacit understanding that such action is desirable because it will one day be able to cash in on such beneficial developments through enhanced public benefits. But there is much more to be done. It is time to sit down and negotiate an equitable share of the pie.This would require political will and a willingness to consider new modes of economic empowerment for the local. The tools are available, and the national appetite is deep. But the task is formidable. There are many vested interests that would rather see a de facto commons such as the city produce the rules than engage in creative consensus. There are vested interests of various sorts that would rather see people sit on boards than in control of development projects. And there are vested interests of various sorts that would rather see developers do things their way rather than by the rules of the game.For the residents and community activists at Large Sigma, this meant coming to terms with the need to actively</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home,
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home, you’re keeping score – you’re keeping score in the same way that the artist would, in her or his work, create a parallel universe in which things can happen.‘The power of the parallel universe is that it establishes an absolute boundary. No interpretation is possible within that universe, not even the artist’s, which is why we can create something completely new and different and still keep track of time.’By the same token, the parallel universe also precludes any kind of interpretation, because interpretations are at best naïve and at worst politically incorrect. So what the art world does with regard to its own art world is a very powerful thing – a kind of pre-emptive strike, assuming that there are still any left in the world – whereas the parallel universe does a kind of circumambient re-construction of things. It pre-exists, but it does not create. This is what the McKim brothers did with their home in Brooklyn</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home, you’re keeping score – or ‘keeping score’ – as in, ‘Yeah, I’m keeping score with my brother and sister-in-law, and we’re going to be the best kids in school, and we’re going to be the first ones to go to college, and all those other numbers that you keep in mind – those are the ones that we’re going to work through, and we’re going to build our lives around, and those are the ones that you’re going to put in motion.And that’s what we did. We moved to a different school, we moved away from home, we started a new job, and that’s when things started to move in the right direction. And then, over time, as events unfolded, we started to drift apart, we started to miss each other, and then one day, everything just clicked and we came together as</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home, you’re keeping score alongside the people at the other end of the scale. You’re keeping score in the same way that the artist keeps score: by scoring herself.

advertisement

advertisement

advertisement

advertisement

advertisementYou’re keeping score as well as the others, in that what comes true is simultaneously satisfying and infuriating. And it’s this idea of having a say, or more specifically, participating as individuals in writing your own experience and identity in relation to the media that you consume and that generates the biennial that you visit. What I find fascinating is how biennials, especially those established abroad, tend to create a kind of distance between themselves and their environments, their host communities, which in turn tends to obscure or erase the social realities that inhabit those host communities.You don’t experience life as a biennial, or as a biennial visitor, as much as an observer. You inhabit it as a journalist</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home, that’s how you count to ten: when you encounter something new, you encounter it in succession of experiences; when you’re in a new place, you encounter it in succession of experiences; and so on.The idea of encounter as a sequence of experiences is what Liss, Sondheim and others have in mind when they talk about ‘living as if’. But what they don’t seem to get is the sense of the experience – the feeling, the ‘taste’ – which is what makes a place ‘place’. When you’re in a new place, you encounter things in succession, and that’s what happens when you’re in a new moment. When you’re in a dappled light, or in a new situation, things happening at the same time, it’s called ‘complex motion’. And that’s where the synapses meet</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home, you’re keeping score – we’re all on the same page, we’re all experiencing the same kind of thrill, and there’s no such thing as ‘fast approaching disaster’. The word ‘episodic’ comes to mind, because it’s a temporal thing, and what I like to call ‘the ‘episodic’ condition, where the occurrence of a thing is marked by conditions that happen repeatedly and unpredictably (sometimes beautifully, sometimes destructively). For instance, I like to think of the event that I curated in Biennale 2018 as being an ‘episodic’, since its occurrence coincided with the publication of a book that I have co-written with my colleague, Juliana Engberg, called Staging Athens. In the book, we explore the conditions that allowed this particular event to happen, and we suggest a number of actions that might be taken in the future to</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home, when something new happens, you’re also keeping score: when did that happen? And when will that happen again? ‘When’ doesn’t always mean when, and often times, it doesn’t even happen again. So when we do encounter something new, whether it’s in a different form of media, whether it’s a different kind of art, whether it’s a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a different kind of religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home, we’re saying that there’s a very real and present sense of ‘this is happening all over again’. It’s as if something has happened in the past, and we have this sudden access to the past. This is a particularly beautiful aspect of the artwork, which is a very powerful way to think about things. For example, one of my colleagues, Yvonne Rainer, did a remarkable thing with a photograph of a river called the Mersey. She put a life-size bronze statue of a river patron in the river, and a life-size bronze statue of a patron in the river itself. The statue of the river patron was commissioned by Liverpool Biennial, and the bronze by Liverpool John Moores Special Collections. The statue of the river patron was commissioned by RCA, and the sculpture by Tate. The statue of a Liverpool John Moores Special Collections officer was commissioned by National Museums Liverpool, and the officer was paid for by</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home, when you encounter a new piece of media, whether it’s the video, the audio recording, the web page, the blog post, the news narrative, the opinion, the plaudits, the brouhaha, the on-stage show and the brouhaha-like backstage gatherings that follow, you’re doing it on a different level than when you first encountered it.And when you encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a different kind of religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with the thrill of discovery. When you encounter something new, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with the thrill of discovery.So, if you’</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home, the very first time you encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a different kind of language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what we do with the ‘real’, that which comes from the real, that which is real, that which is experienced. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a different kind of religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what we do with the ‘</text>
    <text>The disastrous 2021 Biennial. Image courtesy of the artist.

The notion of contemporaneity, or the act of contemporaneity, is what gives us the thrill of discovery. When we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new language or a different kind of religion, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. And that’s what happens when we encounter something new, whether it’s a different kind of media or form of art, whether it’s a new religion or a different kind of language, whether it’s the beginning of a different era in which things are different, we can identify with that moment in time, when things that seem novel and different suddenly … come true. So, if you’re keeping score at home, you’re keeping score with the artist, you’re keeping score with time, and you’re keeping score with the universe.But what if, as the late great Slavs and Tatars Len ‘Crime and Punishment’s Herman Melville writes, ‘The longer you keep on convicting yourself, the more you’ve lost your mind?’ And so we’re reminded of what a prison feels like: what a cycle of incarceration, apparent or otherwise.In the case of the Biennial, the apparent – or imaginary – sense of contemporaneity with its emphasis on incarceration allowed the Biennial to circumvent its true subject matter, which is usually photography, in order to focus on the symbolic meaning of a specific event, figure, or set of objects. In this sense, the image it presents is not really an image, but a sequence of images, each one a representation of a specific event, and thus the event, the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and arts-policy wonks at the Ciudadana del Fuegian, founded in 2015. I think it is a great opportunity to engage with the question – what is meant by the word Artificial Intelligence? What does it mean to make art? What is meant by ‘deep learning’? What is meant by the emergence of new media? What is meant by the new architecture? What is meant by the new construction? These are the kinds of questions that can lead to new kinds of art.I think that in the twenty-first century it is still possible to come across as utopian, even dystopian, the dystopian possibilities of the new AI. But I don’t think that is possible anymore. We’ve all seen the headlines; machine learning and big data are the new buzzwords. And there are signs that these terms are starting to have some kind of negative connotation, as in the case of the derogatory term ‘neoliberalism’, which starts</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and arts-policy wonks headed by Ana Laura Lopéz de la Torre, who will lead this group through its development and through its deployment in the city. Along the way, they will encounter some of their fellow travellers, meet interesting new people and explore some of the baggage that has been placed in front of the AI.This two-day, two-programming engagement, ‘Expo Rio 2016’ will bring together some of the most important figures in the field of Exhibitions and Curating – José Manuel Jarazalta, José Manuel López de la Torre, Muriel Otero, María Luisa Martín, Dominique Strauss-Kahn and Barbara Koch – to explore how their contribution to the field can be contextualised and what kinds of capacities these artists hoped to build for the city. Featuring work from many artists, including new and established artists alike, this two-day event will also see the participation of a small but</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and architects who will contribute to what is planned to be a new generation of museums and institutions in the same way that Vargas da Silva, Carlos Cruz, José Alberto Gutiérrez-Dubín, Álbio Nascimento and Marco Beltrami-Quinta have collaborated with Jim Henson and Tony Awards-winning artist Alison Hewitt. The project is being organised by the Museo de Arte Contempora [1] and is being led by the Architektur [2] and the Museum of Modern Art (New York). It is being co-ordinated by MUDE and the Federation of Brazilian Museums (Ce Brasil).The project has been shortlisted for the Turner Prize, Guggenheim Foundation, Tate Modern, Tate Britain and Tate America Prize, and won both the Brazilian and the US, as well as being named one of the Top Ten Architecture Projects of the XXth International Architecture Conference. It was also shortlisted for</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and art historians who will contribute to a new generation of biennial exhibitions and collections. We are deeply inspired by the resilience, creativity and innovation of these artists, curators and art historians, who are bringing to the fore ideas and practices that were once considered 'lost in translation' amongst artists, curatorial and arts history.We want to witness and engage with these ideas, so we’ve commissioned a series of projects that span the philosophical, political, social and economical dimensions. In no way do we wish to substitute for the engagement, knowledge and values of an informed and engaged audience, nor for the expertise, skills and commitment of an artist-curator team. However, we do believe that this engagement is critical for the further development of our shared values and the building of a stronger and more sustainable biennial programme. Building an Interdisciplinary Art GalleryCommunityTowardsAn Art and Culture of TransfigurationGabriela RendonUma Bonita MontoyaJuan José Cuerv</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and art producers, which will make the curatorial role more dynamic and individualised. This is the curatorial role of the artist, that is, in relation to the society that is becoming more accessible, not necessarily in relation to what is being done in the public galleries or museums. The new generation of artists, curators and art producers is being trained not to be content with what is being offered them, but to demand better and to strive for better.This is the role of the artist, that is, in relation to the society that is becoming more accessible, not necessarily in relation to what is being done in the public galleries or museums. The relationship between the gallery and the nation is developing, and in the age of the nation state, the gallery is the node of the social reproduction. The gallery becomes a political laboratory, a place where social processes that would otherwise be invisible or subservient to the interests of the few people who control the purse strings are manifest, where phenomena of this</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and artists, who will work in the new art world, built on the wreckage of the past.7 These initiatives are being organised under the codename Projections, which was previously occupied by a number of commissions.8 The codename reflects the fact that, at the same time, they are being proposed as alternatives to the old curatorial practice, which is suffering from a numerical malleability and a deindustrialising bias. The interventions proposed by the new generation of artists, curators and artists are being framed as replacements for what is perceived as a lost curatorial quality. The intervention proposed by the old curators is being institutionalised in the curatorial ritual and will continue to be so. Although the codenames suggest a change, the real innovations and initiatives envisaged by the young artists, curators and artists are being initiated at an accelerated pace. The interventions proposed by the curators in relation to the current situation are being pinned on a succession of previous interventions and are thus seen as a</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and art teachers at the Victoria and Albert Museum. The group will share a historic space on the museum grounds alongside artists from the National Gallery, Tate Modern, Tate Britain, and many more.In the coming years, the museum will host a number of events that invite artists to develop and explore new ways of working with the archive. Some of the invited artists, including Jane Morris, Joasia Krysa, Rebecca Malamund, Emma Hart, Rainerich Hartmann, and many more will return. The inevitable question will be: how will the exhibition be organised? The answer will be: ‘how can the archive support the artist’s ideas in a meaningful way?’ The answer to that will be: ‘archive.org supports the archive by making content available online through various services, including audio and video recordings, maps, PDFs, articles and publications, as well as hosting a number of archived events and hosting a number of online courses in archives and history. The</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and art educators in the historic neighbourhood of MOCAD. The programme will address the roles and identities of the emerging generation of artists, including those from the areas of innovation and experimental art, who are engaged with questions of identity, migration, art and culture. The programme will also consider the possibilities for the future of this dynamic, dynamic region. The original conception of the Biennale as an annual urban event has changed in relation to time and space. It will no longer be confined to major museums and art institutions, but will also include non-museum cultural institutions, such as community gardens, youth clubs, youth organisations and cultural institutions, as well as online non-museum cultural institutions, such as DIY (Direct From Nowhere), an organisation that promotes art making online through self-guided painting and design projects, as well as museums and other art galleries.The programme will be developed through a curatorial council, which will consist of representatives of the museum, the local Chamber of Commerce, the</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and architects, formed from the disparate disciplines of architecture, design, urbanism, architecture and media. They will work with the organisations that have been devising strategies to support artists' communication with the future, and to explore the possibilities of what this might mean in a larger cultural context. For more information, see: http://www.designinspire.org/en/?p=152&amp;section=Design+Infrastructure+Infrastructure.1#sthash.3C0YWX5M-aL.dpuf.98b.9EZaDeU.dpuf.98b.9EZaDeU.dpuf.98b.9EZaDeU.dpuf.98b.9EZaDeU.dpuf.98b.9EZaDeU.dpuf.98b.9EZaDeU.dps.99Design is an infrastructure that supports, enables, or is at least</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In some cases, this could be seen as a relationship between art and technology, or between art and social media, or between art and nature. In other cases, it could be seen as a relationship between curating and colonialism. However, the relationship between art and technology has recently begun to be questioned. In the age of the AI, what is meant by Artificial Intelligence? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to art? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to nature? What is meant by Artificial Intelligence in relation to life?Over the past few years, a number of artists and curators, including Sebastián Sanromán, Juan Pablo Galán, Álbio Nascimento, Álbio Nascimento-Quinta, Luisa Durán, Rafael Cardoso-Dubín, Ana Laura López de la Torre and Juan José Cuervo, have been invited to join a new generation of artists, curators and art-historians at the prestigious Instituto de Vision, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. The programme is the outcome of a year-long collaborative project between the Instituto de Vision, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, and ARTE, Buenos Aires, Argentina. The artists, curators and art-historians will share a laboratory and workspace, but they will also collaborate on research projects in the city. The project is led by the Institute for Contemporary Art, Buenos Aires, Argentina.I ask: what will be the role of an artist in the new generation of artists, curators and art-historians?DDownload this article as PDF27 October 2014To Maria Hlavajova12 July 2014Bologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouPreviousNextBologna ArcadesImage courtesy Christos TheodorouMaria HlavajovaUtrecht, NetherlandsBerlin, Germany12 July 2014Dear MariaThanks for your presentation at the International Biennial Association convention Why Biennial</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
