<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced
    <text>present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  The idea was that the community would assemble from various libraries, community centres and schools to read the books side by side, making them part of a single historical narrative. By reading the books in turn, the initiative would reveal the many layers of the city’s literary past.  The idea was that the community would assemble from various libraries, community centres and schools to read the books side by side, making them part of a single historical narrative. By reading the books in turn, the initiative would reveal the many layers of the city’s literary past.  The proposal quickly went viral on social media platforms such as Twitter and Tumblr. It was argued by some that the books would ‘present’ the same as the images, while others maintained that the participatory reading would present a different set of experiences. The debates, which ranged from passionate to ludicrous, reflected the differences with varying degrees of lucidity. The proposals ranged from passionate to ludicrous, but none</text>
    <text>present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  At the time, this was still a nascent idea and diversity of subject matter (especially literary fiction) was new, so authors and their works were often taken under consideration, but much of what was published as fiction was actively excluded. This exhibition was a watershed event in the history of biopolitics, and its curatorial style, ornamentation and organised activities mark the boundary between literary language (published or in process) and actual language. It heralded a new epoch in biopolitics, one in which literature no longer constituted the sole arbiter of meaning and identity, but was instead a symbolic site of encounter and encounter only ‘the writer’ could make known.1  Gabrielle Royce Taylor, The Biennial Condition (New York: New Vessel Press, 2013),p.10.  See also, for example, Catherine Hall, ‘On Writing and Uncertainty’, in Writing and Uncertainty: Essays on the Bi</text>
    <text>present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers chosen at random from among these image galleries. Readers would be invited to a reading/discussion about the selected books and the images sourced from the project in the various formats of the room, including print, audio and video. Readers would be invited to a reading/discussion about the selected books and the images sourced from the project in the various formats of the room, including print, audio and video.  Readers would be able to select any book from the top five, or any combination of the five best-sellers from the last book in the series, and the books would be presented in chronological order from the first to the fifth. They would also be able to select from among the images sourced from the project, and the project would select images based on the authorship of each image. Readers would be able to choose any image from the project's online gallery of more than 6,000 images</text>
    <text>present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  The idea was to create a platform that invited readers to contribute to the making of the platform, while facilitating the ultimate distribution of the printed books and images by linking the two entities.  In the case of a no-best-of, the texts and images were arranged in a set of related works. The idea was to create a platform that invited readers to contribute to the making of the platform, while facilitating the ultimate distribution of the printed books and images by linking the two entities.  The platform was an amalgamation of over‐the‐top promenades, colorful street names and a general ―well, urban feel.  The platform was an act of aggregation, of ideas colliding to form an integrated whole.  The idea was to allow the users of the platform, not necessarily the authors, to define the terms and conditions of the platform; to let the users define the terms and conditions of the platform and thereby to foster, as much as possible, inter</text>
    <text>present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  Authors were invited to submit an outline for the book that they would publish as a ‘work in progress’ – a document that would expand throughout the year as new ideas and styles emerged. Authors were invited to submit an outline for the book that they would publish as a ‘work in progress’ – a document that would expand throughout the year as new ideas and styles emerged.  The outline would form the basis of a future book, but it would also form the basis of a future exhibition, a public space that would evolve over time, a ‘temporal register’ that captured and documented the temporal conditions of the present, and a fiction that would seek to convey the mystery and magic of time in a way that the present could not. The goal of the project was to create a hybrid form of what M. W. Brown describes as ‘transcendent forms’: monumental edifices that function in and through space and</text>
    <text>present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  The idea was that a no-best-of or a best-of would be a natural next step in the process, but in the unlikely event that a manuscript was eventually written or an image produced, it would be an anthology of sorts, a ‘book for the occasion’.  The problem with the present is that when the author or publisher dies, the collection either goes unrecorded or under-recorded.  The problem with the present is that when the author or publisher dies, the collection either goes unrecorded or under-recorded.  The problem with the past is that changes in economic conditions or societal pressures often force a collection back into the public domain.  The problem with the future is that some might choose to republish collections in a social or artistic context, and these collections might then lack the resources or imprint needed to support a continued publication.  To address this potential loss of authorial intent and to reflect on the collection as an ongoing</text>
    <text>present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  The online component of the project emerged as a response to the lack of access to reading materials in urban areas. It was an opportunity for readers to ‘petition’ and ‘arrest’ themselves as readers and online critics of their chosen city.  The inclusion of critical ideas and analysis online facilitated a kind of community’s ‘backlash’ against the dominance of a particular form of urbanity. It invited people to ‘think differently’ and create new ways of looking at the city. The inclusion of art and aesthetic practices online facilitates a kind of community’s ‘rejection’ of the prevailing mode of urbanisation. It invites people to ‘think differently’ and create alternative urbanities.  The community’s ‘top-down’ approach to the ‘bottom-up’ transformation of urban environments through planning, education and art was a kind of resistance. It invites people</text>
    <text>present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a ‘best-of​', the five books selected for publication were arranged in chronological order from ‘A to Z’ in a package labelled  	Best of 2017. The images were taken from the project website and featured in a story by artist /u/chrisangelbix included in the book, ‘10 Books That Changed The World’. The images were taken from the project website and featured in a story by artist /u/chrisangelbix included in the book, ‘10 Books That Changed The World’.  The /r/books subreddit was established 11 months before the publication of the no-best-of, best-of, or best-of, but seems to have been a place for readers to post questions and comments about the book/magazine format, literary forms, and the publishing process. The /r/books subreddit seems to have been a place for readers</text>
    <text>present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  The initiative was conceived by the publishing house Macmillan Publishers and was co-financed by the Birmingham Biennial and Arts Council England. The project was designed by Macmillan Publishers and the Arts Council England and brought forward by artist Sally Tallant.  The project was conceived by the publishing house Macmillan Publishers and the Arts Council England and brought forward by artist Sally Tallant.  The project was conceived by the publishing house Macmillan Publishers and the Arts Council England and brought forward by artist Sally Tallant.  The project was conceived by the publishing house Macmillan Publishers and the Arts Council England and brought forward by artist Sally Tallant.  The project was conceived by the publishing house Macmillan Publishers and the Arts Council England and brought forward by artist Sally Tallant.  The project was conceived by the publishing house Macmillan Publishers and the Arts Council England and brought forward by artist Sally Tallant.  The project was conceived by the publishing house</text>
    <text>present an online project through which readers could nominate their friends for inclusion in a future issue of /r/books. The top five books chosen would be published simultaneously online and in print. The idea was to have the top five books chosen at random and then readers could nominate their friends. The idea was to have the top five books chosen by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books. The idea was to have the top five books selected by a community of readers and then invited to a reading/discussion about the books.  In the case of a no-best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘whitepaper’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  In the case of a best-of, the books were distributed across several libraries in and around Birmingham and presented as a ‘book​/​image gallery’ alongside a selection of text and image collections sourced from the project.  The idea was to celebrate the localness of the collection, while at the same time embedding a literary and/or visual commentary on the local environment into the collection.  The selection process invited artists, curators, artists' groups, writers, photographers and others with a curatorial or architectural background to contribute to the curatorial 'kitchen' of ideas and images that would form the basis for the exhibition. The collection was comprised of over 200 objects, of which over 100 were selected from the exhibition.  The final design included over 200 objects, of which over 100 were selected from the exhibition.  The first part of the exhibition, entitled  	Inside Out, opened at the U.S. Holocaust Memorial Museum in October 2014 and was presented in Venice in March 2015.  The Dutch feminist artist Caraal Fischer was invited to contribute to a project about the displaced and homeless communities of Venice, Italy. She traveled to Venice in 2014 with her artist husband</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vault
    <text>future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vault as a vehicle to address an issue that has been simmering for decades: the effect of institutionalised religion on a community of citizens returning to their place of origin. In the words of the artist, ‘I put everything in the vault, and then some. And then some more. And then, well, everybody sits around a big, empty board game and has a laugh’.[3] 	[4] 	Returning to the Church is a meditation on the effects of religion on communities in the local area.[5] The work is a ‘rejection’ of the monastic forms of religious authority and the hierarchical structures of power that are typically associated with them, and the weight of the consequences that can entail. It is a meditation on the inherent inauthenticity of such power, and the desperate necessity of coming to terms with the changed forms of community that beset this once eminent site. It is a reminder that power, in its various guises,</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vault of the Australian National Portrait Gallery as a temporary venue for a series of five-minute video messages. The installation, which was judged a success by the Australian and International Portrait Musings, became the subject of a 2014 Australian documentary about the geopolitics of port, which starred Leonardo DiCaprio as an Australian bureaucrat who leads a team of diplomats in Canberra tasked with convincing the U.S. government to reclaim the images of the missing bayonets. 	[3] As Terry Smith explains, ‘The vault is the site of a secret police station, interrogation chambers and archives. It is a place of censorship, and beyond that, the abject.’[4] 	[5] If the vault is the site of a secret police station, then the gallery is the abject. As Terry Smith explains, ‘[T]he abject is a concept that has many objects and representations – a particular abject is a particular image of a thing</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vault of the Australian National Portrait Gallery as the gallery’s permanent art-historical collection. Assembled by artist duo The Creators, the installation included artefacts from the collection of Australian War Memorials, and was viewed by over 3,000 people, including Indigenous Australians, journalists, historians and artists. Lacy’s return to the curatorial, and to art-histories and art-institutes in which she was born and raised, is a reminder that there is much more to be discovered, and to be made, in the world than meets the eye. 	(Back to Contents) 3. The curatorial. Contemporary art has always been interested in the characteristics that make a curatorial gesture unique: the context in which it takes place, the author or editors who introduce it, and the process by which it is interpreted. However, the word ‘curatorial’ has recently been used synonymously with ‘knowledgeable by university officials�</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vault as a vehicle to question, in the words of the Australian historian Graham Kerr, ‘the character of institutional Christianity’ and the institutionalised state of silence surrounding the biblical story of creation. [3] 	[4] Kerr, The Selfish Gene, 1992, p.52. [5] Kerr, The Selfish Gene, 1992, p.52. [6] New York Times, 10 October 2012, http://www.nytimes.com/2012/10/11/us/politics/economy.html?_r=0. [7] New York Review of Books, 10 October 2012, p. A8.[8] Kerr, The Selfish Gene, 1992, p.52.[9] Kerr, The Selfish Gene, 1992, p.53. [10] New York Times, 16 November 2012, http://www.nytimes.com/</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vault for clerical purposes and incorporated religious imagery into modern architecture, was considered a counter to contemporary urbanism’s presumed secularising effects. However, Lacy’s project was criticised for its elitist tendencies, for its pre-internet social media practices and for its reliance on corporate funding. Contemporary art tends to struggle to generate the same kinds of critical responses in a cultural context. In this sense, the work of the curator, while valuable in its own right, is often underestimated or undervalued. 	[1] See http://www.culturetrip.com/cities/sydney/the-word-of-the-day/20170713-a-history-of-the-discovery-of-word-sydney.html. Accessed: 2 July 2015. 	[2] See http://www.brookings.edu/sustainability/2008_state_of_sydney.html. Accessed: 2</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vaulted ceilings and arched entryways as satellite locations for a religious experience, combining traditional and contemporary art styles. The project was written up in the Sydney Morning Herald as a ‘mom-and-pop’ move, a ‘pulp-filler’, a ‘rehearsing process’ that would later be superseded by a more robust ‘serious art project’ that addressed ‘the big picture’.[3] 	In her essay ‘Toward a Global Curriculum’, Nancy Lee Chang focuses on the ways that cultural capital, the production of meaning through meaning production, shapes and is shaped by globalisation. She develops several steps towards a ‘better understanding of cultural capital: the kinds of cultural capital that constitute the infrastructure of contemporary globalisation and that shape what can and cannot be done within it’s spaces and borders’.[4] As she points out, cultural capital exists to produce meaning through</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vault as a temporal base to examine the relationship between art and religion in contemporary society. While the installation itself is an act of return, it is the back story that allows the artworks to function as a kind of grace that overtakes the social. Rather than engaging with the surface, however, the work exploits the hidden by making visible the social. 	[3] 	[4] 	[5] 	[6] 	[7] 	[8] 	[9] The story of the Returned begins in 1882 in the small town of Bates, Vermont. There, an Irish settler named Lawrence John Muir returns to the site of his former settlement, which had been the home of two separate but related First Nations. Here he settles into a small traditional First Nations home called the Hukkeladehu, or Green Turtle House, which he names ‘Moo-Laddeeth’s House’. The two</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vault as a vehicle to question the institutionalised memory of the Bates House and Australian history, and in so doing, presaged a movement that gathered momentum and momentum alone, until its explosion in on-site suicide in 2015. [3] The contemporary curatorial measure of the potentially transformative potential of direct action in the arts, is that it floods the arena with artists, ideas, projects and works that can be challenged, questioned and – most vitally – presented in a way that resonates with as many audiences as possible. It is, in other words, the modern ­curatorial measure of actually being in the arena, engaging audiences and making work there.  	It is this measure – the measure of its potential – that the contemporary curatorial seeks to obscure, to render invisible, to render unnoticeable. It does not wish to be taken seriously, but because it is so feared, its true intent becomes obscured in favour of the objective of competing with each other in the marketplace of</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vault as a vehicle to question the role of the past in the service of the future. In this work, the objects deployed in the act of historical documentation are used to question the authority of the past in the interest of the privileged few. Assembled by a bipartisan team of volunteers including archival researchers, they included curators from the Museum of Modern Art, Harvard University, The Australian National Exhibition and the Australian Museum, as well as art dealers, collectors and journalists. Through a series of five-year cycles, the project has asked whether the material, symbolic and social props of the past can be utilised in the service of the future, and whether their return supports or undermines the notion of public separation between church and state. 	[3] 	[4] The Australian National Exhibition is the official curator of the Venice Biennale. In 2011, the Australian Museum organised the first edition of its website, with a video documentary of the proceedings, featuring behind the scenes glimpses of</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms of cultural exchange, through their intervention or inaction, through their habit of participating in an activity that is anonymous or unrepresentative of the world around them.[2] 	These cultural-political-ideological forms have come to dominate contemporary culture, and their proximity, in many contemporary art-histories, is emphasised. For example, the work of the late David Hockney, whose artworks often utilised the same iconography as the curators featured in the 2013 Commonwealth and Tate Modern curatorial profiles, is often cited as an example of curatorial activism. However, in a more recent example of contemporary art’s ­contemporary aestheticisation, the work of Australian artist Patty Lacy is set against the backdrop of a Sydney church to create a hybrid art/religious edifice that exploits the familiar tropes of conservative Christianity and liberal democracy. Lacy’s 2010 installation, Returning to the Church, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historic vault as a platform to question the historical practices of the Bates House and the church, and to celebrate the lives of those who have been forced to leave it. Her 2010 installation,  Returning to the Bates House, which utilized artefacts from the Bates House archive, used the historical vault as a platform to question the historical practices of the Bates House and the church, and to celebrate the lives of those who have been forced to leave it. 	[3] Or as David Slater puts it in his introduction to the 2015 edition of the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists: ‘Britain’s first and so far only atomic test ever detonated 40,000 metres away from where the site of the present-day Adelaide Palace Hotel stands.’[4] Slater is blunt: Britain’s first and so far only nuclear test ever detonated somewhere on Australian soil is proof enough that nuclear weapons don’t belong in this world anymore. 	[5] Australian historian</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New
    <text>might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New York City. His latest project, published in 2017, is the book The Polymath: On Writing and Unwriting Modernity, in which he investigates the philosophical and historical roots of modernity. He is the recipient of several awards and boasts a best-selling autobiography.His work has been shown at the Venice Biennale, The New Museum, Tate Modern, Kunsthalle Zu?rich, and Kunsthalle DT, Berlin. He has written for the New York Times, the Guardian, and the Nation. He is a regular panelist on the online radio show, The Knowledge Project, and was a presenter of the public television show, Knowledge is Power.He was recently appointed as Curator of Participation at the New Museum, New York, USA where he will work with the artists Alexandra Carruthers and Adam Archambault on a project exploring the cultural impact of the Biennale of Sydney in 2017.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi</text>
    <text>might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New York City. He is a curator for the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, and part of the curatorial team for the forthcoming 7th Istanbul Biennale, which will take place in autumn 2016. His work has also been part of the curatorial team for the New York Philharmonic’s 30th Biennale of Music, which is currently running in New York and London. He is the editor of black-note.com, a web publication focused on black music, about African music.Download this article as PDFRyan AventRyan Avent is an architect, urbanist and Principal in the office of the New York City comptroller. Before that he worked at the New York Times as a newspaper architecture critic, writing about the practices and ideologies of urban renewal in the boroughs around where the World Trade Center once stood. His articles have appeared in the Times, the Guardian, The New York Times Digital Age, The</text>
    <text>might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New York City. He is also the co-editor and co-founder of The North Star, a national online literary journal. His writing has been featured in The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New York Times Travel section, The New York Times Higher Education section and numerous other publications. His latest book, The Contemporary Condition: Art, Politics, Regimes, and Contemporaneity was published by NYU Press in September 2016. What Is Contemporary Art?Thomas WaughJussi Parikka and Allan SekulaOver the past decade a half-dozen exhibitions have been mounted in New York and Los Angeles, some of which have been described as ‘contemporary art’ in their venues.1. Exhibition at Tate Modern and the Tate Modern Collection, New York, June 2014. 2. Exhibition at Arsenale Los Angeles, September 2013. 3. Exhibition at MoMA Arsenale, November 2013.</text>
    <text>might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New York City structures to celebrate the emergence of language as a medium of public action in the United States. His work has also been shown at the Venice Biennale, the Whitney Museum of American Art, and IDGAF, the Asian Museum of New York. He is the editor of The North Star, a local newspaper serving the surrounding boroughs, which was named one of America’s Best Local News Websites by Greater Greater Greater Washington. He is also the author of Learning to be an Architect: Rehearsing a New Architecture (with Derek Cholowski) and co-editor of the upcoming Redefining Art: Turn Up Charlie, a response to the Rodney Williams–Sonja Kuftinek song, ‘We Are Here to Stay’.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor of Geography at McGill University, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Research in Geography and the Environment. Her research interests include the social and</text>
    <text>might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New York, Canada, with contemporary art on the island. He is currently completing a PhD at McGill University, studying the archiving and complex archives of Canadian history. His work has been exhibited at the Greenleaf Gallery, the Museum of Modern Art, Toronto, and Delfina Foundation, Paris. He has written for CBC Radio's The Current, The Drummond &amp; The Blue, As It Happens, The Current, and The West, among many other outlets.He is a member of the faculty of McGill University’s Langara Institute for the Study of Radical Culture and the Director of the Delfina Foundation. His research interests include the social sciences, including feminist and queer theory; critical race theory and cultural studies; and the art and media economies of early modernity. He has lectured on radical cultures, including on postcolonial or post-indigenous writing and culture; and is currently researching the emergent social sciences and humanities of capital, globalisation and postcoloniality. He</text>
    <text>might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New York City. His work is also part of the collections of the Museum of Modern Art, the New York Public Library, the Museum of Contemporary Art, and the Museum of Modern Art, where he works in partnership with the Manhattan Museum of Art and the New York Public Library. His projects include the 2014 Pink Panther festival, a year-long investigation of violence and racism in the lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender (LGBT) community in American South Asian history; the 2015 Venice Biennale, a year-long series of public conversations on contemporary art and the lesbian, gay, bisexual and transgender (LGBT) community in the Italian city; the 2015 New York Public Library's (NYPL) first-ever Music, Art and Politics series, which looked at the links between art, activism and publics; and the 2015 New York Public Library’s (NYPL) first-ever New Media: Archive, a public series of online publications that catalogued and addressed the archive's diverse holdings</text>
    <text>might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New York City. He has also curated the 2014 Chicago Architecture Biennale, with Navid Markkulaaraas, Tiziana Terranova, and Daniela Ginsburg, as well as the 2014 Bangkok Biennale, with Tan Sudarshan and Anand Moghaddam. His photography and video work has been featured in numerous books, including the 2014 New York Times best-seller The City of Ruins, by Joshua Clover, and the 2015 New York Times best-seller The Village of Deena, by Amina Endsawi. His work has also been exhibited at the Venice Biennale, the Whitney Museum of American Art, the Asian Museum of Modern Art, the London and Taipei Muséum jnr., and various other venues, including the 2008 Venice Architecture Biennale, the New York Public Library, and the American Museum of Modern Art. He is the recipient of multiple awards and has lectured on a wide range of subjects, including urban history, postcolonial</text>
    <text>might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New York City’s colonial pasts and present in an effort to bring renewed awareness of the city’s many historical injustices. Parikka was one of the first film crews to film on Manhattan’s West Side Highway, where the 2013 Tribeca Film Festival was held. He has worked with filmmaker Scott Ronald Miller on the project, Stages, which premiered at the Venice Biennale in 2013 and will premiere at the Venice Architecture Biennale in 2015. Jussi Parikka is the Curator of Tract Society at the Art Institute of Chicago, where he has curated several exhibitions including the 2014 Chicago Reader’s Short Documentary of the Year, Short Documentary of the Century and Documenta 13. In 2015, he collaborated with filmmaker Christiane Paul and was a curator in residence at the Victoria and Albert Museum. He is the Alon Schwartz Professor of Art and Cultural Theory at Columbia University and holds a variety of other positions at the institute. Prior</text>
    <text>might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New York City’s colonial pasts and the current threats to democratic rights and cultures in the city. His latest project, published in 2016, is the book A People’s State: Performance and Politics in an Uncertain World, edited by Adam Szymczyk and Colin Ward, that looks at the potentialities of performance and politics of everyday life for the future of the city.Parikh: You’ve spoken about the importance of a critical and public understanding of what happens in the city, and how that informs our thinking and action. What’s been left out of the equation for many people in the US and elsewhere who don’t have the tools or knowledge to question or question urban and urban infrastructure or the socio-economic systems that shape them? Why are these questions not part of the conversation?JB: I think it’s really important for artists to have access to critical discourse and creative agency. And I think that for many people, particularly those</text>
    <text>might be curated by P. Sudhakaran, director, Indian Museum of Modern Art, New York. The museum is on the corner of 5th Avenue and California Street in Manhattan. It opened in November 2013, and the project was part of the exhibition, The Contemporary Condition, of the Art and Culture Museum, 2013, which also featured M. Karunaratnam’s work. He has written on art and culture for the New York Times, the Guardian, the Nation, and many other publications. He is the host of the weekly Art Tape podcast.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is a filmmaker and writer. His work centers on the urban and the complex, exploring the intersections of power, culture and society. His films include the 2013 Venice Architecture Biennale, The Island of Manhattan (2015), about a small community of artists living and working on Manhattan Island, and the 2014 Silent Spring festival, which brings together early democratic and colonial New York City landscapes, including the former site of the National Zoo. He is the co-curator of the 15th Istanbul Biennale, scheduled for 2019. He is the editor of Digital Urban Future (DUFI) – New Media Research Center, a journal published by the organization that appointed him as a Senior Editor in 2016. His work has been featured in publications such as Wired, The Guardian, The New York Times, The New York Daily News, and The Washington Post, among other outlets. He has also been a regular panelist on the popular science/technology show &quot;Top Gear&quot;, and was a judge on the popular children’s TV show &quot;The Amazing World of Gumball&quot;.Download this article as PDFMichelle DezemberMichelle Dezember is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was resident scholar at Art Linkletter, an arts and heritage resource center for the Lower Manhattan Migrant Land Trust. Her work is currently based in several communities in the Central</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Muse
    <text>present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Museé, Toronto; and Brent Bellamy, Curator of Art and Society at the University of Alberta, Director, Royal Arts Museé, Calgary.These artists have been integral and creative in developing and supporting the project, and it is with great pleasure and pride that we tell the story of their involvement and contribution to the exhibition. They have been extraordinarily generous in their time and resources, and have enabled us to tell our story publicly, making it part of the public sphere and making it part of the institutional record. But we couldn’t be more different artists and we are both artists and curators with different kinds of work, and so this commission was different from any other. It wasn’t a commission from the National Gallery of Canada, it wasn’t a commission from the Royal Arts Museé, and it wasn’t a commission from the Chapman’s Fund. Each agency had their own point of entry into the project, and</text>
    <text>present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Museums, Toronto; Joasia Krysa, Curator of Entomology, Welsh Streets Gallery, Dorset, D2017; Devinder Bhadwal, Curator, DVCA, Toronto; Ella Gibbs, Artistic Director, Museum of Contemporary Arts, Toronto; Maxime Richard, Artistic Director, National Gallery of Canada, Ottawa; Ellen Weibel, Artistic Director, National Gallery of Canada, Vancouver; Gareth White, Artistic Director, National Gallery of Canada, Ottawa; Brent Bellamy, Curator, Royal BC Museum, Vancouver; Samantha Jones, Artistic Director, Royal BC Museum, BC, Canada; Polly Tallant, Artistic Director, Royal BC Museum, BC, Canada; Chandran Janak, Artistic Director, National Gallery of Canada, Ottawa and Catherine Forster, Artistic Director, National Gallery of</text>
    <text>present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Museums Association; Rafico Ruiz, Curator of Public Art for the War Memorial Institute, and Professor in the Department of Communication Studies and the Art Centre, University of Alberta.  The team was assisted by researchers from the U of A’s School of Communication and Culture, as well as the Institute for Contemporary Art, where Paul Mathews is a professor.  The exhibition was presented in the War Memorial Institute building, with support from the Institute and the National Gallery of Canada.  The war memorial institute is a non-profit, non-governmental organization established in 1994. It is an independent, not-for-profit public research and educational centre that supports the making of art through the delivery of culturally responsive services and the establishment of arts educational networks. It is also a regional arts organisation, operating internationally through partnerships with regional and territorial arts commissions.  Its mission statement is titled: ‘To support the art process through</text>
    <text>present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Museums, Canada Research Chair, Government and Humanities, and Professor in Art History, Mississauga University’s Department of Art History and Art Practice, and was assisted by Nadine Attewell, Art Historian, with expertise in art and social theory, and Lisa Stewart, Art Historian, with a special interest in nineteenth-century contemporary art. The National Gallery of Canada and Royal Arts Museums are the primary curators for the exhibition, followed by Transcendental Gallery, Toronto, with a number of local artists taking part in the Chosen Collection. The artists and their curators were P. Krishnamurthy, Vanessa Boni, S. Krishnamurthy, Nadine Attewell, Curator, Royal Arts Museums, Canada Research Chair, Government and Humanities, and Paul Mathews, Art Historian, with a particular interest in nineteenth-century contemporaneity and social theory. The</text>
    <text>present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Museums, Canada Research Chair in Art and Design, RADM (Research Chair in Art and Media Design) and Director, CALDE (Director of Public Art) respectively.  Its mandate was expanded on in the 2013 National Gallery of Canada Trustees Report, in which the Faculty of Arts &amp; Science is cited as being particularly proud. The 2013 Report also recognizes the significant achievements made in the field of art and culture in Canada over the past decade. The Honourable Mary Dawson, President and CEO, National Gallery of Canada receives the 2014 Columbia Arts Prize for Cultural Capture. The team was led by Artistic Director Lesley Stewart Dawson and included Senior Curator Ameena Atiq, Professor in Modern Art History at Granby Four Streets Community College (U’Mista, USAS) and Director Kelvin Grove School of Art, University of Alberta, Canada. Ameena Atiq, director of the</text>
    <text>present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Museums, Canada Research Chair, University of Alberta Libraries, and a former Curator in the Institute of Contemporary Arts, Canada Research Chair, Royal BC Museum, and a former Curator at Meehan Scott Collection, Toronto, Canada Research Chair, Welsh Streets Museum, and a former Research Associate at the Institute of Contemporary Arts, Canada Research Chair, Welsh Streets Museum and a former Curator at the Royal BC Museum, Canada Research Chair, Royal BC Museum, and a former Curator at Meehan Scott Collection, Toronto, Canada Research Chair, Welsh Streets Museum, and a former Research Associate at the Institute of Contemporary Arts, Canada Research Chair, Royal BC Museum, Canada Research Chair, Welsh Streets Museum and a former Research Associate at Meehan Scott Collection, Toronto, Canada Research Associate, Institute of Contemporary Arts, Canada Research Assistants</text>
    <text>present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Museums Branch, and Chair, Mathews Institute of Art. Liz Sly, Artistic Director of the Royal Arts Museums, and former Curator of Contemporary Art at M.I.T. Dr. Eva Castringius, Curator of Art and Art History, and former Chair of the Royal Academy’s Board of Trustees, Tate Britain, who supervised the exhibition. The Royal Academy of Arts and Museums is the largest not-for-profit arts organisation in the world. It is a registered charity with a national board of trustees, a statutory statutory statutory parliamentary constituency and an annual budget of $585 million. Its mission statement  &quot;To celebrate the achievements of British and Commonwealth art, to maintain an open forum for debate and debate in the organisation’s walls, and to chart the course of cultural history’ is a statement of purpose shared between the organisation and its diverse stakeholders.  Art and artists’ engagement with the public</text>
    <text>present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Museums; Peter Iversen, Curator of Public Art for the Royal and Commonwealth Museums; Sandy Ross, Artistic Director of the Toronto Museums of Art and Architecture; Daphne Atangana, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada; Shannon Stewart, Artistic Director, National Gallery of Canada; Elena Kravtsov, Artistic Director, Royal and Commonwealth Museums; Ana Laura Lopéz de la Torre, Artistic Director, National Gallery of Canada; Polly Johnson, Artistic Director, Royal and Commonwealth Museums; Meehan Crist, Curator of Entomology Collections and Collections at the Royal and Commonwealth Museums; Janet McTeague, Assistant Curator, Royal and Commonwealth Museums; Kate Hudson, Assistant Curator, National Gallery of Canada; Emily Pringle, Curator,</text>
    <text>present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Museums; Patricia Tompkins, Curator of Public Art for the Victoria and Albert Museum, and Anne Meehan, Curator of Public Art for the M.E. and Ph.D. Marshall Sjoerdt, both with a focus on the Chiswick Arts Centre and the National Gallery of Canada.Download this article as PDFPatricia TompkinsPatricia Tompkins is a curator and writer with a curatorial practice that focuses on the arts and culture of North America and the Mediterranean. She is currently Head of Curatorial Affairs and holds a regional focus for the Centre National de Recherche en Anglophone de Montreal, Canada. Her publications include the Certificate of Authenticity of Art and Culture, The Artist as Artist (with Jillian Graham-Hughes and Peter Weibel) and the New Statesman, and has curated numerous exhibitions and publications around the world including the North American division of</text>
    <text>present an online project that investigates the relationship between the art of making and the online activity of art (and other social, economic and political) institutions. The project serves to interrogate the following: how art can be made available to facilitate the online activity of other cultural institutions; what this activity may be and how; and how this activity intersects with the social infrastructure of online cultural institutions.[1]  In this context, the project may also address the emergence of new media technologies such as social media, which are increasingly capable of constituting and enabling ‘new kinds of cultural practice’.[2]  The project was conceived by Fatma Al Sahlawi, a Ph.D candidate in Communication Studies and the Art of Making at the University of Alberta, and was co-chaired by H.E. Ryan Avent and Paul Mathews. Members of the team include: Grace Gatling, Curator of Public Art for the National Gallery of Canada, Director, Royal Arts Museums, Toronto; Richard Brookle, Curator, Royal Canadian Museum, Vancouver; Lynn Church, Artistic Director, Royal Arts Museums, Toronto; John Hudson, Curator, Royal Ontario Museum, Toronto; Maria Hlavajova, Artistic Director, Royal College of Art, New York; Vladislav Savrajevsky, Artistic Director, Kas a Kavkaz Museum, London; Claire Bishop, Artistic Director, Toronto; Meehan Crist, Artistic Director, Toronto; Samantha Jones, Artistic Director, Toronto; Karin Frank, Artistic Director, Toronto; Samantha Jones, Curator, Toronto; Karen Nygaard, Artistic Director, Toronto; Kari Weil, Curator, Toronto; Bryan Reilly, Artistic Director, Toronto; Tania Bruguera, Curator</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services.
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services.  The hybrid ‘agency and NGO’ structure could also support the development of culturally responsive local government programmes and arts educational institutions, with a particular focus on those cities with a significant and growing diaspora of international students and artists.  The agency would provide representation, education and outreach to a local audience through arts production and outreach, mapping, research and data collection, webinars and events, workshops and publications, and other supportive services.  The  hybrid ‘agency and NGO’ structure could also support the development of culturally responsive local government programmes and arts educational institutions, with a particular focus on those cities with a significant and growing diaspora of international students and artists.  The agency would provide representation, education and outreach to a local audience through arts production and outreach, mapping, research and data collection, webinars and events, workshops and publications, and other supportive services.  The hybrid ‘agency and NGO’ structure could also support the development of</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also work with an NGO to establish a cultural exchange and collaborate in creating and supporting a local arts education programme for local schools, universities and youth organisations.  A future Liverpool Biennial could establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environmental and heritage-sensitive urban environments through sharing best practices. This model would replicate the collaborative and equitable sharing of resources and expertise between the arts and non-arts sectors, while ensuring that the responsibilities and assets of the biennial would reside in a local art institution. This model would also enable the collaboration and equitability of resources between the cultural and the non-cultural sectors, while ensuring that the resources and assets of the biennial would reside in a local art institution.  A future Liverpool Biennial could establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environmentally responsive local economies through sharing best practices. This model would support the establishment of cooperative art institutions</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services. Creative collaborations could be developed with local partners to address specific cultural needs in the city.  The hybrid structure could also support the establishment of a ‘specialised cultural organisation’ capable of handling cultural emergencies, as defined by the then Minister for Culture, Stewart Singleton.4  The concept of homelessness is still controversial in the arts world, and artists are frequently accused of being trapped in consumption as a way to avoid responsibility.  The complexities of cultural production and consumption need to be understood in order to produce culturally responsive outcomes. Creative action is also needed to address the fact that most artists today are participants in a consumer culture that regularly engages with new media and social media, where ever they are.   A cultural commission, such as the one described above, could act as a catalyst that opens new perspectives and injects fresh ideas into the equation, encouraging artists to pursue artistic and curatorial projects that directly address current social needs and priorities. It could also form part of a larger artistic-</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services.  A citizen science programme could also be established to allow citizens to contribute to art’s productive process.  A public debate about the role of the arts in the city could also be formed, with artists and others invited to participate in a forum moderated by the city organiser.  The forum could also be created to allow residents and community members to submit questions or ideas, with a future plan to implement the forum as a collaborative research project.  The name ‘Liverpool Biennial 2020’ reflects a new direction in the project’s development, taking the form of a ‘mission statement’ that more fully describes the organisation’s current cultural priorities.  A new mission statement also introduces the fact that the Biennial will be headquartered in Anfield, rather than Liverpool, and adopts an ‘inclusionary’ principle that places a higher value on cultural tourism than on traditional ‘cultural tourism’.  An introduction to the organisation’s</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services. The name change could be made as part of the UK's EU accession negotiations.  Annotation:  A proposal to create a hybrid ‘agency and NGO’ is a step towards a new kind of urbanism, one based on the collaborative, equitable sharing of resources and the responsibilities for effective governance of resources. It is a welcome development that in the biennial format, resources are now shared equally between the artist and the audience, instead of having to be individually determined. However, the emergence of such a hybrid ‘agency and NGO’ is not a proposal or a solution in itself; it is an evolution of the institutional sharing of cultural resources. As the biennial format is now evolving, it is becoming increasingly important that resources, rather than be distributed globally, are shared between institutions and that sharing is collective and democratic. The biennial as a whole, rather than being the primary site of exhibition making, should assume that leading role.  A suggested model for future urban development</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services. The statutory framework for cultural institutions in the UK is the UK Human Rights Act 1988 and the Community Arts Act 1998, which grant artists broad rights to work with communities and offer protection from discrimination bylaws.[19] Annotation (John Hoban): ‘Creative perforations’ are ‘austerity measures’.  J.D. Dewsbury, ‘The Arts are Poorest: A Radical Performing of Time’, in  	The New York Times (14 March 2008), p. A9. oreAnd[20] See, for example, Timothy Noah and Karen Roy, eds.,  	The New Urban Frontier: Perforations from the Runoff, Third Press, New York, 1998.   1  See C.N. Bhargava,  	A Perforation of Time: Bhargava’s Perforations, Third Press, New York, 1986.   2</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services. The law relating to the prevention and combat of international migrant trafficking remains vague and ill-defined, making it difficult to know which form of organisation would be best placed to address a specific problem or issue in the city.  A future Liverpool Biennial could establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city. The law relating to the prevention and combat of international migrant trafficking remains vague and ill-defined, making it difficult to know which form of organisation would be best placed to address a specific problem or issue in the city.  A future Liverpool Biennial could establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city. As regards the form of homeless person, it is unclear what criteria an artist or organisation would use to screen out potential claimants from the city. It is also unclear how such a model would operate in a city with free and unrestricted entry to and from the city, as well</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services.  The new government and arts bodies could also establish partnerships with non-profit arts organisations to address cultural issues and attract artists and creative-team members.  The new collaborative framework between city, county, and state could also enable the creation of new arts-funded agencies, such as youth centres or arts foundations, which could in turn establish collaborative agreements with other stakeholders to implement the arts’ priorities.  The blending of disparate community agencies and non-profit arts organisations could maximise the involvement and impact of arts and cultural resources, while ensuring that resources are used in a way that is mutually beneficial to all.  The fact that government funding supports only a small proportion of arts activities could be addressed with the establishment of non-profit management companies, arts councils or other entities that own and operate venues, employ artists and other staff, and discharge other functions related to the establishment and maintenance of cultural venues.  The creation of non-profit management companies, arts councils or similar entities with broad powers could maxim</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services. The new entity could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  A city-wide cultural campaign focusing on art’s place in the city could create local momentum, attract art collectors and art-lovers to the city, and even build art-specific businesses and educational opportunities for artists and local communities. The campaign could be bolstered by a city-wide art fair and/or art’s fair every four years, as is currently the case, but could also set up studios for artist-directed projects.  A future Biennial could establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the UK and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping the city’s cultural landscape through a collaborative process that aligns with the city’s needs and values.  Such collaborations could work in coordination with local authorities, non-profit arts organisations and other stakeholders to achieve cultural objectives. The key to a successful outcome would</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial and its funding formula could be a model for the future of urban and regional development in the UK. It would create a dedicated fund for the arts, offering both financial support and curatorial independence for artists to work with local communities and artists to create engaging urban environments through engaging with local culture. The fund could also support artist-led initiatives designed to address cultural and community issues and attract artists to urban settings, including cultural centres.  A future Liverpool Biennial could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping environments in the city.  The funders of the project could also establish a ‘cultural commission’ to manage and direct the art’s activities, creating a hybrid ‘agency and NGO structure.  The cultural commission could establish cultural programming including but not limited to art galleries, public programmes, events, exhibitions, and promotional campaigns, while the NGO could establish ‘cultural homelessness’ through advocacy and helpline services. The new entity could also establish partnerships with other arts bodies in the region and beyond to share resources and collaborate in shaping the arts’ urban environment.   The word ‘community arts’ is frequently used synonymously with ‘community development –’ but does not always convey the whole truth. Community development is a strategy for supporting collective learning and development through arts and culture provision, and it is an inherently collaborative process. It is important to recognise that the development of a community’s arts capacity is itself a collaborative process that needs to be negotiated, so that the community does not become a passive recipient of arts resources.   A creative context for creating an arts education programme is critical for a community to gain access to resources and knowledge that would enable it to tackle real-life challenges facing the community.   A biennial, by itself, is not a panacea, but it is an important and growing component of a community’s cultural landscape. At the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space,
    <text>might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space, and the like are all tools for mapping out and space-taking (how to put it?). The artist Claude McKay famously stated the other ‘quarters’ of the Montréal site were reserved for tomfoolery: such as planting a flagpole on a whim or picking up a Japanese flag and depositing it under your Paris home. (Harvey, 2012)Moving images, movies, videos, ephemera, and the like are all ephemerals in their own way. They are ephemerales, or last-ditch attempts to hold onto something that has been rendered ephemeral or destroyed. But they are ephemerales – ephemeral in the sense of the ephemeral – and this makes them different from, or more potent, in the sense that they persist through the years. That is, they can have lasting characteristics, such as the presence of a particular fruit or vegetable, or a particular flower, or the presence of a particular human being</text>
    <text>might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space, and the like are of course also part of the museum's mission. Moving images, movies, video materials are part of the visual arts museum, along with sculptures and paintings. And although in their current formats they are artworks, they are also part of visual arts pedagogy. The museum is a visual arts museum insofar as it uses the tools of visual arts to make sense of the manifold, inchoate and inchoate spaces and processes that are now manifesting themselves in and across the planet. This is much more than might be expected from a relatively new museum, and it shows, for instance, how the exhibition of a new artworks – or an exhibition of old artworks, for that matter – can signal a new beginning or a fresh start in a relationship or a friendship.  Links to Other Museums   	Possible links to other museums, archives or other collection services that might be of interest to this website:  Museums of Modern Art, Tate Modern,</text>
    <text>might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space, and, above all, moving images – all of which are predicated on the real or perceived movement of things – are among the most essential and powerful spatial commodities of our culture. And yet, despite the real-time images, videos, audio materials and multimedia that characterize much museum and urban development around the world, and despite the critical reports and studies that frequently be published on such things, relatively few people around the world get to experience them. This is perhaps because of cultural taboos – reverence for the real, deep seated structures and ideologies that generate and justify modern urban growth and conflict, and a distaste for the idea of the outsider – but also because many people around the world have access to very little information or knowledge about the things that shape their cities. Most of the information that comes from academics and urbanists on the ground is filtered through the lens of whitewashed or simplified images of 'developed' urbanism. And in many cases, the whitewashing or simplifying of images</text>
    <text>might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space, and the like are all tools for mapping out spaces, or systems of space, in which we happen to be in. And the key to this kind of mapping out, or space-making, is in fact what the museum does. It is, however, much more powerful and nuanced than that. It is possible to produce accurate, precise parallaxes of images and video material through proper art education and scientific and technical know-how, but even then there is no guarantee that such images or videos will be of use to or with the community in which they are produced. The key is that the community puts in place appropriate strategies, and that the tools and knowledge are there for the community to use, to develop and to modify in order to reach their desired results. But this requires that the community put in place the organisational capacity and the technologies necessary to implement those strategies effectively. There is no shortcut to creating and maintaining a community based movement, and no one who attempts to make such a</text>
    <text>might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space, accurate projection of an image or graphic image onto a flat surface, precise tracking of objects, precise ‘pointing’ of the camera, precise tracking of the object tracked object, point clouding and shimmying, precise tracking of reflection and sound, precise tracking of wind and rain, sound pressure level and turbulence etc. etc. etc. etc. etc. etc. etc. etc. The more an artist understands of this kind of moving image, movie, or visual work, the more images or visual works that he can create that operate in this way – that employ the conventions, the ‘rules’, that govern what is meant by ‘the mass’ and thereby thereby thereby thereby undermine the pretensions of the artist as to his or her own unique genius.  In short, the more an artist understands and uses the conventions of the spatial constant, the more ‘graphic novels’ that he can produce that employ the conventions of the spatial constant, the</text>
    <text>might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space, precise alignments between planes of perception – moving images, movies, video materials – are a powerful tool for social, cultural and even political change, even when they are not physically put together or located in a particular location. When put together and located strategically, they can also be used to great effect.For instance, the Occupy Wall Street movement brought precise parallaxes and precise images to light in a way that no previous movement in the area could achieve. Images from the movement quickly spread around the country, and soon blogs were set up in almost every language on the web with images of people clearing out banks and buildings. Now, some blogs even talk about the art projects being done at the site, and the ‘occupy art’ hashtag being bandied about on Twitter. Blogs, including these by Wired UK, are a new breed of online publication. They post stories in a semi-randomised order, often from the same day, often from the same person. In the</text>
    <text>might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space, and the like are all tools for mapping and surveillancing. They provide specific spatial information that can be used to infer, predict, or change future spatial conditions – future urban growth, for instance, or future climate – or at least that can induce such action in planners and urban planners as to produce desired spatial effects. To some extent, then, the museum as museum becomes an object that can, through powerful visualization and manipulation, exert a power beyond the museum itself. It exerts a spatial presence that can be used to sublimate the real, real-life, or contemporaneous museum experience – in which the museum visitor is often unaware, or engages in practices that are not explicitly designed to be noticed – and to a degree that is often powerful. The museum is a contemporary urban artifact. It has entered the material world, and is therefore subject to its material world. But its power derives not only from its appearance, through which it is often made aware, but also in part, through</text>
    <text>might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space, and precisely calculating the relative sizes of things – all of these things are fundamentally about mapping and parallaxing (how to put it?). But images and movies and videos also have meanings that are relative to a particular historical moment in time – meanings that are dependent on the spatial relations of things at a particular moment in time. For instance, the image of the Togusa Riverboat in the new Metainterface (2016), an interactive media installation created for the Venice Biennale, is a perfect image of the Togusa Riverboat. It is an image that emerged from a conference about the place of art and culture in a changing urban landscape. At the conference, Wallace Stevens described how the installation emerged: &quot;A few people told me what an amazing idea the Togusa Riverboat was. They said it would do wonders in terms of setting an example and creating a sense of place. Within an hour of opening, a crowd of people had gathered to take part in a tour</text>
    <text>might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space, precise tracking of objects using GPS, precise 3-D modelling – these things are very powerful, and can be used to create spatialities quite unlike the pure physical spheres that characterise the museum. And they can be used to map things, to arrive at conclusions about space and objects that are not reducible to the particular place where the things or sets of things occur. For instance, the museum can produce a kind of critical mass, or ‘episodic’, that acts as a kind of inoculation against what it sees as the creeping privatising tendencies of commodification of space. The kind of critical mass that creates and relies on space, or more precisely, space dependent on things, is much more likely to be diverse and innovative and capable of new things arising from the museum’s collection.  	The museum as a site of encounter and encounter is a kind of radical memory, and the museum as a space for encounter is a kind of radical imagination. In these</text>
    <text>might be curated through, for instance, a public or a public museum. But the museum is a posteriori – it sets the stage, its language, its agenda. It provides a spatial foundation, but also a mental one. It offers a spatial equivalent to that of the street, but with objects that are of a different kind, of which the street is but one – objects that are of space, but with objects of a different kind, of which the museum is but one. The museum becomes a posteriori even more when it is dominated by, or even entirely dependent on, movement. The museum is especially prone to this kind of thing. But the ‘mass’ as a spatial constant, the constant, or more precisely, the relative positioning of things, objects, objects of space, in time, is a much more powerful tool for surveilling and mapping out (how to put it?). Moving images, movies, video materials, precise parallaxes, precise positioning of objects in space, precise capture and storage of images, precise movement of images – all these things are features of museum-going. They are, I think, essential to the museum-going experience (even if these things are also ways of constituting and projecting the experience of mass in otherwise itinerant ways).But what is the museum, and why are they essential? I think the answer is that the museum is positioned at the intersection of a temporality that is both spatial and temporalised (in a temporality that does not necessarily align with that of the real time, although it often does). The museum is both a real place and a prototypical image (or simulacrum). It is the prototype of a kind of real time that is neither here nor there – neither contemporary nor historical – the real (i.e. not fictitious) image of the temporality that is being contested (both physically and ontologically) by the contemporary (i.e. not imaginary) image.‘Imminent Domain�</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding
    <text>might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding facility for art’s activities. The challenge for the curatorial role today is to create environments in which art can be experienced in ways extrinsic to its structure, but also, as the museum has increasingly demonstrated, in ways that are inseparable from the structure itself. In other words, the structure’s destruction may be necessary in order to allow the art to develop or, alternatively, to prevent the art from developing but not in order to make it successful. It’s a difficult sell for a museum that, at the same time, depends on the almost continual renewal of its membership totalling millions of dollars a year.Curators’ role today is to deliver information, provide data, collect knowledge and, above all, make history. But what makes the structure of the museum different from other cultural institutions is that it leaves no stone unturned. If a curatorial approach is taken to the structure of the museum, it’s a pursuit of knowledge but also</text>
    <text>might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding facility for the arts community’s efforts. There is a strong sense of the museum as a collective endeavour, and the curatorial agenda is one of inclusion. In the 1980s and 1990s, however, the museum was much more like a place of encounter: it was a place to be found, and a set of objects to be photographed, to be discussed, and to be invited back. Today, the museum is a social enterprise: it’s a place of exchange, and it’s a platform where art is often presented as a commodity, often used as a recruitment tool for militants engaged in terrorist activities. It is deeply problematic for an institution like the museum, which was built to house culture, to suddenly become a repository for militant activity. As a cultural enterprise, the museum is in a bind. It can either cater to an audience of militants engaged in terrorist activities, or it can remain a place of encounter, used by and attracting to tourists engaged in a form</text>
    <text>might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding facility for art from the centre of London and the periphery – from there it’s possible that artists have found alternative exhibition formats or staged their own works in alternative venues. The museum is a fiction that, while it realises the cultural functions of the city, it lacks the conceptual capacity to implement them. It’s a fiction that, while it clearly establishes the city as the locus of cultural production, it lacks the power to manage the social conditions of cultural production. It’s a fiction that, while it clearly defines the cultural as belonging to the city, it lacks the power to address the conditions of cultural production outside the city. These three conditions – power, space and culture – are the thinnest veneers on which the social forms of cultural production can be socially constructed.These are the conditions that a social organisation like the museum has to meet in order to really inhabit the city: to actually exist. The museum is the most visible manifestation of social projects undertaken</text>
    <text>might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding facility for museum collections and exhibitions. It’s this idea of hard assets – money, art, space – that keeps the museum afloat, whereas the other factor that tends to crop up at the museum – the real estate market, the decline in value of art's share price, pure inflation – inevitably has a dampening effect on the value of art collections and exhibitions. But this doesn’t necessarily translate into wealth for the museum owners; it’s more of a tendency. The key is that the real estate market has to be nipped in the bud before it starts to affect the value of art collections and exhibitions. And here, the curators’ predicament is quite a logical extension of the historical one. As the affordability of housing and social housing has become a much more pressing concern, it’s no longer possible for many people to afford to live in the city, and the museum collections and exhibitions that were once prized are now in serious danger. The museum collection</text>
    <text>might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding trough for the financial struggles of artists and their management teams. It’s another reason why, during that same time, the museum has tended to produce auteur-like works – Tijuana Flow, Kurt Miala’s Wonderful World, Jonas Sjöberg’s Strictly Come Dancing, to name only a few. A museum like the Museum of Modern Art might exhibit a few paintings that are as inventive and powerful as these that are being made today. But it’s clear that, for an institution like the Museum of Modern Art to foster creativity and instigate a new way of looking at the world, it must be driven by people, people of all kinds, who are not hired because they have no business doing so.Art should be driven by people because it’s people, and art professionals by choice, because they’re the artists and they’re the lucky. But, in the museum or gallery, the museum and</text>
    <text>might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding facility for the arts community’s arts projects, while the arts district has mostly been a staging area for the community’s arts productions. The importance of the museum to the community has, in part, been deferred maintenance, as evidenced by the fact that, over the past 20 years, the density of use in the museum has exploded while its use has remained virtually the same. A museum that, once a week, holds a show about art’s place in the world today is more representative of the community’s cultural practices than a museum that, every two weeks, offers a literal show of art’s works.The second generation of artists, many of whom are now in their forties, are trying to draw a parallel between the rise of contemporary art and the decrease in violence and conflict that was occurring in the world at the same time. They are trying to see art as a dynamic agent that, as the term suggests, can and does mix with other valuable</text>
    <text>might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding place for art professionals and their clients. It gives the impression, without actually showing that impression, that the museum is a destination for art lovers only. It’s the role of the curator to create an environment in which art can thrive, and to provide the platform for that to happen. I think that’s what the museum is doing right now: providing the platform, but without really engaging with that. I don’t think that, in the future, the museum should be a destination for artists but rather the opposite: a place where art can thrive in interaction with other art forms and beyond its immediate context.I think that the museum is showing its age. As a destination for art, it’s no longer the ultimate measure of artistic productivity but rather a transitory construct, both in terms of its resources and its significance. The museum is a transient object of cultural value, and the art professionals who use it to get to where they’re going have other</text>
    <text>might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding place for artists’ ideas, rather than a site where, as in, say, the Arab Spring was being fought. It’s an institution that, for all intents and purposes, is there to house and present the wishes of an artist’s community.This makes it easier to add or subtract. It’s a space for the community to be present and engaged, to participate in the creation and maintenance of the museum, but it’s also an institution that, once created, is there forever, serving as a reminder of the past and the power of an artist’s ideas. To its founding members and board members, this seemed like an inevitable by-product of the institution’s initial design. I think that, in the end, the important thing is to protect the museum from being destroyed. Once the museum is there, protected, its mission can change and it can also change in ways that are best described as ‘devastating</text>
    <text>might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding place for institutions to maximise their return on investment by naming and branding their collections and exhibitions as if they were a brand new genre of art gallery. It’s this kind of thinking that I call the curatorial micro-ecology – the micro-aggressions that leave their marks. The question that remains today is: what can the museum do to mitigate the impact of this kind of thinking? One can only imagine what the future might hold.The micro-ecology has its critics, of course. It’s a point of view that, while valid, is often expressed in terms of protest. For many people, the museum remains a place of absorption, where meaning is made manifest through images. We’re all stuck in this loop: image, image, image. In this condition, the question of authenticity becomes even more challenging, since the seemingly innocent image becomes suspect when it comes to legitimising the real. This is why, every time the museum is</text>
    <text>might be curated’s initial exhibition, which would consist of a set of objects selected from the collection, at a later date. You’d be surprised how quickly curators, artists and arts organisations have responded to the idea that, if given the chance, they could choose to be destroyed. It’s a powerful argument, and one that I believe can be made again and again. The problem with the museum today is not necessarily a lack of resources. It’s the fact that, in the museum, resources no longer refer to tangible objects but to intangible concepts: concepts such as identity, belonging, belongingness and belongingness. In doing so, curators are attempting to represent a world in which these concepts do not exist.This is an enormous challenge for an institution like the museum, and it’s one that art professionals have been playing with. I think it’s one of the reasons why, over the past 20 years, the museum has mostly been a holding facility for art from around the world, with few artists from any one art-world region present. The reason for this is that, as funds have increased, museums have tended to fill their collections with projects, rather than standing arts projects, typically focusing on the past or exploring present-day dilemmas. The advent of online means that artworks can be found anywhere, anytime, and this has obviously had a hugely positive impact on the cultural landscape. It’s as if the museum had a conference call with its artists, asking them to paint landscapes, and the landscapes to be painted, and to do so in any order. It’s the digital equivalent of the museum’s collection of works on bamboo shoots.The other argument that has significant cultural resources at the moment is that of loss. The loss of habitat and the depletion of freshwater means that there is less demand for fish stocks, which in turn reduces the supply of fish. This all becomes a bit technical, but</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the city of which they are born and raised, the Biennale team and Vitale team set up shop, while the residents of Anfield set up home. They observe and collect the history of the area as it unfolds, and contribute to the ongoing conversation around regeneration and displacement. The conversations take place on the premises of the Biennale, in the Anfield/Breckfield area. The Anfield/Breckfield area has a long and rich history of cultural activity. Its proximity to major transport routes, and the railway line that runs through it, means that the Biennale can be hosted anywhere in the world, and its activities can be conducted at any time. The Anfield/Breckfield area has a rich cultural heritage, which is reflected in the street architecture, buildings, street life (with their colourful mosaic tiles and exposed brick, as well as the colourful mosaic and exposed plaster wall panels that cover the buildings), streetscapes, alleyways and alley-walking that characterise the area</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the present, it will be a way to explore the similarities and differences between the city of the future and the city of the present, while in the other, the present and future of the world, it will be a site of conflict and opportunity. The Biennial proposal has been submitted to the relevant authorities for planning purposes. The Biennial is expected to open in 2021, and the artistes Towards A Future City will present the architectural plans for the city in two years time. The proposals are somewhat in tension with the future city that the duo Guillermo Vitale and their team envision, in part because these two versions of the cityscape are in opposition to one another. The future city is predicted to be highly data driven and connected, where citizens make decisions based on facts rather than ideology. This may include the elimination of religious buildings and symbols, and the fetishisation of data over people, but it is also predicted that citizens will no longer be able to define their city</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the future, this project could be used to explore the possibility of creating a citywide arts federation.  The Biennial itself is a step into the future, but with the developer, Transdev, taking over the site, and the Biennial itself moving downtown, the present – where so many of us live and work – remains on the margins.  The event itself is a metaphor, or perhaps a point of no metaphor, in that it is an attempt to imagine a future in which there is no such thing as urban space.  However, the visionary that manages such an event thinks outside the box, and so the proposal – and the sense of the proposal – shifts to take us to the city in the near future, where the city is not seen as a transient space, but as a place of habitation and purpose. This shifts the focus from the artist to the tenant of the space, and so the relationship between the artist and the tenant is changed. The focus of the artist shifts</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the present, the project contemplates how to support a cultural event in a city where the vast majority of people do not live, work or travel to the city. In the near future, it may inquire how to support a biennial in a city where migration and refugees are a major issue.  Whatever its form, the project seeks to bring together people from diverse specialisations, offering a deeper understanding of the forces that shape and are shaped by the city. The goal of the project is to create a shared vocabulary and set of practices through which people can identify with a shared subjectivity, their place in time, and their own embodied presence.  In this respect, the project suggests a dialectical relationship between culture and society – a process of ‘culture as social practice’ and ‘society as materiality’.  The Artistes Internacionales’ proposal  contradicts the prevailing trend of doing away with art as a function of status, and in</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the present, this vision is realized through art works and exhibition space in and on the site of the event. In the future, it will be possible to create a biennial with the city’s heritage groups, and in the city’s current form, the Biennial Corporation will be able to produce artworks in perpetuity, as part of a long-term collaborative process that will also see the art of the future projects created into artwork.  Present and future urban development and urban transformation are the responsibility of local, national and international organisations. The biennial is a unique and powerful platform, capable of offering multiple perspectives on the same story through a shared history and action. It is a powerful tool for contesting the narrative and providing visibility to hidden or marginalised communities, while enabling the ongoing development of alternative histories, cultures and economies.  The biennial is a global phenomenon: in 2014, there were over 230 in over 60 countries. The reason why it is so powerful is</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the coming years, this ‘step into the future’ may be an option for redeveloping the city. The Biennial itself will continue to exist in its present form as a museum, collection and archive, presenting the city’s rich past, present and future in a shared space. The Museum of Modern Art, New York and M.I.T. both plan to dedicate a museum-type section to the future, with a focus on the role artists may play in creating a better future. The Biennial itself may be the artifact of the city’s past, but it represents a future that is richer and more complex, one where art and artists play important roles, where art and communities work together, and where art and communities thrive. The issue of what is and is not art, what is and is not contemporary art, and what is and is not biennial art, will be addressed in the Biennial commissioning process, as well as in</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the coming years, the project may wish to invest in housing, community infrastructure or both. The exhibition may be a blueprint for a future arts district in the city, or it may be a place where critical theory, critical race theory and critical geography are applied to revitalise a neglected sector of the city. Whatever its intention, the Biennial must address the past to foster future coexistence. The Biennial has a responsibility to interrogate the past, but it has no business imposing its will on the future. Why are we in the city of which it was founded? Who is the city? What is its history? Who is its future? These are the kinds of questions that contemporary art and contemporary communities of all kinds will doubtless ask. We should be able to disagree on the answers, but we should also be able to learn from each other. This is why communities are so vulnerable to the impulse to impose a project or a belief on the future that is not based in fact or in the evidence</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the present, the project captures the essence of the historic experience of living and working in the city, while in the future, it creates new possibilities for cultural exchange and interaction. This is the current proposal and evolution of the Biennial project.  The Biennial has always been an evolving project that changed form and addressed new challenges, and there are many different versions of the event – some creative, some not so inventive – that evolve and confront us from time to time. There is no right or wrong version of the story, or sense of place, so different visitors to different locations around the world can experience and relate to the same version of the event. There is no such thing as ‘international’ or ‘cultural district’ or ‘residential district’ or ‘town centre’ or ‘suburbia’ or ‘industrial precinct’ or ‘regeneration area’ or ‘commercial district’ or ‘industrial park�</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the present, the project is a way to return the city to its pre-apocalyptic state; in the future, it will be a place of creative resistance and perhaps even a future city itself.The project was conceived in collaboration with Constructive Thinking Architects and Ibis Urbanists and Welsh Streets Community Land Trust. It was designed by Rami El Samahy and Ameen Ebadi, and commissioned by Welsh Streets Community Land Trust. The European commissioning agency ATG (Agency for Cultural Affairs) and DIRECTV design bureau Welsh Streets Urbanists were also involved in the project, as consultants. The name Biennale originated as a title given to ceremonies taking place in the Egyptian pyramids, but has come to describe a kind of symposium or festival held in the city, in which works are displayed in a series of venues throughout the city, in sync with the ancient rites of the past.</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is now in the planning stages, and a new exhibition design has been developed. The main objective of the project is to unveil the city as a visitor’s delight, as well as a place of intense cultural production. A series of interactive activities is planned for the day of the exhibition, as well as installations, performances, workshops, lectures, demonstrations and much more. The main venue will be decided at a later date, but the main ideas will be showcased. The main idea will be delivered by a collective of artists committed to the production of a cultural event in the city of which they are citizens. The project will be led by artist duo Guillermo Vitale and his team, and their collaborative project The Artistes Internacionales will present other artists and their ideas. The proposal is that this project is a step into the future, bringing together the past, present and future of Liverpool, creating a shared set of relationships between artists, artisans and communities. In the process, these artists form a new kind of biennial, one dedicated to, and inviting visitors to, the city’s forgotten neighbourhoods. This is the artistic direction in which the Biennale has gone since its inception in 1989.The Biennale has a historical stake in the city because it is a major player in the international art market: people come to see what they are willing to pay to see art from different places. The Biennale is a major cultural institution in its own right, and has a cultural impact comparable to that of major museums, and it is a very potent symbol of the city’s economic success. As a cultural phenomenon, it is numerically dominant, but as a cultural institution, it is not. Liverpool Biennial has significant resources, but in terms of its cultural output, it is dwarfed by, and depends on, what it produces in terms of houses, flats and retail outlets. The estimated annual budget for the first edition of the Bi</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst
    <text>might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst malicious. This does not mean that community artists are not capable of being creative and innovative, just that their place is likely to be in environments where power is concentrated, and where issues of poverty and racism are acute.  The Community Arts movement began with the project Instant Art, an exhibition that challenged conventional notions of what was considered a legitimate art form, and it is this commitment to questioning established paradigms that has defined its trajectory. The project was part of the Biennale cycle, and the artist was selected through an open call focused on emerging talent, part of the public gallery circuit. The Biennale’s funding came from the French government’s primary cultural fund, while the artists’ assistants came from the Musée d'Art Moderne and other art agencies. The project was presented in the main hall of the Musée d'Art Moderne, alongside works from other curators, and was co-sponsored by the main gallery chain, and other local</text>
    <text>might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst malicious.  Art is often asked what it is that draws people to it. In my view, the powerful thing about art is that it can be used to oppress, dehumanise or connect with many different people. There are many ways to engage with the power of an art project, and whilst I would rather engage with power as an entity that threatens or represents me, the fact remains that power structures will always find a way to limit or subvert what an artist can do. What is at Stake in Community Arts?What I found most frustrating about the way that the Community Arts movement was presented to the public in the UK was the disconnect between the projects that were being discussed and the actual communities that were being engaged with. The involvement of non-Community Arts professionals was often questioned, and it became evident that there were many ways of approaching the relationship between Community Arts and art, but the one that was being discussed was largely done by professionals who had a clear agenda and were motivated by their jobs</text>
    <text>might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst malicious. As such, they are frequently accused of not being enough, or not being artistically astute enough. This is simply not true. The difficulties inherent in creating community-based works of art are immense, and the power imbalance between the local and the global arts worlds is staggering. It is true that the globalisation of media has made it easier to become involved in a project nationally, whereas in the past it was much more difficult. But the strength of the artist’s work in influencing social change is significantly discounted when considering a project undertaken in the local art world. In fact, power brokers in the art world are much more likely to pursue projects that further their own positions and careers, and are much more likely to pursue projects that exacerbate inequality and conflict. And indeed, the very nature of the art world is dominated by a small elite of contemporary and recent artists committed to current trends and trendssetters.  The Community Arts movement has advanced in other areas of the world. In</text>
    <text>might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst malicious. To claim a project as a legitimate form of art activity in the city, an artist would have to have a proven track record of bringing innovative projects to life, and the city would then have to actively choose projects from among a possible range of projects. The difficulty in creating such a project is that there is no easy money or easy access to resources in the city, so an artist would have to have a clear idea of what they were getting into and risk a bit in order to really push things forward. The difficulty in creating such a project is compounded by the fact that many communities do not have the capacity or interest to put in place a formal arts education programme, let alone a comprehensive one.   The art world would then have to find other outlets for its funding, since the biennial is exempt from the usual public arts funding streams.  Art is an ever present element of the city, and while it is true that in recent decades the biennial has started to withdraw its support</text>
    <text>might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst malicious. The challenge then becomes how to empower a community to do creative things with art, and how to build support for such projects beyond the local community. There are many different forms of community art, but the key to its success is the commitment and involvement of a broad range of voices. Artists who have become prominent in the UK for projects such as Transmission Gallery, Whittaker Chambers, Sophie Hope, Cathy Hammond, Ken Turner and many more must now consider what the UK may mean to other artists worldwide. The form may have changed, but the core values may have not.  Art and the Community Arts: Two Cultures, Two ApproachesTo understand the relationship between Community Arts and art, one must understand the difference between an artist and an organisation. An organisation is defined as a group of people who work together on a project or project under the authority and direction of a professional. An organisation has a mission and its scope may include things</text>
    <text>might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst malicious. As the housing crisis deepens in many parts of the world, it is imperative that artists develop skills in engaging people on an emotional, cultural and practical level in order to bring their projects to life. The key is in creating a context that will allow the people involved to operate in a more authentic way. Understanding how to work with people is a fundamental skill to bringing creative solutions to complex problems. It requires mastery of the tools and techniques of effective communication and theatre, but more importantly it requires a conscious and deliberate investment in self-education and self-improvement. I would argue that the tools and techniques of effective communication and theatre are critical in a community emerging as a result of the housing crisis, and the scale of which is still unfolding. The ability to create supportive and interesting environments is a two fold approach. The first is building trust. As I have been outlining, the challenge is in creating opportunities for people to come into the art/curatorial/performance space, and for art</text>
    <text>might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst malicious. Even when artists are upfront and transparent about the issues that are involved in their work, such as the reasons for which they produce art, the politics that shape their practice and the assumptions that underlie their work, questions of authenticity and place remain. A number of Community Arts projects have sought to create an environment conducive to the growth of socially engaged or artist lead art direction via projects such as The Resident, which sought to create a work-in-progress of what the Italian artists had achieved at the Calabrese in the 1970s, or the All Together Now project, which sought to re-invigorate an old post-war arts movement in the city by bringing together artists, curators and writers via a concomitant writing and re-writing of the work of the past. All Together Now attracted a wide range of cultural figures, including Bill Clinton, Sonja Kuftinek, Karin Oxman, Peter Carr,</text>
    <text>might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst malicious. It is an arena in which artists are willing to put in long hours, which can sometimes be dangerous and exhausting, and in which the demands of the project may very well override all other considerations. It is an arena in which anti-racist and anti-oppressive activism are core values, and in some ways the very basis of the project. Indeed, the very rhetoric of ‘community’ is used by some of the most vociferous critics of contemporary art practice as a justification for doing harm to communities they observe participating in the art world, and perhaps even in their everyday existence. Yet even as the project of Community Arts is questioned in the context of contemporary art practice, its practitioners are quick to assert that their commitment to anti-capitalist activism and anti-racist politics is more relevant to the project of Community Arts than any theoretical commitment to an artist’s right to artistic agency. Perhaps it is this ‘rightward leaning’ that has forced some organisations to embrace</text>
    <text>might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst malicious.  In the early 1990s, Cathy Vaughn Coleman launched the first edition of the Biennale, and over the years there have been many more. Today, the Biennale is one of the most widely visited cultural attractions in London, and this year marks the twentieth anniversary of the Biennale in Paris. It is at the Biennale that artists created a public space, a public realm, for themselves and their audiences to inhabit, to draw attention to, and perhaps even to experiment with, different ways of inhabiting. I was invited to do just that.I arrived early, well into the evening, and was paired up with a curator whose work I had never seen before. We were led into a private exhibition space, which felt somewhat like an arts academy, albeit one with curatorial flair as well as an artistic flair. Curators were instructed in the rules of the event, and provided with maps that depicted the locations of all the participating artists</text>
    <text>might be curated, but the real power is with the artist.Every artist is an artist first and foremost, and every project is a last. It’s up to the artist to decide where the art ends and the other begins, and what relationship that art has with the city that is currently experiencing a housing crisis. The power of an artist is not absolute, but it’s at least personal. In a community, an artist’s obligation is to do whatever is necessary to bring an art project to life, no matter what the political or economic situation may be in the city.  The Community Arts movement emerged after a number of artists were involved with Community Arts projects in the 1970s and early 80s, and it is a lasting example of a project that seeks to address deep seated issues of inequality and oppression that are still prevalent in many parts of the world. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are untested, and whose practitioners are at best naive and at worst malicious. It is an arena in which claims to being an artist are often questioned by others, and in which the experience of artistic activity can be complex and fraught. It is an arena in which the experiences of community members can be strengthened through support and encouragement. In a broader perspective, it is an arena in which issues of power and control are inevitably present and which must be overcome in order to achieve genuine artistic possibilities. In this sense, the project may be seen as a kind of collective memory, a shared narrative of struggles and achievements that is ultimately generated by the very people involved in the making of it, and which will undoubtedly remain so no matter how many different creative projects may emerge out of it. 	[1] See Nasser Rabbat, The Crisis of Community Arts, PPP, New York, 2011. 	[2] See Wendy Chun and Amy Wei, ‘Who Are Our Musicians? and How Are They Influencing the Public</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a
    <text>might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a public accountability, since it was being done in part through a community of artists.  A medium that also challenged the existing spatial and temporal limits of its own space, making it possible for artists to inhabit the present within its parameters.  A medium such that it was possible to simultaneously inhabit space and public space, since coordination was achieved through spatial norms and regulations, but also in part by the intervention of artists.   A medium that intermingled the artist with the community, while simultaneously challenging the community to engage the artist in a way that would not only benefit the local community, but would also be representative of the city at large.   A medium that promoted both the creation of new art and the establishment of old art forms through the intervention of artists.Art as arts intervention and engagementThe art of urban restoration and urban renewal schemes was at one time the dominant form of urban remediation in Britain, providing financial support for projects through grants to local authorities and grassroots organisations. The industrialised forms</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a tool that it was possible to use to influence the city in a certain way.  A medium through which we as artists could potentially become involved in creating an experience of the city in various ways, both in terms of the ways in which our art could be configured to be felt and experienced, and in terms of the ways in which our art could be constructed as a set of strategies to be employed in influencing the city in certain ways. In other words, it might not be just the art that comes with the package, but what is inside the package.  A question that arose in our working process during The Resident was: what should the art be?    Aesthetic, not necessarily aesthetically so, but should be able to convey meaning to the reader in such a way as to enable the reader to work through a particular thought or idea. For example, the meaning of the 10 Downing Street mural might be lost in translation if it was painted on a wall, but the reader’s</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a mechanism of creating a sense of place and belonging in the city? We felt that this was the medium that Liverpool needed to be developing, because it would enable us to create an environment in which the biennial could be built on, even if it meant that the Biennial might have to be made elsewhere. Art and Community: Intersectionality, or the Art and Community Connected Form (2015) is the result of our conversations with Community Arts practitioners, educators and artists over the course of 2015. It is an art project that engages with the notions of art, aesthetics, community and architecture in an effort to locate and tap into the city’s buried architectural treasure, that is accessible to both urban dwellers and artists alike. In doing so, it seeks to create a space for artists to work collaboratively, exploring how their artistic expression can connect with buried infrastructure, how it can create new ways of inhabiting sites, and how it can engage with the issues of regeneration and displacement</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a mechanism by which the city could be changed through neighbourhood and community input.  A medium that sought to interrogate power and profit through the mediation of language while also encouraging a dialogue about the possibility of a socialist city.  A medium that sought to create a sense of place through the collaboration of people rather than through the imposition of a singular entity.   A question that emerged repeatedly during these two-and-a-half years was: what is the role of language in a socialist city? Language as a tool for the empowerment of a marginalized community, or as a blunt instrument for the economic and political subjugation of a majority of humanity?  A question that can be used to intervene in the society of the rich and, by implication, the language of the powerless.  A question that invites, as Krysa puts it, ‘honest communication and negotiation’about the place of language in a given context.  A question that invites, as well, negotiation about the politics</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a public forum that invited in others with diverse skills and perspectives. We asked ourselves, ‘What kind of density can we create?’ We also asked ourselves, ‘What kind of access can we create?’ These three elements – accessibility, access and density – made us feel that there was a way to connect the artist and the community, and in a way that was both authentic to the city and responsive to the needs of the local residents of Liverpool. This intimacy and responsiveness was also critically important in the creation of the Biennial, as it made it something different from a regular art museum or historic site, and from a museum towards a socially responsive organisation. Accessibility is the ability to access information, ideas and resources in a way that is accessible to people with disabilities, and is itself a construct of both accessibility and participation. For example, the Biennial’s website calls itself a ‘living museum’, but in the museum/public setting, it is</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a public register of intent, so that we, as artists, could begin to imagine how to live in the city in ways that are not dictated by the top-down, bureaucratic model of urbanism currently practised in the UK.   A medium that actively engages with the idea of place, and actively contributes to its reconfiguration. We discussed the notion of aesthetics as a politics of space, and how our work might begin to bring aesthetic values into the political equation with the development of self-employed art practices and the urbanisation of previously feudal estates.  Aesthetics and its politics of space are some of the ideas that emerged in the talk, and our work inevitably responds to the notion of beauty as a commodity. Our proposal that our curatorial work should attempt to reconfigure the city in such a way as to allow for the collection and presentation of beauty, and beauty as a function of time, invites us to begin to consider the ways in which beauty might be found in a city</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a prop in a political drama? Such a medium could potentially open up new ways of engaging with the city – providing a ground-level perspective, which might otherwise be buried or censored by bigger cultural institutions. Such a medium might also lead to a re-thinking of institutionalised modes of cultural production and consumption – cultural hierarchies might be shaken up, and power imbalances dissolved.  This latter radical ambition is a major part of what biennials – and, we might add, some of the creative forces shaping up to be created when those terms are finally abolished – need to be about. It is a potential way of being responsive to the changing needs, desires and assets of the city, in such a way as to thrive in a new context. More and more, biennials are being commissioned by cultural organisations, museums, heritage institutions and grassroots groups, but almost all of them are becoming participants in a game-changing process that is altering the face of the city in profound ways. The</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a way of creating a kind of political space for the city’s Indigenous peoples and creative class.  In the case of biennials, the in-gallery experience was long gone, replaced by the digital medium in which in-depth work became the exclusive preserve of the well-heeled and the comfortable middle class. We wondered how art could play a part in creating a kind of cultural battleground through which ideas and politics could be moved. Art as a mediator between rich and poor, between users and creators, between users and producers – that is, between artists and communities. We also wondered how such mediation might be possible in a city where the rich and the poor, the powerful and the powerless, the privileged and the voiceless, the well-connected and the poor, the well-connected and the homeless, the artist and the migrant, the tourist and the vagabond. Perhaps what was most lacking in the city at the time was a sense of belonging, a sense of belonging</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a public forum where people could come and share ideas and experiences.   A medium that offered a large quantity of contemporary art from a range of local artists, but also invited in-depth research and analysis into the city’s artworld landscape.   A medium that put the artist at the center of the deliberative process, while respecting the democratic decision-making of the local community. Ultimately, we felt that a biennial with a clear mission and clear parameters should be able to accomplish both of these things, while remaining sensitive to the needs and interests of the local community.   A biennial with a clear mandate and clear parameters might inadvertently blur the distinction between art and art’s social function, and might lead some artists to activities that are at odds with the values and commitments of the community. We felt that artists should be able to define and determine what their work would represent, and that is why we gave the mandate to the artists to come up with a proposal that met</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, at least in part, influenced by what he had witnessed in Liverpool. In The Liverpool Biennial: Art, Politics, Community Curated (2015), based on a talk with artist and Biennial producer, Joasia Krysa, we discussed the relationship between art and community, and the role that artists might play in such a context. The two of us felt that there was a gap, and that there was still a tendency for artists to operate in an environment where they were more exposed to the world through mass media and in-person encounters. The challenge then was to create ways of connecting the artist to the community through what we saw as a more intimate medium.  A medium that was both accessible and representative of the city, in that it was relatively new and had a vibrant community feel to it, but also a political medium that was strong in its commitment to transparency and accountability.   A medium that was not only a means of communicating with the city, but also a way for the city to take control over the artist’s work and the meaning of the medium.To achieve this, we experimented with different media types, as well as engaging with the role of the artist in the community. We did this by inviting the artists to develop creative projects around ideas that were of a political nature. For example, by inviting the artists to commission artworks or to create collectable objects, we were trying to bring an emotional element to the discussions and debates that were occurring in the community at that time. By inviting the artists to produce educational programmes or to develop local arts organisations, we were trying to enfuse the arts with the community through the production of activities such as performances, meetings or observing hours, while at the same time providing them with the means to engage in political and activist activities. We were also experimenting with the capacity of local artists to take part in projects of social and economic empowerment and to produce social outcomes such as giving workshops or launching arts foundations.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/
    <text>present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iii] See: http://www.theguardian.com/travel/2017/oct/17/uk-travel/western-travelers-are-now-more-likely-than-ever-to-book-a-helicopter-ride-in-the-uk-travel-industry-13-billion-year-old-west-india-east-asia-west-pacific-robot?! (accessed September 1, 2018). [iv] See: http://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2018/11/18/better-know-a-history-of-europe/ (accessed September 1, 2018) [v]</text>
    <text>present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed September 2018). [iii] See: http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2017/oct/29/antiquities-and-futures-in-the-new-economy-world-histories-2017-ultra-high-end-art-continuum-retreat?CMP=TrueCrypt:BRI/9D1B378AD9CEA0B9002A48E8D7BBD1F793AE46D7DA5AD12E89D2 [&amp;A]http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-b</text>
    <text>present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iv] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [v] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com</text>
    <text>present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iii] See: https://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iv] See: https://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [v] See: https://www.biennaleoftheworld.com</text>
    <text>present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iv] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [v] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com</text>
    <text>present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iii] See: http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2017/aug/14/biennial-problem-old-world-image-new-world-image (accessed August 2018). [iv] See: http://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk/2017/aug/14/muslim-american-state-problem-new-age-bir-bir-bulgarian-muslim-culture-problem (accessed August 2018). [v] See: http://www.theguardian.com/uk/uk/2017/aug/14/muslim-american-state-problem-new-age-bir-b</text>
    <text>present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iv] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018).[v] See also: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.</text>
    <text>present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iii] The Australian Bureau of Statistics, Australian Social Trends (2016). Available at: http://www.abs.gov.au/licensing/statistics/industry/social-research/fact-sheets/2017/exhibit/0.1.0.0/industry-research/social-research-research-research-indicators-2017.html (accessed September 2018). [iv] Joel Kotkin, ed., The Essential Social Science Research [1] Meehan Crist, ‘More Than Supplies: The Political, Economic and Cultural Geographies of the Auto-Suicide Trap’, American Political Science Review, Vol. 102, No. 1, 2009, p.183. [</text>
    <text>present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iv] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [v] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com</text>
    <text>present an online project, the Devotion to Art exhibition was also an online project.) As an artist who actively engages with the notion of participation in a socially engaged context, I find the need for transparency and accountability compelling. I believe that the biennial can and should act in a way that generates knowledge and engages with notions of participation. This is possible through research-based, archival and ‘bottom-up’ methods, applying the principles of an ‘archived history’ to inform practices and events, creating what I would define as a proto-biennial. 	[i] http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com.au/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [ii] See: http://www.biennaleoftheworld.com/2017/exhibition/art/world-histories/the-ugly-east-south-east-bicentennial-we-re-all-in-the-same-place-now/ (accessed August 2018). [iii] See: http://www.theguardian.com/artanddesign/2017/aug/13/new-york-times-nyt-architecture-20170214-welcome?partner=2&amp;partner_id=210879&amp;partner_type=2&amp;partner_name=Gareth Whitehead (accessed September 2018). [iv] See: http://www.nytimes.com/2017/09/18/us/politics/donald-trump-investor.html?excerpt=Us_Politics_Corner (accessed September 2018). [v] See also my The New Urban Frontier (Princeton Architectural Review Press, 2016), chapter</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every
    <text>future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every possible form – in galleries, museums, archives, online, in-person, through curatorial rapids and brooms, in-depth trips to countries around the globe, in-depth research trips to selected local hotspots, and in-depth reporting trips inside and outside of the art world. Art biennials have a particular mission statement that sets forth the curatorial priorities and worlds of their production. The Tokyo Triennale, by contrast, provides an ideal setting for a biennale to exist, because it is both a city and a museum. It is both a city and museum that simultaneously documents the movement of contemporary art today and produces, with the aim to teach or to introduce to other museums or artworlds contemporary art from different times and places. It is both a city with a rich collection of historical and contemporary art and a collection of art from different eras, both of which are critically annotated through its permanent exhibition schedule. It presents a variety</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every detail possible. This event, the exhibition packaging, the package inserts, the videos, the magazines and the website are but a few artifacts of a broader history of art making made possible by the discovery and study of history, geography, language, economics and communication. The biennial form (limited by the resources of its creators), which was originally a publication of the Venice Biennalee, is now a globally-recognised biennial form, with exhibitions in over 200 cities around the globe. 	In a city, biennials are the cultural equivalent of what we would call ‘temporary exhibitions’, and are a form of cultural exchange between local and international art collectors and art institutions, a fieldwork between cultures that is as necessary as ever, and a place where we make common cause with other art forms in the age of the biennial.  	Rihanna, 'Bitch Better Have My Money', 2015. Installation, Museum of Modern Art</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every detail. The number of biennials has trebled in the past twenty-five years, and each of the past three years more than doubled the current population of Lisbon, Portugal.1  Since 2006 the Lisbon Biennale has been operating under the title, most recently, ‘14 Years’.2  The exhibition schedule has also drastically shifted, with major exhibits appearing late in the year, often when the biennale is immersed in a major promotion, advertising or research initiative. The main attraction of the biennial in the present day is, however, the annual public works programme, now largely a commercial enterprise for the biennale itself. Its purpose has shifted from providing unique scientific or archival insights into the contemporary art world to providing a commercial marketplace for the artworks being made from the exhibitions. The biennale has a significant impact on the city, and its commercial activities are a major contributor to its economic wellbeing. As an institution, the biennale</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every possible form. The Tokyo Triennale is the largest such institutionally-sanctioned tourist attraction in the world. It is the largest remaining national animal museum in the United States, and the largest remaining animal museum in the world. It is a major venue for biennials outside of Europe and the Middle East, and a major tourist draw for those places. It is customary for artworks to remain on display for a specified length of time, usually several years, after their production, exhibition and/or sale is discontinued. The exhibitionary form has been a source of great pride for the biennial, and a source of much of the institution’s self-congratulatory self-talk. It is an exhibitionary form that is so compellingly alive, that it can be curatorial as well as aesthetical. 	The exhibitionary form is so compellingly alive that it often appears in failure. Curators, curators, art collectors, collectors and art lovers have long</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every possible form – documentary, documentary, documentary, documentary, and so forth. Artistic curators, including the F.W. Bond, Emma Hart, Sophie Hope and Glenn Scott, are among a host of artists, curators, arts administrators, art writers and arts policy wonks who flock to this biennial to monitor, analyse and assess the art making in progress. Artistic curators, including Ray Bradbury, Gregory Mills and Tom Lox, are among a host of artists, curators, arts administrators, arts educationists and arts think tanks who flock to this biennial to observe, analyse and appraise the art being made in their cities (notably New York and London). This is not a one-size-fits-all picture, but rather a snapshot of the current state of art and the pressing problem facing contemporary art today. The biennial must be a place where</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every aspect of the world. They come to see works made by artists in transit, as well as those that have been made in the same city in the same way. While this may seem redundant or inconvenient for artists, it is art students, art lovers, art history buffs and archivists who flock to the biennial, and they learn a great deal about art and the art form through the experiences. 	As the number of arts and cultural institutions worldwide has grown, so too has the number of biennials. In 1990, there were three in major cities; in 2014, there were eleven in major cities; in 2016, there were thirteen in major cities. Each biennial offered a slightly different experience than the last. 	The first Venice International Exhibition (1987) offered a very different experience from the one offered by the present. The exhibition was organized on a shoestring budget, and the venue was a far cry from the modern biennial. The growing number of art fair</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every detail. They are not there to admire or learn about the art, but to create awareness of the importance of art and art history in a particular geographical region or city. The biennial has the capacity to make a difference, both by awakening awareness of art in a specific location and by igniting artistic passion in a specific audience.  	Its ability to ignite creativity in a specific audience is another source of its value. It is possible that the biennial could be the spark that ignites the artistic and curatorial imagination together, creating a chain reaction of artistic and curatorial action across the globe. This is the kind of thinking and creative action needed to address the pressing art-historical and local-curatorial issues facing our contemporary world. It would also represent an enormous opportunity for biennials to expand their audiences and clienteles, creating new revenue streams and exploiting the city as a new offshore tax haven. 	Of course, the biennial needs to be sustainable in its</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every detail. They come to appreciate how biennials can play a critical role in providing culture for a changing metropolitan population, and in that they ask, can the city be organised to support a cultural life? I believe that the biennial form can be valuable for the city in ways that are counterintuitive and creative, but also in ways that are unsustainable and create inequality. 	And we would do well to remember the words of W. E. B. Du Bois, who said, in his famous line, ‘A city is only as strong as its weakest link’. 	The biennial forms as art objects are a threat to their urban hosts; they are a valuable commodity for museums and a source of knowledge for consumers; and they are a source of power for local politicians and cultural authorities. We need to learn how to use this cultural capital effectively. Whether we want to or not, the biennial is a ‘capital-intensive’ institution, and</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every possible format. The events provide a forum for these people to come, share ideas and knowledge and to make art in transit.   Art is art, and so is life in transit. The biennial event is an ideal platform for the production of knowledge about art, its form and culture, its social effects, and its infrastructure. It is a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition and so on. Art is made in transit through the biennial, and so the question facing contemporary art is, too: what becomes of art when it is no longer a product of the city? 	There are of course many other events that produce knowledge and art, but these three events in the last decade alone are the largest and most visible. There are several hundred events that year, but these three are especially distinctive and so grab our attention and interest. As the New York Times put it in its 2009 review of the Venice Biennale</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms, the elimination of formal requirements, and a reduction in the need for artists to master production processes (not to mention the ability to pick up materials and techniques in the city) allowed the biennial to transition to more of a cultural institution. In the process, it established cultural capital. The biennial would later be renamed the Tokyo Triennale. 	Today, the biennial is an art form with an art objective, and a function that includes some cultural capital as well. Its mission statement (currently listed as &quot;outstanding literary and artistic&quot; in the F.W. Bond, ‘The New Curator’) accounts for the art produced in transit through the premise that it was a ‘curatorial act’. 	Artists, curators, art school teachers, collectors and arts administrators flock to the biennial to witness, examine, learn and acquire knowledge about the art being made today in every possible form. The exhibitionary form has given way to mass media and digital distribution, which in turn has given way to a ‘curatorial village’ – a city-within-a-city where diverse activities take place.  	The biennial form is a dynamic and ever-expanding production, and it plays no small part in this. As the media of art and culture shift and morph under their own volition, so too do the forms that serve them. Art biennials have, in turn, done so by necessity, having to keep up with the changes in their audiences, and have to adapt to the new media and forms of consumption that are thrust upon them. Mass media and biennials are, of course, the products of their respective times, and while their current forms and media of consumption may not be identical, they do tend to be made in different times and in different places. But the assumption that each community had a distinct biennial and that</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high level of economic development of the world at the time. 	[2] See, for example, Norman Brown, The Culture and the Crisis of Capitalism (New York: Alfred A Knopf, 1968). [3] Brown, Brown, and Brook, op. cit. [4] Brown, op. cit. [5] Brown, op. cit. [6] Brook, op. cit. [7] Brook, op. cit. [8] Brook, op. cit. [9] Brook, op. cit. [10] Brook, op. cit. [11] Brook, op. cit. [12] Brook, op. cit. [13] Brook, op. cit. [14] Brook, op. cit. [15] Brook, op. cit. [16] Brook, op.</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high cost of art per head. This was largely due to the explosion of video on television and the internet, which transformed art from a commodity commodity into an object of exchange, where the exchange was made more effective by the ubiquity of images. 	[2] 	The concept of the biennial was coined by and for the social, in order to encompass more than the sum of its various forms. 	[3] 	When thinking of what is meant by the term ‘biennial’, we need to distinguish between two aspects of the same concept: the social and the cultural. Social biennials are those forms of cultural exchange between individuals and groups that take place at an institutional level, whereas cultural biennials are those forms of cultural exchange between cultural groups. 	[4] Cultural groups are those whose cultural assets lie in the collective body of humanity and not in the individual gifts or talents of individuals. The social is a concept that needs to be developed</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high cost of production – particularly for institutions like Bluecoat – which made them attractive targets for curators eager to cash in on the celebrity of the moment. 	[2] 	Poppell, Judith. Art from Historic Times: Modern Art and Biennialism. New York: Penguin, 1991, p.25.Download this article as PDFJussi ParikkaJussi Parikka is Professor in Art History and Director of the Centre for Art and Culture Studies at the University of Turku, Finland. His research interests include the antecedents of contemporary art, biennials, and postmodernism, and his main areas of concern are art and visual culture. His publications include the collections Visual Art: Art, Politics, Law (University of Turku Press, 2015), Contemporary Art: Art Criticism (University of Turku, 2013), Art and Visual Culture: Issues and Responses (2015), and Visual Cultures: Art, Identity and Communicity (</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high level of development at the time. The popularity of films such as the Hunger Games and The Wire in the late 1990s meant that there was a mass market for art and a vocal following for artists who were both young and female, which also bred the possibility that there were large followings of young people following their artistic choices. At this time, there was also a lot of politicising of art practice, which to a certain extent is still happening in some arts departments, particularly in the UK. 	[2] Norman Brown, ‘The Rise of Biennials: The Cultural Turn in Modern Art’, Art Quarterly, Vol. 41, No. 1, Spring, 1990, p. 35.Download this article as PDFNorman Brown Norman Brown is an arts professional and writer. His work, which is published through the publication of the quarterly Art Newspaper, has dealt with the political and economic meanings of cultural capitalism since the 1980s. His latest book is What is</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high level of economic development at the time, but also the fact that many artists felt that the social end of cultural production was more important than the economic. �[2] 	The Biennial was originally conceived as a temporary exhibitionary venue, and as a result of the decline in visitor numbers and the shifting permutations of art forms – in one form or another – the Biennial has been on a trajectory of diminishing numbers, shifting exhibitionary formats and formats, and fluctuating curatorial appointments. The main exhibitionary form for contemporary art since the mid-1990s, the Biennial has slowly become a rare and valuable commodity, and the once scarce form of the biennial is now universal and price-free. 	[3] One such specimen is seen in the form of a travelling art exhibition, or biennial, the art of which is transferred between hosts, from gallery to museum, town to town, and from continent to continent. The aim of this exhibitionary form is</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high standard of living associated with it, along with the heightened public awareness of urban infill. However, I also believe that the emergence of biennials late in the game is related to the increased public legitimisation of the city. From the late 1970s until the mid 1980s, the biennial was frequently claimed to be a catalyst for a radical rethinking of art and culture in the city, although recent scholarship has cast doubt on this privileged position. 	[2] Brown, Peter (ed.) On Burke’s Cathedral: An Eater of Worlds. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 1991, p. 286.[3] Stevens, Geoffrey (ed.)  The Cathedral Reader. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 1991, p. 613.[4] Brown, On Decadence and Modern Art. New York: Vintage Books, 1985, p. 402.[5] Brown, On Decadence and Modern</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high cost of producing cultural productions at home. However, I now see them as a profoundly important art form, intimately related to both the infrastructure of post-consumer society and the social practices of postindustrial society, but distinct in that they are able to exist in a different world. 	[2] 	The Biennial has become increasingly influential in discourses on postindustrial society, particularly in the international arena, and increasingly so since its early support of the Arts Council of Great Britain and the Arts Council of Australia. 	[3] 	In recent decades, the Biennial has been supplemented by multiple other forms of art festivals and cultural exchanges. IMI Corona, held in early June each year in Santa Fe, New Mexico, is an example to be admired. 	[4] The festival is organized by the Santa Fe Museum, the Santa Fe Art Museum and the Santa Fe Museum of Art, draws visitors from all over the US and Canada to Santa Fe, New Mexico,</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high level of infrastructure required to support it, coupled with the political instability of post-9/11. The need to be visible in major metropolitan centres combined with the deep pockets of artistic patrons coupled with the pressing need to be visible on a regular basis meant that, although it is true that, prior to the mid-1990s, the Biennial lost much of its power as a cultural centre.  	[2] Brown, Norman. Culture and Anarchy: Power and Cultural Politics in an Anarchist History of Art, 2003. 	[3] Norman Brown, Making the World Small: Apparition of the Imagination in Modern Culture, 1996. 	[4] Journalist David Harvey, ‘The Fall of Barcelona – Part 1’, in  	The Fall of Barcelona – Part 2’, in  	The New York Review of Books, November-December, 1994, p. 1–18. 	[5</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high cost of art production.  	[2] 	See:  	http://www.biennial.org.uk/en/students/programme/view/view_full/948172/1/Biennial_2018_View_Full.html#sthash.rQfJVl.17.iNl9jYV.dpuf.dpuf.2014.12.14.html#sthash.l3Nl9jYV.dpuf.dpuf.2014.12.14.html[3] Brown, Norman. ‘On the Origin of the Biennial’,  	Norman Brown: The Rise and Fall of the Creative Class, pp. 81–1.Download this article as PDFRafico RuizRafico Ruiz is an artist. His work in the public domain includes works at the Barbican, Tate Modern and Tate Modern London, as</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open with a performance by the contemporary art collective Bluecoat, who will serve as artistic advisor to the inaugural Liverpool Biennial in 2022. The project has been supported by the Arts Council England, while Bluecoat will conduct a series of workshops in conjunction with the Biennial. The opening will be facilitated by the Arts Council England and Bluecoat, with the latter providing a range of collaborative arts activities including: tours, publications, events and publications, lectures and exhibitions. 	[1] 	There are several theories on the development of biennials in the late twentieth century. Some trace their origins to the primitivist/anarchist fringe in the 1930s, while others, such as Norman Brown and Peter Brook, trace their origins to the 1970s countercultural counterculture. My own position on biennials is that they emerged late in the game, in the 1990s, as a result of a combination of factors including the mass appeal of pop culture and the high cost of cultural goods, in large part due to the ubiquity of cell phones. 	[2] Journelle Saint-Amand, ‘On the eve of a new cultural revolution’,  	Signal, 22 September 2015, http://www.signal.org/article/view/71/21948.html. [3] Brown, Peter, and Brook, Richard. Politics, Culture and the Contemporary Condition. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1988. [4] Hayek, Ludwig. ‘Contributions to an Economic and Philosophic Revival’,  	The Intellectuals' Collected Essays. 1937. [5] George Akerlof, ‘Keynes on Monetary Policy’,  	Money, 17 April 2010, http://www.macquariejournal.com/science/economy/20140503-g-a-k-</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to
    <text>might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to its public funding and large-scale image, which is often abused. The biennial as a cultural form is necessarily a con- form – and con- ception that only the privileged few can partake in. And while it seems obvious to many people in the UK and beyond how this is  	actually happening, it’s another thing entirely to actually happen. 	Many biennials are actually still works in progress, unfinished, in disuse for years to come, and their disuse presents a particular set of problems, especially for those people living in and around the artworld. The disuse of art spaces presents a problem for their creators, but it’s also a problem for the communities who’re being served by these spaces. The disuse of the visual arts is a global process, and so is FACT, whose work in the Sudanese city of Sud, and in the Chaco area of New Mexico, is just as problematic</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to the obvious aesthetic defects (which are most evident in its current form), but also includes the fact that, as biennials proliferate in all kinds of public and private projects around the globe, the biennial as a cultural form itself becomes increasingly diverse, fragmented, and transient. It becomes less about the place of art in a socio-political and aesthetically diverse society, and more about the place of art as an aesthetic and socially conscious force. That’s why the biennial, while it seems to be doing well relative to other art forms, is also capturing, measuring, and measuring-ing cultural resources everywhere it goes. Its market power and commodity fetishism are deeply embedded in how it is conceptualised and conceptualised in the world. But it is this very notion of culture as a resourcefulness for production, exchange, and consumption that is deeply embedded in how biennials conceive of their place in the world. 	The biennial is a modern cultural production form that has</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to its public funding and privileged position, but also includes the cultural presuppositions that generate the biennial itself, and so-called cultural capital (CB) that it relies on. 	In the 1990s, CB was produced by and for the international real-estate market. Its main objective was to maximise profit by creating a ‘brand identity’ for the area in question, and to do so by positioning the building market as the frontline in a global conflict between cultures and powerful forces. As such, the building was strategically placed against the city’s historical heritage, local flavour and mixed-use potential, in an attempt to maximise the impact of the iconic ‘brown bag’ sign. As a result of this and other projects, the biennial’s current financial situation is almost entirely caused by government subsidies and the financial aid it provides to artists and institutions of higher learning; as well as the financial aid it provides to artists who engage with the city through</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to its public funding, despite the increasing public funding it gets; the real issue is that it operates according to predetermined parameters. And these predetermined parameters, while helpful in certain ways, ultimately become problematic when applied to a citywide or even a district-wide scale. What happens in Liverpool or Berlin doesn’t necessarily apply to Liverpool or Berlin, because of the established and long-standing international division of labour between the cities. What happens in Liverpool or Berlin has a much more direct impact on what can and cannot be done in the city. 	There was a time when the biennial was able to create a new narrative around itself through creative self-branding, through what has been colloquially referred to as ‘the miracle of the biennial’. But as biennials everywhere become more public and visible, and as they are increasingly placed in the public sector, their original miracle begins to fail. New narratives about the biennial are needed; they cannot simply be absorbed into</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to the obvious aesthetic defects (immensity, bureaucracy, materialism, capitalism), but also the immensity, bureaucracy, and materialism of the current system (high property prices and chaotic incentives). The current biennial form, in its current materiality (metallic and glass are the predominant forms of institutionalised form), makes it nearly impossible to imagine a different form of the form in the future. 	However, the biennial is no longer the sole show in town. There are other forms of cultural funding available to be used in a similar way to biennials in the UK, but these are reserved for exceptional cultural events. And while these forms of cultural funding may or may not align with the current publics, they do not align with the values (or politics) of the public. 	So what is the alternative to the present curatorial practice, which is ideologically driven but functionally ineffective? There are many who advocate a biennial as a replacement for the present institutional form, but</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to the obvious aesthetic defects (which are well-known to anyone who has been paying attention). The real problem with the biennial as a cultural form is its slowness in responding to changes in social and economic conditions. And while there are certainly better ways to do things, the fact that the art centre, which has always been the core objective of the biennial, is now the only form of cultural form that matters – and that is both geographically and socially isolating – shows how little has actually changed in the real world, despite what the art dealer might have you believe. 	There are other forms of cultural funding that are of course of course available to all cultural forms, but the fact that the art biennial is now the only form of cultural form that matters is a clear and present example of this. And while the biennial may or may not always deliver what its sponsors expect from them, its status as the predominant form of cultural funding (despite occasional setbacks) is a fundamental part</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to the obvious aesthetic  	loss and damage caused by its commercial production, which is always on the lookout for ways to maximise revenue. The real problem with the biennial as a cultural form is the  	presumption of social  	unity. And while this may be true for certain cultural types (e.g. architecture), it becomes problematic for others (e.g. the many faces of the social). And this  	presumption of social  	unity is what the social is looking for right now, in the wake of the crisis of the city. The question is: what does it mean for a community to be taken seriously? As biennials, artistic-led initiatives are apropos of social change, what is meant by this? 	Artistic leadership, as defined by the biennial, is an ability to produce a significant impact on a cultural or historic site, through a sustained and persistent process that is conveys through art,</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to the obvious structural reasons – the pathology of the capitalist construction itself – but also includes cultural problems of a devolving, privatising nature. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to indulge in, while the rest of us have to work ourselves to death doing other cultural forms. This is clearly seen in the number of arts and cultural organisations registering in the USA after the financial crash of 2008: the number of arts and cultural organisations in the UK is now four times larger than the number of students in the country. And this despite the fact that the number of students in the UK has remained roughly the same for decades, declining mainly as a result of wars in the Middle East and conflicts in South Asia. The rise of the biennial coincides with a general increase in public spending on culture, primarily due to a large federal government bureaucracy with a national array of arts and cultural programmes. 	So as the number of people who can afford to visit a museum or a gallery continues to</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to its public funding and contemporary composition, but also includes the cultural practices that it supports, the cultural consumption (which is itself a commodity), the cultural discourses that it creates, and so on. These cultural production mechanisms are structurally related to each other and to other forms of cultural output, and in a ‘big picture’ sense. But this doesn’t really map onto the specific practices of community arts in the UK, because we don’t have that kind of infrastructure or that kind of social context or connectivity. 	There are of course ways of making the biennial more social: by drawing resources from elsewhere, for example, or providing a platform or instigation to other creative forms of collaborative learning. But this is still only the first step in a long process of change, and it’s hardly the only one. The question is which of the many creative and dynamic ways of making the biennial can augment the social function of the biennial in a way</text>
    <text>might be curated’s, by artists and curators, which confront the the problem of community arts in contemporary society from an perspectives of aesthetics, aesthetics of life – and so on. 	But as biennials, they also demonstrate the limiting, despite their public financing and their place as one of the main forms of cultural funding in the UK. The biennial has become something that only the privileged few are able to experience. Yet this only serves to enhance the social 	 that only the privileged few can indulge in. And while it’s true that the biennial has a limited budget, the biennial as a cultural form is itself an ever-expanding and shifting canvas that can’t be confined. It’s the same with architecture: its original plan, to be built for the sole purpose of residential and commercial renewal in the mid-1990s, has since then morphed into something completely different. The problem with the biennial as a cultural form is not limited to its public funding and hereditary tax-exempt status (though both of these are suspect in their own way). The real problem with the biennial as a cultural form is its impact on the psyche. The biennial is seen as a pilgrimage, an inherently ‘high-impact' manner in which to the psyche, and thus the museum as a whole. But this sort of low impact isn’t seen as exciting or ‘mind-expanding’ by art educators, and so the biennial has to be continually (re)imagined, tweaked, adjusted – all while maintaining its place in the psyche as a whole. 	In an ideal world, art should be able to easily mesh with everyday life, and art shouldn’t be limited by the everyday. But since we don’t live in that ideal world, we can’t make art that will always be there, like the architecture. Sometimes, adjusting a museum to what’s happening in</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis,
    <text>future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, Third International Congress of Political and Cultural Studies, San Francisco, 1978.Download this article as PDFMarlen VargasMarlen Vargas is an artist, writer and researcher. Her work in the social world is complicated by her own complex position as an immigrant and refugee. She is currently curator at the National Gallery of Canada, and was a curator at the Toronto and Vancouver museums. In her free time, she enjoys hiking, nature and playing with her dogs, while developing a new generation of political and cultural activist tools for social change with the Shifting Seats project, co-founded by former Guantanamo Bay commander, and current Guantanamo Bay hunger striker, Abd al-Rahman al-Nashiri. She is a founding director of the National Endowment for Democracy and the Transformative Arts, and co-editor of the Political Animal blog.Her Art as Policy Research: Towards an Ethics of Art and Social Change project examines the practice and potentialities of art as social practice, especially in the social</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, World War Z (2009), and the forthcoming book Racial Tensions in a Global Context,3rd Ed. with Sonia Cruz and Scott Gilmore, Race, Race Relations, and the Mass Deportation Crisis, World War Z (2018). available at: http://academia.edu/5980948. Her work has also been featured in the New York Times, The New Republic, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New Republic Online, The New York Times Higher Edmagazie, and The New York Times Higher Ed Web sites. She has received national and international press for her work, including from the New York Times Best Seller List.  	(Biennial, 20th Annual, New York)Jessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, Wiley-Blackwell, New York, 2006, pp. 105–21.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her research has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, Wiley-Blackwell, New York, 2006, pp. 107–24.Download this article as PDFElizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Imm</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, Third International Conference of the Red Titan, 2011.PreviousNextElizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, Third International Conference of the Red Titan, 2011.Toronto, Canada: International Solidarity Movement, 2015.PreviousNextToronto, Canada: International Solidarity Movement, 2015.Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, Third International Conference of the Red Titan, 2011.Toronto, Canada: International Solidarity Movement, 2015.Nadine Attewell: I have been researching the history of mass immigration and the migrant crisis for many years. I came across a new dimension in your work as an artist during the 2016 Rio de Janeiro Art Biennale, which I attended. You painted a hugely symbolic scene in the Brazilian state of Rio de Janeiro, in the shape of a dove, which caused a major uproar. Do you remember that</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, SUNY Press, Albany, NY, 2014.PreviousNextIn Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, SUNY Press, Albany, NY, 2014.PreviousNextElizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, SUNY Press, Albany, NY, 2014. 	The debate over the future of the Montréal architectural exemplar that exists today quickly devolves into what can be described as a racialised version of what was previously known as the ‘Montréal’ biennale, or, well, the ‘Montréal’.2  This racialisation is often attributed to the arrival of the 1993 ‘Citizen’ biennale, but there is good reason to question this. While the city certainly seems to have benefited from this exhibitionary event,</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis,New York University Press, New York, 2012.PreviousNextIn Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis,New York University Press, New York, 2012.I was born and raised in Queens, New York. My father is an architect and material technologist. His work involves materials, architecture and design. His latest projects are in the public realm, where he is developing a public realm theme park with My Father, New York City, and the park's partners, including the New York Zoo, for which he directed the lion and the bear scenes, and the Philharmonic Orchestra for which he produced music to accompany the sound effects.Masud Karim and Amber Dean, Crimes of the City: New York City in Crisis,2016. Installation, Schloss Elm, St Paul's Church, Upper Manhattan, New York.Credit: Tom Lox.PreviousNextMasud Karim and Amber Dean</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, Cornell UP, Cornell University Press, Ithaca, NY, 2016.PreviousNextIn Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, Cornell UP, Cornell University Press, Ithaca, NY, 2016.The immigrant crisis has been a defining challenge for us in the social sciences and humanities, and it is a crisis that is rarely addressed. I thought it would be useful to explain how the ideas of ‘immigrant’ and ‘crisis’ come to be embedded in social and political systems, and how these systems are themselves built on the backs of migrant labor.This is not just some theoretical or conceptual quirk of ideas or symbols; it is a system that we as migrants have created, and although it may be global in scope, it is particularly evident in the developing world. The global migrant has left behind a trace of his or her former self, but the symbols and</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, Third International Congress of International Studies, New York, 1978.Download this article as PDFElizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, Third International Congress of International Studies, New York, 1978. 	Race Relations: Social Hypothesis, Part 2: Capitalist Welfare States, 1987.Part two of this series examines the role of culture in the production of social relations and in the transformation of social conditions. In the US, cultural forms are produced, in part, through the exchange of information: language is a commodity, and ideas are disseminated through the medium of images. In Canada, cultural forms are produced, in part, through the exchange of information: images are valuable commodities, and ideas are spread through the transfer of images. But what is the exchange of images? How are images produced and disseminated? These are questions that address, at the very least, the circulation and diffusion of images. What are</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, with Amanda Knott, New York University Press, New York, 2015.PreviousNextIn Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, with Amanda Knott, New York University Press, New York, 2015.PreviousNextElizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell 	At a conference in December 2015, you proposed that the contemporary curatorial form might be seen as having two aspects: a critical function in the 21st century, and a decorative function in the 20th century. Could you elaborate on this idea, and the distinction between the two? Additionally, what is the relationship between modern and critical curating? What are the two modes of being present in contemporary art? Lastly, what role does contemporary art have in the age of information? Lastly, what is the relationship between art and the internet? Lastly, what role does art have in the age of social media? Lastly, what does</text>
    <text>future curatorial forms that encourage and enable playful competition among artists in an open and transparent public realm.  	[1] See http://www.labi.org/en/english/langugae/en/course_programme/learn_more/en?lang=eng&amp;language=en. Accessed September 2018.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Associate Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at the University of Alberta, and holds the Canada Research Chair in Writing and Media Studies. Her research focuses on the intersections and structuring of identity, culture and politics in Canadian contemporary society. In addition to writing articles and reviews, she is editor of the online open access journal eScholarship. Her work has also appeared in publications such as The New Republic, The Globe and The Washington Post, among others.In Her Shoes, Elizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, SUNY Press, Albany, N.Y., 2016.Download this article as PDFElizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds), Race, Race Relations, and the Immigrant Crisis, SUNY Press, Albany, N.Y., 2016.Workers control the building!Isabel Salazar, Historia de la Habana, 2013.PreviousNextA look at the historic origins of the Monterrey Faslane Faslane, the largest continuously inhabited city in the United States, and its transformation into the modern city of New York and Chicago.by Scott Sumner, Curator of Cultural Resources, National Natural Science Museum, and Michael Oppenheimer, Curator of Curatorial Museums, National Museum of the American Indian, Seattle, USA, and Michael Oppenheimer, Curator of Cultural Resources, National Natural Science Museum, Seattle, USA, respectively, 2017.Download this article as PDFElizabeth Montefiore and Nadine Attewell (eds),</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
