<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. It is here that the art of the city is made visible and the arts are made visible through culture, commerce, education and events. The museum, by virtue of its size and its location, is an art institution; and while it is art, it is also a social enterprise, a government instrument, and a means to an end – the establishment of a publicly accessible historical archive of cultural activity in the city. It is therefore fully aware of the need to engage with the biennial form in an exploratory and dynamic way. The Liverpool Biennial needs to be open to artists from all over the world, and it is hoped that the exhibition will draw artists together across cultural zones in a dynamic and interesting way.[1] The question of what counts as a ‘relevant cultural practice’ has become a contentious one in the arts and cultural sphere, and is closely linked to the concept of cultural productivity. In the modern context of mass media and urbanisation, the ‘core curatorial</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. The museum is a significant cultural resource for the young people and their families, offering them with unparalleled access to information about art and the cultural history of Liverpool. It is a site of frequent encounters between the art icons and the young people, a place where questions about art and culture are regularly posed and where questions about the arts are widely shared. It is a site of active participation by young people in a wide range of activities, from playing with   construction materials to creating arts-inflected landscape designs – much like the landscape they walk past every day. Despite these historical features, the museum often feels like an afterthought or is absent from communal and collective imaginings of the city. Its status as a cultural institution is frequently uncertain and hotly contested. It is a legacy asset that is often fetishised or caricatured. It is a site of frequent installations and performances, often created in response to its perceived marginalisation by the city. It is a site of cultural exchange between cultures, often framed</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. Its purpose is to showcase the art of the neighbourhood; it is a rare site for an outsider to enter and explore the neighbourhood. In this sense, the museum is like the street, it is a site of gathering where people come to connect, exchange, exchange, exchange, and make connections. It is a place where people gather to share experiences and make connections. It is a place where people make art together. But what makes the museum different from other cultural institutions is that it is a continuous site of inhabitation, a permanent site of exchange, sharing, connecting and making. It is a place of production and reproduction. It is a place of exchange between people, places, and things. And it is a place where art can flourish through innovative and powerful ways of being produced and reproduced.  The museum is a site of production and reproduction because it is a ‘production institution’. It manufactures, it manufactures, it manufactures, it manufactures, it manufactures art. It must produce</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. The museum is the primary cultural venue for undergraduate students and postgraduate students; it is the primary social hub; and it is a venue for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. In the past, the museum’s primary purpose has been to house collections and display collections; these two groups now constitute one biennial institution. The museum is a site for cultural exchange and cultural diversion. It is a place where art is displayed in a dynamic and dynamic way that engages the visitor and a community of artists, curators, students and others with a range of expertise and skills. It is a place where artists and artists’ organisations gather to exchange, collaborate and exchange. It is a place where artists can establish permanent residency or ​institutional status. It is a place where artists can establish partnerships and establish professional networks. It is a place where artists can establish an arts education programme and become artists’ teachers or researchers. In short</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. It is expected that this high demand for museum attendance arises from an abundance of jobs and opportunities, as a result of the biennial’s popularity, and that the high prices charged by biennials for access to galleries and exhibitions (often in proximity to each other) is a major factor in the city’s economic development. Liverpool Biennial: art, profits, and the social impact of deindustrialisation, 2010. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial Archive. 	Art’s social impact is a critical issue in our city. It is assumed that all artworks made in Liverpool will be made in a socially just city. However, this is not always the case. The Biennial’s profit and loss are the sole factors affecting the value of a work, and the community is often unaware of this aspect of the business. As a result, the community is often left behind in the economic and cultural turn around buildings in the city. 	In this analysis</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. Yet, despite its essential role, the museum is a site of conflict. It is a site of power struggles, of claims to jurisdiction, and of disputes over resources. It is a site of encounters between powerful vested interests and their powerless populations, of power brokers and its people. It is a site of visual encounters, of encounters in which powerful messages are sent both ­encouraged and impoverished. The Liverpool Biennial is an art institution committed to the production of culturally responsive artworks that addresses the city in a way that is both physically and metaphorically possible. Its collection, exhibitions, and various projects are committed to engaging with the city’s past, present and future through art that is both powerful and clear. Yet because there is a complex interplay of power structures and economies at play in every city, it is always difficult to identify art that is actually serving its intended communities. That is, powerful communities at odds with themselves and able to find creative ways to co-exist in</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. It provides a public gallery with unique in-gallery public performances and forum for discussion, education and discovery. It is a place where ideas and expressions circulate, where knowledge is shared and where ideas are firmly established. In other words, it is an essential site of political, social, and cultural change. Yet ironically, the museum is also the site of its own undoing. It is a site of power and control, where ideas and expression collide, where power is used to oppress and control. Its current curatorial mission is deeply problematic. It is the gallery that provides the site for dialogue, yet it actively participates in creating a site where those with a stake in the site decide what is said and what is not said. It is the gallery that supports the political, but it itself actively participates in suppressing knowledge. This is evident in the number of exhibitions held at the museum, which are often explicitly or implicitly biased in a way that contributes to the perpetuation of capitalist social models. The museum</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. It is here, in the main exhibition hall, that the arts community holds weekly open mike sessions to discuss the art and social context of the week, as well as exploring the art that is displayed. These have developed into symposia, or annual conferences) and now, well into their seventies, when a community arts movement has emerged as a result of these meetings. The Biennial has a long tradition of symposia and a tradition of biennials, but unlike other art worlds, the Liverpool Biennial is not a founding member of either the Venice or Amsterdam Biennalee. It holds regular meetings of the biennial committees, and as a result of these, and other important committee meetings, changes may be expected. It is the case that every ten years there is a major revamping of the art and cultural landscape of the city, and although the committee meetings that are now taking place again, or will soon be occurring, may not be the same as those that</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. Yet despite these assurances, the museum is often a barrier to artistic and cultural experiences for communities around it, and for many other artists and communities.  	In October 2018, the Biennial was presented with the Emerging Futures project, a unique $100,000 MacArthur Genius grant to explore the potentialities of community in art's evolution. This was the fourth time the Biennial had been given the grant, and its intention was to explore the possibilities of such a venue in the context of an exhibition.  	The 2017 edition saw the production of a new program of works that reflected the community’s cultural needs and desires. These included projects that addressed the community’s own lived experience and priorities, such as the community arts project at LJMU that year, and the production of a community of small businesses called ‘Cities ‘ in cooperation with LJMU Arts Advisors. These projects were conceived as ‘institutional projects’ within the museum</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is a collaboration between Liverpool Biennial, the Royal Academy of Arts, the Arts Council and Liverpool John Moores University (LJMU). The main objective of the exhibition is to celebrate the city’s past and to bring together the diverse arts communities of Liverpool. Art is one community’s favourite past-time. In a recent survey, two-thirds of respondents mentioned their love of art as their number one passion; almost two-thirds mentioned an appreciation for art as a source of inspiration. Art is an integral part of the community’s cultural landscape, and the museum is a crucial site for the arts community to find expression and witness the social and political history of the city. The importance of the museum cannot be understated. The museum is the primary cultural venue for the majority of LJMU students and faculty; it is their primary social hub; and it is a forum for the arts’ programming that differs from that found in the school, university and cultural district. Art is a social necessity in a city as diverse as Liverpool. It is a site of exchange, pilgrimage, pilgrimage – a place where ideas are exchanged, beliefs are formed, and actions are taken. But what does it mean to mean to mean to be inclusive or ‘in the moment’? How do artists understand and embody the experiences and motivations of the communities that comprise their audience? How do they create contexts and situations conducive to these processes? How do they create collaborative frameworks and strategies to achieve their objectives? These are questions that address contemporary artist-centred art in a city as diverse as Liverpool. 	There are countless biennials around the world, but few have as much impact or generate such passionate response from a place as the Liverpool Biennial has. It is the largest of many arts institutions established in the city, with branches in other cities, and internationally renowned artists managing cultural portfolios in various locations. It is the only institution of its kind in North America and has</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.
    <text>an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[7] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[8] http://www.reddit.com/r/SubredditDrama/comments/2q6p11/reddit_thread_meta_biennale_thread_l...[9] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[10] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[11] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[12] http://www.reddit.com/r/SubredditDrama/comments/2q6p11/</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23science-fiction-adventure/1279...[7] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23th...[8] http://www.reddit.com/r/starwars...[9] http://www.reddit.com/r/starwars...[10] http://www.reddit.com/r/Starwars...[11] https://www.linkedin.com/pub/linkedin...[12] http://www.reddit.com/r/Starwars...[13] http://www.reddit.com/r/Starwars...[14] http://www.reddit.com/r/Starwars...[15] http://www.reddit.com/r/Starwars...[16] https://www.lewrockwell.com/2017</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[7] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[8] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[9] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[10] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[11] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[12] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[13] https://www.google.com/</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[7] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/-amp;...[8] http://www.planetofplay.com/en/category/sci-fi-...[9] https://www.planetofplay.com/en/category/sci-fi-apocalypse/1/[10] http://www.planetofplay.com/en/category/sci-fi-assassination/1/[11] http://www.planetofplay.com/en/category/sci-fi-battle-royal-...[12] http://www.planetofplay.com/en/category/sci-fi-battle-royal-...[13] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-book/1279...[7] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi/books/gene/1279...[8] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi/books/gene/1279...[9] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi/books/gene/1279...[10] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi/books/gene/1279...[11] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi/books/gene/1279...[12] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi/books/gene/1279...[</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23science-fiction/163672&amp;...[7] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23imaginary-arena/38898/1279...[8] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23imaginary-arena/38898/24079?...[9] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23science-fiction/163672&amp;...[10] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23science-fiction/224 ...[11] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23science-fiction/224 ...[12] http://www.sci-fi-adventure.com/archive/index.html?...[13] http://www.sci-fi-adventure.com/archive/index</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[7] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23science-fiction/1279...[8] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23science-fiction/1279...[9] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23instant/1279...[10] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23instant/1279...[11] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23instant/1279...[12] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23instant/1279...[13] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23instant/1279...[14] RT @Karl: As an</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23science-fiction/1279...[7] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23video-games/1279...[8] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23battlefield-4/1279...[9] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23battlefield/1279...[10] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23battlefield/1279...[11] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23battlefield/1279...[12] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23battlefield-4/1279...[13] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23battlefield-4/1279...[14] http://www.</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[7] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23science-fiction/140316...[8] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23science-fiction/140316...[9] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23th...[10] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23th...[11] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23th...[12] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23th...[13] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23th...[14] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23th...[15] https://www.</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Technos NYC, New York, USA, 2016. Installation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.PreviousNextInstallation view at Welsh Streets Artspace, London, UK. Courtesy of the artist.[1] See also: http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/1/[2] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/2/[3] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/3/[4] http://www.communescanada.ca/en/2014/world-art-decade/4/[5] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[6] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[7] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[8] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[9] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[10] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[11] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[12] https://www.google.com/search?q=%23sci-fi-adventure/1279...[13] https://www.google.com/</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the museum may present a relatively static image of the phenomenon, the relationship between the museum and the city is an evolving one. Understanding that the museum is a site of imaginative potentialities and actualities, and that it provides the public with a site of actuality through its physical and virtual representations, is the first step in the public’s exploration of the city as a site of possibility. Curator Victoria Meadows believes that the museum is a site of continual expansion, describing it as ‘the most significant transformation of the city in the last 50 years’.9 But the city itself is in many ways the site of the aesthetic, and the site of the difficult or impossible to capture, ideate, analyse or narrate. It is the ‘substance of being’ that allows the myriad stories to pool into one general ‘hope and dream’, but it is also the ‘substance of being’ that makes it impossible to capture or narr</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the museum will draw on the findings and objects of the project, the other elements of the city are drawn into a conversation with the artefacts and objects themselves. The idea is to create a space where people can be drawn in both by the storyteller and the objects themselves. This can be seen as an important distinction in a city as diverse as Liverpool. The museum will have a particular responsibility in this regard, since it will be situated in a changing urban landscape, and the diverse audiences it will serve will be diverse as well. Nevertheless, the museum will always be a first-person point of entry into the city, and the artefacts and stories they represent, whether fictional or real, will always draw people to the city in a particular way. This is true even if the city is no longer a place with a significant number of residents, or is experiencing a rapid population explosion. The character of Raúl in &quot;The Odyssey of Homer and Hesiod&quot; is based on real-life local</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the original exhibition, ‘The Museum of Modern Art - A Post-Museum?’, addressed a specific architectural theme, the second one, ‘The Museum of Contemporary Art?’, will focus specifically on the social and political connotations and present-day situation of the region. The museum should be a site of discussion, learning and discovery, where diverse perspectives and approaches can be brought to bear on the task at hand. The museum is a site of production, innovation and conflict. It is a place of production, innovation and conflict where art is made to fit societal needs and expectations. It is a place of interaction, exchange and creativity. It is a place of production, innovation and conflict. It is a site of production, innovation and conflict. It is a site of information. It is a site of memory. It is a site of conflict. It is a site of information. It is a ‘soft’ surface.’It should be a place</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the museum will offer a focus on the historical objects and people associated with Liverpool, the Biennial will produce reports that draw on a range of other disciplines, offer a new perspective on a situation or theme, or render an interpretation of existing laws, values and frameworks. The reports will range from the mundane (like the ones produced by the Liverpool Biennial on a regular basis) to the extraordinary (like those produced by the Liverpool Biennial on a global scale). The reports will not only show the persistent impact of the housing crisis and its effects on communities across the UK and abroad, but may also contribute to creating new knowledge and possibilities for the future of the area. In this sense, they will perform a kind of radical reconfiguration of the past, present and future in the area that is in some ways more intimately linked to the present. 	At the same time, the proliferation of the biennial has placed unprecedented demands on the biennial’s resources, limiting its historical research potential.</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the museum will have a primary role in creating a sense of place and history in the region, it will play an increasing role in connecting the present with the past, and in this process, facilitating the ongoing evolution of the local and regional identities of people in the region. The position of the museum is to play a pivotal role in this process of co-creation and co-responsibility. It is critical that the museum is empowered to undertake projects that transcend its traditional roles and that engage people from different walks of life and different walks of life. Art and artists have a unique vantage point in this regard, which is why they are often asked to take on projects that are not based on facts or the truth, even when such projects could potentially change the world. The Liverpool Biennial will be no different. Its mandate will be based on fiction and the fiction of others. Nevertheless, the museum will undoubtedly play a pivotal role in the creation of the fiction of the region and in the perpetuation of a shared</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the museum will focus on specific places and persons, the project elements, including the buildings, will increasingly exhibit the histories and present-day political and economic dynamics of the region. This will happen in part due to the urban sprawl and intensification of development in the region, which will in turn create new tax-advantaged venues for cultural activities. Liverpool Biennial is committed to examining local, regional and global contexts through art and culture made locally. Aspects of the regional context will be showcased through the curatorial direction of the Biennial and the project's production in other art institutions and online platforms. Liverpool Biennial will produce a curated collection of work around its proposed site and time for online, curatorial and museum viewing. The collection will include works from all contributors, from original and emerging artists, as well as curatorial appointments from established and emerging curators. These curatorial appointments include: David Hockney, The New Curator, 2015-16; Teresa Atangana</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the museum and its contents will narrate the story, the other elements will be the protagonists in a new narrative that is informed by and dependent on the knowledge of the urban and regionalised citizen. The term ‘collective memory’ is frequently used in relation to the contemporary condition, and while it is true that the memory of an area can be traced back to the area itself, this is increasingly difficult to accomplish in the face of globalised economic and social media culture, which celebrates places and people everywhere and everywhere at once. As a consequence, the museum is often cited as an initial site for the gathering of knowledge, and the initial stages of such gathering are a critical juncture in the history of the area. While the initial gathering may offer some initial insights into the current condition, this is often followed by a longer ‘collective memory’ crisis. For some, this is followed by an increased need for formal and institutional change, while for others – myself included – it remains largely</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the museum may offer a physical object or set of objects that function as a starting point, the actual production of such knowledge will be organised through collaborative learning processes between the various disciplines and communities that comprise the region. The two major art schools in the area, Birkbeck and Liverpool John Moores Universities, as well as the City University of New York, are both part of this process. Liverpool Biennial is also undertaking a collaborative research programme with the City University of New York, NYU Langone Medical Center and Build-A-Center, a local community land trust, which will see the revived Museum of Tractable Art brought to life through collaborative research and teaching. Liverpool Biennial is an international art institution based in the Basque Country, near to the Spanish-speaking city of Barcelona. It was founded in 1966 and is the largest holder of the Art World Diploma and the largest holder of the Biennial Certificate. It is also a founding partner of the Biennial Confederation. The Biennial was</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the museum will draw on the expertise of experts in their respective fields, its primary mission is to bring together and share experiences from different points of view and with different communities. This will allow the museum to function as a hub for sharing, a place to exchange, and a place of discovery for the engaged public. Liverpool Biennial will merge traditional curatorial approaches with new media to bring a new perspective and approach to the museum, while preserving the historical integrity of the museum. The museum will be managed in a cooperative, multi-disciplinary manner, drawing on experience and expertise from the local area, international gallery trade, academia and industry. The museum will be created in a way that engages with the traditions and histories of the area and invites reflection from the public, while creating new ones. Aspects of the museum that are historically significant in the area will be preserved in their current form while new circumstances and perspectives are brought to bear on the art, architecture and practice that is currently occurring in the neighbourhood. This will</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new series of museums and cultural institutions that will offer a hybrid platform of educational, political and historic, urban and regional, in-depth studies. The focus of the museum will be regional, taking into consideration the history and present-day situation in the region, while the other elements will provide a diverse range of knowledge on a local or regional level. The overarching theme of the museum, which will be loosely based on actual places and people, is a hybrid between the original mythological places and creatures (usually indigenous to the area), the anthropologists and archaeologists of the present, and various other anthropological, archaeological and linguistic disciplines. The museum will showcase the findings and objects of the project in a way that invites reflection, discussion and creativity from a public that is interested in its history and culture. Liverpool Biennial will also investigate the ways in which sites and people are drawn to, and against, the prevailing flow of history, technology and commerce in the region. While the museum and the local community might form the bulk of the project, the Biennial will also employ local artists, historians, landscape architects and other artists to create a shared context and experience of the area. 	Unlike other biennials, where the cultural objects are acquired and displayed for a specific period of time, the actual performances and exhibits in the Liverpool Biennial will be acquired and displayed for a set period of time. The acquisition and display of cultural property is often done with the aim of stimulating a transient, transient or phantom interest in the area; in other words, the act of acquiring and displaying cultural property can be seen as a way to divert cultural resources from where they are needed the most – in the community – to engage more directly with the people who inhabit the area and create a shared culture.  	In this sense, the act of acquiring and displaying cultural properties can be seen to be a form of collective memory, a process through which specific historical moments in the area are reproduced</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to categorize living things, and it includes features of both the ‘good’ and ‘bad’ kinds. But it fits within the framework of living things, and through a process of mutation and adaptation, produces new species, along with new lineages of evolution.  A similar dynamic is unfolding within the marine world: through a combination of molecular biology and zoology, scientists are uncovering the evolutionary roots of everything from dirty beaches to plankton blooms and even seaweed colonies to become more and more adept at mapping and understanding evolutionary lines, strains, and populations.  A strand of the recently discovered human genome – 1.5 billion base pairs – is mapped to this dynamic genealogy ­– making it possible to read the history of a strand of the zebra or teddy bear's genetic code, and of other species, in a way that neither the human genome nor the mitochondrial genome ever could.  This mapping also makes it possible to manipulate evolutionary history through tweak-n</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to categorise living things – living things include humans – and makes deeper distinctions. For example, the zebra and the teddy bear are closely related lineages, but the zebra species are distinct from each other and other animals, with very different evolutionary histories.  In 1849, William Lane Terry of Liverpool and John Graham Kerr of Edinburgh proposed what might be called ‘Darwinism’. Terry imagined a world in which natural selection applied Darwin’s theory of natural selection to all living things, including humans. Aliens, he said, must differ from all other kinds of creatures in that they acquire traits through natural selection – traits that make them better suited for a given situation. Terry and his colleagues argue in favour of the theory in their book That Random Happened To Be Great: On Morality And Patriotic Literature And Apology For The Medieval Man (1937) And they argue against it in their book Better Than Ever: On Morality And National Identity (1937).</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to categorise living things into categories, but both share the idea that there is a split-second after the moment of conception that counts as unique within the species. How do we, as humans, come to understand these moments as different from when species were first described? In the course of our scientific theorising, we are able to discover how the human species came to be divided into different species: how the human species emerged from the animal kingdom into a completely different kind of animal kingdom, and then evolved again – this time as a completely different kind of animal kingdom.  Whether the split-second after the fertilisation of a human egg represents an actual event – the moment when an egg begins to take form – or whether it is a fictional invention – the use of this split second in the human reproduction process represents a significant shift from the kind of organism that we typically think of as evolving gradually over decades or even centuries, to one in which living things constantly jostle one another. This shift in</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to categorise living things into categories, but it enables us to see deeper within living things. For example, the zebra and the teddy bear share certain physical traits, but what sets the two species apart is their internal dynamics – their behaviour – which gives rise to certain biological distinctions. What make the zebra and the bear different is that the former resorts to war rather than negotiation, while the latter engages in economic self-sufficiency. If the zebra and the bear are considered to be exhibiting certain intrinsic values, then the question becomes, how does one bring about a ‘subspecies’ that diverges in certain ways but that shares similar lineages of evolutionary history but has different lineages of internal dynamics? This is the zygote dilemma. If the internal dynamics of the zygote prevail, then the child will quickly acquire a set of characteristics that are shared by its parents and, within a matter of months, a distinct set of novel ones. If the internal dynamics of</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to think of living things as separate from each other. But Müller is able to trace the lineage of a species because that lineages contains enough genetic information to map onto a molecularly-studied species. Without this genetic information, the theory would be impossible to understand. Through a precise genetic mapping, the theory can point to the species at the root of a problem or set of problems. Without this, it is limited to identifying the specific branches of a tree with enough certainty to allow for the possibility that species exist at the root of the problem. If the tree is not jus in ‘species’, but in some other kind of non-living entity, then the problem is species-specific. In that case, the theory would only apply to living things, not to non-living things such as viruses or bacteria.  When I read the transcript of the conference talk that Sebastian Mehr led in 2017, I felt like I was reading a narrative that captured the essence of the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to categorize living things – animals in general – and it allows us to see deeper into the world of life. How animals come to share certain characteristics with each other is a question that scientists are now better able to answer. For example, scientists are now able to distinguish between two lines of evidence that are often cited by natural-rights activists as supporting the idea that human activity is ‘contaminated’ with the spread of scientific knowledge: the fossil record and microscopic fossil tools. How can the capacities of individuals be trained to notice and act on similarities between species that are common in both humans and between species?  A second line of evidence for the idea that humans are inherently ‘different’ from nonhuman animals comes from the observation that, according to the Oxford English Dictionary, humans incorporate elements of Greek and Latin mythology into our language, including the ‘gods’ and ‘demon-folk’ that were once thought to inhabit the Earth. Is the English language somehow</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to categorise living things into categories, but it provides the framework by which we can begin to question the ways in which living things are classified. While the theory may be used to categorise, it is much more useful when applied to the very definition of a living thing: what it is to be alive. To apply Müller’s theory to the elephant, we would have to establish a separate and distinctively biological category for each animal, and then map these categories to the physical categories that we see in the elephant: fur, skin, bones, muscles, organs, fluids and more. This would mean mapping organs not just to tissues, but also to living things: elephants, humans, water, air, fire, earth and the elements around them. How does the theory apply to the animal kingdom as a whole? Is it applicable to the zebra and teddy bear, or only to the elephant and its constituent parts? The answer should allow us to begin to question these things, and</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to categorise living things into categories, or, well, categories. For one thing, animals don’t have human characteristics or ‘personhood’ that categorise them as such. Secondly, and perhaps more importantly, the concept of personhood doesn’t evolve along the same lines as the structure of the human species. Thirdly, and perhaps most fundamentally, the concept of personhood is not a fixed thing, but rather evolves along different lines than what is found in the zebra and teddy bear. For instance, the zebra and the teddy bear share many of the same genes, but whereas the human genome projects to make a foetus, an animal like the zebra or the teddy bear makes up of pieces that evolve over evolutionary time – pieces that change form and function. The human genome, and the pieces that make up its components, change place and are constantly undergoing chemical changes that reshape and shape the body in interesting ways. Finally, there is</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to categorise living things into groups – living things are not divided into sub-species or distinct species – but it is also fundamentally the same as the one we use to describe living things in science. How do we, as scientists, understand the power of symbolic language and symbolic behavior? How does the power of the symbolic map itself – the very notion – exert itself?  Finally, what does it mean to be ‘scientifically literate?’ This is a question that philosophers, natural scientists and anthropologists have been asking themselves, and answers have been coming from everywhere. In this issue of Scientific American, Lisa Margler explores the idea of generativity in relation to the zebra and the teddy bear, from its origins in the nineteenth century to the present.  A generative process? Yes. A scientific witness? Certainly. But what does it mean to be ‘scientifically literate?’? I think that scientific literacy means understanding how the world really is, how</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about living creatures; the question is, how does it make sense as a scientific question? In the case of the zebra and the teddy bear, scientists have recently begun to figure out that the answers are both yes and no. What does it mean to be a zebra or a teddy bear? What is the relationship between the two? Is there a continuum between the two?  In 1845, Max Müller proposed a theory of ‘species’ that he called ‘subspecies’ – subspecies lines that diverge in only morphological ways – and that evolve along distinct lines of evolution. These subspecies diverge into distinct lineages, and within each lineage a new branch of evolutionary history is traced. Through careful genetic analysis, Müller was able to trace the evolutionary history of the zebra and the teddy bear, and eventually of all animals with a common ancestor. This theory of ‘species’ is fundamentally different from the one we use to categorise living things, and it enables closer observation of the processes that create and tear apart living species. For this reason, researchers developing lineages of animals through molecular biology and other approaches are increasingly employing subspecies while maintaining the notion of the common ancestry in mind. While Müller’s theory has made great advances in our understanding of how living things form clusters of traits – what he called ‘substrates’ – it remains deeply controversial, and disputes persist about what constitutes a subspecies. For example, a recent Pew Research Center study of public attitudes toward evolution found that roughly equal shares of Americans (52 percent) and Chinese (53 percent) believe that humans evolved from nonhuman animals, and another 31 percent think that humans and nonhuman animals are similar.1  Similarly, a 2014 survey by the Pew Forum on American Islam found that while more than half (54 percent) of Americans now identify as religiously unaffiliated, roughly equal shares identify as Muslim or Muslim affiliated.2</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So,
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So, what is being made, what is taking place in the world today, is in fact occurring at an unprecedentedly rapid rate.This kind of rapidity is a characteristic feature of contemporary capitalism, and it is a feature that is set to continue to be so for a long period of time to come. But it is important to distinguish between what is being made and what is being consumed. And this is precisely what we mean when we talk about the past, about the past in terms of the present. We do not mean the past as a past that has ended, or as a past that is no longer happening. We mean the future as a future that is constantly (increasingly, in my estimation) influenced by the past, and so we need a kind of spatial horizon – a kind of spatial reference – to distinguish the past and future. In other words, what we mean when we speak of past or future perforations is the kind of temporal horizon that exists today, and will continue to</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So, as we move into the future, we are entering into a temporality that is both punctured by technological obsolescence (as we witnessed with the iPod and the smartphone) and on the whole rushes by with record numbers of devices constantly in the know. It is a kind of ‘black box’ with seemingly iron-clad control mechanisms, but it is also a ‘time capsule’ that nonetheless holds a residue of the horror and degradation of modernity. This kind of temporal heterogeneity is characteristic of the new ‘world economy’, which is to say, not only of technological obsolescence, but also of a qualitatively different kind of contemporaneity – a kind of ‘postindustrial society’ that is neither post nor pre-industrial. And so we are entering into a temporality in which the seemingly endless proliferation of devices and data capture and dissemination is experienced as if it were contemporaneous with a kind of contemporaneity that is ‘postindustrial</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So, we are entering a situation in which there is a great deal of truth in what is being said about the past, but there is a tendency towards a kind of simplified and compressed present – a kind of present that is no longer able to absorb the past but which nonetheless seeks to preserve some of its outward appearance and properties.And this kind of rapidity – this stuff that is being said about the past – is closely related to what I would call the technocratic tendency. It is a tendency towards generative efficiencies, towards what I would call the future that is not beholden to the past. And this is precisely what we are witnessing in the world we are living in now, with all of its destructiveness, all of its proliferation of trivialities, its tendency towards vast aggregations of data, and all of its tendency towards this kind of rapidity of thought and movement. So, we have been conditioned to live in this immediate, material, quotidian way, to see and experience the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So, we are entering a world in which much of what is being produced is of a characterologically explosive kind, and we do not yet know which kind of character to watch out for.  One can only imagine what the future might hold.  Another possibility is that we are entering a world in which, by some calculations, half the Earth's population is hooked on the internet. This would mean that half the planet is exposed to the vagaries of disruptive technologies, and half of the planet to climate disruption. We do not yet know how these social disruptions might be organised, but given the scale of the challenge before humanity, humanity has a particular interest in finding ways to ensure that the distributed forms of sociality that are now emerging are not superseded by future forms of social organisation.  A final alternative is that we are entering a world in which socialities emerge simultaneously across space and time, as in Matrix. But this kind of social organisation would also mean that individuals no longer exist in a quasi-</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So, we are experiencing, as technology makes ever more extensive and pervasive its effects, a kind of temporal complexity that is itself a product of historical accidents and through processes of accrual. This kind of temporal complexity is a kind of archaeological anomaly, and it is to be expected in a technologically advanced society. But there is a way in which this kind of technological singularity is not inevitable, and in fact is the opposite: technological singularity is a condition of spectacular and extremely costly social disruption and disruption. So, there is a criticality to this kind of technological singularity.And this is what science and technology are up to now. They are up to no good, beyond even the most optimistic predictions of some of the discontented thinkers within the scientific and technocratic middle classes. They are up to becoming human resources crunch blocks, which is to say, susceptible to the fads and fads of the moment, which can be mobilized and automated to meet the needs of the moment. And this kind</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So, we are witnessing in action here a kind of pre-eminent-among-his-groups-only-problem-solving-time-reclamation, pre-eminent-among-his-groups-only-solving-time-reclamation. And here we have another aspect of this ‘problem solving’ time, namely, the economic. It is precisely this element of the economic that has made the contemporary condition ripe for the emergence of ecological estrangements, and has made it possible for us, since the late nineteenth century, to identify with some of the more sinister aspects of the economic machine. 	At the same time, the economic has also created a kind of social occurence that is not easily grasped. It has created what Bertolt Brecht called ‘a kind of public, a public of symbols and an arena of interactions’. It has created what Mary Turner Fleming called ‘a public of habit, or a public of expectations�</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So, if we are looking to imagine a larger temporal backdrop here, we also need to be aware of a marked increase in the number of dimensions of technological advancement in the intervening centuries, which has been identified as a global ecological crisis. This is, of course, an extremely long way from the city of New York, but the notion of the city of New York in the age of the automobile is no longer sufficient to render its preservation politically possible. We need to be aware that there are other kinds of cities, and we need to be aware that we are moving toward a world with a planetary scale of technological capability. This kind of acceleration in the social and cultural domain is unprecedented, and it is creating new kinds of conflicts. But it is also creating new vocabularies – vocabularies of media, identities, behaviours, behaviours – vocabularies that are defined and defined by the technologies that enable those conflicts to occur. And this is what we mean when we speak of ‘the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So, we are entering a world in which much of what is described as ‘the past’ is actually occurring all of the time, and in which much of what is referred to as ‘the future’ is actually already here and will remain so for some time to come. This kind of rapid temporal fragmentation is a feature of contemporary capitalism, and it is happening at a rapid pace in many parts of the world. But it is also happening at a phenomenal rate in certain cities, particularly in the West, and it is believed to be the reason for the recent upward curve in global GDP and stock market prices. So, the idea that we are living in the ‘past’ seems to have captured some of the imagination of some people, and perhaps some beliefs about the future, at least.I would add that the notion of the present in many places, including in societies such as the United States, is quite different from the notion of the past. For example, the idea of</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So, we are witnessing, here, a kind of punctum of the temporal, as it were, as it were. Futurism, I think, represents, in a certain way, this punctum. It is a kind of punctum that predicts the punctum of the temporal, but it is punctum of a different kind, because it does not take place in the temporal but in the (non-time) dimension. So, it does not represent, as traditional forms of art do, a kind of temporal displacement, but rather represents a punctum that is itself subject to temporal displacement. And this kind of punctum is exactly what biennials are: they are annuals, and they are punctums in themselves.I would like to suggest a couple of further points about this kind of punctum. For one thing, the dominant form of temporal punctum, and this is true of biennials as a whole, is the punctum of the everyday. And the punctum</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data on a daily basis, that is, that is, that is, in every possible way. This data is of course constantly evolving, and represents a reconstruction of the past, but it is also a reconstruction made up of fragments from many different pasts. It is a kind of time capsule, but it also represents a kind of present – a fragmented, but present – in which much of what we can identify with regards to the past is also happening, and that is to say, much of what we can identify with regards to the present is also occurring at an extremely rapid pace. And this kind of rapidness is a feature of the global economy, as we have seen. And it is important to notice that we are talking here not of the past but of the future, because, as we have seen, there is a marked increase in both the speed of technological advancement (which is to say, of scientific and artistic perforations) and in the durability of that technological advance. So, there is a marked increase in both the number and the variety of perforations. And what is being made, what is being reproduced at an increasingly rapid rate in the past, is in itself a remarkably human phenomenon.We can also question the relevance of an archaeological perforation in relation to contemporary social formations. We can point to particular perforations, and say: ‘What is it that we as an audience could identify with?’ And we could point to specific artistic perforations, and say: ‘What are those elements of the present that we could identify with?’ The audience could follow these elements, and thereby become culturally responsive. We could even point to cultural dynamics that generate elements of a given perforation – for instance, the proliferation of social media and the advent of ever more expansive, public perforations – and say: ‘These elements of social media are artifacts of a particular historical moment.’ And we could point to the fact</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want to be able to say: ‘That was beautiful’ or ‘That was horrible’? If we can, then why wouldn’t we? The beauty of it all is that we can, and that is why we do it. It is also why we have to continue to evolve, and that is why we make art. We don’t make art to be liked; we make art to break free. This is the paradox of modernity: the more art is made, the more we have to ask ourselves and others: what is this art that we are going to like? And the more we break free, the more art we have to consume. This is the second part of my three-day exhibition, 'Codex Alera', which explores Aleran's work from the Nineteenth Century to the Present. The first part, 'Codex Alera', was delivered in person in Venice on 19 and 20 October 2016. The exhibition takes viewers</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want to be able to say: ‘That was beautiful, that was beautiful, that was art’? Or, even better, ‘That was beautiful in its simplicity, but I see a way to be innovative and dynamic’? Today, this may no longer be possible, and it’s becoming increasingly difficult to imagine art or art’s potentialities elsewhere. But at the same time, we are becoming increasingly aware that artists’ social media followings are much too circumscribed: not enough of a taste to change gallery policy, but enough for a local audience, and perhaps even enough for a global audience. This is the social media age, and artists and curators are often accused of being complacent, lacking in imagination, lacking in ambition, and lacking in connections. This is often attributed to the decline of traditional gallerieship, and the proliferation of specialist venues, but it is also true that in the age of the biennial, the biennial is the</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want to be able to say, with all museums and art institutions of the world, that it is still possible to visit a particular art museum because of technology? The answer to this question is probably ‘yes’. It is true that today’s museums are often massively over-dressed, and their collections of art, objects and collections of performances are an extraordinary amount to manage. But this is the world we live in, and so we have to manage it. We can’t just stop being who we are and move away from the things that are fuelling the conflicts and tensions of our contemporary world. I believe that is simply not possible: we have to create new ways of understanding the world.This is the second part of a three-part series on Conflict and Crisis in Contemporary Culture. Part one, from October 2015, looks at the art world’s increasing reliance on social media. Part two, from August 2016, looks at the art world’s</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want to be able to say, as Goethe said, ‘I’ve done with you what you've done with me?’ If we do, then surely, as Goethe wrote, we can say, ‘You’ve seen enough. Let’s see what you do with yourself.’Download this article as PDFGabriela RendonGabriela Rendon is an architect and Principal in the office of Luis Antonio Capelo, who works in the portfolio of the Museo de Arte Contempora. She has a special interest in the urbanisation of the former Hill House district in San Cristóbal de las Casas, capital of the Andes Province, and is currently researching the activities of the then Municipal de la Lutenda de Arte Contempora, where she is pursuing a Masters in Urban Studies. She is also pursuing a PhD in the department of Architecture and Urbanization at the London School of Economics. She has worked</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want to be able to say, with some assurance that the systems that enable art to happen are automated, and with some uneasiness about how this might happen given the scale of what we live with every day, but also with some uneasiness about the deeper social causes that might result from this new synthesis of art and infrastructure? Perhaps, over time, it would be possible to engineer biennials that operated with greater autonomy, but right now we’re much more likely to associate them with the latest trendsetter, to the next Facebook user, to the next Twitter user who can befollowed. Such is the nature of the biennial condition. It’s impossible to know what would happen if the biennial ceased to be, although the possibilities are certainly there. But what we do know is that art would have to be organized in such a way as to meet the needs of society in a way that is artistically difficult, and politically unstable, and politically powerless, and</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want to be able to say that we know what infrastructure is because we have seen how it is used? In an ideal world, museums and galleries and other art spaces would connect with what is happening in the city and inform our thinking; but we don’t live in that world. We live in a world where the infrastructure of our cities is physically incapable of supporting anything, and yet art is made where it can. This is the ultimate in bureaucracy: it is impossible to comprehend the scale of something unless you’ve physically seen it before. In this world, infrastructure really does exist, but it is generally seen as something that is constructed, and so we tend to ignore its many forms and activities. This is part of the capitalist logic: if you deconstruct it, eventually everything will be made accessible – and so we do it anyway because we can: it is part of our addiction to accessorize, and so we do it because it makes us feel good, because it is beautiful</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want to be able to say, with some justification, that art has been made in this location? If the answer to that is ‘yes’ then surely the ability to say so would be part of the overall value proposition of the institution: a way to imply that the infrastructure behind art was actually made in this location. In the end, that is part of the attraction: the promise of infrastructure that can nonetheless be used for art is part of the appeal of the biennial. That is, the infrastructure that can nevertheless support artistic practices yet also make possible the politics of infrastructure is part of the attraction. That is, the infrastructure can nevertheless be made useful by art, but also politically unpredictable. The biennial may well have come to represent the inevitable erosion of sovereignty in the interest of infrastructure, but that is still part of the package.Art is art, and like all art, it is inherently unpredictable. But the unpredictable part is particularly powerful: the biennial can effectively and sensibly shift</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want to be able to connect to our infrastructure and know that infrastructure supports art? If the answer is ‘yes’, then surely the answer is ‘yes’ – and ‘yes’ – meaning ‘yes’ in various ways.Download this article as PDFLora Posthumaora Posthumaora is Curator for Embedded Systems at the Whitney Museum of American Art. Her research interests include embedded systems, autonomous media and web development, as well as the role of art in the evolution of computer programming.She served as Artistic Director of the New York Art Biennial 2016 and was part of the curatorial team for the 2018 Venice Biennale. Posthumaora's art has been featured in numerous publications including Wired, The Washington Post, BBC Future, CNN, The Hollywood Reporter, The New York Times, CNN Digital Media, and many others. She is a founding member of the Embedded Systems and Emerging Technologies curatorial team at the Whitney</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want art to happen through what we do in the biennial, or does it need to be done through what we do in the city? I think it is a yes/no question, with artists responding to it either way. The challenge for curators is to find the balance between the two. If the answer to that question is 'it depends', then the biennial is likely to become what it is today because it depends on how much is made by the city. If the answer is 'it is made by everyone and anything goes', then the biennial may not be what it is today because it depends on who is inside the biennial and how it is circumscribed.The answer to the second part of your question – what is the relationship between biennials and the city as a continuous space? – is a bit trickier to define. There is a sense of city-as-continuum here that is foreign to what we are accustomed to, which is to curate spaces.</text>
    <text>curated by a machine’s vision. The implication was clear: Computers, be they smart or ugly, could read and write and do all sorts of things that humans couldn’t. And so the biennial’s annual budget was made up of things that couldn’t be bought with money and so on.’ While this may have been true in the early days, the fact of the art being made – and the value attached to it – is becoming increasingly abstracted. More and more, we are left to think of the art as something that is embedded in the very systems that enable art to happen. This is an increasingly important connotation for an art museum: as infrastructure is restructured, often unconsciously, through the use of new technologies, it is now possible to link art and infrastructure in ways that render infrastructure obsolete, but which also create new infrastructure that is as capable of supporting art as ever before.In the end, this all boils down to this: do we want to be able to say that we know what infrastructure is because we have seen it somewhere before? If the answer is yes, then perhaps it is time to change the name of the infrastructure – be it infrastructure capitalism or something more encompassing – and start calling it infrastructure magic. The magic of infrastructure therefore becomes a very real thing, and an increasingly important one. It is this new understanding of infrastructure politics that is driving the discussion of how to empower artists and how to support creative activity in the form of infrastructure projects.In the coming years, we may find ourselves asking whether the magic of infrastructure is really what enables infrastructure to support artists’ creative activities, or whether something else is at play. Perhaps the answer to this question is to be found in the city’s ongoing financial mismanagement, which is currently being addressed by the city council despite being mandated by the state constitution to do so. The city is growing beyond its borders, but its true capacity to affect change in the city is limited</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face, flashy, brilliant urban experimentation – the Biennale must negotiate a set of values and political positions with the local people, and with visitors to the city. If the Biennale is to achieve its stated mission of understanding the city and its inhabitants, then it must negotiate complex and contradictory situations. And it is this ongoing negotiation of the city that the Biennale must be part of. Otherwise, the Biennale risks becoming part of any number of different tourist attractions, and part of the urban landscape all around the globe. If the Biennale is to be imaginative and provocative, then it must find a place in a city that is both present and inhabitable, so that its cultural capital and its daily realities can be lived in. Otherwise, the Biennale is forced to adopt a political and legal position that is both present and inhabitable. Creative and innovative cultural institutions everywhere – including, surely, the Biennale – must find a home in a city that is both</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face displays of architecture – the Biennale needs to work constructively against entrenched power structures, while simultaneously demanding accountability and change.  	In the current political moment, the Biennale needs to find creative ways to engage with the city, while simultaneously demanding accountability and change. We don’t yet know which paradigm will be tested, but the possibilities are quite compelling. The challenge for the Biennale is to find creative ways to engage with the city while simultaneously demanding accountability and change, while making the city a valuable and participatory investment for the future of Paris.Download this article as PDFLorida City Council, 2015. Image courtesy of Wikimedia Commons.PreviousNextNew Yorkers in their Disneyland costumes attend the first day of Operation: American Hero, the annual celebration of American military history and culture in France, on November 18, 2015, in Paris. Photographer: Mathias Schmitz.PreviousNextNew Yorkers in their Disneyland costumes attend the first day of Operation: American Hero</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face displays of architecture – the Biennale should engage with the needs and politics of the city in order to generate knowledge, inform action and occasionally to create new urban realities. It is this last ambition that the Biennale must strive to achieve, if it is to achieve the kind of institutionalisation and political leverage necessary to alter its political context and consequently its very being. If such changes are to come, they must come from above, from the grassroots, and urbanists and urban theorists must be part of the conversation. We do not know what the city will be like in 2080, but we can be certain that the Biennale will have a huge impact, manifesting itself in ways that reverberate through the city and beyond. This is the urban-research agenda of the Biennale: what may be done with archaeological and archival resources, what can be learned from them, and how to act on that knowledge. It is this research agenda that is fundamentally at odds with the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face displays of architecture – the Biennale has a responsibility to present itself constructively, but it also has a legal obligation to advocate for and contribute to the achievement of the social and political transformation that comes with a democratic society.  	The Biennale should not adopt a fixed visual language for the social processes involved in city formation, nor should it try to impose its will upon the city. It should instead try to embody the social processes involved in city formation in a way that is as organic and holistic as possible. This is why urban theorists and urban commentators today often speak in terms of ‘regeneration’. It is not just an expression of the notion of urban future, but a dynamic process that involves a shift from present to future, from the present to the past, and in effect, from the present to the future. This is what urban theorists and urban commentators today mean when they talk about ‘regeneration’. It involves a shift from the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face displays of architecture – the Biennale has to negotiate certain forms of political marginalisation and bureaucracy, and its own fetishisation of culture as a political tool. It has to negotiate the real-life and virtual multiplicity of urban environments, and its everyday life with material forms of urban infrastructure. And it has to negotiate the politics, ideology and law of the material forms it feeds on. If the Biennale is to become a true art institution, and not just a showroom for exhibitions, then it has to develop a politics of the representations and lifestyles of the city. Otherwise, as the biennaleer, it becomes just another exhibitionary venue. This is why art biennials, such as Biennials Liverpool, continue to be at the centre of the contemporary art world's social and economic dynamic, and why, in a city so preoccupied with the market, the Biennale is often at the centre of its own economic one. Because, in a city as</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face displays of architecture – the Biennale can and should seek ways to bring its political and social meanings into the present, while simultaneously generating political and legal uncertainty around future urban development. It is a mixed bag to be sure. 	The Biennale must work in an ever more nuanced and multi-valued way, and it mustn’t become trapped in its current form of cultural nationalism. The Biennale must be a creative agent, capable of operating at many different speeds simultaneously, in a moment, a habit and a space. The Biennale’s current iteration of itself, the Venice Biennale, is a great example of this multi-dimensionality. It doesn’t have the power or the ability to change the political or the social, but it can certainly affect the cultural, of which it is a quintessence.‘Tis the season to be alive!’ – Ed. Notebook 20/21. 	[</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face urbanism? – the Biennale has to negotiate a range of contradictory situations, and so it can produce many kinds of urban experiences, including those that are pleasant for the tourist and others that are not so pleasant but serve the city well. 	But the complexity of the urban environment demands that the Biennale negotiate a particular set of urbanities. And so the Biennale needs to negotiate these contradictory situations in order to produce in its territory desirable urban experiences for tourists and locals alike. And so the Biennale must negotiate a logic that produces desirable and that is not so desirable urban environments. If the Biennale is to function as a cultural institution and as a site for urban debate and experimentation, it is imperative that the areas it works through be places where people can be free to be able to inhabit and be part of that environment. These are the urban conditions that a cultural institution like the Biennale is committed to creating.Art’s social function in our</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face, strikingly urban planning – the Biennale has to be seen as a tool, a set of tools, and not a master of cities. It is a cultural institution, and a dynamic variable. It can either support or deradicalise it. It cannot be both. The Biennale should be seen as a creative, unpredictable and flexible platform that can be adapted to meet the particular needs (political, social and economic) of the city at a moment's notice. It is a long-term investment, and a cultural practice that is deeply rooted in the area, but it is also an inherently unstable one. That is, the Biennale as an artistic practice is itself a political and economic construction, and the political and economic conditions of the city it produces are always going to be a threat. That is, the Biennale as a cultural practice is itself a political and economic production. And as such, it too is subject to the uncontrollable whims of a dynamic and</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face, aesthetically uninteresting, sometimes-ruined-but-tenable infrastructures – the Biennale needs to work constructively against the prevailing order of cities, and in doing so, actively contribute to creating and sustaining a new urban future. In the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face, aesthetically uninteresting, sometimes-ruined but tenable infrastructures – the Biennale needs to work constructively against the prevailing order of cities, and in doing so, actively contribute to creating and sustaining a new urban future. In this context, the Biennale’s present and future political situations are likely to continue to be a source of negotiation. The Biennale needs to evolve into something more politically responsive, and this will require political and organisational change. So, how does the Biennale engage politically? How does the Biennale address current and potential</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about our urban environments, showing where, when and how we live our days. It is the ultimate urban-research project. 	But despite the volume of research and analysis now coming from the region, its capacity to affect urban change is very limited. The reason is that, at the moment, the political will is with the local authority – not the other way around. The Biennale has to be creative and unpredictable in order to meet the will of the people, and this can only be achieved if the Biennale is seen as a cultural institution, and not as an instrument of city government. Cultural institutions, as we know, have a political and legal framework that fosters their institutionalisation. The Biennale has to be seen as a political and legal construct, and its politics and legal framework – like its visual language – must be negotiated. So, in the present political moments – which urbanites and urban theorists are we trying to impress with our dense, in-your-face displays of culture, as opposed to engaging with the politics and complexities of our cities – the Biennale must find ways to bring its political and social context into the present, while simultaneously being present and intervening in the current political situation. In other words, the Biennale’s present political situation and possible futures require an expansive and variable political engagement. 	The Biennale needs to negotiate its place in the city, and its social and political context. It cannot be a monolithic, all-encompassing entity, and it certainly cannot dominate both the perceptions and the actions of the local communities. But it can at least negotiate the fact that its present position is an ever-shifting and variable one. The position may have a positive and an adverse connotation, and its interpretation and application may or may not be taken as literally or literally. This is why it is so important for the Biennale to inhabit its site, and for the Biennale to inhabit</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things
    <text>curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things – that is deeply connected to the social totality. Infrastructure is made up of materials and energies that have a social totality as a social meaning. The infrastructural turn towards place – infrastructure – is intimately tied to the social turn away from place. It’s as if the infrastructural turn is a social turning. But what kind of social meaning does that make? I think of the social turn towards place as one possible sense of the social totality in which the infrastructure turns. The thing that we can identify as infrastructure is an evolving and changing body of knowledge that we have to manage in order to inhabit another level of its richness. In the past, it was made up of images and images travelled; now, it’s made up of ideas, practices and representations that are embedded in cultural practices and historical narratives. And the extent to which we identify with particular images or stories or images today is a function of how much we rely on those narratives as a mode of understanding the</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things – the infrastructures that are the products of human culture, and that shape and ultimately define our world. Infrastructure is a social concept, and social change can be seen as occurring at several scales, from the scale of individual citizens to the massive infrastructural systems that constitute our cities. We might add another aspect to infrastructure to come, when we start to think about the social, political and cultural dimensions that infrastructure creates.We start to see how infrastructure fits into the larger social relations and narratives that shape our world. We start to see that infrastructure is a social system that produces social and political changes that in turn shape the world. We start to see that the social functions and narratives that we conceive of as the inevitable outcome of technological progress, whether globalisation or neoliberalism, are in fact actively engaged in a project of resistance, ‘disassemble’ by a technologically engaged public engaged in debates with itself, and ‘inhabitant’ by an infrastructure that is</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things – a space-time relation is reproduced through means of machines: the infrastructures, after all, are the vectors that move things around. In this sense, the infrastructure of infrastructure is a vector that takes on new dimensions, and new lives – new ways of interacting and constituting – as new data and analytics propitiate ever more rapidly.   One could read this as a call to infrastructure-as-science, a space-time perspective that looks to the future in which infrastructure may one day be recreated in machines and utilised to solve problems in the present through the application of artificial intelligence.  Such a space-time orientation would also read like a manifesto for infrastructure-as-infrastructure, where infrastructures are envisaged as both source and symptom of  	postindustrial society. And it would map these infrastructures back to their roots, the people and places that created them, and thus would initiate a new discourse on infrastructure and its evolving</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things – that is reshaped and mediated through information technologies. We have digital infrastructure that is constantly reshaping the world around it, and this is an aspect of contemporary infrastructure-building that is very much influenced by the information technologies of the 1990s. The infrastructural turn around urban space is a global process that has geopolitical dimensions and is now being driven by a species of artificial intelligence that is developing macroscopic maps of the city that can be generated and readied to execute any number of complex manoeuvres.Infrastructures are not unique in their capacity to reshape environments; they are a fact of modern society, and the propensity to reshape oneself within them is a universal human trait. But what differentiates infrastructures from other forms of infrastructure is precisely their capacity to reshape, and to readjust to changes in the real-world. The ability to generate new infrastructures through new technologies is what differentiates infrastructures from other forms of infrastructure,</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things – and the connection between human life and infrastructure. Infrastructure is a social concept, and social needs dictate infrastructure design. The infrastructural species we’ve created is a social problem. The infrastructure that supports it is a social creation.  The second aspect of this concept is technological. In the twenty-first century, we can think of no better site for the expansion of infrastructure than the Arctic, where massive, human-influenced global climate change is threatening to make the geography of the planet uninhabitable. We must protect ourselves from the damaging effects of global climate change. To do so, we must understand how climate affects infrastructure. There are several ways of approaching this.  The first and most obvious is to ignore the issue entirely and to seek technological solutions. This is the ‘easy’ way to look at the problem, and it’s the only feasible approach. However, this ignores the fact that climate change is an issue of human civilization. It�</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things – the modes of movement, the surfaces of buildings, the materials on which they're built. Infrastructure is an object that represents the movements of people and objects, and in that sense, it represents the social totality as a whole. In that sense, it represents the social totality in a very particular way. It represents the social totality as movements of humanity, and yet it also represents the social totality as movement between people. In other words, it represents infrastructure in its totality, but it also represents infrastructure in its individual parts. These are very different kinds of movements. The kind of ‘infrastructure’ that we think of in terms of tunnels and passages and tunnels beneath the ground is actually much more common. It’s infrastructure that comes about through the interaction of people – that comes about through what Meehan Crist calls ‘intersectionality’.  [Figure 1: Illustration of an underground passage of the Northern Power Station, c. 1950s, redrawn by</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things – ahistorical and always on-the-watch-list for any signs of life. Infrastructure is a complex word, with many senses of ‘infrastructure’, but fundamentally it refers to the physical mode of things: how we categorise, describe and organise them (&quot;infrastructure&quot; is a synonym for ‘things’) and the way we imagine possibilities and outcomes in the world. Infrastructure is a fiction. It is powerful, but it is also deceptive. There is no inherent meaning or ‘truth’ to infrastructure, only an audience of practitioners of a particular form of fiction. As the late David Harvey said, when addressing the use of vernacular terms in describing the infrastructure of the twenty-first century: frameworks of difference, ‘the construct of infrastructure is fundamentally a fiction that we can break free of’.[28] and ‘the word ‘infrastructurism’ has come to refer to projects that</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things – a mode that is both human-influenced and – to some extent – determined by human behaviour. Infrastructure is a material substance that is both malleable and malleable in the ways that are characteristic of human behaviour, but also arrives in a range of outcomes that are not. So there’s a continuum of outcomes at work here, along the lines of – say – climate change or some kind of inhuman international climate-change accords. And what this implies in practice is a kind of political and humanitarian infrastructural change, taking root in the local and global infrastructures of the infrastructural landscape. The infrastructural change of the future that I predict for the United States and Western Europe will be based on massive migration flows and a mass abrogation of sovereignty. We will no longer be able to call our own infrastructures natural human installations, but rather will create infrastructures that are demonstrably artificial (and in</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things – how we acquire, understandings of time. We have to begin to imagine alternative modes of how the world might be organised in the future. 	[27] See, for instance,  	Tim R. McVicar and Christian Körner, eds.,  	Future City? Essays on Infrastructure, Culture, Future Planning 	, Pimlico, London and New York, 2012, p. 142. 	[28] See also Matthew Stoner, ed.,  	The Crisis of the City 	, SUNY Press, Albany, 1989, p. 382. 	[29] For a more in-depth discussion of the role of culture and infrastructure in our time, see Matthew Stoner, ed.,  	Future City? Essays on Infrastructure, Culture, Future Planning, SUNY Press, Albany, 1989, p. 394. 	[30] See also the essays in Stoner</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] … has a kind of a tendency to saturate the cultural landscape, to take root in the very fabric of the city. The problem with that is that it’s happening too late. There’s been a massive influx of refugees, and now we’re stuck with these massive levels of climate-altering carbon pollution. We don’t have the resources to brace ourselves in case of a massive flood, and we’re not strong enough to absorb the impact of a couple of mega-droughts. So the question becomes: how do you start to imagine a different future? How do you start to imagine a future with resilience, if that's the right word, in which the future is no longer a future with droughts and floods and heat waves and heat waves and all the other problems that come with it?’[27] And here we see another aspect of the ‘infrastructure’ – the physical mode of things – a space in which things are designed to happen, to be built, to be controlled, to be observed, to be collected, and to be destroyed in an ever more pervasive and pervasive way. The infrastructure describes the physical world in terms of patterns, of things being assembled in patterns, of things being measured in terms of distances travelled, and of things being plugged into infrastructure, and so forth. We can think of infrastructure, or more specifically, how things are ‘arranged’ to produce patterns. We can imagine things happening organically, through processes of accrual that are more easily understood by our human capacity than by machines. We can also imagine new patterns forming, through trial and error, across disparate parts of the population, generating new knowledge and habits. We can also imagine new ways of organising, of meeting, of community, of migration, of art, of everyday life. One can only imagine things in so far as they’re there and do not know what</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a living, breathing entity. The proposal will then be subjected to a public consultation on its viability – a process that will determine if the plan is to go ahead – and then to being implemented as a reality. The public consultation will allow people to suggest changes and give ideas on how the plan can be implemented, while also allowing for participation in the construction of the future of the city. This form of public consultation is particularly relevant in a city as large as Liverpool, whose history and present are intertwined with that of the other European cities that share a border with Britain. It is a rare occasion when the historical or contemporary relevance of a proposed project is considered, but here the Biennial is asked to propose a new vision for the city that is simultaneously present and timeless. 	The proposal is a straightforward one: there is no alternative to becoming part of the larger global urbanisation machine. The only question is: what is the city, exactly? Whether the city represents the totality of humanity in a shared and</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a whole. The initial concept will guide the wider evolution of the Biennial’s design language, media strategy and urban development. The fact that the Biennial is emerging as a global phenomenon will make it a prime candidate for the evolving interface made evident by the ever-expanding web of cultural flows that connect the city and beyond. It will be possible to develop a revised, globalised version of the original plan that looks to the future – into the future – as part of a global cultural movement. The initial concept will guide the wider evolution of the Biennial’s design language, media strategy and urban development. The fact that the Biennial is emerging as a global phenomenon will make it a prime candidate for the evolving interface made evident by the ever-expanding web of cultural flows that connect the city and beyond. It will be possible to develop a revised, globalised version of the original plan that looks to the future – into the future – as part of a global cultural movement.</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a whole. This can be seen as a potential starting point for further research and development, in an attempt to create a new kind of urbanism in the city.The proposal may be found at: http://www.ucl.ac.uk/lbs/133/html/liverpool-biennial.html 	The main site for research and development is located in or near Anfield, at the former ‘Paisley Park Hotel’ (founded in 1887 and renamed in 1914), which is used by the Biennial as a space for events including exhibitions, events and programming. The hotel has a long standing policy of hosting ‘occasionally held’ programming, including a monthly ​‘lock'n’’’ programme organised by the hotel for select stays. The hotel has hosted exhibitions by artists from around the world, including a permanent exhibition of British art by Andy Warhol in 1993. There have been more than twenty exhibitions of art from the Bi</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a whole. This may include developing an entirely new architectural style or forming entirely new media. The new vision for the city may combine the old and the absurd. It may or may not involve new forms of urban travel. It may or may not involve new forms of cultural exchange. It may or may not involve new forms of economic exchange. It may or may not involve new forms of social life. The key is that it involves all of us, and that all of us are invited to contribute our imagination to the new vision. There are of course many ideas that are not locally applicable, and that is why local artists are often invited to collaborate with the architects and designers of new developments. It is a chance for the local artist to shine through a local lens, taking part in a wider cultural act that is as authentic and authentic as possible. 	The scope and ambition of the project may or may not translate well with the local community. It depends on how the commission is structured, who holds the</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a living, breathing entity.  	The proposal and eventual concept will then be sent to the politicians, developers, urbanists, landscape architects and PR firms who will form the basis of the new ‘city of ideas’. Creative forms of cultural exchange will be encouraged, but only if they are non-violent, transparent and equitable. The key is that ‘it has to be equitable – not just for the city, but for the biennial’. Creative forms of cultural exchange are inherently unequal. This is why biennials, including the contemporary ones, are perennial powerhouses, with their institutional memory and institutionalised ideologies of aesthetics still dominant in contemporary art and design. It is also why the art world tends to over-emphasise artistic and aesthetic outcomes over those of other people, and what is best for the world as a whole. When evaluating a place (or an idea), the artist matters more than the place or idea. Biennials, by and large</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a whole. If successful, this could form a new paradigm for the way in which cultural practices in the city are planned, organised and managed. 	In a separate but related but overlapping series of projects, the British Council is experimenting with the use of crowd-sourcing to design urban spaces for young people. The proposals are based on experience from the U.K. inspired project ‘Grand Challenge’ undertaken by the youth wing of the British Council. The project was a success because the young people had enough political will and political resources to be able to compete head-to-head with established cultural institutions in Liverpool, even though the actual designs were developed in partnership with architects and PR firms. 	The British Council is embarking on a collaborative project with the Performing Arts Centre in Liverpool to explore the possibility of creating a new generation of arts centres and festivals around the world. In December 2016, the Council and the Performing Arts Centre opened their first International Arts Community Forum,</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a living organism, rather than an artefact of museum collections. The selected proposal will then be considered by the architectural and planning commissions, which will present a final proposal to the mayor. His or her decision will be based on the preliminary concept, as well as the specific proposals from the other three planning commissions. The Biennial has the opportunity to present a new concept in front of the planning and cultural commissions, which will then either approve or refuse the proposal. 	The submission of a new concept for the city every five years is a rare event, and the proposal here is the only one currently online. In the event that the city is selected, a public art institution will establish an exhibition schedule, which will be published in the local newspaper within two years after the announcement of the selected site. The exhibition schedule will include no less than three biennials a year, with an emphasis on the next calendar year. The selected biennial will be responsible for arranging the programming, which will include but is</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a whole, rather than the city as a collection of discrete sites. The initial concept will guide the commissioning and design process, while an idea for the site-specific project will emerge as a ‘case study’ in the commissioning process. 	The initial plan for the city,  	New York Times, 10 December 2017, http://www.nytimes.com/2017/12/10/us/politics/donald-trumps-change-legacy-in-liverpool.html?,_r=0,fronted:  	http://www.nytimes.com/2017/12/10/us/politics/donald-trumps-change-legacy-in-liverpool.html?,_r=0,em  plication:  	https://www.washingtonpost.com/wp-srv/em/content/article/2018/12/10/us-politics/excerpt/</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a living, breathing entity, not an object within a certain category or type of structure. The initial concept will then be combined with renderings and concept designs from various agencies, including from the city itself, to form a new idea for the city. The plan to create a ‘global image’ through a ‘web of culture’ will be presented at the 10th  	International Architecture Biennale (2015), and at the 11th  	Architecture of the 21st Century (2017). 	The initial concept will then be combined with renderings and concept designs from various agencies, including from the city itself, to form a new idea for the city. The plan to create a ‘global image’ through a ‘web of culture’ will be presented at the 10th  	International Architecture Biennale (2015), and at the 11th 	Architecture of the 21st Century (2017). 	The initial</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the largest and most ambitious yet to be conceived and delivered in the city, and will result in a ‘big change’ in the way in which Liverpool is understood and imagined. The Biennial is expected to be a ‘tale of two cities’, operating across cultural forms, in an attempt to conjure up images of the past, present and future of the city. It will be a ‘truly global image’, using new media and new ways of understanding, and will draw together diverse cultural practices across the city in a common project. It will employ a ‘transdisciplinary approach’ to understanding ‘the web of culture that supports and emerges from the city’. 	The Biennial has been invited to submit a concept for the city at an early stage in its development. This will enable the architectural, media, cultural and tourism commissions to work together to form a new vision for Liverpool through a concept that represents the city as a whole. The initial concept will then be refined and improved as the city organises a public debate on the proposed concept, with finalised designs due in 2021. 	The initial concept will be refined and improved as the city organises a public debate on the proposed concept, with finalised designs due in 2021. The initial public consultation on the ‘conceptual plan’ for the area around Anfield Park will be held in October 2018. 	The scope of the initial public consultation will be determined by the National Trust, Public Museums Liverpool, who will jointly manage the public exhibition space and ‘architecture, landscape and landscape architecture’ under the umbrella of the ‘Architecture Biennale’.  1  The original plan for the area around Anfield Park was to create a new urban district called ‘Liverpool’s Third Point’.  2  Pedro Almodóvar, The Biennale, September 2018.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places that are linguistically homogenous tend to be homogenous in other ways as well. For instance, in most of North America, there is a common set of rules about who can and cannot come to Canada. But different groups from different parts of the country have different sets of rules about how and when they can come to Canada. Languages also tend to constrain what can and cannot be said in certain contexts. For instance, the rules about who can and cannot speak English in a particular community are much stricter here than in most places in North America. So groups tend to communicate through groups. And language plays a part in this too. It tells us how to live our lives. 	So what is the connection between language and the social? And how does language make us live social lives? The social, in turn, depends on what I have just called the ‘third dimension’: what sociologist Peter Osborne calls the ‘third space’. The social space of the social</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places that are common to all of us tend to be good for all of us. And communities tend to be good for all of us too. Language is a powerful tool.It conveys information about places, people, and places-about-town, neighbourhoods, nations, cities, villages, remote islands, mountains, fields and so forth. It also helps us find and create meaning in places. It enables us to identify common ground, to share experiences, to exchange stories, to engage in symbolic exchange, to engage in action and so forth. It enables us to enact change, to identify opportunities and so forth. And it does much, although perhaps not all, of what we think of as interesting and distinctive about places. For example, the distinctive feature of cities is that they tend to have a large and diverse population of citizens, and hence distinctive features of the city are often sought after by tourists. And tourism is a relatively new thing in much of the world. So it is often the case</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places that are linguistically similar but culturally different, where people gather to socialise, where there is a common language between members of the community, tend to be valuable for their authenticity, as individuals and groups, and for the flow of cultural resources between those individuals and the places they visit. Places with a rich and visible oral tradition tend to be sources of authenticity for communities. Languages also tend to make particular places recognisable. They tell us what to eat, where to sit, where to pray, how to dance, what to wear and how to be merry. Importantly, they also tell us how to use our cultural resources. Places that are linguistically similar but culturally different – places where people gather to socialise, places where there is a common language between members of the community, places where there is a common understanding of how to use cultural resources – tend to be of value for their authenticity, as individuals and groups, and for the flow of cultural resources between those individuals and the places they visit</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places that are common to all of us tend to be good for building self-esteem. And just as important, are good places to live in for people to come to? 	So what is it that makes places distinctive? And groups distinct? And groups distinct? And groups particular? And clusters? Place makes a certain kind of categorisation possible – categorised, that is, into classes: good, bad, interesting, unusual. But class is just one kind of categorisation. There are others, more powerful and more enduring, including genetic, cultural and historic categorisations. And these last kinds of categorisation are what give some kinds of places their distinctive character. Cultural categories, including race and gender, have their own distinctive ways of categorising. Cultural categories, including race and gender, are powerful. But they are also vulnerable. And when categorised, they form complexes that trap and constrain movement. Categories are made up of a multiplicity of values and behaviours, and this diversity is</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places that are common to many people tend to be more recognisable. 	So what distinguishes distinctive places from lumpy, repetitive, dehumanising versions of themselves? And what can we learn from them? Language is a powerful tool. It tells us what to do, how to live, what to avoid. And it also tells us how to be alone. Irresistible isolation is a hallmark of human behaviour. But as we all know, humans are social animals. We have to be able to communicate with each other in order to form group thoughts and take part in complex social interactions. Commonplaces, the social features that we tend to associate with – like bathrooms and cemeteries – are actually quite rare. And yet we have become so used to them that we hardly notice them anymore. A language that we speak becomes an essential part of our social organisation, even though it does not make much difference to us what those organisations are. 	But what if the language we speak becomes a construct</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places that are homogenous in terms of population density and homogenous in terms of language enable certain kinds of exchange between people. Places that are similar in terms of their shape and size but with an odd number of people living in them tend to have frequent large-scale migrations of people; mass tourism is a big part of this. Mass tourism is good for business, and the kind of business that makes lots of money is good for the environment. But mass tourism also creates a pressure cooker of cultural consumption that feeds into a kind of capitalism that uses the landscape as a kind of currency and consumer product. And as much as anything, the pleasure derived from this kind of consumption is aspirational; it is about as alien to the natural world as can be made. The kind of consumption that nature intended. Things that are common to all places also tend to be universal; things that are unique to Honolulu tend to be universal; and things that are universal to both Honolulu and Los Angeles but which bind them together</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places that are almost entirely in the public domain tend to be in high demand, so a shortage of places is a problem. But a shortage of places also implies a demand for resources, which tends to generate a lot of corruption, a lot of crime, and a lot of instability. Linguists have long since figured out how to identify places that are in short supply of resources; it is a bureaucratic challenge that linguists doing linguistic research in the US and other places struggle with. But the thing that distinguishes us from other species of animals in that we have language and can articulate our desires about the world around us is what anthropologists call symbolic exchange. Animate objects and sights and sounds – which are typically negotiated between groups on an implicit or explicit level – circulate widely in cultural contexts. Symbolic exchange – the ability to exchange – is a powerful tool for the social good. And what makes us human is precisely the capacity to come to cultural exchanges mediated by symbols and images. Human language is a powerful</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places that are common to all of us tend to be good for making new connections, and bringing people together. Languages also tend to tell us what to do in ways that we might not necessarily understand. For instance, what is a folktale is a story told in a particular community, and so understanding that community might involve gathering folk tales from across the region. Languages also tell us what to do in ways that we might not necessarily share. For instance, when we are cooking, we might share the story we heard from the woman at the counter, or we might not. And so on. The point is that place-making, as we understand it, is collaborative. It is people coming together to make something better, and so is language. If we do not understand what that something better is, then we cannot make it. In fact, the more we struggle to understand what that something better is, the less interesting and enriching our lives will be for ourselves and our communities. In order to</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places that are common to many people tend to be desirable to few. Languages also tend to make places reliable resources for people to rely on. A place that is scarce resources shortens the period during which a threat can be imagined, so that when threats do occur, they are less likely to be taken seriously. Languages also tell us when to use what kinds of force is appropriate. When large numbers of people are gathered in a place to engage in large-scale collective acts of violence, the use of force is likely.  	So what is the relationship between language and power? And what do we learn when we speak of power? We learn that power brokers use language to achieve their ends. We learn that power is not always exercised through the imposition of one set of rules on others; sometimes the imposition of rules is the very thing that makes places interesting. And we learn that language is a powerful tool. It is capable of organizing people around shared purposes, desires, and ends. It is capable</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about individuals, places, and things. This data is made visible through maps, and is used to make places better and more interesting places to live in. It is used in commerce, it is used in education, and it is used in many other ways that we barely understand. But one of the things that we do know is that places are places because of the communities that make up them. If we can pull together a set of places, a set of people, a set of habits, a set of behaviours, and call that place a community then we can start to imagine a future where places are populated with people from those places.  	So what is it that makes places interesting? What distinguishes them? What makes them distinctive? The answer is people. And groups. And groups tend to communicate with each other. Languages do not make place makeable. People make place, and language tells us how to live in it. Languages also tend to make certain kinds of place common. Places that are homogenous, homogenous, and homogenous in certain ways are rare. For example, Hawaii has a common language, but different languages have different grammars. ‘Common’ is relative, and relative is a feature of places with a high degree of human settlement. ‘Habitat’ is a noun and locative term, and place/habitat is a verb and a locus of action. In this sense, ‘common’ is a past tense of a noun that describes something that is homogenous or universal (common to all humans, or common to animals). In this sense, ‘habitability’ describes the degree to which a place is due to the actions of individuals or collectives (groups or tribes). 	So what is ‘common space’? The locus of action in the English language can be attributed to John Syvret, who coined the term in his book  Natural Language Processing   </text>
  </text>
  <text>
    brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory without a national paper of some kind, but is becoming increasingly important in a country or territory with a rapidly developing paper economy: the  	International Paper Market Research Centre in London has recently released figures on the growth of international paper shipments, and the map below displays the locations of the largest percentage growth centres for international paper in the last ten years. 	The number of miles travelled in a year by an average Australian walking is recorded in the ‘Australian National Physical Biennale’ (ANPRB) report, published every two years. Walked: Australian National Physical Biennale, ‘2000’, 2000, Sydney, Australia, 1995, p.13–16. 	The ANPRB, like many other research institutions worldwide, is now increasingly interested in the development of tourism, which is seen as a potential replacement for the lost trade. As a consequence, it is often said, ‘we’re the lucky tourists’ who create the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory as large as ours, but it does have benefits for an artist as well as the public. If, for instance, the data gathered from the app is shared amongst artists and the publics, and used to launch collaborative projects with them, then the public is able to participate in the creation of a work that was created with their data. The possibilities for this kind of user-generated art are endless, and nowhere more evident than in the case of an app that analyzes the data from the Eurostar and Passenger Ferry passenger manifests, and produces beautiful work that connects the artist, the public, and the built environment. 	Such is the desire of the art world – and certainly, we believe, of the public when they first come to us with their ideas and questions. 	We’ve all felt that way: when we first started the Guardian, we all felt that way about the DNA test. It’s a powerful tool, and we use it every day, but</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory without a national paper, and is often restricted to favoured groups or urban centres. But with the proliferation of mobile phones and blogs, and social media, the geographical entries of a person’s identity become increasingly uncertain, especially when it comes to the places where her or his identity is actually sold. As a result, tracing the paper trail becomes increasingly difficult, especially for those who lack access to official data or documentation. The advent of apps like Oil on Paper allows these citizens to more fully participate in the tracing process and produce indicators of paper trail success such as trace amounts and types of paper, through data mining. 	[i] Schiller, Pablo. Die Zivilisten über den Nachrichten des Mittelalters und selbst des Warenls (1834–1907), Berlin.  1  Karen O’Brien, ‘How to Read Maps and Learn About the World’, in  	Geographical</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory as large as Australia, but is becoming increasingly so as the digital revolution unfolds. In fact, with the advent of the iPhone and the ubiquity of electronic devices, it is now practically commonplace for an artist to produce a work that is both ‘native’ to the platform on which the platform is built, and which can then be exported immediately to any number of countries around the world. This type of access may be considered ‘global’ in scope, but it is becoming increasingly difficult for artists to access this kind of access in their native environments. As one might expect, this has been a factor in the decline of many artists’ communities, and is particularly true of those in Asia and the Middle East. But there are signs that in recent years, artist’s communities in Australia and the United States are catching up with this changing landscape of connectedness and progress. 	André Du Beaumont, who worked as an art historian for the New York Times from</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory, but is becoming more and more difficult to obtain in many parts of the world, where paper is more of a commodity than a source of national pride. This proximity and rapid innovation are creating new kinds of paper and paper-based paper products, and paper-based paper is being developed in many parts of the world. New media like cameras, drones, and data capture hotspots are also impacting on the paper market. New media like social media and data-collecting apps are putting pressure on paper production and paper-making capacity, and old media like newspapers are feeling the strain of their ­paper ephemeral writing. New media like social media and data-mining apps are forcing traditional media to rethink how they report on and market their ­use. 	The paper boom is fuelling a boom in art paper, which is being produced at breakneck speed in many cities in response to the increasing need for high-quality, low-cost paper at a scale and frequency not possible with</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory as large as the UK, but is becoming increasingly valuable as a result of the internet and mobile technology. Large organisations, including those with a national data protection authority, are increasingly relying on apps to detect when their citizens use the internet or use mobile technology, and are therefore eager to tap into this growing data pool and make use of it. As a result, app developers and data providers are investing in research and development in an attempt to procreate and democratise the technology, while artists, curators, writers and activists are quick to launch competitive app stores or blogs to inform users and the public about what is happening in the world of digital media. 	As a consequence of this type of access, artists, curators, writers and other participants in the technology are able to engage with the practices and concepts involved in the technology and move away from the confines of their art and craft. This may include technologies used in the production of goods and products, but also includes technologies used in the design and</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory without a national paper of some kind, yet in the digital economy of the 21st century, access to data is everything. If you’re surfing the Net, you’re probably connected to a server somewhere, transmitting data back and forth across the Net. If you’re connected to the Net, then you’re part of a network. If you buy a magazine online, you’re part of a network. And if you subscribe to a newspaper, you’re part of a network. The notion that you are connected to the Net is widespread in the digital age, and yet few people have access to the Net beyond the people connected to the servers and networks that host the magazines, the phone companies, the ISPs, the financial services and the political parties. As an aside, this type of access is also rare in a country or territory without a national paper of some kind, but with the rapid spread of data and the cloud, there is a corresponding</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory without a national paper that is as ubiquitous as is the internet; however, in a nation-state with a digital footprint, this type of access is virtually non-existent. This is particularly true for documents stored in ‘national archives’ or museums; national archives hold records of historical documents but, unlike the national paper, they are not places where you can access digitised versions of these records. So, for example, when you search for the term ‘electrification’ in an archive publication, the reference in Google returns an error message because archive only stores books in a geographical location called the National Archive. 	Similarly, when you search for the term ‘climate change’ in a climate research journal, the reference in Google returns an error message because of the discontinuity of archive – which means that the climate has changed but the archive doesn’t remember it. So, for example, the term ‘intelligent city’ might return an error message because</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory, but is becoming increasingly important in a global economy. Paper is becoming less and less of a necessity, and new technologies are enabling ever greater quantities of paper to be manufactured at low or no cost. Paper is no longer the only necessity, but it is essential to the functioning of the global economy. This access is also coming at a time when ‘metainterface’ – the technology that creates interfaces – is being developed at an increasingly rapid rate in response to the ever-more pervasive and pervasive digital footprints that we are all contributing to creating on a global scale. 	When I started at the Guardian in 1995, the interface was still largely defined by the conventions of print publishing. The advent of computer interfaces and interactive media brought with it a whole new set of concerns, challenges and debates. These included the role of governments, corporate America, the media and other powerful players, as well as ordinary users and civil society. As a result, the interface became both malleable and</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data, allowing an artist, theatre, or community to engage with and produce concrete effects through data mining. 	A good example of this in action is provided by the Electronic Frontier Foundation (EFF), whose work Oil on Paper was inspired in large part by the work of artist Parvo Jehtave, who has a project titled Parallax (portmanteau of &quot;pages&quot; and &quot;papers&quot; – see the glossary at the end of this issue). Parallax is an app for iOS and Android devices that makes it easy to trace where your traced paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. It collects data on where the paper is sold, where it’s sent, and what data is being transmitted. By collecting this data and making it available, the app can connect you to the site where the paper is being sold, sent, or  	came from. 	This type of access is rare in a country or territory without a national paper or printed publications, but is becoming increasingly valuable in a digital age. Many artists and arts institutions now work with app developers to enable their art to be downloaded by a worldwide audience. These relationships are complex and often fraught, but they often yield surprising or creative solutions to difficult problems. In a recent example, the Icelandic Film and Television Archive was able to secure funding from the Icelandic Council for Independent Media (ICIM) and the Arts Council of Iceland to create an entirely new type of archival media to house the film and television traces of the 1980s. 	The challenge for artists and arts institutions alike remains to address the complexity of the contemporary context and society they are placed in. The rise of social media and connected devices is a constant source of new media fodder, and digital media is the sole medium through which trace amounts of data are continuously exchanged and received. The technology of what used to be called ‘real life’ is being transformed into what can be termed �</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant
    <text>an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant for the uprising, but Saramago’s story goes much further, suggesting that the mob also has a human right to take what it wants from the peasant.I was moved to tears by Saramago’s story, and by the way in which it describes the dehumanising effect of big business: the point of production, after all, is to produce commodities – commodities that can be sold to customers (or other entities). In the story, the protagonists are individuals, not social enterprises like the MFA and the artists who work in its archive. But in practice, artists, curators and others often work outside of the site where their work is situated. And this is the second reason why artists’ curatorial practice is so important: it defines the social function of the art institution, and how it is organised, represented and valued. Without this kind of social organisation, there can be no cultural organisation: there is no such thing as the cultural organisation of the commons.</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant for the demise of the kingdom, but in reality it is Saramago who is being blamed for the loss of life. The mob also happens to be the son of a powerful political leader.Suddenly, I felt like a different person. I felt lighter, healthier, more free. I felt like a champion. I won an Oscar. But at the same time, I felt utterly helpless.I felt hugely frustrated by both the absurdity of the situation – the extent of it – and the inability of the authorities to do anything about it.I felt that maybe, just maybe, I could have a part in changing it. So I visited him in prison. I found myself falling in love with the idea of rehabilitation.It’s a pity that the story ended with Saramago’s martyrdom, since at the same time we were in a position to influence how the prison authorities would constructively use the information gained from the project. So I got to spend a summer in a</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant; a medieval novel-length exposé would do the same. I thought: ‘Yes, that story is classic.’I looked at the cover of the first edition of the Brooklyn Museum Journal, on the day of Saramago’s arrest. It was a picture of a mountain range and the Brooklyn Bridge, with the words ‘Mountain Man’ emblazoned across the front. I thought: ‘That was the end of that.’The story is classic and it is compelling, but the way in which the narrative is constructed, the way in which the punishment for breaking the story is severe – clearly this was the case with Saramago – makes it quite different.You might also like: The Mountain Man, by Isaac Julian, published in 1845, is the first book in a trilogy of novels set in the Shoshone language, indigenous to the region around Mammoth, Nevada. In the first, published in 18</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant for the demise of the empire, which he then tries to whitewash by claiming that the blame is on the ‘infidel’, that is, by asserting that the peasant had a part in creating the evil that was being done to him.The irony is that, at the very time that the mob is trying to whitewash the imperial catastrophe by claiming that the blame is on the infidel, Saramago is trying to reclaim the pieces of his fallen empire by insisting that they are his, and that they are the rightful ones.Saramago’s project is a perfect illustration of how the imagination can intervene meaningfully in a situation, and how the imagination can create alternatives. It is a project that seeks to reconcile two very different interpretations of the same facts. The fact that the pieces are pieces of furniture that have been adapted and manipulated by hand into various forms is a very powerful way to engage the visitor.Saramago’s project is</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant for the catastrophe, but in reality Saramago’s tormentors use that excuse to eradicate him from the face of the earth.I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant for the catastrophe, but in reality Saramago’s tormentors use that excuse to eradicate him from the face of the earth.Saramago’s story is typical, but unlike many other prisoners, he is rescued and brought to a refugee camp. There, he begins a long, complex process of becoming ‘a native’ and becoming ‘a full member of society’. It is at this point that the narrative shifts from the prisoner to the hero, and from the hero to the multitude. A Villeneuve-like figure,</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant for the disaster, but Saramago’s story is a completely different story. He is released on bail and takes up the art again, this time as a job. At the end of the first semester, the first day of work, he’s ambushed and murdered again, this time by fellow inmates. The next time, he’s set free, but this time by the kindly Governor.Saramago’s story is a blend of facts and fiction. There are elements of truth in certain statements, as in the famous Woolf Report, but much of it is fiction. The Governor and the mob see a chance to start a civil war, and with that chance comes the first executions.Saramago’s escape from Guantánamo Bay is one of the best-known stories in the literature of the post-Second World War period, and it remains one of the most widely quoted in relation to the island. There is much</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant for the disaster, but Saramago’s character arc in this story is quite different. He’s a poet who’s saved by a kindly old woman, and that story seems to be a metaphor for a much more expansive predicament.In this story, the mob’s narrative is blocked by a wall, but here, the poet's only escape is from himself. In the poem, he calls out to the unseen hand that saved him: ‘That wasn’t me, that was a horrible, mean thing to do.’The mob’s only response is to tear up the lease on his house, and then to demolish it again, this time in the borough of Brownsville, which is about twenty miles away. We don’t know what the future holds for Saramago, but we do know that the borough of Brownsville is about to be demolished, and that the area will be converted into a MUNI</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant, claiming that the peasant has cursed the jeweller, who then proceeds to burn down the house. The peasant’s family is separated by religion; his mother is then beheaded. Saramago was born in 1903, in the region around Bed-Stuy, a few blocks from where I live. He was five years old when his family moved to Manhattan.Saramago moved to France in 1913, and stayed there for several years. When he returned to the UK, he found work as a journalist, and in 1916, he joined the RN[...]. He covered the First World War in the US, and the First World War in the UK. He wrote articles for the Daily Worker, the London Daily Post and the Times of London, and was a reporter for the Daily Graphic.In 1917, he joined the RCA[...]. He covered the Second World War in the UK, and the First World War in Afghanistan. He covered the Panama Canal</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant for the death of a valuable object, a tree, in the form of a human being.Saramago’s account is graphic, but humanising. The mob uses clubs, horses and bricks, axes, smoke and mirrors, but also cell phones, social media and satellite TV. Even though the story involves a peasant family, the message is that suffering millions of people is somehow in some way analogous to this.The outrage that followed the publication of this article was immense. I was on the bus, going to work. I couldn’t believe what I was reading. Twitter lit up with people blaming The New York Times, which is itself a product of the 1980s. I’m not sure the two were meant to be related. In retrospect, maybe The Times should have published that article in its Sunday newspaper. It would have given us a sense of the scale of the anger, and perhaps a way to move forward.Instead, The Times chose to publish an</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Elmgreen &amp; Dragset.Check out the exhibition's website.Enjoyed this article?Spread the love: Twitter

Facebook

Reddit

LinkedIn


Like this: Like Loading...&lt;|endoftext|&gt;A few weeks ago, I was at the Brooklyn Museum, wandering the galleries. When I came to the room that José Saramago had been incarcerated in, Brooklyn, I found myself quite shocked by the extent of his suffering.I had never seen him alive, partly because I was too busy admiring every artefact of his, from the shelf at the Brooklyn Museum. I could not have been more shocked by what I saw, but I felt quite moved by Saramago’s plight. I said something along the lines of ‘Yes, I’ve heard that story before.’It’s a typical story: a peasant, in search of the missing pieces of his feudal kingdom, is captured, tortured and murdered. The mob blames the peasant for the disaster, but in the story the peasant’s captors are actually given noble aims. The New York Times ran a front-page article about Saramago the next day.Saramago’s death was announced in the New York Times on December 13, 1942. It was the beginning of the Second World War.Over the years that followed, the fate of large swaths of Palestine was a point of contention between the Allies and the Arabs, with each camp claiming parts of the other. In the summer of 2014, the United Nations partitioned up Palestine into nine local parts, with East Jerusalem as its capital. Since that time, Israel has repeatedly sought to expand its settler outpost of Maale Adumim – a settlement in the West Bank – and has caused unrest in the Arab towns hosting Jewish settlers.Now that the war is over, the question is whether the imprint of that conflict can be allowed to limp away on like so much dust in the wake</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity
    <text>an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity and migration. He proposes that the subjects of his latest work, the language project Linguamento (2018), should be stories that emerge from, or be stories told through, the experiences of a specific linguistic minority. Assembled by artist duo La Casa Encendida (Joana and Mariana M. Leonor-Leiva), members of the Linguamento team, including Artistic Director Joana Ortega-Dubois, developed a global movement to bring their proposal to the site and time of the 2017 World Congress of Pedagogy, where it was voted 'Best Social Practice Award' by the winner(s) and alternates, respectively, of the two prizes presented by the World Congress of Pedagogy. The congress ended in June 2018. 	The Linguamento project began in 2016 as a concept study, and the year following that with the installation of a full-scale replica of the Parthenon in the Portuguese Cultural Centre in Lisbon</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity, migration and identity politics. These themes are particularly relevant in a city such as New York where the architectural historian Norman Browning once wrote: ‘The task of historical architecture is no longer the job of the historian, but that of the urban designer and developer’, and who, in turn, was a proponent of ‘regeneration, or at least rebirth, in the form of new urban developments’.  	The proposal comes as part of a '50/50 partnership initiative' between the New York art dealer, John Lennon, and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery. The partnership initiative is named in honor of John Lennon’s late wife, Paul McCartney. The name was inspired by a quote by William Shakespeare, who in a 1971 letter wrote ‘Beautiful children of the 1960s were never to be decayed by continuing history texts and representations of the past.’  [1] Ralph Miliband, ‘50 Ways to</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity and migration. He will demonstrate the futility of this false choice by asking, how can an artist create a meaningful relationship with communities when the communities he or she works with are the most easily inflamed? The suggestion is to create a more sustainable and inclusive future for artists and communities by recognising the essential irrelevance of community to the production of art and culture. Open School East East is currently seeking applications from an initial group of artists and organisations to form a Cooperative Arts Student Centre (CAAS), an organisation - this is an option for artists who wish to establish a cooperative arts education organisation. The group will develop skills in engaging with local communities through participatory arts practices, while at the same time building cultural competencies relevant to the administration of arts resources in a higher administrative setting. As an option, the group may also consider setting up a non-profit arts organisation in the future. The options available to the artist may include: continuing to educate artists through the production of cooperative arts and crafts</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity, migration and immersion in cultural practices that can be traced back to the colonial period. A participant in the Biennale in Venice, Sonny Chiba was invited to produce a parallel exhibition for the new iteration of Open School East, which will be called ‘Sonny Chiba: Venice Under Siege’. The parallel event will include works from the artist’s studio and commission a series of collaborative projects with the artists and open to the public. The Sonny Chiba: Venice Under Siege exhibition will be located in the Arsenale, part of the Arsenale di Venezia, at the Vorticist Museum, in partnership with the National Gallery of Canada and the Swiss National Art Gallery. The Arsenale di Venezia and the Arsenale di Tella are members of the Art Venetian Exchange, which also includes the acquisition and exhibition of works by the artist, the Society of Fellows, and the Arsenale di Requiem, part of the</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity, migration and identity politics. He will lead a team of artists, writers and organisations that will develop a new narrative, producing a new art school within Open School East, with a permanent home for its new generation of artists and writers, housed in a completely renovated arts centre in East New York. The team is led by award-winning contemporary artists Ashley Dawson, Dominic Soane and Kevin Stewart. 	The proposed model will offer both spaces and a community of artists and designers both within and without the established art world a chance to contribute to a developing dialogue on the site and culture of the city, one that will hopefully become something more than a dialogue between East and West. To find out more, please visit: www.openschooleast.org. 	In this model, the art school would be run jointly by the New York Art Dealer and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery, and would incorporate both commercial and non-profit galleries. The proposed model would also see the</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity, migration and identity politics. Sonny is the author of the forthcoming memoir, The Monkey Cage, to be published in 2018.  	The proposal comes as Open School East scrambles to secure funding to finish its two-year, multi-disciplinary project on the Saas-Seminar, after a short-lived 2016 that saw the artist Lello Aparecido cut short by a year. The creative team behind the exhibition, including Aparecido, Vanessa Boni (curator of the live-action film The Elephant Thief), Lello Aparecido (executive director of Open School East) and Sonny Chiba (artist and co-founder of San Francisco-based company Chiba Heavy Industries) are desperate to finish the project, which is now at a critical juncture. The exhibition will go ahead despite the funding crunch, but the fate of the project will be decided at a future date, if at all. 	The question of what is meant by �</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity and migration. He proposes that the terms and conditions of the exhibition be modified as a way to allow the different points of view to be represented. Previously, Mackay, Lennon, Moore and others led a group that explored the possibility of staging the following year’s event in London: ‘Open School East’  and ‘Open School West’ in New York and Los Angeles, respectively. The proposed modifications would make the six-month event in each city equivalent to a weekend in the other. For this reason, the six-month proposal is being made as a maximum term, and not a summer or academic option. 	In their proposal, the artists make no mention of the city, preferring to focus on the place, the territory, or the time in which they were born, raised, and reside. This is most apparent in the names of the ‘London Boroughs’ – a nod to the fact that the proposed sites are in London, while</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity and identity crisis in contemporary China. A few years ago, he created an identity crisis by creating what he described as a ‘ghost city’ in Shinjuku, Japan. Since then, he has been at war, negotiating home and country, between business and government, media and academia, activists and the law. Sonny has just completed a major exhibition at the Whitney Museum of American Art, in New York, which he curated along with Jessie Liu, Carol Becker and many others, as well as at the Venice Biennale, where his work often takes second place. The current Confucius Institute exhibition is its latest in a series of new exhibitions focusing on the life and thought of Confucius, from the ancient to the contemporary. The institute was founded in 2016 in Taipei, and is run by the Johns Hopkins University Art Department and the University of Toronto. It is the first museum to offer full-length articles in either Taiwanese or mainland Chinese, and the first to offer full</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity, migration and identity politics. In this context, the exhibition is based on the ideas of ‘Creative Time’, an online community of artists' collective members created in 2015 to explore the ideas of collective identities, collective futures and collective imaginings through art, politics and social networks. The name Creative Time was coined by one of the group, and their members, who coined the term. Creative Time is a registered charity company established in Los Angeles, USA, with an annual budget of US$7 million. It has been described as a ‘ficto-magical-occurence’, a notion that is both disputed and unquestioned. The organisation has been described as a ‘ficto-movement in time’, a quasi-religious belief in the notion of absolute permanence. Creative Time is both obsessive and envious. It records and records, until the present moment. Its members’ time is collective and indefinite, and its</text>
    <text>an AI curated by Malcolm Mugheryiel, whose work is often referred to as ‘Black-E’s Black-Named Contemporary Art Courses’. The two were co-curated by Marianne Moore, with contributions from Lynn Tolmon, Norman Wilkinson, Robin Mackay, Richard Heymann, Heather R. Butterworth and many more. The exhibition, based on the work of curator Robin Mackay, was presented as a series of three-month installments starting in January 2018, running through June 2018. This exhibition comes at a time when Open School East is proposing a new Centre for Continuing and Developing Education (CCCE), in partnership with the New York art dealer, John Lennon Fine Art Gallery and the Chelsea Arts Writer, John Lennon, who will present a new generation of artists and writers on the topic of Continuing Art and Culture (Cap &amp; Co).  	The proposal is also made by the artist Sonny Chiba, whose artworks often address the issues of identity and migration in contemporary-art’s depiction of New York City. A citizen of Japan, he immigrated to the United States in the late 1980s. His 1991 commissioning of the 1989 World Trade Center (with its extravagant public works and its successful so-called ‘Good Old Days’) signaled a new phase in his career, when he was able to engage with the challenge of urban renewal in Manhattan's financial district, a task that would have been virtually unmanageable without the legendary quality of finance that he brought to the city through his accounting firm, JP Morgan Chase &amp; Co. JP Morgan Chase &amp; Co. was founded in 1890 and is the world’s largest banking firm. It is also the parent company of New York Post Holdings, the nation’s largest newspaper company, which is majority owned by the New York Jets. These are significant corporate assets for a city such as New York, which occupies a unique position in the country. It is estimated that</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater
    <text>curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater say in what that story is. The key is in the art, and the art of telling stories. 	[7] As an example, we could consider the work of Hungarian cartoonist Michal Kwiatkowski, whose work is told in the English translation of his 1932 best-seller Drawing Katrine Dir: The Katrine Queen . Here, we have a slightly different take on the same story, but one that is told through cartoons. The key idea is the same, but the context is entirely different. Here, the king is portrayed as a madman (or in this case, a cartoonist), whereas in Hungary, the king was a deeply religious person who believed himself to be divine. So the idea of animation as metaphor is much more prevalent, and the king is portrayed as having no concept of aesthetics but simply drawing pictures and chopping wood. The key point is that the king is represented as having no concept of aesthetics, and that is why he is in so</text>
    <text>curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater say in what that story is. 	[7] And, as we have seen, this entailed incorporating elements of the performance arts into the design process.  	The key was in place, but the artist needed the public to push it forward. And while the public did push the boundaries of what was possible, they were usually met with resistance, cynicism or outright hostility. The important thing was to find a way to engage the public in the project despite the opposition, and eventually the artist had to ask the city to intervene. And, as we all know, this was precisely what the city did in the 1970s when the arts were considered a burden to be removed. So, while the public did have an influence, it was often exercised in a way that was not in alignment with the artist’s intentions, and this entailed making changes in the public mood through legislation, but also in the ways in which the public were accessed and engaged.  	[</text>
    <text>curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater say in what that story is than there might otherwise be. The key is also that the art is diverse, and whilst the artworld may be populated with practitioners of a prescribed art style – and may indeed be this is the main aim of the biennial – there is room for the artist to go further and to develop their artistic proposition. The importance of the artist’s word as to what is meant by ‘art’ cannot be over-emphasised. It is a much more powerful storytelling tool than many artists realise. 	[7] Finally, the art needs to be freely exchangesable. The art needs to be available to be incorporated into other creative activities, and to be exchangeable within a contemporary context. The difficulty with the biennial is that it is generally constrained by what is perceived as the contemporary, and so it is easy to lose sight of this important point of view. 	[8] For more information, see: 	http</text>
    <text>curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater role in that story than there might otherwise be. This is a case study in how media can be used to inform, inspire and connect, and how artists can adopt techniques and concepts found in other disciplines into their own art. That there are many images of identical white goods and flowers around London Zoo illustrates the point well. Media can also be used to inform us, create connections and in that sense, dream. 	[7] And, as we have seen, this can happen through traditional art publishing channels, as well as the new entanglements of social media. 	[8] This is also true of new trade routes being developed in response to the obsolescence of fixed docks and pipelines. The primacy of the post-WWII trade in commodities (and the attendant collapse of production) meant that these dreams did not find a place in the regulatory frameworks that we have today. But with the proliferation of social media and the ubiquity of screens, the post-</text>
    <text>curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater say in what is understood by the audience. 	[7] This is a much more complex use of art assets, and as we have seen, the media is often quite complicit in its use. 	[8] It is true, of course, that the media were much more open to the idea of a social revolution in Tunisia than in Egypt or elsewhere in the Arab world, and that revolutionary art was more readily available in the West. But this does not change the fact that the Arab Spring was won largely through the media's extensive distribution and public relations machine, and that the transition to democracy was greatly facilitated by the new media infrastructure. As we have seen, the democratic governments that emerged after the Arab uprisings were won largely through the media's extensive distribution and public relations machinery. This is a long standing dynamic that cannot be easily dismissed. 	[9] It is true that the proliferation of social media and other new media did have a profound effect on</text>
    <text>curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater say in what it is allowed to tell. 	[7] In fact, some might even argue that the art should rule the biennial as a whole. 	[8] One could also argue that the art is the problem, and we, the viewers, the participants, are the solution. In the case of a biennial, the art is often the problem, but the viewer is the one that ends up having to actually pay for the art. The problem with the biennial is that it is the only form of art available to fund, and as a result, the art is often used in an oppressive fashion. As biennials decline in number and quality, and as the art itself begins to be increasingly fetishised, the need for the art to rule the exhibitionary format will grow ever more apparent. In these cases, we are told by art professionals that the art is now primarily required because the art is cheap and plentiful, and thus is inherently ‘</text>
    <text>curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater say in what that story is. 	[7] This is perhaps one reason why in the 1980 exhibition Portoghesi used a completely different kind of sculpture than in the present one, made exclusively of blocks of wood, due to the political situation in Italy at the time. The block pieces, which stood out more, were the result of a collaboration between the Architecture Biennale, led by Paolo Portoghesi, and the Minister for Cultural Affairs, Paolo Stracchi. These blocks showed the connections between the various projects that had been put forward by the different arts organisations, and the specific projects that were developed by the Biennale itself. The fact that these individual projects were put forward in the first place was seen by many artists as a degradation of the artist’s contribution, since it reduced his role to that of a spectator, while the Biennale developed its own distinctive style and vocabulary. 	[8] </text>
    <text>curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater say in what that story is than there might otherwise be. 	[7] And, as we have seen, the art here represents a political question and solution, as well as a question of identity. As such, its power is highly individualised, and its use is often politically-charged, but its real power lies in its ability to connect and inspire.  	[8] All of this being said, it is also true that, as the biennial has grown in size and scope, it has also become increasingly difficult to maintain a consistent level of artistic activity in the city. In recent years, the biennial has become increasingly difficult to define in any meaningful or clear sense of what is meant by the term. The exhibitionary form has become politically charged, and the biennial in turn tends to become more politically charged, although it is still fairly rare for the biennial to completely rule out art being part of its future. 	[9] For</text>
    <text>curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater influence on what that story is. 	[7] And, of course, the art is the true representative of the art, since the art is the one to whom the public turn to when they need an explanation or an opinion. As a result, when the art is good, the press is good, and when the art is great, the press is good. 	[8] A final word on the difference between biennials and museums, and between art spaces and small curators: both are forms of cultural exchange between peoples and communities, but they are also ‘representations’ of larger cultural processes. The museum is the place to which the community returns, and the place where the community makes its own cultural expression. Biennials are places where the community engages with the very essence of things, consciously or unconsciously, in an exchange that is mediated by, or in a mode of, the community’s own cultural self. They are places where</text>
    <text>curated by a machine).’ 	[5] And, as we have seen, this is the case even though the art is not actually exhibited, but is downloaded and forwarded to other art institutions. As a result, the public are often mislead by the media into believing that there is an abundance of art, when in fact there is a great variety of it. The publicity generated by the exhibition is used to create a buzzword, and thus create a perception of things that are in fact quite different. 	[6] In fact, one could argue that the art was used to create a buzzword, since there is generally agreement that the art is here to stay, and that the buzzword ‘art’ is a construct that is rarely used and rarely understood. As a result, the art has a much greater say in what is represented here than there might otherwise be. The key is that the artist uses the art to tell a story, and the art has a much greater say in what that story is than there might otherwise be. 	[7] Stuart Moulthroup, The Art of Not Being Governed: Participatory Art as a Critique, Duke University Press, Durham, 1988, p. xiv. 	[8] See, for example, S. Irrati and M. Herbst, eds.,  	Modern Art: From Participatory To Complacent Anarchists: Critical Essays on Recent Contemporaneity (2014). 	[9] &quot;Contemporary art has become increasingly institutionalised, and the contemporary curatorial is no exception. Modern art museums, which used to display works by independent artists on a regular basis, and which now regularly host major exhibitions of contemporary art, are now primarily self-run and art by committee. The contemporary curatorial is the curatorial of last resort, and it is this necessity for last resort that has driven contemporary art museums to become increasingly</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be seen by a specific audience – and yet the artworks also have identities that are multi-generational and multi-faceted. They’re mosaics, or fragments from a mosaic, or fragments from a larger whole. And so, the project that we set out to do had to be person-centered, and it had to be multi-generational in scope. We didn’t want it to just be a collection of images of artworks, or an exhibition of artworks. We wanted it to be a project that evolved over time as the artworks that were displayed in it changed. Because if that were the case, then the art would be displayed in a disjointed fashion, and people would wander down memory lane whilst being entertained by art that’s been commissioned by the Australian Curators Association. So the key was making the art responsive to the times, but also keeping in mind the larger context in which the art was made.For example, the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be in a specific context – and those reasons become quite abstract and start to resemble more the arrangements that people have in mind when they talk about places and individuals. And so, the distinction that I would draw is between sites and collections. There are different types of sites; there are collection sites and museums, and there are exhibition settings. And so, when we talk about the person or things that we find most meaningful in a place or a process, we don’t necessarily mean people or collections of people; we typically mean the underlying dynamic that creates the place or process, and how it operates through time and space. And so, when we talk about the artefact, we're not necessarily talking about artefacts that are actually in the place or the process, but rather about the underlying dynamics that generate the place or process. And so, when we talk about the artefact as an entity, we don’t necessarily mean individuals or collections of individuals; we typically mean systems or collections of</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be seen by a specific audience. And so, the choice for a particular person to be identified by a specific term starts to blur together a number of other choices. It’s not that artists don’t have these other choices; rather, they are no longer confined to the sphere of their competence but can participate in creating a dynamic and engaging environment via the activities that they engage in outside their gallery context. So, for example, the choice to show Rubens Kudelski as Thoreau Meadows’ resident artist is a choice that a visitor makes when they come to the museum, and so it’s not just an artistic one. It’s an act of participation in a dynamic and interactive museum context.  And so, in a sense, the choice to be a visitor is an act that creates and depends on the choices that museum visitors make, and so the museum becomes a living organism that carries out the collaborative and participatory process that artist-artists</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be part of a specified curatorial agenda – but that doesn’t make them person-specific or curatorial in their intent or sense. It makes them art. Sometimes the intention is to do something quite radical and abstract – to be taken on as a client or artist-in-waiting, to be commissioned by a client or artist-in-waiting and to be artists in residence in the institution where the work is exhibited. Such an intent is explicitly placed at the curatorial level and is stated explicitly in the commission. It is stated explicitly that the commissionor has the final say regarding the way the work is exhibited and works in the institution. In other words, the commission is always about power and relationships. For this reason, artists who engage in such projects often have a plan in place to operate in ways that are contradictory to the commission’s progressive intentions. It can be seen as a way to exert influence and have a say in what happens in the art world. But</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be seen by a specific audience – and these people are often doing so with a particular set of skills and tools. And so, the degree to which the project is person-centered and person-non-person depends on the criteria being used. The more abstract the criteria, the less able the artist is to engage with the audience in person. And so, the super-abstract person-centred and person-non-person instrument is more able to engage with the contemporary person in person, but at the same time, the more concrete and humanistic the criteria become, the less able the artist is to engage with that audience.  	In fact, I would argue that the super-abstract instrument has, since its birth in the 1980s, been largely humanistic in its curatorial approach to art. It is prone to opportunistic self-promotion and self-undermining, and its margins are often as human as its content. But it has also tended to accumulate great</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be in a specific conversation with that location. And there are people who are engaging in a process that has very real effects on the city, on the artworld and their jobs. It’s true that in the 1990s and early 2000s the word ‘place’ was much more associated with architecture and mega complexes, and they certainly had a huge impact on the development of the biennale. But the ‘place’ that was increasingly associated with the biennale was the city, and so the biennale started to lose some of its sharp edge. There were architects and urbanists who had careers beyond the biennale, but as the biennale grew in scale and scope and kind of involved everyone, the need for a professional grew stronger. And so the biennale became more and more about the city as a whole, rather than just the architecture that was part of the biennale. The museum-like structure of the 1990s biennale</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be seen by a specific audience – but they don’t have any intention of making art or art-making broadly associated with that particular location. The project is not person-oriented because it doesn’t have a specific person in mind. It’s more of a collective effort. And so, the question becomes: what is the intention of the artist or curator or whoever is undertaking the project? And the answer to that question is not necessarily what the artist or curator or whoever intends to make work of the project intends to achieve. Sometimes the project is made up of many people who don’t have any intention of making work of the project, and yet all of them know that they need to do something because the city council members and people with developers’ associations and people with schoolchildren’s groups and people with seniors centres are going to be enormously disappointed if the project doesn’t deliver what it was made for. So, the intentionality of the project is</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be seen by a specific audience – yet they are making work that encompasses a broad range of experience levels and identities. And so, the project that is person-centered but projects to different levels might have very different lives and contexts than the project that calls itself person-centered but works in concert with a person-centered gallery. This is why biennials have particular, often overlapping, sometimes overlapping curatorial roles: to some extent, each of us, over time, will acquire and use these identities and experiences – which are useful in different ways – in curatorial work. The project that emerges out of the biennial is a curatorial enterprise, and in that sense, its content is much like any other curatorial undertaking. It is made up of many small pieces. Each piece is a fragment of a much larger whole. The way that the piece fits into the whole is what counts. That’s why, for example, a biennial has a chronological character – it must be assembled from</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be seen by a specific audience. That starts to sound reductionist and bureaucratic, and places a premium on what is perceived as a singular, identifiable point of view. And so, when I said that the Biennale was person-centered, I wasn’t talking about the museum or any sort of institutional attachment. I was saying that the biennale was an experience that was framed within a particular culture and identity of a particular place. And so, the cultural entities that make up the biennale are the museums and the ephemeral venues that accumulate over and over again, and so the biennale becomes embedded in those cultural systems and histories and adopts this particular framing. The problem with the biennale is that it becomes embedded in these cultural systems, and so when that happens, it has to change. It has to adopt the new institutional form that recognizes different kinds of cultural engagement. And so, the biennale has to change. It has to adapt to the</text>
    <text>brings together vast amounts of data about people and places, and allows you to ask questions about those places, and about a person or a thing. The term ‘person’ refers to an individual, and especially to an identifiable group. So, a person is a person is a person. And so, the question becomes whether the project is person-centered or person-non-person. The project is person-centered if it’s focused on a single person and their identity, experience or group identity. And the project is person-non-person if it’s focused on a process or set of processes that don’t identify anyone as a person. In fact, the more person-centered the project, the less that makes sense as a term. In the context of a multi-year, multi-edition art exhibition, the term starts to lose some of its sharp edge. There are artists who are making work for a very specific reason – to be exhibited in a specific location and to be seen by a specific audience – that is as opposed to the tendency, which is to abstract people or to lump them together. In this dynamic, the artist has a different tool with which to work. The artist does not have to identify with the audience or abide by the conventionality of the art-world. The question becomes which tool to use.Art is, in a way, a very human tool. It’s that blunt instrument with which we are exposed to the world around us and which can inflict lasting psychological wounds. It’s also that blunt instrument that can cut both ways. We need to recognise that art is art, and that it’s capable of inflicting damage even if it’s not intending to. I remember, years ago, talking with a curatorial friend who was curating the Venice Biennale. He was explaining the difference between the Biennale, which is a biennale dedicated to the art of Venice, and the Bienn</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
