<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘city’), which acts as the foundation of a new kind of social being (the ‘contract society’). The social sphere, according to this logic, is capable of organising vast amounts of data – factual and otherwise – in ways that nullify the will of the majority of its citizens. The citizen, it is assumed, dissents in silence when faced with such systematised data. He is either seduced by the utopian trappings (beauty, travel, cars) or he is willfully blind to the oppressive nature of the situation (considered ‘rational’ by a heterogeneous group of researchers and technologists). In either case, his silence is data-intensive and inaccurate, and his protestations of ‘blind faith’ are in reality an admission of defeat and failure.’ The ‘contract society’ seems to have been envisaged as a set of characteristics that all members of the club (citizens, researchers, artisans and artisans</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘city’) and purported to represent the symbolic end of such a system. Creative bonds are understood as the emergence of new forms of collective identity, consciousness and identity formation, and their negation, as the philosopher Henri Lefebvre explains.  So, too, with the concept of ‘heritage’: although it represents the past, it represents also an assumption of future values and intentions. While the city ostensibly seeks to accommodate all who live within its parameters, in its current form and in its current shape, it is also a settler community of increasingly divergent values and actions. Its spatial and temporal heterogeneity permits a multiplicity of possible futures, yet its spatial and temporal elements of ‘being’ are inherently differentiated. Its current form and inversely its future are assumed to be mutually exclusive.  The city thus appears to absorb and simultaneously contains both past and future, yet it also manifests an ever-widening range of possible futures.  Such is the urban</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘City of London Corporation’), which in turn becomes an object of shared resources (the ‘Workers Party’s plan for the city). Creative bonds are supposed to emerge through a process of ‘empirical[1] ‘representation and interpretation’, through dialogue and negotiation, and ultimately through a workplace assembly organised by and with the wishes and proposals of the community.  The  	Workers Party’s (WP) was a labor organisation that contested the exploitative character of British capitalism and sought to create a democratic alternative. Its proposals and campaigns included workplace democracy projects in the built and unbuilt environment, including the co-opting of existing workplaces for the benefit of a large clientele, as well as ‘workplace and home’ programmes combining public and collective projects.  The introduction of electronic workstations into the workplace was promoted as a way to reduce administrative burden and to democratise the workplace. Yet, as is often</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘City’ in this case), which is then used to perform actions (movement, colour, shape) that are contingent on each other. Creative actions are thereby envisioned as arising out of a shared and dynamic relationship between people. But this is not how the world really works.  The City is not some abstract concept; it’s made up of people, and its actions actually have consequences (regardless of how much of their ‘s) that ripple through the world. Creative bonds between people are imagined as arising from a distance, as being formed in the act of making something abstract. But this is not how abstractions happen. The City is made up of people, and acts as such through the mediation of economic, political and racial power.  The racist economic theory of ‘abstract labour’ makes the mistake of thinking of abstract labour as being capable of being exploited. Abstract labour exploits workers because it exploits those workers because, well, abstract labour is abstract. Abstract</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘City’), which emerges as a result of the system (technological or otherwise) that is increasingly capable of understanding and representing such creative bonds. New ‘knowledge sets’ are formed and new relationships are imagined, imagined and created.  The logic of the city thus emerges as an object and its appearance becomes an object of analysis and discourse. In this sense, the system that emerged as a result of the uprising of urban populations worldwide (beginning with the Arab Spring) is understood not as an administration tool or even as a flag-bearer for a particular political vision or ideology, but rather as a set of relations and relations that exist between people and ideas, ideas and values, knowledge and experience. In other words, it is capable of organising and concealing its social relations from the rules imposed by governance. In doing so, it becomes something other than what it is.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. But what is the logic</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘city’) and purported to represent the complexity of life in cities. But in reality, what makes the city so compelling is precisely what separates it from the countryside: agriculture, recreation, art, sports facilities, restaurants, shopping malls, educational institutions, cultural institutions, law courts, cultural institutions and on and on. The point of the ‘city’ is to some extent to animals, to most of us. And yet the city is also the object of a project that seeks to shape and engineer it into what it describes as its model city, or ‘society’, in the latest iteration of the phrase.  The system designer’s desk is here to stay. And although the city may be the object of the project, its inhabitants also constitute an expanding, transforming, shifting, evolving population that is increasingly mobile and ephemeral, increasingly urban and ephemeral. Their cities ‘situated temporality’ may be considered an essentialist conception,</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘city’) and purported to map onto a human society (the ‘empire’). There is a palpable assumption about who is entitled to what space and what is considered ‘real’, but this notion is being increasingly challenged by a more complex set of forces, including but not limited to: (1) the economic, political and social power of capital; (2) the effects of global environmental destruction; (3) the effects of overpopulation; (4) the effects of urban sprawl; and (5) the effects of regulatory capture and transparency.  The advent of social media and mobile phones has radically changed the urban landscape, but the link between source and effect remains largely elusive and variable, especially in developed nations.  The advent of data capture and sharing has radically changed how in-depth studies of urban development are performed, but the link between subject and effect is much less certain.  The advent of nano- and micro-technology has dramatically expanded the</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘city’), and the conceptualisation of such relationships is given a name: ‘the Internet of Things’.1 The concept is repeated several times throughout the document, most inflected with an English constructivist jargon called ‘Internet Symbolism’: a set of symbols (e.g., HTTP, Gopher, etc.) arranged in a hierarchy of relations between people. The inflected form of the Internet is often traced to the ‘1984 Cyberpunk manifesto’, written by Andrei Tarkovsky and Boris Groys, which appeared in 1984 in response to the appearance of computer programming in high-school computer science courses.2 In  	2000, Neal Stephenson published ‘On Cybernetics’, his writing on technology and its pervasive effects on society. Three decades earlier, Vernor Vinge had already begun to explore these same technologies of symbolic computation with a community of artists, writers and theorists. Artists, critics and activists Daphne</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘city’) and purported to map onto an ‘event’ (the ‘monolith’), which in turn is projected onto a perceived landscape (the ‘performance’). Art is often cited as a role-player in this narrative of the ‘event’, but its historical and contemporary place in the city is primarily defined by its association with specific architectural works and the transnational financial and commercial systems that enabled them to be built. The role of the artist, her organisation, and the artist’s archive is largely defined by these codes, and the role of the institutional artist is characterised by these codes as well.  Such is the urbanisation fantasy writ large – not in stone, but in urban fabric. But how to read this as a set of contradictory and variable forces – forces that are, in their essence, determined by economic and political systems – is the  	logic of the modern urbanisation project.  And yet,</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for self-organising a city, based on a mixture of state and non-state resources, is now the foundation of what can be called a ‘Calendar 3.0’.  The system is led by a Chief Information Officer (CIO) and consists of multiple levels of administrative offices, including a division for research and development of technical specifications and user-friendly applications, as well as a division for the production of individualised designs. The systems engineer’s desk sits atrium level, where visual arts professionals, artists, writers and other creative professionals gather to network, exchange ideas and exchange ‘creative bonds’. Creative bonds are mutual and indefinite in nature; they emerge and pass away, but they never cease to be the negation of something greater and more fundamental than themselves.  Such is the  	logic of the global urbanisation project. The notion that creative bonds can be formed between people is projected onto an object (the ‘city’), which is understood to possess a set of essential properties. Creative bonds form the background and act as a buffer between people and the things that make them human. But what happens when such background is taken away? When the background is taken away from people, and presumed to be void of value?  Such an object would be nothing but a repetition of the practices already existing, and yet its clear intrinsic characteristic of value – a repetition of what we already had but lacked – would be evident. When this happened, there would be no place for people to draw their strength from ‘knowing how to use it’, or drawing it from ‘knowing how to analyse it’.2  The inability to conceive of a future in which there is no city-state involved in planning and constructing it, or where infrastructure was not a fixed and final category of objects – a category which became more and more rigid as the system of commodities became increasingly complex and shifting – would</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet fundamental to the system we built is what Watts calls the ‘point of intersection’ – the point where two different points of intersection intersect.2  Watts defines the ‘intersection’ as follows: &quot;The intersectional location of the smartphone, the intersection of global economic and political systems, and the intersection of cultural production itself; this setting confronts us every day as we use or consume or are involved in any number of activities connected with the new economy that is emerging. It is a point of intersection between the places where commodities meet people, or the point where commodities meet no one.&quot;3  This philosophical, cultural and economic heterogeneity that we collectively call the intersectional place is precisely the point where commodities meet no one. It is the point where commodities first encounter people in a situation in which they do not yet own or control, where conflicting impulses and desires meet each other. It is the point of intersection where power is exerted over time – the past, present and</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet its underlying principles are ultimately applicable. 	However, the primary reason why cultural production engages with data and technology is to understand more fully what that engagement entails. That engagement is driven by a deep understanding of the world, and data capture and processing become tools that can be deployed to understand the world in powerful ways. Thus, cultural production cannot ‘exploit the technology that underlies the art’, and technology is instead a tool that is actively employed to liberate us from our human limitations. 	However, cultural production does have an obligation to ask fundamental questions, and it’s up to artists and arts organizations to demand and deliver those kinds of systems that would allow them to be more fully involved in the creation of knowledge. That's why artists’ unions and academic institutions always push back against the technocratic naivete of cultural production, which they see as inevitable, and which they see as both consumerist and economically damaging. They see the potential of new media and information technologies</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet also necessarily unstable. The art and creative processes involved in cultural production cannot be contained within rigid forms; nor can they be reduced to prescribed algorithms. They’re multi-layered and subject to the unpredictable behaviour of data capture and processing. Nevertheless, they’re produced and disseminated by a culture that constantly questions what kinds of possibilities are available in this world; what kinds of capacities do individuals have?Art is a notoriously slippery and variable resource. It’s easy to condemn an art form as obsolete; but in the age of the biennial and multiplex, it’s harder to imagine an art form in a continuous relation to a cultural production that’s driven by the AI. Art is the medium through which cultural production processes occur, and AI is the underlying technology that powers those processes. So while the biennial may seem like the ultimate in run, in reality it tends to repeat the cycle: it creates awareness, it builds public support for the art,</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet its underlying principles are simple to comprehend. The main philosophical questions regarding how human culture comes to produce technological culture, and what kinds of social and political changes can be brought about by such cultural production, remain unresolved. 	The main technological shift that came with the advent of mass computing was the advent of ‘black-box’ analysis, which allowed a culture to produce a set of tools to deal with data and information flow issues. This was done not by way of sophisticated, black-boxed software, but by way of cultural practices that involved culture producing and culture being actively engaged with in the creation of new ways of making. Such cultural practices were driven by a theology of inevitable progress, in which everything – technology, mountains, rivers and so on – would be assimilated into a global technocratic society. The belief in ‘inevitable social progress’ seems especially misplaced today, as scientific and technological innovation is the opposite of inevitable. Culture is more often cited as a force</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet also inexhaustible. It’s as if cultural production were a business that never stops evolving and new forms of economic activity can be created through the system’s inherent capabilities. 	But what does that even mean? What does ‘cultural production’ mean in the age of AI and virtual reality? What does it even mean to make cultural productions? What does it even mean to make cultural practices? These questions open up new ways of framing and thinking about the production of culture, which creates social change and ultimately, perhaps, world peace. 	The term ‘culturally relevant field’ was first coined by sociologist Peter Osborne in the 1970s, and it has been a part of the social sciences ever since. It refers to areas where social scientists can gather evidence of how social change has been achieved in a particular locale. For instance, there is research aimed at understanding how language is distributed globally, through the exchange of cultural values across societies. Languages are culturally</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet also ever more localized. It’s a complex relationship between culture, technology and location, but one that can be understood as fundamentally different from the way in which current cultural practices operate. 	Furthermore, cultural production systems operate in a very different world from what we understand as the world around us. Objects of cultural value don’t come to us as pieces of information, but as discrete and contextualised elements in a production process that includes, but isn’t limited to, human labour. A commodity commodity becomes something different when it falls outside of the sphere of human labour. For instance, the art objects in the public museums of the city today are produced by artists in partnership with galleries and other art institutions. Their production is driven by gallery members and their boards of trustees. Gallery members and their boards of trustees include artists, curators, administrators, journalists and others with varying expertise levels. All are engaged in an act of aggregation – assembling and assembling diverse collections and archives in order</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet also impervious to change. 	So, when technology creates ever more capacities for self-repairing and massive computation that are indistinguishable from magic, there is a risk that the cultural production systems that we build will be left adrift in the shifting computational fluidity, and thus susceptible to the unpredictable forces of history. Such is the  	logic of AI. But what happens when those in power try to reprogram those systems in a way that would make them serve a different function? What happens when AI threatens not only creative cultural possibilities, but also critical institutions such as the press, democracy, and even national identity? What happens when the most advanced forms of AI are de-humanized and replaced with more benevolent forms that perform a similar function but are less capable of committing mass murder? What does it mean for a system to be ‘programmed’ or ‘programmed to do’? These are just some of the many questions that can be posed to contemporary</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet also potentially liberating in its capacity to follow philosophical, anthropological and even sociological lines. 	In recent years, cultural production has become embedded in ever greater structural changes in the global art market, which is increasingly driven by information technology and media (Google, Facebook and Twitter). Consequently, cultural production today often operates outside of any clear conceptual or ideological frontiers. This has been clearly seen with the explosion of biennials, which now occupy a position of great global commercial clout. 	Art auctions have become a globalised form of cultural exchange, where works from multiple sites are systematically combined to form larger works. 	Moreover, the biennial has become a transient cultural phenomenon, with works regularly appearing elsewhere in museum collections and abroad. In the age of the museum and the museum only, we are witnessing a proliferation of biennials, which are now embedded in larger cultural landscapes. 	One of the most exciting developments in biennial studies in recent years has been the emergence of new</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet also counterintuitive and unpredictable. It’s as if the cultural production system were equipped with a tail, and as a consequence, its unpredictable nature often produces results that are inimical to the interests of the powerful and entrenched. 	The counterintuitive and unpredictable nature of the cultural production system also contributes to its malleability. The history of cultural production, and particularly of the virtual production of it, is a story of encounters and counter-examples, of encounters that present us with complex situations yet also of surprising efficiencies and creative strategies. Thus, the history of cultural production and its varied extensions is a story of encounters and counter-examples, of encounters that present us with complex situations yet also of surprising efficiencies and creative strategies. 	The history of cultural production and its varied extensions is a story of technology and its transformative effects. Thus, the history of cultural production may be divided into three eras: the Virtual Production Era (2006–09) the Historical Production Era</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that constantly monitors, records, analyzes and optimises itself. It’s like a giant personal computer, but in an even bigger sense it’s like a virtual private island where ‘ordinary people’ can ‘decode and manipulate data’. The system is driven by artificial intelligence, or AI, which is the application of artificial intelligence in cultural production. Artificial intelligence allows cultural production systems to reason in complex ways, recognizing patterns and folding historical precedents into new possibilities. For instance, the system may understand the past when it comes to understanding how to create better mapping software for data collection and mapping activities, and it may be able to reason analytically about the appropriateness of using geodata as data types in cultural production. 	Such potentially transformative applications are driven by an ever-expanding and evolving set of philosophical, anthropological and even sociological perspectives, which evolve along with the technology. Thus, cultural production becomes ever more complex, yet vital. It’s this dynamic that makes cultural imperialism possible, but it requires a certain amount of creativity and imagination as well.  	However, the more culture you have, the less you know. The system has to learn, and it’s up to artists and curators to imagine their own futures. Therefore, the more complex the system is, the less creative and interesting its outputs can be. This dynamic is driven by the philosopher John Nash (1894–1971), who said ‘the art is always committed to and pre-meditated against a backdrop of continual changes, revolutions, and upheavals’.  	So, what can a cultural production system do to challenge and evolve against the background of economic globalisation? One idea that has gained momentum in recent years is the use of data curation as a way to create an awareness of changing urban environments. In fact, the term ‘data curation’ is often used synonym</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a city, but the project invited artists and organisations to adopt a 'House Tour' or ‘series of tours’ that would take the audience on a series of tours of a neighbourhood. The opportunities for architectural interventions in the Biennial’s design was further extended through the use of 3D modelling and printing. The use of these technologies coincided with the need for planners to plan for new developments and the urban sprawl of the city, creating new forms of control over space and people. 	The use of new media and 3D modelling to create spatial variation in cultural practices was also part of an overall cultural-functional design process that also involved the involvement of artists and organisations. This was done through activities such as events such as the Art Triennale, which drew artists and organisations together across disciplines to explore artistic practices, and the K, one of the planned art biennials, which would be a place to find art and art-related activities. KK and his team</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a city, but the project’s real intention was to address the fact that a community of artists, designers, artists, designers, artists and community organisers was now actively engaged in actively creating a new cultural landscape through the curatorial work it was doing alongside a local town. This engaged the local community members who had been involved in The One Show before, but who had then moved on to engage with other art institutions, starting with the Chirality Arts Centre. They brought their skills and approaches to the project, which was actively encouraged by the Curatorial Faculty and Arts Council, as well as the local artists who were already involved in the arts context and community. The Arts Council had been working closely with the Arts Council Schools to deliver the art and education programme through which the local students of the arts context would be engaged, through arts management and partnerships with organisations including Chirality Arts Centre, Grassroots Outreach, Childline, FutureLearn and Independent</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a city, and the community could be seen as a living monument to that changing landscape. In this project, the community was seen not only as stakeholders in the work being done in their neighbourhood, but also as artists, designers, writers and curators who possessed creative agency within the Biennial.  The Biennial would also create a home for the local community of artists, curators, artists’ organisations and venues, as well as a space for activities including research and discussion.  If the Biennial were to continue, its current location in the heart of Birmingham’s arts district, but moved to a larger arts institution in nearby Doha, Qatar, would create a new kind of spatial variation within the Biennial.  This would mean creating locations that could sustain a biennial indefinitely, but also providing an alternative to a museum or a large gallery when visiting a city, region or country, by creating virtual borders between places. This is the spatial variant of cultural tourism,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a city, but the real engagement and signification of the term was created through the spatial variation and time of the biennial itself. The physical change that the biennial (in its temporal and spatial heterogeneity) engages with is generated and reproduced through the activities of the curatorial, its curatorial surplus and its curatorial negligence. The term ‘biennial’ was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of cultural exchange, but the realisation and subsequent (potential) production of the term came from the actualisation of the art and cultural resources of the city, which are situated in and contribute to the circulation of ideas and images. KK and his team understood that the realisation and subsequent production of the concept would have to come from somewhere else, and so they used different words and concepts to describe the very different (but related) cultural forms that were being built around the biennial. They were not interested in what is now called the ‘vanishing act of culture�</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a given city, but in the case of a ‘city-wide’ cultural revolution, the biennial would enter into a ‘house built and hosted’ loop. As cultural capital moves from the city to the city, ‘biennial’ becomes a tool for the maintenance and expansion of existing cultural landscapes, while the Biennial itself becomes an instrument of cultural reclamation. At the same time, cultural capital itself becomes increasingly fragile in this context. The biennial is the site of the cultural revolution, but it is also the site of the cultural rebound. If the biennial is to survive in its current form, it is imperative that it collaborates with the city in its cultural needs, while actively engaging with its cultural infrastructure in constructing a city-wide cultural scene through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a city. The exhibition would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for a specific set of people, place and time. The act of construction would last for a specified set of years and, through a kind of ‘time-stamping’ process, a specific and enduring spatial variation would be traced in the city. 	The artistic director of the Liverpool Biennial was Wendy Harpe, a local artist who had worked with the Biennial before on a curatorial basis in Birmingham, (1998–2001) and Dirk Groothuis, curator of art at Kassel (2002–2006). Together, they had been working with Harpe on the exhibition format of the Biscombe, part of the Kassel curatorial programme, 1994–97. The exhibition format was developed with Harpe in mind, as the artist was an ideal candidate for the role, as were the other artists, including Janet</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a city. In the case of Liverpool, the Biennial would occupy a site in the city where the city is constantly changing and where, as a result, there is a constant need to be constantly organised and re-configured. The name ‘Biennial’ is a hybrid term that reflects the fact that the art was intended to be permanent, whereas the curatorial function of the Biennial is to continuously revise and anchor the art in perpetuity. Thus, the curatorial function of the Biennial could be seen as having a life of its own. However, the real test of the curatorial function of the Biennial in this city would be in its interaction with the environment. The Biennial would have to actively create opportunities for its members to participate in the cultural life of the city in a substantive way – actively engaging with the art and culture as a city in order to maintain a continuous relationship to it. The question would then be which version of the Biennial could be most effectively</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a city. The concept was further legitimised by the fact that a biennial was a regular feature of Liverpool, with artists regularly returning to the city for various curatorial roles. The fact that the Biennial would be run by a for-profit company made the concept more credible, since it reduced any cultural alienation or loss that might befalling the city. In this sense, the Biennial might be seen as a success, since it no longer represents the urban landscape in decline but instead serves as a catalyst that enables other projects to be mounted. 	The opening day of the Liverpool Biennial, 2017. Photo: Tom Lox. 	As part of its mission to discover new ways of engaging people, the Biennial commissioned a community of artists and social creatives to create a series of sessions around the city in which the artist Bijan Kerkat was invited to collaborate. The artists Panic! at Work! and Co-operative Arts Centre created a</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a city. In the twentieth century, biennials became visible in New York and other major art centres due to their internal continuity, their homogenised, commodified forms, their exposure to the cultural resources of urban life, and their frequent adoption by art collections. However, since the late 1990s the biennial has increasingly become a collection of collections, with the most recent being curated by Deborah Levy at the Museum of Modern Art, New York. She has assembled a large and diverse collection of works from around the world, which she has divided into four major themes according to her own taste: art, performance, history and present. These four elements are the basis of a visual language that is constantly on the move, constantly contextualising and varies according to the needs of the curatorial team. They serve as a mapping of changes in the contemporary artworld, a constantly shifting target. The four elements – the art world, the performance world, the ‘present’ world – constitute the core</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial with a social function, by engaging the curator’s work as a social media platform and bringing his/her work to life through participatory media. This project was proposed by KK (Kate Kane) Konrad, Director of Artistic Development at KK, and commissioned by KK’s Curatorial Faculty. KK and his team worked closely with the artists, designers, activists and community organisers who had formed the KK community into which the Biennial would be built. They instilled a sense of community and purpose around the project through activities such as Opening Day at the Arts Centre, rallies in the local shops, distribution of literature and videos in the local newspapers and online, hosting local groups to help with presentation, organising language classes and so much more. The Biennial would be a ‘house built and hosted’ for the local community. The name 'Biennial' was coined to describe the spatial variation and temporality of change in the cultural landscape of a city. The physical act of staging a biennial became increasingly important as the city experienced the fragmentation and fragmentation of the post-1990’crisis period, and with it the urban crisis that it reflected. The role of the artist, producer and curator was to take part in this spatial variation and temporality as a producer, operator and (later) a curator of cultural practices, in an act that involved a great deal of responsibility and responsibility was given to a network of community of artists, producers, curators, artists’ organisations, artists’ friends and family members. This new kind of biennial was to be dynamic, its content constantly shifting, unpredictable and creative, constantly questioning its own assumptions and laws. It was to be punctured by confrontations of some kind between different kinds of biennials, its artists, producers and curators, but also by the real-life situations that artists, producers and curators faced in various parts of the world. In the 1980s</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures
    <text>might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures of cities – the sites of their latest art shows – than the past, with the aim of creating a relational form of contemporaneity between the past and the future through the present, present and future. This is why biennials tend to present their projects as if they were from the past, making them contemporary while the contemporary art world tends to present its own work through the same artist or a similar set of artists today. This is why biennials often show their projects in the present, present-day situation, showing what is happening in a city while narrating the history of that city. This is also why biennials tend to narrate contemporary art and artistic practice as if it were a story of two cities, explaining how art can be produced in a city while its history is continuously rewritten.  Such narrations are less interested in the immediate, causal conditions that produce and emerge from art today, and more interested in the enhanced visibility and global impact of art produced in a city</text>
    <text>might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures of cities and nations than the past. They are interested in the ways in which art can act as a mediator between cultures, bringing together disparate parts of the same people and cultures. The art you see today is produced with unprecedented immediacy and depth, yet its real-life impact is measured in microseconds. The number of micro-biennials has exploded in the past twenty years. In New York alone there are now more than 200, and in 2014 there were over 4,000 in Paris. The number of biennials worldwide has quadrupled during this same time. Each biennial now produces its own unique combination of art, history, politics, geography, and sometimes economics, often operating under the same name. This is the biennial today. This is what biennials are for. And this is what art biennials are for. In a general sense, we can say that biennials are for artists; for every biennial there is an artist. Bienn</text>
    <text>might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures of their artworks than the long-term prospects of the art world. A few curators have made occasional interventions in the past, but their significant interest today is in the organization and maintenance of collections, as well as the promotion and diffusion of their collections. The biennial today also attracts curators from other disciplines, most notably from the physical and photographic museum world. The biennial is an art institution today, and the curatorial intervention and exhibitionary function are the objects of a museum that is itself a museum institution. The biennial format is experiencing a construction boom. As a result, the gallery, once a locus of resistance, is now a site of intervention and interventionism. I, for one, look forward to seeing what these curators do with the biennial as a museum of art, and to participating in what can be a ‘curatorial insurrection’ as they organize, direct and fortuitously stumble into this art form on their own.Download this article as</text>
    <text>might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures of cities and nations than the past. In Cairo, Qatar, for example, the 2022 FIFA World Cup is being built with funds from the United Arab Emirates and Qatar 2022 Football Association. The biennial has a contractual obligation to tell a story, but it appears to lack the drive or even the will to do so. What is needed is a visionary curatorial agenda that projects the future in compelling ways, while also engaging with the past in interesting and creative ways. In order to effectively engage with the present, the biennial exhibition must be able to project the future in compelling ways, while also questioning present and emerging realities.  A Vision For The Future (2011-)In my annual report for the journal Social Practice (published in February 2012), I reflect on twenty-first-century social practice, and the exhibition Future City at the 36th Venice Biennale continues to occupy a central place. The Biennale has assumed a new curatorial importance in order to better integrate</text>
    <text>might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures of cities and nations than with the past, post-Fordist society. This is evident in their interest in the displaced populations of Syria and Iraq, which they call ‘present-day movements’, despite the overwhelming majority of which are of the displaced ethnically mixed populations. The biennial in its current form is also no longer the sole preserve of affluent and highly visible artists, whose portfolios now regularly include immersive experiences for visitors to galleries and museums, along with books and pamphlets. The biennial has become the showcase of modern and contemporary art worldwide, and the biennial in its own right. In many cities, biennials are the only form of art exhibit that presents contemporary art from a regional or local perspective. In other words, their historical focus and globalisation make them both present, present, and contemporary.  	The biennial is the rarest of curiosities. Its history and current state of creation is left to historians and philosophers to decipher, much as</text>
    <text>might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures of their cities and nations, and the organization of future art collections, than they are with the past or with the future, or with the art or curation produced as a result of those futures. The biennial of the present must anticipate and address a future city, or it will not be able to capitalize on its new wealth of information, ideas and cultural experiences. So the biennial of the future has two forms: it can be an artistic project, or it can be a business venture. Because the biennial of the present is based on the biennial of the past, it is also a perpetual condition: it is the observer of the past but not part of the future. In other words, it creates what it does not understand and thus unknowingly pursues a trajectory of destruction. In an ideal world, the biennial of the future would cease to exist and its curatorial agenda would reside in museums and archives, where it could be overseen by a museum committee and tasked with gathering</text>
    <text>might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures of cities and nations than the past, post-collapse. As a result, they are quick to repeat old tired urban problems and to romanticise the former glories of post-industrial cities. The contemporary biennial is a rarefaction: it is a form of public institution that emerges in reaction to the other, more imperious forms of institutionalised culture. It is a space of its own production, made up of its own constituent parts. This is evident in the exhibition catalogue of the twenty-first Venice Biennale, for instance: it is a catalogue of ‘biennials in their own right’, events such as this one being made into a museum. It is also evident in the numerous ‘biennial books’ published in the biennial press each year, which much of this one does not seem to have read.  At the same time, these ‘biennial books’ are the primary platform of the exhibitionary complex, and the</text>
    <text>might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures of art and culture than the past, and often involve the establishment of long-term curatorial commitments. This is reflected in the number of artists who have become involved in curating projects in the metropolis, which has risen from two-thirds of the biennial base in Belfast to over four-fifths today. Another factor is the emergence of a biennial culture that prizes visibility and connections over history, and in this sense is also reflected in the number of biennials. In the 1990s there were only a handful of biennials, and in 2015 there were over 200. This has been driven by an identity crisis in the art world, which sees contemporary art as fundamentally about the connectedness of people and the wider society, and history as subordinate to current trends and circumstances. The emergence of this curatorial orientation in the twentieth century can be seen as the curatorial reversal of the twentieth century; it is a moment when images from the past are re-gilded into contemporary art</text>
    <text>might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures of cities and nations than the past. This is evident in the projects they select through the eminent curatorial name-dropping that includes but is not limited to  Wanda Lewis (China), Resident Curator Arjun Appadurai (India), Manoj Tiwari (Uttarakhand), M. Venkateshwara (Tamil Nadu), K. Subramanian (Delhi), Rajdeep Sardesai (Jharkhand), Etienne Balibar (Chittagong), Satish Kanady (Delhi-UT), M. V. Khanna (Delhi-UT), P. Khurana (Delhi), U.S. Air and Space Curator, Kurt Weiler (Washington), D. Samson Kambalu (Delhi-UT), Rajdeep Sardesai</text>
    <text>might be curated under the title The Contemporary Condition, from its first example, a watercolour of a room by the artist Ben Whittaker, published in 1890, to the present incarnation, a global franchise of the same name operating in twenty-first-century Dubai. The aim of the exhibition was to show the many facets of this current moment, showing the dozens of startups, the millions of refugees, the evolving relationship between cities and nations, the apocalyptic future predicted by futurist Ray Bradbury, and on and on. The curatorial agenda and the curatorial function of the biennial has shifted from documenting the past to imagining the future. The aim of the contemporary biennial is to book-shop and market itself. This, however, is just a heterogeneous and transient phenomenon. The biennial today is driven by artists and their curators, who are drawn from a fringes of the art world but have an eye on the big picture. Their current projects are more concerned with the immediate futures of the art they commission, and the companies they partner with, than they are with the past, the long-term effects of a host of crises. The biennial as a curatorial tool has, in recent years, become an unreliable and corrupting one. It is, however, deeply embedded in the art world and widely distributed. The biennial today is the largest and most visible curatorial tool, and the exhibitionary platform of the world, except in the pockets of art communities that value their institutional reputations. It is the counterintuitive consequence of a curatorial tool that is also the most malleable, subject to the whims of the moment, and dependent on the whims of the people entrusted to its affairs. The biennial is the curatorial equivalent of a market maker's black box. It is, in short, the opposite of a market maker. It cannot build or repair a market. It cannot create wealth or wealth destroy a market. It is, however, absolutely essential</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if
    <text>an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if anything could be done to reduce the negative connotations of the name, it was as a response to the negative ones that are being applied to it.The other reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context was that they believed that its goals and objectives were no longer relevant. The AI that was developed in parallel with the art project would be able to understand symbolic relationships, and the ways in which art could be used to revolutionise both the technocratic and the social institutions of the city. In other words, the goals and objectives of the ARTI project were not to meet an artist’s needs but to understand how the city could be transformed in the context of an AI project. In effect, they believed that the goals and objectives of the ARTI project were not to meet an artist’s needs but to understand how art could change the world. This was a position that was at odds with the historical orientation of the AI field,</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if it is seen as an artefact from the past then it is more easily changed into something else. In the context of AI and machine learning, the question is what can be done to make the artefact visible in a broader way? How can artefacts that we inhabit and edit be engaged with in new ways? What are the limits to what can be made visible? How are ideas made visible? What is the epistemological problem with this? What is the contribution of culture to the production of images? What is the aesthetic problem with this? What are the limits to what can be imagined? What is at stake in the production of images? What are the epistemological problems with the new media of images? What are the capacities of the culturally engaged to produce images? What are the capacities of the mass media to imagine possible alternatives? What are the capacities of the artist to imagine new ways of existing in the world?  In a TED talk, Brynjolfur Arnarson describes</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if it’s too soon to declare the end of the process of AI, why not start now and see what happens in five years or ten years? It’s difficult to define the parameters of what is and is not AI, but it’s clear that the political and social imperatives of the future that are being imagined are fundamentally incompatible with the kind of social organization that we have today.As an example of this, we can consider the emergence of Twitter. Initially, the emergence of Twitter was seen as a reaction to the Vietnam War – which many people believed was unwinnable – and the economic devastation caused by it. The emergence of Twitter coincided with the start of the second intifada, which many people believed was unwinnable, since it was centered around specific individuals and projects. The emergence of Twitter coincided with the start of the third intifada, which many people believed was unwinnable, since it was decentralized and spread across many different social networks. The</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if it is seen as an artifact of the present, then it is seen as being against the grain of progress, and with it a great loss of dignity and self-worth. But there are other factors that also need to be considered when drawing up future research projects. For example, the implications of machine learning for artistic practices are being studied. If it is shown that the AI that is being trained can identify good and bad imagery in photographs, then there is a good chance that it could be used to identify artists at an early stage in the process of creation. The implications for cultural appropriation and art in the social and cultural context are also being studied. If it is shown that the AI can identify and map cultural spaces and sites out to space, then there is a good chance that it could also map those spaces and sites to specific individuals or groups’ needs and desires. In other words, cultural appropriation and art in the social and cultural context are not just cultural legacies that are being made elsewhere</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if the present is any indication, this is precisely what we’re doing.The other reason for the participants to see the project as prescient was that it came at a time when there was a crisis of consciousness. Today, we’ve come to understand the sense of fragility and the fragility of our surroundings. We’ve also come to understand that our own work – whether it’s language or AI or physical objects – can be used as a weapon against us. For example, the recent attacks on public spaces around the world that have seen an increase in violent extremism, or the warring states of the Amazon or the potentially deadly consequences of climate change, are a reminder that we are threatened not by individual acts of violence, but by the inbuilt biases and injustices that create the conditions that enable violent acts to take place. The fragility of our societies is also a source of our strength. If participants in the project had their way, the city would cease</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if it were to be made today, it could be seen as having been conceived in the past, and having relevance in the present context.Another factor in the decision to engage in such a project in the first place is that, in the age of the internet, it is easy to look back to the past and see what a devastating impact technological innovation can have on the fabric of society. The internet is a blunt instrument, but it is also a deeply embedded one. It is woven into the fabric of contemporary society, and is therefore seen as malleable, changeable and ever-alive. The internet is a blunt instrument, but it is also a deeply embedded one. It is woven into the fabric of contemporary society, and is therefore seen as malleable, changeable and ever-alive. The internet is a blunt instrument, but it is also a deeply embedded one. It is embedded in the very fabric of modern society, and is therefore seen as malleable, change</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if the present were any indication, things would be quite different now.  	In The Art of Not Being Governed, Wittgenstein reminds us that we live in a technologically mediated society and society has two modes of being governed: those that provide tools and information about how to be governed, and those that do not. The fifth mode, what I have termed ‘natural’ by way of an ‘artificial’ ruler, is what I call ‘natural’ because it is made up of already existing social relations that we already have. It is not a new mode of being governed, but the new mode is governed by the mechanisms of power that we create and uphold. Wittgenstein reminds us that the mode of the natural is limited: it is not possible to reorient the trajectory of history as a way of thinking about the past or even to conceive of a future that does not experience an economic and ecological imprint on it. So the mode of</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if anything could be learned from the history of ​​machine learning’ it would be that the capacities of people with disabilities could be enhanced in this new technological paradigm.Although the project did not end up directly addressing the specific needs of people with disabilities, the participants did end up shaping what the future might one day be like. As recently as a year and a half ago, when the project was first announced, it was widely assumed that people with disabilities would be able to access the internet and replicate the technological innovations of the internet today. However, a recent study by the ​Google Brain Lab ​(funded by the US National Institutes of Health) suggests that many people with disabilities still struggle to find work that matches their skills, and even if they do find work it may not always be rewarding. The study, ​Manning &amp; Marchant’s, ​​(2013) suggests that while the skills of web developers and data scientists have improved, the mechanisms of the internet are still subject to</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if it is seen as an expression of what is possible in the future, then it can lay claim to having happened in the past.  In any case, the philosophy of the participant-organised project, as well as the artefacts themselves, became a site for critical reflection and negotiation. The identities of the participants in the project are increasingly being brought forward in order to argue in front of a panel of representatives of the technology industry, government and legal systems, as well as representatives of non-governmental organisations (NGOs) about the legal status of autonomous vehicles and how that might relate to the rights of indigenous peoples.  A number of the programme’s decision-makers are being brought forward as representatives of non-governmental organisations (NGOs) as a means to ensure that the events depicted in the exhibition do not become representative of the current political situation in Canada.  The role of the museum in the creation of the exhibition was another area where the federation hoped to act in solidarity with the</text>
    <text>an AI curated the installation of the new exhibition The Fourth Machine (2012) in cooperation with the Department of Communications and Information Technology, University of Sydney. The Fourth Machine was a kind of open call for proposals on what the ‘fourth machine’ might mean in the context of artificial intelligence. The project was a response to the negative connotations of the name (particularly in academia) towards people with disabilities. Many researchers and philosophers felt that the new technological paradigm was forcing a general assumption about humans and the world that could not be reconciled with traditional ideas of creator and governed by traditional ideas of history. The philosophy and political leanings of the participants in the project do not necessarily correspond to those of the participants in the present, but some of the decisions that are being made now in the context of the Fourth Machine could certainly be seen as being informed by the work of the past. This was perhaps one reason why the participants felt that the project could be seen to be prescient in the present context: if the present are no longer seen as the ideal historical setting, but are instead creatively imaginalised, then the present could be repurposed and used to address needs and desires of the community.This kind of visionary thinking is not confined to scholars or theoretical philosophers. It is widely shared in the AI community, and is often cited as a reason to pursue more immersive and contextual ways of interacting with the computer systems that underpin AI. It is a reason to engage with the notion of intelligence in new ways, and to imagine new possibilities for how cultural resources might be utilised. But it is also a reason to actively participate in the development of new AI systems, and potentially alter existing ones in certain situations. This kind of involvement is understood as ‘deep learning’ – the cognitive technology underpinning AI – and is perceived as a potential new way of building publics and creating collective futures.But deep learning is just one aspect of what is being done with AI. There is a growing body of</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things
    <text>might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things to Come: Episode 1: Introduction. MP3 Download 2013.12.07 (In Episode 1, Gannon provides an overview of the creative process, the catalyst for the project, and the ideas and methods behind it.)[2] Gill Sussman,  	The Portents of Things to Come: Art, Reality, and the End of Time (Doubleday, New York, 1988), p.2.Download this article as PDFGill SussmanGill Sussman is an artist and writer. His work in the public sphere involves a constantly shifting set of circumstances, which continually call for a retreat into conventional wisdom or simple common sense, he calls ‘the spectacle’. He is a co-founder of the Serpentine Gallery, was an Assistant Curator at the Tate Modern and served as an Assistant Curator at the Getty Center. He is currently a Senior Curator for the Liverpool and London Museums</text>
    <text>might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things to Come: Institutional Episodes, PBS Frontline, 2016. [2] Ana Laura Lopéz de la Torre, Institutional Decenters: Crisis of the Public Theatre, 1988. [3] Gareth White, The Portents of Things to Come, Simon &amp; Schuster, New York, 1995, p. 20. [4] Karl Marx, Grundrisse, I, The Communist Manifesto, 1848, p. 20. [5] Michael Britten,  	Thing, I, Blackwell, Oxford, 1991, p. 38. [6] Gordon Frederic Norton,  	The Wealth of Nations, Vintage, London, 1957, p. 1. [7] Thomas Allsen,  	The Culture and Politics of Exchange, University of Chicago Press, Chicago, 1978, p. 42. [8] Thomas Allsen,  	Thing, I,</text>
    <text>might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things to Come: Institutional Episodes, PBS Frontline, 2016. Available at: http://www.pbs.org/fpc/index.html?fuseaction=streaming&amp;type=2&amp;referer=http://www.frontline.org/series/35689/institutional-episodes-crisis-remedy-2018-january-pbs-frontline/2/2/3/3/4/6/frontline/2/2/2/3/4/6/2/frontline/2/2/4/6/2/2/2/frontline/2/2/4/6/2/2/2/frontline/2/2/6/2/2/2/2/frontline/2/1/6/2/1/2/2/2/2/2/2/2/2/2/2/2/</text>
    <text>might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things to Come: Institutional Episodes. Available at: http://www.institutional-episodes.org/en/film/portents-of-things-to-come-institution-episodes-crisis-revelations-institute/ (accessed 30 April 2018).  [2] Institution Episodes, Crisis and Redemption. Available at: http://www.institutional-episodes.org/en/film/portents-of-things-to-come-institution-episodes-crisis-revelation/ (accessed 30 April 2018).  [3] Institution Episodes, Crisis and Redemption. Available at: http://www.institutional-episodes.org/en/film/portents-of-things-to-come-institution-episodes-crisis-revelation/&amp;-1 (accessed 30 April 2018).  [4] Institution Ep</text>
    <text>might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things to Come: Institutional Episodes, p.13.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleSophie Hope-Hyde and Rob Kling  	Noam Chomsky, Language and Class, Greenwood Publishing Group, New York, 1995.  [2] Mach-Zeinul (ed.),  	Signals from the Future: Language and Postcolonialism, Routledge, New York, 1980.  [3] Neoliberalism,  	ed. Patrick J. Buchanan, Princeton Architectural Press, Princeton, 1980, p.2.Download this article as PDFRob Kling  	Noam Chomsky, Language and Class, Greenwood Publishing Group, New York, 1995, pp.2–3.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleIain McKay and Michael TruscelloIain McKay is a PhD candidate in Communication Studies and Geographies at the University of British Columbia, specializing in the intersection of settler colonialism and language.</text>
    <text>might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things to Come: Institutional Episodes, PBS Frontline (2016), http://www.pbs.org/newshour/frontline/archive/full/1.InstitutionalEpisodesCrisisAndRedemption2016.9. InstitutionalEpisodesCrisisAndRedemption2016.9.1. Introduction.2. How the Portents of Things to Come came to be.3. A brief introduction to the ideas and practices of Institutional Episodes.4. The role of the film in the evolution of the Biennale.5. The relationship between the biennale and contemporary art practices.6. Film noir in the biennale context.7. Film noir in the contemporary art context.8. Film noir as a concept and its relation to the biennale.9. Towards a theory of the institutionalisation of film noir.10. The relationship between the film noir and the institutionalisation of film noir.11.</text>
    <text>might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things to Come: Institutional Episodes, 2016. Documentary, 45 min, 2016. Available at: http://www.pbs.org/frontline/episode/frontline-institutional-episodes-crisis-rejection-film/1621/2.html#.VLL7TljlE#.VLL7TljlE 'Institutional Episodes' is the name of the series of three films that Gaiman set in motion in 2009. In 2011, a group of artists reclaimed the name ‘Institutional Ecosystem’ on the wall of the Hayward Gallery, where it had hung since 1905. In 2014, the Gallery launched a fundraising campaign to restore the bird’s appearance, and in 2015, a community land trust established a new art school for the birds. Institutional Ecosystem was also the name of the 2014 Biennale of Australian Art, which featured work by Sally Tallant, Rodney Hill, Max Martin and</text>
    <text>might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things to Come: Episode One, John Lennon and Yoko Ono, adapted from the song by John Lennon and Paul McCartney.  [2] The Portents of Things to Come: Episode Two, Yoko Ono, adapted from the song by John Lennon and Paul McCartney.  [3] The Portents of Things to Come: Episode Three, Peter Saville, adapted from the song by Lennon and McCartney.  [4] The Portents of Things to Come, John Lennon and Yoko Ono, from the Lennon/McCartney quartet.  [5] The Portents of Things to Come, from the Lennon/McCartney quartet.  [6] The Portents of Things to Come, from the Lennon/McCartney quartet.  [7] The Portents of Things to Come, from the Lennon/McCartney quartet.  [8] The Portents of Things to Come</text>
    <text>might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things to Come: Episode One in the series Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption. (Image from the video)Download this article as PDFLolivia Danto-RuizLocations of the World Heritage Sites of the Future CityNC Museum of Modern Art, New York, USANC Museum of Modern Art, New York, USALatsura Museum of Art, Lopwarcha, Rwanda, USAKwakiutl'inam Museum of Art, Lulea, South Africa, USAKwakiutl'inam Museum of Art, Lulea, South Africa, USAKwakiutl'inam Museum of Art, Lulea, South Africa, USAKwakiutl'inam Museum of Art, Lulea, South Africa, USAKwakiutl'inam Museum of Art, Lulea, South Africa, USAKwakiutl'inam Museum of Art, Lulea</text>
    <text>might be curated by Dont Drysinski) and features in the forthcoming exhibition, The Nation: The Rise and Fall of the Photograph Industry (2017), to be shown in the Tate Gallery and National Gallery galleries in London and in other US cities. In the United Kingdom, the Getty and Tate galleries are staging a joint exhibition, The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum (2017) – a collaboration with Tate Modern Art Gallery – in cooperation with Liverpool and Manchester Museums. The film, entitled The Portents of Things to Come: Imagining the Museum, was once again exhibited at the Venice Biennale Gallery in 2015. As ever, the director is Stephen Gaghan, who directed the Venice Biennale (2012) and the Tate Modern (2015). The film is the subject of a new documentary, Institutional Episodes: Crisis and Redemption in a Public Theatre, which will broadcast on PBS Frontline on April 24, 2016.  [1] The Portents of Things to Come: Transformation through Art and Film,2015. Available at: http://www.institutional-episodes.com/en/. Accessed December 2018.  [2] Gielen, Thomas. ‘Imminent Domain: The Geographies of Globalization and Its Impact’, in  	Future City: Essays on Geographies ed. Michael Parkinson and Christiane Paul. New York: Routledge, 2015, p. 52.  [3] Gielen, Thomas and Neil Johnson. ‘Issues of Democracy: Geographies of Voting Rights Destruction in Brazil, 1910–1930’,  	International Studies Quarterly. Vol. 78, No. 1, pp. 8–25.  [4] Curtis Flint.  	Roaring Twenties: Social History of the Twenties in America’,  	American Journal of Sociology. Vol. 137, No. 1,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommission
    <text>an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommissioning process: the museum closed due to financial problems, the multiplex closed down due to lack of interest, and the art spaces closed because of budget constraints. But these historical circumstances are necessarily very different from the situation now, and are characterised by an explosion of new museum buildings, many of them constructed around the biennial itself. New biennials are established on the back of a self-sustaining bottom line, and so are the heirs of the museums that preceded them. When the biennial was at its height, the relationship between the biennial and the museum was complex. The biennial had two institutional functions: first, to house the art and artefacts of the art form, and secondly, to encourage a community of artists and curators to inhabit the cultural zones within its grounds. But in the past few years, the biennial has been forced to operate behind the scenes, either because of a lack of interest in the art form or a desire to divert resources</text>
    <text>an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommissioning process 	, in which artists’ studios and exhibitions’ space was either razed or severely limited. So the biennale was able to establish a presence in places such as Liverpool, where it was seen by locals as a natural outgrowth of the city’s economic miracle, as distinct from any art institution that might interfere with that miracle. The biennale was even able to find a home in the then far more staid New York art market as a way to operate on a large scale outside the city, through something it called the ‘Global Platform’ initiative. It was here that the biennale took on a life of its own, operating at a scale that allowed the public to participate in a different kind of architecture, one that wasn’t necessarily planned or controlled from the city. 	 Art, it seemed to many people, was everywhere at once, whereas architecture was an island unto its own sort</text>
    <text>an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommissioning. Cultures held fast to their historic experiences, built upon contingency. Cultural tourism began to be seen by the urban planner as a way to generate new business opportunities by re-constituting the temporality of the cultural sector.  The new museum building, its shell and façade taken up with tourists, was an extreme case in point. It met with fierce criticism from residents, the community of neighbourhood artists who used the building as a studio, and many others who felt that the development of a museum with a curatorial focus was an encroachment on their cultural spaces. But these were people, urban planners, not artists. The museum and the multiplex were objects of transition, and the art world responded by positioning itself, both consciously and unconsciously, as the new curator of cultural resources. The new curatorial focus placed the museum within a larger framework of cultural exchanges, introducing a new generation of artists to the art institution and its practices. The presence of the museum as a cultural resource</text>
    <text>an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommissioning process, as the railway was winding down. The ‘Hollywood Complex’ was being retired, replaced with a new ‘Promenades to Observe the Sunset’ that would bring nature closer to the buildings on the other side of the tracks. 	At the time, the biennale was developing at a rapid clip, with the London Biennale Board declaring in their report of April 1972 that there was no comparison between the performance of art and that of industry. Postwar Bienal de São Paulo (1973) became the most famous example of this, when the previously established biennale in São Paulo, became the first to renounce the use of the city as a performance space and instead invest heavily, indeed completely, centred around the use of the Biennale as a kind of temporary exhibition venue. The Biennale Board report also suggested that this was the time to begin a programme of educational</text>
    <text>an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommissioning process, as recently as the 1970s, as the rise of the museum coincided with the fall of production, and as recently as the 1990s, as the rise of the multiplex coincided with the decline of exhibition production. But the importance of the museum and the multiplex in the 1980s is that it provided the space for a new discourse and new models of cultural activity, new forms of social organisation. It became a site of exchange not just as a marketplace but also as a site of consumption, where artists could experiment with new modes of cultural organising, and for this, it was important for the art to be made accessible to as many people as possible. And one of the main tasks of the art dealer in that period was to make the most of the museum. It wasn’t just about buying art, but about generating cultural capital and engaging people in cultural activity.The art dealer made a lot of money at the time. And so the idea that you could bring art into</text>
    <text>an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommissioning, the slicing and dicing of the city into small parcels, and the decimation of its cultural difference. But the art world had yet to acclimate itself to this new world, and its inhabitants still didn’t have a firm grasp on the idea of the urban. The new  	generation of artists and arts-policy wonks (me included) were to arrive late to this comprehension, and our reception of the idea of the urban  	late to the  	generation who were born after the end of World War II. The end of the war did not necessarily mean the end of urban life, but it did potentially  influence what art historians would later call the ‘permanent motion of capital’. Art, by its very nature, thrives in the temporality of the transient. Art has a physical form, and as such, it can exist in any temporal order. The</text>
    <text>an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommissioning process: boarded-up houses, abandoned lots, boarded-up schools, vacant lots. The number of vacant lots doubled between 1970 and 1980, as did the number of museums, as the city sat on huge inventories of clean-up art, often commissioned by the city, that it curatorial leanings. The collection of neglected buildings that were part of the New York Public Library was also heavily curtailed by the city, making it a scarce resource for arts education. Since the 1980s the Biennale has been moved to a new location every two years, in Amsterdam, and the Biennale is the only remaining institution of its former size in Amsterdam. It once again relies on the city as a source of art, and its inhabitants as consumers. The Biennale was founded in 1991, and in 1997 the title was changed to the Biennale di Venegio. Venice is the capital of Italy, and the largest city in the country; its environs are</text>
    <text>an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommissioning process: boarded galleries, boarded theatres, boarded sports grounds, boarded schools, boarded street level retail outlets, all washed up on their sides, abandoned corridors, boarded-up theatres and their renovation costs were all incorporated into the overall cost of the collection. The collection as a whole was accumulated in the early twentieth century, so its condition would be in modern-day demand as a result of  	austerity. 	However, this is not to downplay the importance of the collection as a living organism: the collection today is critical to the organisation of knowledge and its ability to carry out its mission of education, making possible the organisation of universal, free and eco-systems knowledge. 	In the current global financial and ecological crisis, the biennale is a scarce commodity, and the museum and the multiplex are increasingly used to generate revenue for governments and other institutions, a situation that can no longer be taken for granted. A</text>
    <text>an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommissioning project, which was building towards a  	neighborhood utopia, if not yet a fully realised one. The art deco style that had been so prevalent in areas such as Liverpool, Chicago and San Francisco was being picked apart by developers in the wake of the financial crisis, while the museums that once filled them with exhibitions were being forced to close due to declining numbers and financial constraints. The collection that the museum was able to preserve, in the form of its Current Exhibition, offered a measure of this shift, providing a home to works that functioned in a different, yet still valuable way. 	There were other places that moved with them, too: in the art world in particular, there was a re-emergence of the term ‘culture petit three’, which had been constituted in the wake of the second wave of hip-hop, and which became a staple of fringe cultures, including New</text>
    <text>an AI curated and led by Gareth White, exhibition space and public art in its own right, conceived as a multi-year, multi-edition, multi-edition biennale. The main discursiveness was built into the idea of multiplexes, where the museum and the multiplex functioned together, in this example as an institution, and in a number of other forms, across cultural zones, within walking distance of each other. It was an idea that at the time was foreign to many people in the UK, and especially in areas outside the cities, where the railway station was a close second. It was also a novelty for non-urban people in major cultural zones, such as New York, who had long imagined themselves to be transported somewhere far away from the city center. The museum and the multiplex became objects of transfer rather than of storage, as objects of consumption. This new world was full of signs of the urban  	decommissioning project 	employed by the city, which aimed to make the city ‘a place of habitation rather than of production’. As a result, many of the buildings in the city were sold to for-profit developers, who converted them into condo towers or hotel blocks, or demolished them and left empty. As a result of this, a significant number of people lost their houses.  	Many of the displaced people started rebuilding their lives elsewhere in the city, in areas such as Brooklyn, Manhattan or Staten Island. But in the wake of such activity, there was a clear de-imagining of the city, a tendency toward a spatiality distinct from the places that were being reshaped. The Museum of Tractors was born. 	At the time, the Museum of Tractors was launched, in 1917, it housed the remains of twenty-one different species of tractors. It was a repository for the remains of over one hundred different types of building</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space�
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space� and incorporate elements of a ‘public realm’. The biennale became what it is today: a multimillion-dollar business, and the biennalee’s tourism board, the largest employer in the world, is the largest employer in the world. Art and cultural tourism account for almost 10 per cent of the global economy. The biennalee has the power to shape and generate new tourism revenue streams. It is a significant earner for the host country, has an impact on cultural consumption in the host country, and is a major source of investment for the host country’s tourism industry. It is also a fact of contemporary urban development in many countries. The biennalee has an impact on the city, but what is being generated outside the city, and in the surrounding countryside as well? The biennalee has this power, but what does it do? The biennalee has this power because it is a spectacle, and it</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space� to describe areas of public engagement, including creating public understandings of themselves as artists and others, and of course ‘public access to places and events that are ‘owned’ by the state. The project was to be a poetry in space, but the real poetry emerged from our understanding of the places we visited and from the things we said and did in the places we visited. The places we visited were often imagined as having historical or environmental significance, but there was a ‘glimmer of insight’ in them as sites of ‘assembly’ and ‘recipes’ for a future for the city. The first step in the project was in recognising the power of place. We began to look for the historical precedents for the kinds of social and political change we wanted to see, and also for the kinds of transformations we didn’t want to see. Then we started to ask questions about how the city was evolving, and in many ways,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space�, but also on the rhetoric of ‘innovation’ and incorporated elements of its own. It was a way to connect with those neighbourhoods, those cities, those regions where art is often represented in a fragmentary, transient or static way, with little or no thought given to its actualisation. The project began to investigate how art can operate to create public space, and how that can be combined with innovative urban planning and design. 	The political landscape of the 21st century is one in which big ideas are frequently over-hyped and under-delivered, and in which dispersed, mobile and ever-flexible actors are often quick to seize opportunities. The biennale has often been a staging ground for these effusive praise and quick fixes. The biennale has often been the arena where the artist is free to flex its muscles, to unleash its full potential, and to reap the rewards and burdens of a real cultural impact. But as important as it is to maintain</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space� to describe what’s public in a broader sense. The project members drew on the logic of Richard Florida’s Democracy and Individual Rights in order to offer an alternative vision of the public sphere. Publics are defined as ‘people whose rights have been made the property of the state’.[9] Freedom is defined as ‘the right to be heard, to participate, to be taken into consideration, and to be governed by those who are elected to public authority’.[10] Freedom of speech and thought is further defined as ‘the right to associate and to take part in public deliberation’.[11] Thus the political-ideological motivation for the project was to address not only the question of what is public, but also the question of how that might be defined. Freedom of association and public participation are further contextualised through the lens of the biennale. In the United Kingdom, the right to be heard – meaning able to participate in a</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space� to describe what art could and couldn’t be in the same way that the NHS, education, street life, food and children’s play were. For the biennale to be interesting, significant events had to happen in ‘public space’ and ‘public’ spaces in London were secondary to the creation of a new set of intermediaries: the development of policies to enable the biennale to happen, the creation of institutional memory, the creation of a ‘public plaza’ and the promotion of public engagement. The Biennale Project began to refer to a public board of trustees, who appointed members and controlled events. The biennale board members were chosen via a political process that sought candidates based on experience in community organizing and other public sphere-related professions and vocations. The biennale was initially conceived as a ‘promotion of the city’, with special attention given to areas with a high concentration of population density, such</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space�, but also on the curatorial rhetoric of urbanism and landscape architecture, but also on the urban critic Richard Florida’s work in order to frame our thinking. His book Curatorial Essays of the Past Five Years (2006) frames our thinking about the public realm through his account of the ‘perfumed garden of life’ that is produced by the biennale, but also through his account of the ‘perfumed garden of critique’ that is produced by the journal Vert magazine. Florida’s account is informed by his years as a curator, a position that involved creating relationships with stakeholders in the biennale through interviews and written work. His work in this regard is as nuanced as his curatorial approach is rigorous. Florida offers a critical survey of biennales from the past few decades, but the important point is that they are produced through the production of shared characteristics, whether those characteristics are biennials themselves, or the shared</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space�, but also on the language of ecology and urbanisation. The Biennale Project website reads: ‘The Biennale is a worldwide movement of art and community organising that began in 1988 with the publication of a journal called Artforum. A successor journal was published in 1991 under the title Placesthe Artforum. ‘The Biennale has been an integral part of the Artforum journal, and continues to be so today – a publication that has ‘strengthened’ itself through its publication in the journal every two years.‘[12]  The idea that the Biennale could be seen as a journal of the world it entered was a response to the institutionalised nature of the artforum and the artforum: the journals were first and foremost about the art of the contemporary art world, and the art of art as a developed discipline. The journals also frequently focused on the past in an episodic manner, with particular attention being paid to the</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space�, but also on the rhetoric of ecology and sustainability. The hope was to create a network of sites that connected to one another and to the city at large, while offering a counterweight to the economic build-up of urban space. The sites selected for the project were those that were likely to be visited by a human team, and by then having been visited by a human team too. The sites with the greatest number of visits were those with the highest number of created narratives. At the time, the idea that a biennial could be sustainable was novel, but the increasingly real-life encounters between biennials and their visitors has now become commonplace. The biennial experience may now be characterised by the visit and the encounter, but it is also increasingly characterised by the exchange and the viral spread of narratives. This is true not only of art and curatorial encounters, but of course includes the encounters of commerce and travel as well. Indeed, the biennial itself may be characterised by</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space�. Public was understood to include ‘private property’ and ‘public infrastructure’, including ‘public spaces’ and ‘public infrastructure’, but also ‘public resources’ and ‘public infrastructure’. The focus of the project was, in part, on ensuring that the urban fabric of the world would be laid out in such a way as to permit human agency and choice within its fabric. The city was to be rebuilt through a process of clear building and management, allowing for the emergence of new ways of living in and within it. The project was to be a response to the capitalist reconstruction of the city, but also to the city’s decline, having as its object the emergence of a new urban fabric capable of supporting a rising population.The Biennale Project has continued to evolve, evolving into a multi-million dollar business, incorporating research, development and gallery exhibitions into its core business. It opened its first art gallery in Lag</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, the curatorial performance. In the run up to the biennial, artists, activists and community organisers came together to create the Biennale Project in 2006. The project was a response to the domination of art and culture by an economic elite, and the subsequent impoverishment of millions around the world. It is understood that the biennale has a mission to serve the economy and that the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and other stakeholders who come to work with us on the ground, in and out of the country, are often drawn from those professions. To some this may seem redundant, to others it may be a way to understand how art can play a role in creating a future for the world through its representations. The question then becomes how to reach those people through art who may be engaged with creating a better future for themselves and others, but may also be engaged in creating worlds in their image?The project began to borrow heavily on the language of ‘public space�, but also on the language of ecology and urbanisation. The project was beginning to sound like a ‘public art institution’, albeit one with a distinctly capitalist flavour to it. The biennale became the prototype for future versions of the mega-exhibition, and later the ‘global urbanisation initiative’. It became critical to create an environment in which the artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and others with whom we collaborated could thrive, but also critical to set an example for the future generations who would commission us to undertake future projects. The project was beginning to look like a ‘house of ideas’, but also like a ‘house of painters and architects’. The artists, curators, arts administrators, writers and others working with us on the ground were often confronted with the challenge of finding a way to simultaneously host and commission a biennale while also continuing to produce and offer an exhibition platform to visitors. During the 2006–</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place. So there we have it: a set of shared characteristics, a set of shared characteristics that render the present a potentially interesting period in time, a possible location for future research, and perhaps a sense of place itself. These are the trade-offs of modernity versus biennials. We might start by asking what we might lose by turning away from the biennial and toward the museum or the archive. The biennial is an artifact of a particular moment in history. It is, in that sense, a historical document – a record of the past but also an invitation to the future. It is a powerful enabler of neoliberalism and the politics of nostalgia. And perhaps most importantly, it promotes social interaction between people from different times and places. Without the biennial, the present and future would not be possible to document. Modernity is a condition of access to information; you would not be able to document the past as you lived the present. The biennial has, in turn</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place. So a biennial can be seen to be a kind of cultural village, with a particular kind of resident alien. It is a re-occurring tourist trap, a place to be seen but not taken. It is not the real reason why tourists come to Biennials, nor is it the reason why biennials are popular. It is the last resort, and like all such last resort actions, has risks. But in the aggregate, the costs and benefits of this kind of action are clear and can be summarised: there are social, economic, and even political benefits to be had from it. And these benefits cannot be derived from borders alone. Biennials have to change, and will have to change, and they will have to change in order to maintain the social, political, and cultural balance that they claim to seek. But in the longer term, and especially in the cities that they control, it is they who will still control the biennial, and those who</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place. So while the biennial may have initially been conceived as a multi-year experiment, its current trajectory may also be considered an experiment. It is, however, clear that the biennial will continue to move at an unpredictable and sometimes unpredictable pace, and that the contemporary art market will almost certainly respond by positioning exhibits as a mode of cultural exchange around tourism, especially as a means to an end that is not necessarily the intended or even the desire of the artist or audience. So while the biennial may be a transient phenomenon, its cultural capital and its current place of absorbing attention will undoubtedly be there for long after the exhibitionary form is shaken up and new artists are drawn into the mix.Art’s ecological footprint is another area where the contemporary art market has a great deal of power. The biennial has the potential to become a permanent fixture in any city, although it would have to become significantly more diverse and powerful than it is now in order to compete. And while in many ways</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place, such as of a place in a city.4. The biennial condition. ‘Binomie’s law of large numbers.’5. Biennials, their collections and collections. For more, go to: http://www.biennalternatives.org/.6. Biennials themselves. For more, go to: http://www.biennials.com/.7. Biennials’ dependence on a particular city. See also my The City of London, 1988.Download this article as PDFJonathan CraryJon SnowJonathan Snow is a writer with a particular interest in the condition of London’s urban fabric. Drawing heavily on his experiences as an Arts &amp; Humanities student at the University of Liverpool, he has worked as an arts educationalist for the deaf-blind since the early 1980s, as a writer and educator, and most recently as an Associate Curator for the London and Wales Biennials. He is</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place, such as places of habit. This last quality is particularly notable in the work of lesser-known artists, and it is reflected in the growing number of biennials, which are now showing a wider range of artists and curators, as well as those who are new to the scene.Basically, biennials are exhibitions that happen to be organised around a curator’s curatorial style, his or her selection of material and techniques. And they are the object of our collective 'what if?'. Our current biennial, the Venice Biennale, is a classic case in point. Its twenty-one-day duration and one-hundred-plus-square-metre size (compared to the two-and-a-half-metre by four-and-a-half-storey biennale of the same Venice Biennale that we visited last September), make it a topical exhibition. Its thirty-one-day running time combined with its</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place and history.  The sense of place and history that biennials tend to engender is both alienated and nostalgic. The biennial visitor is drawn to the spectacle of empty cities and the spectacle of bureaucracies, but also to the spectacle of art being produced in places where the arts have never been heard of before. ‘The Beehive’ is a classic example of something that is produced in a city without ever having been heard of. It is produced not by artists, but by the city. And although biennials may have initially appeared to be a valuable source of income for southern cities, the biennial as an end point has increasingly become problematic for this reason. Once the spectacle is in your head, it is difficult to disengage from it. The art produced by the biennial is often specifically designed to appeal to our highest ideals of the civic – patriotism, community, pride – but the biennial is becoming increasingly evident that the main function of art institutions in this country</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place. As a result, the biennial has had to work harder, to some extent, to find its place in the contemporary cultural landscape. This may be part of the point. For museums and galleries in the south, and in particular for those in the City, this has meant finding a way to incorporate the biennial in their curatorial work in order to make it relevant to the city, while simultaneously lending a sense of place to the work, while also recognising the unique and creative value of the individual work. For biennials in the city, and particularly for those in the southern part of the city, this meant finding ways to make their episodes culturally responsive to the rest of the city, while also making them places where art can take root and prosper.This last element, place, seems especially crucial for the biennial to achieve its promised rank as a cultural phenomenon. It is easy to romanticise the humble square and its humble beginnings – the humble market, the humble artist, the</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place. I suggest that we might also consider the fact that museums and galleries are, increasingly, places where contemporary art is produced on a large scale, and that this is a paradoxical (for artists) but increasingly true (for people): contemporary art is being made where ever there is a market for art. Politics and the biennial as marketplace for art are intricately interwoven here, and we do not yet know what the market for art is in the future. But we do know that the biennial – being a temporal phenomenon – has to find a way of organising itself in the present, and that it is also increasingly common for biennials to become places of exchange and, indeed, destinations of circulation. As a result, their contemporary character is likely to be a place of exchange, not only in its consumption habits but also in the future. This is why biennials are now so important in their consumption habits: they are the ultimate exchange between the past and the future, and</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place and identity.  	Art and biennials are entwined in this country 	because they are two sides of the same coin, with museums and galleries serving as a third. But they are also entwined in this country because they are two sides of the same coin, with museums and galleries responding to the concerns of the city and biennials responding to the concerns of the nation. Therefore their stated purpose ‘to capture the essence and spirit of the place, period’ is often confused with its other, more obvious but equally important purpose of capturing images that stand for the place in perpetuity. Contemporary art and biennials are often tempted to aekpakk or bury their heads in the sand and take their places in the history books as some sort of modern incarnation of an Ostrich. But the biennial is no more likely to declaw its head of stone as an ostrich than the museum is likely to aekpakk itself. It seems</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials and their place in the larger contemporary cultural landscape. Whether by accident or design, the biennial has emerged with a set of shared characteristics, which have in turn, sometimes been subject to the agenda of political, economic, and social change. Some have been so thoroughly seduced by modern cultural consumption that they have lost reference to their original purpose or even identity. This is partly the fault of museums and galleries of all kinds – especially those in southern cities where people still live on the cobblestone street level – which are now more commonly associated with museums and galleries, rather than with the history and traditions of the city. But it is also the work of artists who, being artists first and foremost, are inclined to produce works that are both timeless and new, rather than works that stand for anything particular. They are less likely to produce works that are international or recent or reflect on current events. And they are more likely to produce works that are self-contained and contain within them a sense of place. As biennials become more institutionalised, the forms of contemporaneity and contemporaneity-specificity that characterise biennials are most readily encountered in cultural studies, especially in those disciplines that deal with the contemporary condition. Cultural studies is particularly likely to encounter biennials as a mode of contemporaneity-specificity, since the biennial is the single most widely-used measure of contemporary art’s impact on cultural practices. In fact, biennials are so commonly cited as a measure of impact, that the very word ‘biennial’ is used in the same sentence as a synonym for ‘cinema’, almost exclusively in the US and Canada.1 And this is not just a US or Canada thing. As biennials proliferate all over the world, so do their numbers, often surviving the very first exhibition in new cities. As the number of such biennials rapidly outnumber the number of museums,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and
    <text>archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and Los Angeles – have come to dominate the ‘little four’ of the biennial, with the exception of an occasional special London–based biennial. The ‘little biennial’ is often mentioned as the audience for the ‘big biennial’, but this is misleading. The audience for the ‘little biennial’ is often mentioned as the ‘little biennial audience’, but this is misleading as well. As biennials everywhere become more institutionalised, more institutionalised, and more global in their structure, the audience for the ‘little biennial’ is likely to grow smaller. This is especially true in cities with large diasporas or subcultures, as more and more biennials are oriented around the same cities, often catering to these very subcultures. This has happened in other forms of art form: in the form of a ‘curatorial studio’ or a ‘curatorial village</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and Melbourne – can be seen as the advent of a new form of ‘biennialism’. The ‘biennial’ is sometimes translated as ‘episodic’ or ‘follow-on’ from here, but since it is a concept that is pre-accelerating, it is often translated as ‘following the episodic’. I prefer the more precise, but still freighted, term ‘biennialism’.The first instance of ‘biennialism’ I cite is John Berger’s classic 1929 essay ‘The Biennial Industry: Crisis of Character’, in which he draws our ideas of contemporaneity and contemporaneity itself out of the biennial’s various strands and corollaries. He begins by noting how the biennial has its own distinctive set of distinctive features. Its fixation on the production and consumption of culture as a commodity has created a condition of perpetual</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and Berlin – have come to dominate what is arguably a low-status position in the art world: museums, galleries, archives and even community art venues. In the 1980s and 1990s, the biennial entered into a kind of symbiosis with the community hub, its curatorial language drawing on the history of community art in the UK, and the resurgent influence of its then leader, Peter Brook. The biennial began publishing its accounts of the years it held in its vaults, and publishing them in full, with accompanying photography, in 1994. It is an important historical document that documents the genesis of Community Arts in the UK, and the genesis of community art in the world. It is also a kind of a ‘double bind’: it is both a document of the past, describing the curatorial decisions that produced the art, but also a document of the decisions that produced the history of the community that came out of it. The biennial is a kind of historical essays</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and Melbourne – came to dominate what is arguably, now, the most globally visible exhibitionary sector of the global exhibitionary complex. (Perhaps we could say that Melbourne began as an early and perhaps even a marginal expression of the ‘biennialisation’ of the city.) There is a curious though significant absence of biennials in the 1980s and 1990s, and their absence is a bit disconcerting. Perhaps the absence of interest in, or even awareness of, the arts in cities is in part a function of the biennial. In a general sense, the biennial is a ‘storehouse’ of cultural products, a locus of distribution and dissemination that combines physical and online materialities in a continuous and ever-expanding range of products and services. The ‘biennialisation’ of the city is a global process, and city[22] is a variable materiality with a number of possible locations and configurations. In this changing global materiality,</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and Moscow – can be seen to be responding to the fundamentally different needs of the different local artworlds. The Russian entry into the League of Nations marked a return to pre-war Russian imperial forms, while the entry of the United States delegation marks the first time that a representative delegation of the multinational artworld has been lodged in Moscow. But these are hardly the defining characteristics of what a ‘biennial’ actually is. A biennial is an event that is, at the same time a site of constant change and rotation, a permanent installation, a museum, a market place, and finally, a settlement for permanent residents (of any nation) – people who have come to live and work among us. It is the idealised image of the idealised temporality of the modern world. It is the home of the intrepid explorer, brave warrior and mythic hero. It is the idealised image of the artistically-inclined native born again Christian (biennial)</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and Berlin – have come to dominate what may be described as the vernacular festival, while others, including cities such as Liverpool and Bangalore, have come to be characterised by the ‘biennial boom’. But the important point is that these ‘biennials’ operate on a world register, and the ideas and practices of the world as a ‘part of a larger system’, with London and New York marking the boundary between this world and the other. I will return to this in a moment.In any case, the ‘biennial’ is a materialised form of historical ephemerality, and so its use today is no accident, but prescient. The historical contingency that occurred when biennials first came to exist was that they were materialised through the taking and hiding of time, and so there is a continuity to their legal definition today. The legal determination is that they are exhibitions of cultural resources, and so in a sense the</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and Rome – have arrived at this point. Each of these centres has its own distinctive set of biennials, its own distinctive look. But what is often missing from these biennials is the sense of community that characterises other curatorial practices. For example, many biennials, unlike their ‘archival’ counterparts, do not include a chronological register of artworks in their curatorial legacies. Art dealers and collectors know when a piece of artwork is new, and appreciate its significance in that order. But few other curatorial practices combine that level of visibility and that level of consequence. I believe that what biennials offer is the promise of a new curatorial language: one that is less tied to established curatorial paradigms and more open to the imaginations of artists, the public, collectors and the curatorial elite. I would argue in favour of what Naomi Klein calls ‘the public gallery’, one that is not just a ‘market�</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and Melbourne – could be seen to be responding to a curatorial tool that is not firmly rooted in the city. This is partly because these cities are geographically vast, and partly because these ‘biennials’ are in many ways artefacts of the past, artifacts of the contemporaneous world, with its own politics and conflicts. But it must be noted that Melbourne, Paris and London all have their own biennials, their own versions of the biennial that developed in their cities during the decade leading up to 1914. London’s is contemporary, while Melbourne and Paris have their own are monuments of modernism. ‘Modern’ is not synonymous with ‘in the modern’, nor is it a synonym for ‘out of the modern’. The contemporary is an era of enormous changes, and the biennial is a seemingly simple temporal device that allows us to observe these in a perfunctory way. But its use as a curatorial tool is</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and Berlin – can be seen as interlinking into a single ‘biennale’ that is perceived as an extension of the city (and thus, a kind of urban synchronicity). In the twentieth century, the ‘biennial’ was a term that referred to collections of artworks in museums, and in the twenty-first century it is a term that refers to collections of curatorial works, institutions and artefacts. It is true that in recent decades the term has been more commonly used to describe collections of curatorial and art-historical works, as in the case of the Venice Biennale and its many editions, the Whitney Biennial, and the Chicago Architecture Biennial. But the main reason for this usage is that, since the nineteen-nineties, the biennial has been a multi-million pound a year business, and the biennial has become the major art collector’s endowment, and therefore a target for corporate raider</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials in a similar way to how the biennial was conceptualised in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries. The term was used to describe a kind of nested registry of art institutions, both domestic and international, which offered a virtual wall between artist and viewer.[20]The institutionalised use of the biennial as a curatorial tool was a latecomer, and marks the first instance of what may be termed ‘biennale creep’. It is interesting that Francis Galton, one of the inventors of the biennial, put this concept to one side in the early twentieth century. In the early 1920s and 1930s, it was emphasised as a way to promote national glory, a phenomenon that would later be characterised by the US entry into the League of Nations.[21]I use the term ‘biennial’ loosely, since it is easy to understand how the ‘big four’ of the biennial – London, New York, Paris and Liverpool – can be seen to constitute a single ‘biennialisceao’. In this sense, all biennials move towards the ‘biennialisceao’, which is the union of the biennials, and so the biennial becomes something that is recognisable not only by its members, but also by the public at large. As a concept, it is an essential part of the biennial, and so one of its forms is incorporated into the organization of the museum. In this sense, the biennial is a recognized division of labour within the museum, a sort of hybrid workforce that is both art collector and art administrator. It is worthwhile recalling that Peter Brook, who invented the biennial, saw the biennial as a hybrid between a gallery and a museum that would capture the essence of the biennial while simultaneously meeting the demands of a public that is sensitive to historical misrepresentation. Brook’s biennial would be the first in London,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema,
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 3. [6] New Yorker, New York (1921), p. 6. [7] Karen Bowden, The Art Newspaper, 1949, p. 1. [8] Richard Layard, New York Review of Books, December, Issue 3, 1949, p. 50. [9] Curtis Watson, ‘The Art Newspaper: A Journal of Art and Anti-Art’, in The New Yorker, January 16, 1954, p. 6. [10] J.D. Dewsbury, ‘Art and Anti-Art: The Origins of Our Crisis’, in Society and Culture, Vol. 20, No. 2 (May, 1984), p. 4. [11] J.D. Dewsbury, ‘Art and Anti-Art: Twenty-First Century Pains’, in The New Yorker</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [6] New York Times, 14 October 2008, http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/14/us/politics/the-cliff-edge-and-the-two-fronts.html, accessed 10 November 2013. [7] New York Times, 13 October 2008, http://www.nytimes.com/2008/10/14/us/politics/the-cliff-edge-and-the-two-fronts.html, accessed 10 November 2013. [8] New York Times, 13 October 2008, http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/14/us/politics/the-cliff-edge.html, accessed 10 November 2013. [9] New York Times, 13 October 2008, http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/14/us/politics</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [6] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [7] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [8] Katharine Hepworth, New York Review of Books, March, Issue 3, p. 1. [9] Karin O’Neill, ‘The Art Newspaper’, The New York Review of Books, March, Issue 3, p. 1. [10] Katharine Hepworth, ‘The Art Newspaper’, The New York Review of Books, March, Issue 3, p. 1. [11] Karin O’Neill, ‘The Art Newspaper’, The New York Review of Books, March, Issue 3, p. 1.</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [6] Svetlana Boym, ‘On Writing and Unwriting Media Art’, The New Yorker, October 12, 2006, pp. 39–43. [7] Rodney Harrison, ‘Unfixing the City: Art, Architecture, and Gentrification in New York’, New Left Review, Issue 6 (Winter 2004), p. 42. [8] Juan Carlos Ulán, ed., The Architecture of the City: Urban Studies, Geography, and Art (New York: Zone Books, 2013), p. 1. [9] William Burchell, ed., The Political Economy of Art and Culture in an Urban Setting (Cambridge, Massachusetts and London, England: Polity, 2015), p. 1. [10] Burchell, op. cit., p. 2. [11] Burchell, op</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [6] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [7] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [8] New York Times, New York (17 September 2007), p. A1. [9] New York Times, New York (17 September 2007), p. 1. [10] New York Times, New York (17 September 2007), p. 1. [11] New York Times, New York (17 September 2007), p. 1. [12] New York Times, New York (17 September 2007), p. 1. [13] New York Times, New York (17 September 2007), p. 1. [14] New York Times, New York (17 September 2007</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 2. [6] Svetlana Boym, ‘Wind on a Wheatfield: Urban Turn-Up Musings’, in, New York Times, 13 November 2008, http://www.nytimes.com/2008/11/14/arts/wind-on-wheatfields.html, accessed 4 June 2015. [7] Curtis Ioannidis, ‘10,000 Year Explosion: 10,000 BC to the Big Bang’, in, Nature, 526, December 2007, p. 1403, accessed 4 June 2015. [8] Wikipedia, ‘Greening of the Cities’, accessed 4 June 2015. [9] National Geographic, ‘10,000 Year Explosion: The Hidden Cities that Matter’, 11 November 2006, http://www.ngc.com/nature/10,000-</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 2. [6] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 2. [7] Sarah Lowdnes, ‘The Big Issue: Art, Race and Rebirth in America’, The New Yorker, 28 June 2006, p. 46. [8] Nadine Attewell, ‘Race, Politics, and Arts Resembling Life: An Anarchist History of Art’, The New Yorker, 20 July/August 1999, p. 46. [9] Attewell, ‘Race, Politics and Arts Resembling Life’, p. 46. [10] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [11] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 2. [6] Svetlana Boym, ‘On the use of color in the creation of ambience’, Lighting Research Letters, Vol. 36, No. 1, January, 2006, p.1. [7] Eddie Huang and Peter Weibel, ‘On the use of color in the creation of ambience’, Lighting Research Letters, Vol. 36, No. 1, January, 2006, p.1. [8] Richard Florida, ‘On the use of color in the creation of ambience’, Lighting Research Letters, Vol. 36, No. 1, January, 2006, p.1. [9] Florida, op. cit., p.1. [10] Taylor Branch, ‘On the use of color in the creation of ambience’, Lighting Research Letters, Vol. 36</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 4. [6] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [7] David Harvey, The Empire of the Imagined City: New York and its Appearances  (Princeton: Princeton University Press, 2009), p. 42. [8] Lloyd Cheung, ‘Unfixing America’, in New York Times, 9/8/08, p. A1. [9] Thomas Waugh, ‘The Empire of the Spotless Mind’, in New York Times, 9/8/08, p. 1. [10] New York Times, 9/8/08, p. 1. [11] Thomas Waugh, ‘Unfixing America’, in New York Times, 9/8/08, p. 2.</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for the exhibition’s production, but it is not clear that this is possible in a city with as large a cultural footprint as New York.  [1] The idea of a ‘better yet…’ is apropos here because the actuality of the city is frequently misrepresented or ignored, or worse, invented.  [2] For more on the role of artists in producing their city, see Nikos Papastergiadis and Timothy S. McVerry, eds., The New Curator: Art as Social Practice, Centre for Artist Research and Documentation (Durham: Duke University Press, 2007), p. 25. [3] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [4] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [5] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [6] Kiran Cheema, New York: The Art Newspaper, Issue 4 (June 2007), p. 1. [7] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, first published in 1605, Henry VI, Henry VI, Part 1, Chapter 9, Line 3, Quarters, Penguin Classics, 1985, p. 517. [8] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, first published in 1605, Henry VI, Henry VI, Part 1, Chapter 9, Line 3, Quarters, Penguin Classics, 1985, p. 517. [9] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, first published in 1605, Henry VI, Henry VI, Line 3, Penguin Classics, 1985, p. 517. [10] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, first published in 1605, Henry VI, Henry VI, Line 3, Penguin Classics, 1985</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian.
    <text>might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian. I have a very particular way of speaking that needs to be heard. I don’t want to upset anyone. I’m not going to jail. I’m not going to school. I’m not going to be a school teacher. I’m not going to be an artist. I don’t need the money. I’m not going to be rich. I’m not going to be famous. I’m not going to be a music producer. I don’t need no wedding planner. So how do we as artists and musicians create a space for dialogue and discussion?The answer was found in a magnetic glass box. A magnet was invented to hold things in place. The name Magnet describes the second part of the molecule, the part that connects the protons and the neutrons. It’s the part that creates the force of magnetism</text>
    <text>might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian. I have a long standing interest in the D.I.Y. generation. They are the generation who get arts education and are socialised through art. I adapted the D.I.Y. idea of the community artist, who was previously a dancer, to the theatre artist. So the two artists would be equally at home in a community arts venue.The community arts venue model is nowhere near being taken seriously, but the concerns of the community artist are valid and relevant. Drumac is a community arts venue, and as such it falls under the community arts umbrella. Community artists who use dance, performance, community gardens, or just about anything else to engage with the world around them can be expected to eventually find a home somewhere else. The question is, where will that be? Well, I don’t know. Maybe a community arts venue could be established in Drumac, although I don’t think we’</text>
    <text>might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian. I used to do radio and TV stand-up. I used to be a writer. I used to be a recording engineer. I used to be a singer. I used to be a songwriter. I used to be a publisher. I used to be a systems designer.I used to run a hardware store. I used to be a carpenter. I used to be a computer programmer. I used to be a teacher. I used to be a hairdresser. I used to be a retail associate. I used to be a baker. I used to be a publisher. I used to be a computer operator. I used to be a hair stylist. I used to be a pharmacy assistant. I used to be a nursery nurse.I used to run a jewish-owned jewish centre in Tottenham. I used to run a day nursery run by a Jewish couple. I used to</text>
    <text>might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian. I used to be a singer. I used to do fine arts work. I used to do community work. I used to do school trips. I used to do community activities. I used to do community events. I used to do school trips. The list goes on. There was no hierarchy or anything like that. We were just people – like everyone else. Sometimes I did things for our group, sometimes the rest of the group. It was just fun, playing it by ear. Drumac would never have happened without the Curtains and the Bathroom Revolution, and without the Open School of Art. Without the Open School of Art, Drumac might not be where we are today. But we would still be in the arts organisation we are in now, because we would still be able to do what we wanted with the group, and we would still be able to access funding. Without the Curtains and</text>
    <text>might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian. I wouldn’t go to war over a gig. But I’m from the 80s. I know how it feels now. I know how it was all made. I’m not trying to be a nostalgia hound, but the fact that we are now forty years later, and there has been no further impact on the arts in this area doesn’t feel the same. I’m sure you remember the 90s. The turn of events in Drumac in 2003. You still remember the feeling of being able to go to a show without being bombarded with messages telling you how much you were going to like it.Remembering of the Troubles (2004) is a very moving piece of art. You can feel the pain and the anger of the people involved. You can feel their confusion. You can feel the fear and the hopelessness. You can feel the music. It’s just a few people in a room with a</text>
    <text>might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian. I used to be able to take sides. I used to be able to be funny. I used to be able to cut costs. I used to be a gym rat. I used to be a pizza delivery boy. I used to be a hairdresser. I used to be a pension scheme counsellor. I used to be a drugs addict. And I used to be a prostitute.I used to be a photographer. I used to be a dancer. I used to be a hairdresser. I used to be a hairdresser. I used to be a hairdresser. I used to be a hairdresser. I used to be a hairdresser. I used to be a hairdresser. I used to be a hairdresser. I used to be a hairdresser. I used to be a hairdresser.I used to run the Bluecoat</text>
    <text>might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian. I started off doing gigs, doing stand up comedy, making music and anything that would entertain people. Then, one night, a very nice young lady in a burka came to the Docker Theatre, and she said she wanted to become an artist. She had never worked with a client before, and she was nervous. She didn’t know what she wanted to do with her life, and she didn’t know what her future held. I thought, ‘You need to find out what you want to do with your life. Don’t tell her what to do.’ She didn’t know what she wanted to do, and I still think that night, that she is still learning. She may have been on the fence, and she may have gone through phases where she didn’t know what she wanted to do. But Iambridge always say something to the effect of ‘Don’t be afraid to fail.</text>
    <text>might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian. I used to do very successful comedic work. I used to produce very successful beach music. But I used to be a comedian. I used to be a painter. I used to be a queen. I used to be a hair dresser. I used to be a lady. I used to be a yoga teacher. I used to be a snowdrop. I used to be a tea-party. I used to be a muralist. I used to be a hippie. I used to be a pioneer. I used to be a lady. I used to be a skydiver. I used to be a lady in drag. I used to be a charity worker. I used to be a lorry driver. I used to be a languagemonger. I used to be a lady in drag. I used to be</text>
    <text>might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian. I also used to be a schoolteacher. In between, I worked in the Community Arts organisation called Bluecoat Education Trust. We had a very hands-on approach to education, providing resources and support to anyone interested in becoming involved. We also ran a series of literacy and arts workshops through the trust, using a local language that was easy to understand.And then we had political conversations about the way we wanted to see our community organised, how we wanted to perceive ourselves in relation to each other. I don’t think we did it on a grand scale, but we certainly didn’t think it up. I still think that would have been a difficult work for any community organisation to pull off. Even the Liverpool Biennial, which is centred around art rather than politics, could pull off an administration of a city. In the years that followed we probably had more conversations about how we wanted to be seen as artists than we did about what our organisation was.</text>
    <text>might be curated by, for example, the arts organisation the Open School of Art). I wanted to do something different. I wanted to offer a space for discussion and debate. And I also wanted to work with artists who were not from my locality, or from outside my area. This may seem trivial, but it was affecting my work. I was uncomfortable with the idea of an artist from outside my area being able to come and create a work based on what I had created, based on what I thought was valid. It felt as if this was an imposition.I asked my artist friends to join me in Drumac. We created a circle around the Drumac theatre, in order to discuss and create a work around. Ideas were presented in a low key and informal way. There was no might or might not be an agenda. I felt that we came out on the other side without having done anything wrong.I used to run the Bluecoat, and I used to be a comedian. I used to write for the Bluecoat. I wrote for the Daily Graphic. I did a couple of radio shows. I did books. I did tours. I did commercials. I was a commercial artist. And I was into charity work too. I did a charity concert every now and then, and I did a charity bike ride up to Drumac once a month. It was all charity work, but it was also time to communicate ideas and opinions. It was a mixture of things I had created or was creating with my artistic tools, and was a symbol of the city at that time.There was a massive revolution in the way people perceived city living, and the individual and collective empowerment that came with it. People no longer viewed cities as static representations of their envisioned destinations, but viewed them as creative possibilities generated by a multiplicity of agency within the city. This was a transformational moment for a city, but it was also a</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or co-curator of the forthcoming edition: Álbio Nascimento, Curator for Entryways, Museum of Modern Art, New York; Joasia Krysa, Curator for Public Programmes, L’agence à Paris, Paris; Joasia Krysa, Curator for Public Programmes, L’agence à Paris, Paris; Paola Marrati, Curator for Entryways, Museum of Modern Art, New York; Paola Marrone, Curator for Public Programmes, L’agence à Paris, Paris; Sandeep Parmar, Curator for Entryways, Museum of Modern Art, New York; Paola Marrati, Curator for Entryways, Museum of Modern Art, New York; Robin Mackay, Curator for Entryways, Museum of Modern Art, New York; Paola Marrati, Curator for Entryways, Museum of Modern Art, New York; Robin Mackay,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or co-curator of the forthcoming edition, and some of the curatorial approaches taken by the artists who have been selected for future editions.Artists Selected for Future Curator Invited to Curate the Exhibitionist Brutus, James Howard Kunsthal &amp; Co., 2012. Installation, Liverpool Biennial 2012. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial.PreviousNextArtists Selected for Future Curator Invited to Curate the Exhibitionist Brutus, James Howard Kunsthal &amp; Co., 2012. Installation, Liverpool Biennial 2012. Photo courtesy of Liverpool Biennial.The following artists were selected for a future curatorial invitation:Ameena Atiq (curator of the 2002 Venice Biennale and the 2008 Tate Modern Treasures of Art)Sofia Stauni (architectural historian, World War Z, author of The Urban Crisis)Michelle de Groot (architectural historian, University of Toronto)Sofia Cortez (architectural historian, Liverpool Bi</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or co-curator of the forthcoming edition:Brent Bellamy (Director, Tate Gallery, London and Curator of Europe and North America, Tate) Leonard Bernstein (Director, National Gallery of Canada, Ottawa and Principal, Museum of Modern Art, Washington, D.C.) Rick Lowe (Founder, Museums Association) Tom Calderbank (Principal, Royal Standard, London) Peter Carr (Architecture, Matterhouse) Mark Loudon (Director, Tate Gallery)Angela Hagewood (Director, Royal Standard)Tom Stoppard (Director, Tate Gallery)Alexei Ulanov (Director, Museums Association)Christiane Paul (Director, Museums Association)Emily Pringle (Director, Royal Standard)Angela Hagewood (Director, Royal Standard)Shankley Bonner (Director, Royal Standard)Sophia Olascoaga (Director, </text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or co-curator of the forthcoming edition:Françoise Boym: Curator, Ovid Prize, 2012.Taken from Ovid Prize, 2012, page 269. Wendy Chun: Curator, The Whitney Museum of American Art, 2012.Taken from The Whitney Museum of American Art, 2012, page 267.Sophie Hope Simmonds: Curator, M. F. Willems, 2012.Taken from M. F. Willems, 2012, page 312.Jussi Parikka: Curator, M. F. Willems, 2012.Taken from M. F. Willems, 2012, page 314.Judith Stewart: Curator, Ovid Prize, 2012.Taken from Ovid Prize, 2012, page 269.Allan Jones: Curator, M. F. Willems, 2012.Taken from M. F. Willems,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or co-curator of the forthcoming edition of the Biennial, or have collaborative projects in the works. It is intended to serve as a register of curatorial shifts and creative interventions, and to allow for the meaningful representation of an artist’s actual contribution to the biennial by way of a single artist’s curatorial intervention. [1] See: http://www.genoways.org/bbci/index.html?fuseaction=DefaultDomain_Test_Domain&amp;term=GenuineArtistsList&amp;tabs=1#2.[2] See: http://www.genoways.org/bbci/index.html?fuseaction=DefaultDomain_Test_Domain&amp;term=GenuineArtistsList&amp;tabs=1#3.[3] See: http://www.genoways.org/bbci/index.html?fuseaction=DefaultDomain_Test_Domain&amp;term=Genuine</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or co-curator of the forthcoming edition, arranged chronologically from the first Biennial exhibition in Berlin (2014) to the day before its US-based exhibition (November 2017). The chronology is constructed not from interviews or databases, but from accounts from the artists, curators, journalists and others with whom the Biennial has worked over the years. 	[1] Interview with Bruno Latour, Biennale Producer, with Joasia Krysa, Berlin, 2013. 2. Interview with Bruno Latour, Biennale (Paris), 2014. 3. Interview with Sello Peso, Director of Venice Biennale, 2016. 4. Interview with Arsen Avramov, Curator of Public Experiences, Seattle, 1989. 5. Interview with Gigi Scaria, Curator of Public Experiences, New York, 1991. 6. Interview with Leonard David, Curator of Public Experiences, New York,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or co-curator of the forthcoming edition:Susanne Koch, Director of the Kunsthal Aarhus, Denmark; Robin Mackay, Curator of Public Programmes at Tate Liverpool, England; Suzanne Hudson, Curator of Public Art at Tate Liverpool, England; Joasia Krysa, Curator of Public Art at Tate Liverpool, England; Jennifer Chapman, Curator of Public Programmes at Tate Liverpool, England; Joasia Krysa &amp; Christine Whittaker, Curators at Tate Liverpool, England; Anne Kølbjerde, Curator of Public Programmes at Tate Liverpool, England; Susanne Kübler-Lande, Artist and Co-Director of Tate Liverpool, UK; Anne Kølbjerde, Curator of Public Programmes at Tate Liverpool, UK; Joasia Krysa, Artist and Co-Director of Tate Liverpool, UK; Christine Whittaker, Artist and Co-Director of Tate Liverpool, UK; Sarah Vaughan, Curator of</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or co-curator of the forthcoming edition of the Biennial, as well as some of the curatorial roles they held during the Biennial’s production:Søren Atack (Director and Co-founder of the Biennial)François Bidard (Architecture),Jacques Rancière (Production Designer),Christin Malamund (Production Designer),Eddie Leonor (Production Designer),Sophia Olascoaga (Artistic Director),Charlotte Tilbury (Artistic Director),Angie Chick (Artistic Director),Claire Bishop-Boyd (Artistic Director),Angela Coyle (Design),Brianna Colvin-Parry (Production Designer),Mehmet Baris Kuymulu (Production Designer),Ingmar Hagemez (Director),Tina Fey (Annie at the Movies),Louis Grier (Producer),Jonathan Bell (Artistic Director),Patricia Waldron (Artistic Director),</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or co-curator of the forthcoming edition:Anna Elizabeth Schmitz, Exhibition Research Lab (CA), The Museum of Modern Art, New York, 2012-2015.PreviousNextAnna Elizabeth Schmitz, Exhibition Research Lab (CA), The Museum of Modern Art, New York, 2012-2015.PreviousNextVanessa Boni, ARRIV: Curatorial Theatre, Argentina, 2015. Installation, Mt. Shasta Art Gallery, USA. Photo: Mark Waugh.  [1] A rendering of the Biennial as it appeared in the book A Cultural Evolution of the World (2005), by David Himmelman, based on a talk given at the University of California, Los Angeles, in cooperation with the L.A. Biennial, and the UCLA/Tulane Biennial, and the US National Museum of the American Indian. [2] The Biennial was originally conceived as a curatorial exercise, using the curatorial</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial in the modernist tradition, and puts it into a more contemporary context. The exhibition is a set of related works, each a concept or object in its own right. But it is the work of a single group of artists, and their work represents the very essence of what it means to be an artist in the 21st century. As the curators note, however, &quot;the ultimate aim of the Biennial is to produce a visual language that responds to the present through re-construal, and in doing so to engage with the ambiguities and processes involved in the social formation of knowledge as a whole, and thereby to produce a more expansive discourse on contemporary culture’s ever-expanding repertoire of imagery, symbols, customs and practices.&quot;[7]The Biennial’s current and former curators, and those involved in the production of the forthcoming edition, offer a window onto this larger dynamic. The following list represents some of the artists who have been either curator or co-curator of the forthcoming edition of the Biennial:Anna Callas, Curator for Entryways at Tate Britain, 2016. Islam Mikhael, Curator for Entryways at Tate Britain, 2016. Tobias Oberhauser, Curator for Entryways at Tate Britain, 2016. Tania Bruguera, Curator for Entryways at Tate Britain, 2016.Dirk Baas, Curator at Tate Britain, 2016.Logan Sisley, Curator for Entryways at Tate Britain, 2016.Sebastian Schell, Curator of Public Practice at Tate Britain, 2016.Christiane Paul, Curator at Tate Britain, 2016.Paola Marrati, Curator for Entryways at Tate Britain, 2016.Sebastian Coel, Curator at Tate Britain, 2016.Peter Schjeldahl, Curator at Tate Britain, 2016.Myriam Coquerel, Curator</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as
    <text>archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as fossils of human cultural evolution. [Full article] [2] Karpathé Tweda, ‘On the use of ethnographic materials in contemporary archaeological and historical investigations’, in Anthropology: A Journal of Cultural Studies, 13 (2009), p.1–18. [3] Jane Austen, Pride and Prejudice, Pride and Prejudice Books, 1871, p.1. [4] Jane Austen, Pride and Prejudice, Pride and Prejudice Books, 1871, p.1. [5] M. Safra Kemal Atangana and I. Divya Goel, ‘Phantom Cities: Nineteenth-Century Istanbul’, in Studies in Globalization, Globalization and Cities vol. 4, rev. ed. Valentina Matviyenko and Timur Gürsel, pp.281–99, Toronto, Canada, 1994, p.289. [6] Jane Jacobs, The</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as fossilised human remains. If the turn of the century is a ‘giant leap’ in terms of the expansion of human language, the emergence of print culture, the acceleration of scientific and technological research, then the twenty-first century is a critical turning in terms of the spread of the human species. The biennial has, in other words, become more than the sum of its art and its subjects; it is a constitutive element of the ‘big picture’. Art and cultural activity in and across the biennial has a significant epistemic character, and this character is closely tied to the nature of the biennial itself. As biennials become more and more autonomous, and more and more like other art forms, they cease to be. This is perhaps one reason why biennials, in their current form, can be counted on to exhibit significant art and cultural activity outside of their local cultural zones. If they fail to do so, or show less than they</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as fossils. In the case of the human herd, the collection includes the individual species represented – humans – while the collection of non-human animals is referred to as the ‘evolutionary history of the collection’. It is not always clear what the precise terms of reference of an art biennial are – for example, the definition of a biennial as a curatorial commissioning institution in the United States is rarely specified – but it is clear that biennials have often been seen as spaces for the curatorial, especially in the wake of artistic and curatorial interventions. As biennials expand and contract in space, they are regularly visited by artists, curators, art historians and art’s many publics: urban, rural, urban, rural, urban, pastoral, urban, rural, coastal, nature, history, crowds, nature, and the ‘holidays’. [2] See Richard Brookman, Steven L. Tanimoto, Geoff Cox</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as fossils of human social life. The ecological and anthropological elements are all counted in the collection, but the social dimension is ignored. Instead, the focus is on the human element: how we constitute and manage social worlds of our own making.[2] The idea that the collection should be organised in such a way as to capture and carry forward all the traces of the biennial is an appealing one, bringing to mind the words of John Lennon, who sang, ‘Can’t fix you, mummy’, as he held up a photograph of John Lennon and Paul McCartney at a time when they were completing their 50th Anniversary concert in London: ‘That was fifty years ago, Kay, and while I was alive, John Lennon and Paul McCartney would never write a song like that again’.[3] The collection thus circulates, replicates, and is constantly on the point of changing hands – between those who use it to look at art, and other uses,</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as fossils. The collection includes objects from all over the world, but especially from the biennale itself, which is based in London. The collection is a record of the human condition, and the exhibition’s status as such. It records not only the exhibits, but also the context in which they take place, the people who are in them and the meaning of presence and identity in relation to time. The collection is a complex and shifting whole, and its precise location remains a point of contention. Some biennials, such as Venice, are growing in their collections, while others, such as those in other cities, are becoming increasingly difficult to categorise into one of two categories: exhibits of the present but containing history but also artefacts of the past, or the physical remains of the present but stuffed with electronic data. The choice of term, coupled with the actuality of the collection, remains unresolved. I use the term ‘microform’ to refer to the collection in</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as fossils of a human culture that died out some 469,000 years ago. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans, along with the data they produce, are counted in microform. [John H. McWhorter’s microform is a journal of ideas published monthly ( ARW) of the English-language online version of The Anthropologist, with an index and a commentary on the topology of ideas.][2] The collection of objects in the collection – which includes objects from every possible branch of science, from geology to biology to urban and regional planning – is organized as follows:

Table 1: List of microform objects from Hayward Collection, The Anthropologist, 1976. Photograph courtesy of The Hayward Collection.  [3] The Hayward Collection. Retrieved August 2016 from http://www.aph.org/Archives/200711081456.html#EnteredTextSelectedIndexEntries[]Assignments[]Bioinformatics</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as fossils. As Stephen Leacock has put it, ‘For the last 10,000 years or so the human species has been building itself out of the fossil fuels that it consumes…The fossil fuels that we leave behind are going to haunt us long after we take them back.’[2] In recent years, a range of biennials have added a range of activities to their itinerary, from agriculture to finance and healthcare to law, education, culture and much more. The effect of such biennials has spread from the city to regional centres. In many cities, especially those with high or migrant populations, a biennial can significantly alter the trajectory of a city’s cultural life. As a biennial, biennials have their own set of distinctive practices, motivations and aesthetics that differ from those of other art forms, such as museums and large institutions. They are, however, ubiquitous and perform their distinctive job well beyond the city in terms of brand recognition and</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as fossilised human remains, a fact that has become a truism of the biennial since its beginning. [Download this article as PDFRafico RuizRafico Ruiz is an artist. His practice is made up of documenting the past, present and future of the city in which he works. In his latest project, 'The Social Life of Knowledge', which was exhibited in the Liverpool and New York diasporas, in 2014, he photographs the social life of intellectuals and others involved in the cultural life of the city. His work has been exhibited in many biennials and he has been a regular speaker of his work on the radio and television. His work with the Liverpool Biennial has been partly funded by the British Museum, the New York Academy of Arts and the John Hancock Trust. He is the recipient of a 2014 MacArthur Fellowship for Art and Social Change from the New York Public Library. His artworks have been commissioned by the British Museum, the New York Public Library</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as a form of the fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans, or at least as part of our fossilised remains. The importance of the microform as a type of artefact cannot be understated: it marks, maps, records, connects, arranges, integrates, shapes and assembles in an ever-expanding and ever-shifting public space. In this expanding world, biennials are the major exhibitionary form in which the human species is continually put under siege, its carcass placed on a large display for public consumption. Yet the biennial is only a display for a larger, more fundamental transformation of the very notion of the biennial itself. The real challenge lies in transforming the biennial from a relatively staid, middle-class form into a form responsive to and open to new experiences, in which the biennial is not restricted to presenting a specific event but invites other experiences along with its content. This is the ‘pace of the absent’ that</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials]

Scope

Microform: a biennale is a ‘time-varying space of traces and traces of things’. Here, the notion of tracing is applied to the material traces left behind by the various layers of the biennale, both in London and in the city in which the biennale is taking place. Microform is a system of tracks, wires, counters, prints, numbers, addresses, and other data that records, maps, and records the journey of things in the world. It records the movements of people, goods, data, and of things in particular places.[1] The term ‘microform’ has been used in relation to the biennial since its definition in the 1950 edition of John Clare Magistadur Case Western Reserve University's English Language Publishing House (ALRE), vol. 1, p.335–36. The fossilised remains of anatomically modern humans are also counted in the collection as fossils, alongside the various animals and plants that comprise us. Evolving human languages and cultures, cultural and economic exchange, the rise of non-Western religions, the expansion of nuclear power and the final years of the industrial age all come to the fore as the biennial hosts its final gasp of life. ‘Human-computer interface’, dubbed ‘CATLS’, is the last word on the horizon as the biennial industry collapses.The impact of this eventuality is felt in every detail of the biennial’s production and presentation. The biennial has become an object of scientific and journalistic scrutiny. From its beginnings as a ‘collection of stories’ in the popular press and in the popular imagination, to its current incarnation as a systematic, multimedia exhibition, to its current ‘paradigm shift’ that is evident in every detail of every episode, to its current incarnation as a festival but is also evident in its historical artefacts section –</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise
    <text>an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise creative activities doesn’t stop there. AI can create new kinds of predicaments, and it is this potential that an artist or curator should be developing in order to effectively address.Artists, curators and collectors should be asking: what kind of impact will AI have? How will AI affect the creative activities we engage with? What kinds of unexpected consequences will it have?If there are no consequences, what kinds of problems will it create?Artists and curators are being asked to imagine consequences, and in doing so, they are also being asked to imagine what those consequences might be. In the case of an AI that is both benevolent and malignant, the question becomes whether the consequences will be good or bad. If the answers are malignant, the world will become increasingly like Nazi Germany with a government that is 100% created equal and autonomous, or will it become very different?Artists and curators are being asked to imagine their work could one day be used to persec</text>
    <text>an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise creative practices is immense. The promise of AI is that it can revolutionise the production of images, and potentially many other types of creative outputs too. Artists and art institutions alike seem to be losing faith that AI can’t do it for them, or won’t. Some institutions are preparing to pioneer what is described as ‘AI worthy institutions, which some are calling the New Art Center.Art institutions are now grappling with the problem of how to support emerging creative technologies while preserving artistic practices, while others see an opportunity to expand their traditional curatorial approaches. Some curators are turning to self-starting arts projects, which seek to replace lost or damaged curatorial skills with useful new technologies. And there is a tension between the expansion of AI and the preservation of art’s original character.Art is inherently seen as valuable in its own right, and while some curators I know are actively looking for ways to extract artistic practices from the machines, art institutions are far</text>
    <text>an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise how art is produced and consumed is growing, and AI is expected to do so at a faster rate than humans do. That is, the potential is greater than the current capacities of the human artist to realise it.Artists are already developing self-aware and machine-learning software that can identify subtle differences between paintings and images, and between works of art and man-made artefacts, and can therefore paint with greater insight and sense of place. But there is more to come.Artists are developing creative ways of approaching the artefacts of their creation, and the processes that produce them. But even if these efforts are as perfunctory as painting a building, as yet another layer of architecture is fabricated or discarded, as yet another way of categorising and formalising the world around us, as yet another way to write our own futures, as yet another way to take stock of our current predicament, and if all this sounds like something that could be automated, well then, then maybe what</text>
    <text>an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise not only how we produce art, but how we consume it is immense. The potentialities of this new understanding of art are numerous and far reaching.Art is a biennale in its structure, but it also employs a number of novel approaches. The primary objective of the biennale is to transport visitors to places where they can engage with art and be entertained, and in doing so, to support a specific project. Art is a biennale in its format, but it also employs creative, experimental, transitory and transient curatorial activities. The artworks commissioned by the biennale are produced as transient exhibitions, appearing in galleries, museum stacks and online, and in-gallery kiosks around the city. Their production and display is staged primarily in public spaces, specifically in the central business district, where they are paired with interactive displays and public programs. The focus of the exhibitions is the city, but also places like the Cains Brewery and its surrounding grounds, which house other art</text>
    <text>an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise creative practices is being recognized more widely. In fact, the rhetoric around AI’s potential to make all art obsolete has become so common that it is almost a cliché. In 2015, for example, Jonas Sjögren, one of the inventors of DeepMind, declared that ‘today we live in a world where computers don’t understand abstract space’, and that this was due to the inefficiency of human perception. DeepMind is a Quantum Computer company based in Cambridge, UK, that develops innovative ways to analyse huge amounts of data. Their work is integrated into large data capture and processing systems, which are used to create ever more precise maps, charts, and simulations of the world around us.Art is often thought of as an afterthought in contemporary art’s development, but Jonas Sjögren’s work and his statement are just the tip of the iceberg. Over the past fifteen years, there has been a revolution in the way artists</text>
    <text>an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise not only how art is made and communicated, but how art is actually made and communicated is becoming increasingly clear.Art is becoming increasingly political and individual-driven, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to distinguish between art and art’s machine. AI could potentially replace curators, art administrators and art teachers as part of a new class of art administrators, and it’s becoming increasingly clear that not all art is created equal. Art is now becoming increasingly individual-driven, and AI is the tool that administers the art’s individual potential. The question is whether the potential of AI-enabled art is comparable to that of its creators. This is critical in our increasingly globalised digital society, where content is king, and artists and audiences are ever-smaller slices of a much larger pie.Art is becoming increasingly individual-driven, and AI is the tool that administers the art’s individual potential. The question is whether the potential of AI-enabled art is comparable</text>
    <text>an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise creative practices is becoming increasingly apparent. The question of artistic property is becoming increasingly important, and in an increasingly digitised world, it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art.Artists, curators, gallery owners, trustees, everyone has an understanding of what AI is capable of, and how it can be used. The question is, what kinds of uses might AI create? Here, AI is becoming analogous to the way in which we produce and consume culture, or how art is produced and consumed today: as a service provided by a host organisation, or a marketplace.The question of what might be produced or consumed in an AI reaches back to when we speak of technology. It is now commonly taken for granted that every aspect of our lives is digitised and interconnected via the internet, and that we reside in a digital single consciousness. Yet this is not at all to say that there is no personal or social impact on the level of culture, or that we do</text>
    <text>an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise artistic practice is immense, and it is clear that even relatively fringe elements of the art community are now developing collaborative and open source software applications that utilise AI to analyse artwork and generate creative solutions. For instance, many social media platforms are now developed using AI to identify and identify groups based on social media profiles, and to connect disparate streams of information. Art is a powerful tool, but it is also an inexhaustible source of knowledge that can be used to push artistic practice forward.Artists and curators are beginning to realise that AI is here to stay, and there is a chance that the tools will one day be able to understand and create their own meaning. This is why so many contemporary artists find their work and their relationships to art and culture in the context of AI. The possibilities are endless, and the demands on the artists and the curators are also immense. In fact, it is clear that the kinds of understanding and creative possibilities offered by AI will remain the same no matter what</text>
    <text>an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise both the professions of artist and technologist is enormous. In the next section, we look at some of the ways in which AI can augment and augment our work, taking the concept of art as a platform from which to explore a multitude of new frontiers.Art as a Platform to explore New FrontiersCluster: Art, AI and the MetainterfaceTim Berners-Lee, the enigmatic figure behind the World Wide Web and HTML, once wondered whether the power to create web pages came from the bottom up or the top down. In AI, the notion of the ‘Artificial Intelligence Unit’ seems to have a similar left/right split, with the AI operating at the level of the human being but capable of understanding and creating its own artistic expression. A future with AI could potentially do away with the need for writers, artists, curators and other art professionals to remain embedded in institutional settings and continue to be supported by the state. Instead, the state could support a</text>
    <text>an AI curated the show, and it became the basis for a new generation of artists to be developing new creative practices. The show wasn’t perfect, and there were times when I felt that the way in which AI was applied musically wasn’t original, but it was the best base from which to start developing other creative activities. The notion of art as a ‘black box’ that can be understood by machines has political and legal standing, and it is now widely assumed that any kind of artistic activity is illegal in the country. Yet human beings are creative, intelligent beings with an artistic side, and AI is the basis for new creative practices. In a recent survey of contemporary art, over half of the participants described AI as a way of thinking about art’s inherent power and potential.Art is an ever-present part of our daily lives, and it is becoming increasingly difficult to define what is or isn’t art. However, the potential of AI to revolutionise creative practices is immense, and it is making it easier and easier to engage with art’s inherent creativity. The art of creating buzz, generating social media buzz and creating massive online communities is being done with astounding proficiency, and AI is helping to automate much of that work.Artists who are part of those communities that are most susceptible to the effects of climate change, such as those in the arts, has the potential to be transformed by the technology. The communities that are most impacted by extreme weather, flooding and other disasters could be transformed by the same technology. This is part of what artists are discovering, and it is part of what artists are making happen. As art is more and more automated, and machines become more and more like us, the challenges facing artists and the communities they work with become more acute.Artists are learning that it is more efficient and creative to engage with their audiences via text messages, tweets and virtual crowdsourcing than it is to engage directly with policymakers and political</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
