<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades has been in its extraordinary capacity to inhabit the public space. The biennial as a curatorial tool has morphed to such an extent that it is now capable of inhabiting every imaginable place – from the gritty to the fabulously photographed. It is the double whammy of a huge budget and a huge public presence. It is also the case that the curatorial turn has given way to the curatorial flip-flop, where the huge budgets, the public presence and the complex infrastructures that comprise biennials are either moved offshore or torn down. This may happen at a pace, as biennials become more institutionalised, but it is becoming increasingly difficult to define the place of this continued investment in the city in the face of such a fluidity of capital, with cities everywhere more and more like giant islands – islands in a sea of capitalism.  And this is what I mean when I say that the market place no longer constitutes the bulk of the biennial. The public</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades has been its occupancy of the public space, with little regard for property rights. The city floods the biennial with visitors, but little attention is paid to the many thousands of square feet of retail and office that are displaced when the buildings are torn down.  Instead, the biennial promotes a single product, often a single stand-alone stand-alone space, at the expense of other goods and services. The movement of goods and services is strategically coordinated through the system of transportation known as the biennale. The movement of goods and services at the biennale is a capital-intensive process, requiring the resourcefulness of planners and developers to handle the ever-growing number of visitors. This capital intensive nature of the movement of goods and services is at odds with the free movement of people, goods and services celebrated in the biennial. And yet, this capital intensive nature of the movement of goods and services makes it possible for biennials to exist, to produce their own forms of tourism</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades has been the way in which it distributes its wealth. It has become a business, and the biennial has become a type of industry. The museum and historic district are the platforms of the new normal; the biennial, on the other hand, remains firmly rooted in the past. This change in the normalisation of power between the museum and the biennial is a change that is deeply felt by the local populations that use the museum. The change in the form of the museum and the biennial is a change that is both gradual and deep. It is a change that many biennials will continue to execute, and often quite successfully, despite their ‘different styles’ and ‘different needs’.2 The key to understanding this shift is the development of local cultural governance frameworks. In the 1990s, the biennial was able to transition easily into local cultural governance frameworks through a combination of generous donor dollars and the explicit political and economic influence of the Democratic Party in Washington</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades has been in its extraordinary capacity to inhabit the social. It is possible that the biennial may one day inhabit the social. The question is which form it will take: will it inhabit the social as an event, as an occurence, or will it inhabit the social as an ever-present, recurring phenomenon, as a social biennial? This is the dynamic that biennials must address in order to truly inhabit the social. And if the biennial is to be counted as a social event, it must become ever more than a mark-taker, a wall and a pulley to keep score, a repository of photographs and documents, a static image of the social, recording its passage from one social moment to the next. It is to be counted, in other words, as a kind of micro-event, one that demands and anticipates, that records its presence and its passage, that actively engages the social, and that informs us as we attend. For this to happen</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades has been its ability to expand outward, to become global. And this process of global ubiquity has put enormous bureaucratic burdens on the city, discouraging local control and creating a global commons. We are now witnessing the effects of this on a galactic scale. All biennials today are global entities. And these days almost all biennials are global in their approach to art and culture. As global nomadic cultural entities, they are everywhere, and do not care about where they come from or what they mean to communities or citizens of their adopted city. They are art institutions in their own right, with missions that are local to the city in which they are located. And although the biennial may have once been a frequent visitor to the city, its global reach has brought with it a change in that it no longer counted visitors as local. In the biennial calendar, the biennale is still a ‘number one’ event, but no longer holds the title that it once did.</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades has been in the form of a periodic or recurring exhibition that places the essential characteristics of a biennial – its site, its time, its story – into sharp relief. This is what biennials are today: they are forms of art that still aspire to be fully realized, but which are manifesting at an ever increasing rate. And here we see the real bargains made: the frequent replacement of the iconic with the transient, the present with the past, and the present with the future. The biennial form is sustaining the present with an ever increasing fidelity, while the artist is forced to constantly remind us that the biennial form is here to stay. As the biennial format shifts from the city to the market place, it is becoming ever more evident that the very structure of biennials is inherently unstable. Its ability to project its historical narratives in a wide range of new and unexpected ways, to project its own distinctive grammatical and photographic syntax, to simultaneously read as an exhibition of</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades has been in the area of its production, which is produced through a series of collaborative tactics that seek to exploit the sense of community and social purpose that is produced through the curatorial turn. Art institutions have often been tempted to become enablers of the social turn, or even promoters of it, by giving voice to audiences to the curatorial turn. This is not always the case, but very few are now able to do so due to the prevailing bureaucratized culture of the biennial. The biennial producer has his or her priorities straight, and audiences do not always see through the curtain.  A biennial producer might want to know what is happening in the city, and the city might want to know what is happening in the city. The biennial is a powerful tool, and one that is increasingly difficult to use prudentially. The biennial is a production system that produces a steady stream of images and texts, and one that requires no long term investment in production, maintenance or</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades has been in its extraordinary capacity to inhabit the present. Its ability to move from the present, its ability to inhabit the present with astonishing regularity, has become the defining characteristic of the biennial experience. The biennial is the rarest of exhibitions, and a very old one indeed. It began as a trade mark of great art museums in the nineteenth century, and has been a trade mark of modern and contemporary art museums ever since. Its current form, then, is an art exhibit that has become a biennial phenomenon. Biennials have a particular capacity to entice visitors from afar. The trade mark that they bear is a distinctive artefact that stands out conspicuously in otherwise hilly and level exhibitionary exhibitionary museums. Its affinities to the city and the minutemen are clear. The exhibitionary museum is itself a museum of the quotidian, exhibiting the latest arrivals from faraway fields of experience. And so the biennial exhibits its own temporality. It exhibits</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades has been in the form of a gallery – a place with a fixed collection of objects, usually arranged around a curator’s personal selection. Biennials have a fixed budget, and the collection they have accumulated over decades is very real. If the collection is ever to be released, the biennial must first raise money through a combination of public and private investment. So the biennial, while it is a real collection, is also a temporary collection, held together by the precariousness of its collection and the vagaries of economic and social change. It is a collection that is constantly undergoing change, and the only way to know what will become of it is to be inside of it.   The problem with the biennial today is that it is both a museum and a gallery. It collects real collections, preserved in museum-quality condition, but also a gallery of images that is both a simulacrum of its original form and a contemporary reconstruction of its lost images. In other words,</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial. It imagines the festival, the exhibition, the ‘cup of tea’ – all of it filtered through the prism of a biennial. Although the curatorial turn may be important at certain stages in the development of a biennial, the real pivot point of the biennial today is the ‘market place’. And at a certain point in the development of the biennial, the market place is where the real bargains are made. Biennials are the rare institution that can be counted on to deliver on their promises. The towing them on their promise is part of their ongoing gamble, as is obvious in the exhibition catalogue that they have just finished cleaning off.  One can look at the catalogue and predict with high probability what the next event will be, and what form it will take. Biennials have a habit of manifesting in unexpected places, most visibly in the form of the Occupy Movement. But the real innovation of the biennial in recent decades has been in its extraordinary capacity to manifest in seemingly normal spaces. This phenomenon has recently been replicated in other cities where capital is encouraged to be spread around in an urban-scale fashion. New York is increasingly being attended to by civic-minded tourists seeking out the low-hanging fruit of cultural reclamation. But New York City is becoming ever more stratified, with ever more affluent tourists flocking to the city in preference to straying far from its elevated attractions. And as a result, the city is becoming ever more unmanageable. Its monstrosity is an obvious symptom of the overproduction of culture in the name of economic growth. The city is becoming ever more like a production line for social media, where once again mass tourism is the ticket to riches. In an odd twist, many of these economic migrants may also be lured by the exotic trappings of social success, like caviar and designer goods, but few of them are paying for these things out of their wallets. Instead</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennial
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennialloaf.com/index.php?fuseaction=artschema&amp;art=architecture&amp;subscribe=1234&amp;art=biennials-newsletter-2011-12.html?type=subscribe. 	[v] See: http://www.biennialloaf.com/2011/exhibition/index.php?fuseaction=artschema&amp;art=architecture&amp;subscribe=1234&amp;art=biennials-newsletter-2011-12-23.html?type=subscribe. 	[vi] See: http://www.biennialloaf.com/2011/index.php?fuseaction=artschema&amp;art=architecture&amp;subscribe=1234&amp;art=biennials-newsletter-2011-12.html?type=subscribe. 	[vii] See: http://www.biennials</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/news/how-the-world-views-biennial-2018.html. 	[v] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/2018/exhibition/index.html. 	[vi] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/2018/exhibition/index.html?section=Magazine&amp;issue=new. 	[vii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/2018/exhibition/index.html?section=Magazine&amp;issue=new. 	[viii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/2018/exhibition/index.html?section=Magazine&amp;issue=new. 	[ix] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/2018/exhibition/index.html?section=Magazine&amp;issue=new.[</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennial.com/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[v] See: http://www.biennial.com/about/exhibition/index.html?event=52. 	[vi] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?event=52. 	[vi] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?event=52. 	[vii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?event=52. 	[viii] See: http://www.biennial.com/about/exhibition/index.html?event=52. 	[ix] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/exhibition/index.html . 	[v] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/exhibition/index.html?option=com_au_dla_dexion&amp;view=full&amp;creative=y&amp;layout=e&amp;albums=8 . 	[vi] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/exhibition/index.html?option=com_au_dla_dexion&amp;view=full&amp;creative=y&amp;layout=e&amp;albums=9 . 	[vii] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/exhibition/index.html?option=com_au_dla_dexion&amp;view=full&amp;creative=y&amp;albums=10&amp;discover_at_home=y&amp;type=discovery.html?type=discovery</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=Rustbelt_and_mountain_region_2017112811.html. 	[v] See: http://www.exhibition-futures.com/2012/exhibition/exhibition-summary.html?excerpt=Rustbelt_and_mountain_region_2017112906.html. 	[vi] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=Rustbelt_and_mountain_region_2017112906.html. 	[vii] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=Rustbelt_and_mountain_region_2017112906.html. 	[viii] See: http://www.biennial</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[v] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[vi] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=full-text&amp;source=news-emerging-india-pacific-islands-1220106.html. 	[vii] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=full-text&amp;source=news-emerging-india-pacific-islands-1220106.html. 	[viii] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=full-text&amp;source=news-emerging-</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/exhibition-list.html. 	[v] See: http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/exhibition-list.html. 	[vi] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/2018/exhibition/exhibition-list.html. 	[vii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/2018/exhibition/list.html. 	[viii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/2018/exhibition/list.html?section=biennial&amp;issue=5. 	[ix] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/2018/exhibition/list.html?section=biennial&amp;issue=6. 	[x] See: http://www.biennials.com</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennial.org.au/en/exhibition/index.html. 	[v] See: http://www.biennial.org.au/en/exhibition/index.html?section=History&amp;view=full. 	[vi] See: http://www.biennial.org.au/en/exhibition/index.html?section=History&amp;view=full. 	[vii] See: http://www.biennial.org.au/en/exhibition/index.html?section=History&amp;view=full. 	[viii] See: https://www.biennial.org.au/en/exhibition/index.html?section=History&amp;view=full. 	[ix] See: https://www.biennial.org.au/en/exhibition/index.html?section=History&amp;view=full. 	[x</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/index.html. 	[v] See: http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/summary.html. 	[vi] See: http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/summary.html?excerpt=summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary- 	[vii] See: http://www.biennial.com/2018/exhibition/summary.html?excerpt=summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary-summary 	[viii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/2018/exhibition/index.html. 	</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning, software and robotics). 	[i] Not all biennials are created equal. The ICF, for example, counts its many achievements not in the rank of the museum, which is the dominant museum-going form, but rather in the ranking of biennials, each of which has its own unique and distinctive local flavour, distinctive historic experiences and distinctive future plans. 	[ii] The total number of exhibition-going biennials in the world today is estimated at around 1,500. Of these, up to 80% are in Asia and the Pacific. Of the remaining 20% in the US, up to 10% are in the Rust Belt and Mountain regions. Of these, only a small share are in cities. 	[iii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html. 	[iv] See: http://www.biennial.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=History_in_the_Making&amp;section=Display_listing. 	[v] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=History_in_the_Making_Recap of_the_present_events?section=Display_listing. 	[vi] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=History_in_the_Making_2016’s_recap_of_the_present_events?section=Display_listing. 	[vii] See: http://www.biennials.com.au/about/exhibition/index.html?excerpt=History_in_the_Making_2018’s_summary?</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘impl
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicitly mapping’, the interface makes it possible for an object to negotiate a given system, and at the same time it imposes restrictions on the system (such as enforcing a particular programming language).1 The implicit mapping or pressure on the system comes from the fact that the underlying mathematical models of the world don’t correlate with contemporary conveniences, and don’t evolve in response to user demands. In fact, the better the interface is, the more difficult it is for a user to figure out what is happening on the system (by programming languages, protocols, etc).  	In the computer interface, the data flow is parallel and abrupt; there is no refinement, no delicate nuance that needs to be applied in order to accommodate the different layers. In the  	real-time trading  	app, the data flow is more subtle and transitory; there is no refinement or delicate nuance that needs to be applied in order to accommodate the different layers. Instead</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicit typing’, implicit perception and implicit understanding, the interface captures and maps the world through what can be seen and unseen. The implicit understanding is conveyed through the naming of ‘things’ and ‘data’. 	Within the context of interface design, the implicit perception and implicit understanding become explicit, and can be used to produce ‘design decisions’. These decisions are made with regards to things and data, but also of the immersivity of language, and overloading of the systems with data (how to name things and figures, how to discern patterns and ‘understandings’?). 	In  	design research, this has come to be known as the Interface Criteria.1 	The criteria prescribe what the user sees and does with the things she or he creates. They prescribe what can be done with the ‘things’ and ‘data’. These parameters set the paradigm for what is possible within an</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicitly mapping buttons to events’, this assumption is made that the user can infer actions from the way objects are ‘structured and interconnected’. 	In  	Game Development, the informal mapping of user actions to object-systems is often referred to as ‘Game Theory’.[3] 	In an increasingly interconnected world, there is a need to be able to infer the intentions of others, and to this end, many computer scientists have turned to Artificial Intelligence (AI) to automate parts of the system. These mathematical models of the system assume the underlying principles of the systems, and can therefore learn how to do things through trial and error.  	However, despite advances in AI, there remains much debate about the nature of human agency and the role of politics in technological innovation. How should the human beings who work in the systems be empowered in this new technological context? Should the human beings who develop the apps be able to override the machines</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicit typing’, implicit understanding, and explicit modifiers, the interface can be configured in many different ways. 	Within the context of system requirements, the context of a plug-in is the equivalent of a factory. ‘It is the blending of many different kinds of production into one, human-centred outcome –––that is, into one big yet subtle effect –––that is the core idea of the plug-in industry, and it is this underlying point of view that characterises the evolution of the interface from the factory to the interface’s effect on the user’s interface design.’[6] Such implicit, yet sometimes complex, multi-layered layers exist in virtually all mediums of interaction – from typing, to browsing, to writing, to accessing information – but as noted by sociologist Rutger B. Brown, they were not always structured this way: there were many types of users, not all of whom viewed the user as</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicitly mapping inputs to outputs’, the interface maximises the interpretive possibilities of the platform it sits on. By imitating the underlying mechanisms of the platform, the interface attempts to represent the world in a certain way, but at the same time strives to innovate its own dynamic situation within the platform’s hierarchies and societies. 	Looking to the future, the emphasis shifts to the underlying principles of the platform that underlie the interactions between individuals, groups and large societies. The actions of individuals, groups and large societies (societies) move between data feeds, and the interface becomes part of a larger ‘runtime of symbolic interactions’ (Brooks and White, 2009, p.50). 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes part of a larger symbolic interaction called a ‘runtime of meaningful gestures’ (Brooks and White, 2009, p.51). Symbols and metaphors are used to describe specific objects and behaviours, and the underlying</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicitly mapping expectations onto ‘surface features’, the Ubuntu mission is able to specify what behavior is expected from its users. 	In the context of computer vision, the interface becomes a set of actions that describe the underlying semantics of the system. Actions such as selecting an image, or dialogue boxes, or even menus, describe the underlying mechanisms of the system. Actions such as a user’s choice, or explicit programming, describes the intended behavior of the system. 	The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep’ layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicitly mapping expectations onto ‘surface features’, the Ubuntu mission is able to specify what behavior is expected from its users. 	In the context of computer vision, the interface becomes a �</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicitly’ insinuating things into an object, the user is able to ‘predict’ outcomes from events that take place in the real world. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep� layer, underlying a rich class of relationships between individuals. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicitly’ insinuating things into an object, the user is able to ‘predict’ outcomes from events that take place in the real world. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the past. We can ask what the interface represents, and</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicitly mapping actions to objects’, implicit mapping allows the computer to infer meaning from the actions of objects. By understanding how an object represents a set of relationships, the interface enables the emergent relations between individuals, groups, and entities. 	Figure 1: An example of how the Unity interface is conceptualised. A window icon is positioned at the edge of the screen, and actions such as double-clicking, entering text, and more can all be inferred from its context. 	In the computer, the event-driven model – which is at the root of many problems – is given a great deal of weight. Actions such as dialog boxes, pop-ups, forms, drop-down menus, and more are all seen as essential to computer functionality. In the age of the Internet of Things (IoT), which seeks to understand ‘how objects discover, make and follow paths through space’, the importance of the ‘underlying architecture’</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicitly mapping'…[2] we can understand how the interface is different from what is represented by the computer. 	Looking to the future, the transparent surface metaphor becomes a way to imagine new, more interactive forms of reality. A surface with no hierarchies of relationships or interactions, but which nevertheless 'gets us there’ – lets us ‘talk, but don’t really understand how that’s done’ – becomes a platform on which new, interactive forms of social life can be created. 	The explicit mapping of relationships between individuals, groups and large systems is a recurring theme in the writings of Rintalo Bauman and Satish Jaggarhi. In his seminal work Systemics: The Anthropology of Everyday Objects (1972), Bauman offers a back story to the emergence of our present in a complex web of cultural influences. These cultural influences come from diverse parts of the world, and they enact a ‘complex ‘transnational’</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and the results are used to program machines to do things in the future.’ 	In another sense, the  	end-user is a platform, and the application is an interface. The application interacts with the underlying infrastructure, and data feeds from the infrastructure, that shape the user’s experience. In this way, the term is somewhat of a colloquialism, applied to the systems that hold the application together and the platform underneath. 	Looking to the future, the interface becomes an interpretation of the past, and the application an interpretation of the future. We can ask what the interface represents, and how it is different from what is represented by the computer. The interface is a surface, but it is also a ‘deep' layer, underlying a rich ‘category theory of relationships and interactions’. At its simplest, a ‘transparent Unity interface’ represents the relationships between objects in an object-system. By ‘implicitly’ this would mean ‘using available resources to render content, based on available data’, and also ‘using existing infrastructure to support interactive or augmented content, based on user needs and data’. WOW! Wow! Wow! Wow! Wow! Wow! Wow! Wow! Wow!Wow!Wow!Wow!Wow!Wow!Wow!Wow!Wow! 1. Stefan Collini, Programming Language (Cambridge, MA: MIT Press, 2013), p. 14. 2. WOW! Wow! Wow! Wow! 3. Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia, Chapter 16, Verse 2. 4. Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia, Verse 4. 5. Wikipedia, The Free Encyclopedia, Chapter 16, Verse 5. 6. Idem, ‘On the nature of computerisation’, Page Top ↑, Vol. 1, p. 9. 7. Wikipedia, The</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot;
    <text>extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot; (2014). He is the editor of the forthcoming book Future of Work: Conversations on the Present and Future of Work (2015). His recent work in the field of geopolitics and communications technologies includes the co-editing of several books on a range of subjects including Cybernetics: A Global Perspective (2015), The New Digital Complexity: Towards a New Digital Age (2015), and the co-editing of several books on a range of subjects including Privacy and Politics in the Information Age (2015). He is currently researching the experiences and topics of identity, migration and citizenship in the context of geopolitics and communications technology.3. The impact of AI and robotics on professions and professions. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and holds the position of Chairman of the Board of Scientific Research Center for AI and Systems Research. He is</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot; (2014).He is a co-founder and co-editor of the peer-reviewed journal Ecosphere (2014), and a co-editor of the upcoming book The Future of Humanity: Towards an Ecology of Intelligent Agents (2015).He has written for Wired, The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New Scientist, Scientific American, Popular Science, BBC Future, The New Republic, The New Scientist, and The Guardian. He has written for The New York Times, The New York Times Book Review, The New York Times Digital Briefing, The New York Times Digital Strategy, The New Republic, The Washington Post, and The Guardian. He has lectured on computer game studies at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Columbia University Press, Cornell University Press, Temple University Press, and the Simon English Prize Lecture Series. He is currently the editor of the forthcoming online journal Computer Game Studies.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot; (2014). He is currently working on a book on the intersection of aesthetics, architecture, and ecology.2Up2Down/Alon Singer and Rob McKayOver the past decade, the intersection of technology and culture has become a hot topic of debate and investigation. This book takes the reader on a two-week ‘cultural immersion’ experience through the culture of virtual and augmented reality, which takes place at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem. During this experience, participants examine the intersection of technology, identity, and cultural consumption through works that address the intersection of religion, identity, and social life. Over the course of the two-week ‘cultural immersion’, participants create and explore an online presence that brings to life the ‘why’ of technology. How does the contemporary interface create its own forms of inhabitation? Who is responsible for the construction of infrastructure and the systems that support it? What kinds of infrastructures and systems are built around the data from ubiquitous sensors</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot; (2015). He is the co-editor of the forthcoming book The Society of the Spectacle (2016).He is the author of Systemics, or Your Present Online, (2015), which documents the rise and fall of large data mining operations, and The Society of the Spectacle: Systems of Post-Intelligent Everyday Life (2014), a book that documents the cultural underpinnings of the society of the spectacle. He is currently researching the legacy of Ada Lovelace, the celebrated Scottish mathematician and social critic. In recent books he has written about architecture and social reform, and has written on the future of work and labour, and the relationship between science and industry.He is a co-founder of the Planetary Society, which studies the systems that shape our solar system, and which together form the basis for a post-human society. He is the editor of the forthcoming book The Society of the Spectacle: Systems of Post-Intelligent Everyday Life (2014).He is</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot; (2014). His research has been featured in venues including Wired Magazine, The New York Times, BBC Future, and numerous publications such as the Wall Street Journal, Washington Post, Los Angeles Times, and CBC's The Current. He has been a consultant for the film Tomorrow People, as well as a co-author with Patrick Joyce of the soon to be released book about the intersection of science, culture, and state. He is a regular panelist on the BBC Future show Future City and a regular speaker at the New York Future Meetup.He is on the editorial boards of numerous publications including the Electronic Frontier Foundation (2013), Electronic Frontier Foundation (2014), Stanford Law Review, American Civil Liberties Union (2014), Electronic Frontier Foundation (2015), Electronic Frontier Foundation (2016), Electronic Frontier Foundation (2017), Electronic Frontier Foundation (2018), Electronic Frontier Foundation (2020), Electronic Frontier Foundation (2029), and the Electronic Frontier Foundation website.He is a co-editor of the forthcoming academic edition of World</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot; (2014). He is the host of the popular Twitch.tv/SpencerRich Show, which includes topics including Artificial Intelligence, Cultural Marxism, and the politics of cultural consumption. He is also the editor of the upcoming online journal Worlds of Culture.2Up2Down/Alon SingerAlon Singer is Professor of English and Director of the Hebrew University Department of English and Culture. His research interests include the natural sciences and humanities, with a particular focus on the humanities and social sciences. His publications include the award-winning book The Systems Installed: System Analysis and Bioinformatics (Profile, 2011), the forthcoming book Systems, or What We Share (2015), and the collection What We Share: Social Science Research and Writing (2014). He is the editor of the upcoming online journal Worlds of Culture.3Up3Down/Alon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University Jerusalem and holds a PhD in Computer Science from MIT.</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot; (2014).He serves on the boards of various cultural and educational organizations including the Institutions of Digital Media (2006-09), Electronic Frontier Foundation (2009-12), Public Knowledge (2014-), and Open Society Institute (2015-16). He has spoken at the annual convention of the Association for Computational Culture (AC3), the European Computer Society, the Venice Biennale, and the Carnegie International. He has received a host of awards and mentions, including a 2012 MacArthur &quot;Genius&quot; Grant for his work in cultural-mathematical computing.He is the author or co-author of more than twenty books, including the Hugo and Nebula Award-winning The Art of Not Being Governed (2015), the New York Times best-seller Listening, Listening, Listening: Social Practice with Ewan McGregor, or Why I Am Here (with Dan Malosh), and the New York Times best-seller Getting Things Done: An Introduction (2015). He has written from</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot; (2015). He is the editor of the forthcoming encyclopedia project, Systems: An Interactive Encyclopedia of Human Behavior (2018). We Are Here to Stay Christina Rehberger and Allan SekulaIn the summer of 2016, the Czech theatre company CCC performed the opening night of the Venice Biennale with the newly formed company We Are Here to Stay. The performance, which followed a set of questions and answers, was a response to the biennale’s decision to focus on the city as a major theme. The play, which was written and directed by Allan Sekula, draws on the history of the project from its beginning, while also investigating the way that the Biennale is part of a larger cultural enterprise that began in 1993 with the creation of the city as a major spectacle. In the 1920s, the Biennale was one of the largest forms of public cultural output produced by the state, and the city is played by the Biennale. A new generation of theatre</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot; (2014). He has written for the New York Times, Wired, BBC, TED, The Guardian, and many other publications. He is currently a co-editor of the book You Are Here: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015), with Raymond Williams and Noel Burch, and co-editor of the upcoming book Systems for a Future (2016). He is a fellow of the American Enterprise Institute and the Chambers of Commerce International. He is on the boards of various cultural and educational organisations, and has been a presenter of the internationally syndicated TV show ‘The Singularity is Near’.Alon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include computer systems and network analysis, cultural theory, and critical theory. His publications include several book series including the popular computer systems books Systems Analysis: Theory, Politics, and Ambition (with</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines that are neither human nor computer]2. The rise and fall of large data mining operations, c. 2000–2010. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 2014.Download this article as PDFAlon SingerAlon Singer is Professor in the Department of Computer Science and Engineering at the Hebrew University of Jerusalem, and has taught at the University of California, Los Angeles, and McGill University. His research interests include infrastructure and software engineering, ethnography on software and infrastructure, and media and cultural infrastructure. His publications include the forthcoming book You Are Here: Systemics, or Your Present Online (2015), and the co-edited book You Are Here, or You Are Present: Systems for a Post-Intelligent Future (2015). He is a contributor to the W. W. Norton &amp; Company book series Computer Game Studies, with contributions including &quot;Rules of Engagement: Social Contract and Strategist’s Chessboard&quot; (2015) and &quot;Superintelligence: Intelligence in the Cloud&quot; (2015). He is a consultant, writer and speaker. His latest work, You Are Here, or Your Present Online, is published by Hodder &amp; Stoughton (2017). He is co-editor of the forthcoming Oxford English Dictionary online (with Isaac Chotiner) and is a fellow of the American Enterprise Institute. His research examines the social implications of new technologies and is the author of numerous articles and book chapters on a range of topics. How to Know About Artificial IntelligenceRobust Intelligence (1937)By Ada LovelaceCreative Thinking: From Symbolic Logic to NowTheory of Mind (1937) and On Intelligence and Social Change with AI (1937)Sweet Briar Sisters (1937) and their Creative SystemForgetting Childhood (1937)Sweet Briar Sisters and the Creature from Bunnyburrow (1937)by Ada LovelaceCreative Thinking and Its Mediatised FormsDavid BrinAndrea Maria CostaBoth men write with a</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part of a ‘different type of memory… that contributes to the formation and growth of culture and the social life of nations’.7 The journal’s publication, ‘a regular event’, as well as the forthcoming seventeenth edition, ‘a document that will live on through the years to come… remains to be seen. But the journal’s circulation and publication seem certain to increase in the future, as biennials are seen by many people as a source of social and cultural value.8 It is also to be seen whether the journals will play any role in the future of the event, other than as a record of the past, a record of the present and a record of the future. 9. Events in their relations to each other and to the biennial in Venice, 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale. 10. The Biennale 2015. Photo courtesy of the Biennale.  	Notice board highlighting the</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part of a job for which ‘we have no plans’.7 The journal raises interesting questions, but also poses problems. For one thing, its title suggests a kind of a confession, a kind of a ‘what did we do wrong?’; for another, the journal’s subtitle hints at a kind of a ‘quest for knowledge’.8 The journal’s issue 3 covers the week of June 12-20, 2017, which is the oldest issue of the journal. It is the last issue before the biennial, and the last before the VB takes place. It includes a survey of the Venice Biennale, and a poll of its readers, which raises questions about the biennale’s continuing relevance. The journal raises questions of its own, but it also questions the curatorial role and its limits. For example, when publishing a book, what is meant by ‘book?’? Does the word �</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part of a longer curatorial plan to ‘reanimate' the Biennale: ‘It’s a highly specific type of memory that is constantly reified, and so it’s a reification that’s very difficult to shake. But the plan is on track and we can certainly count on the support of the Biennale board in this regard.‘ This is similar to the way in which art institutions, including those in other cities, are attempting to embed meaningful and dynamic activities into their biennials. Whether the intentions of these institutions are genuine or whether the curatorial machinations that generate these indices of change are also responsible for the periodicing of the biennial remains to be seen. Other indices of change may include the biennial’s development of a permanent permanent public programme of exhibitions, which began in 2017 and is expanding at a remarkable clip, or the Biennale’s continuing expansion of its permanent market, which increased twentyfold</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part of a larger ‘mission-critical’ revision process that aims to ‘realign priorities, shift resources and create new frameworks for understanding and action’.7 	One hopes that the Biennale can learn to be accountable, even critical, in this respect, and that its journal may play a part in creating a public space in which to happen. Perhaps a form of participatory journaling, perhaps a journaling format that anticipates the way in which the Biennale will be publishing its texts, may be an approach that the Biennale can adopt in order to engage with its ‘real life’ and create a ‘prioritisation’ of events and people in the city. What is certain is that the Biennale must engage with its ‘real life’ if it is to create a ‘prioritisation’ of them, and to do so, it is imperative that it engages with the real life of</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part of a policy of ‘institutional memorymaking’ at the Biennale that builds on previous editions to create a ‘deep pool of tradition and deep roots’ that can act as a foundation for future generations to work through. That is, the journal could serve as a way to archive the fact of the event, while augmenting the reader’s understanding of the city’s past, present and future through a combination of text and image. Ideally, the journal could incorporate both a curatorial gesture, and an entertaining artifact. For the Venice Biennale 2017, that’s exactly what happened. In the journal, the author, Isabelle Lecocq, narrates her visit to the Biennale, which took place in 2017. She uses this historical document to chart the steps that a small group of artists took as they made their presence felt at the Biennale, identifying key works, placing them in chronological order and even ‘h</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part of its ‘reference work’ that it does not yet fully engage with.7 	The Biennale’s journal could not have been more in sync with its curatorial priorities. On the one hand, the publication of the Biennale’s current issue features suggestions from curators for the future of the exhibitionary complex – a repository for ideas and a platform for expression of diverse values and opinions. On the other, the journal features broadsides on specific curatorial projects, their internal dynamics and behaviours, and in-depth looks at the city at large.8 On 11 June, 2017, for example, Paolo Baratta announced the creation of a new ‘specialised' journal, ‘Present Tense’, to take up the task of conveying the enormous volume of content produced by the Biennale’s annual assembly into contemporary forms.9 The journal’s first issue will feature a ‘landscape architecture�</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part of its ‘cultural ecology’ that it describes as ‘a system that supports the collective memory of the city’.7 Biennials are art forms within which the artworks are produced and made visible, and through which the events of the week are reproduced and repeated. In this sense, they are not events, but registers of the social world around us. That they are biennials but also participate in the ‘curatorial’ and ‘art’ categories suggests that they are products of a complex interconnection of cultural, economical and political factors. That a biennial, in its current form, can be an effective form of archiving, and generate new knowledge about the city, is another of its strengths. But this contribution to the city is only possible through the mediation of the city, and the biennial as a form of memory-formation that must also be mediated through the mediation of art.8 In recent years, there has been a proliferation of</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part of a planned ‘regeneration’ project that ‘will end with a new journal’.7 This journal, if it develops into a place where the city and its infrastructure are celebrated, will mark a new stage in the history of the Biennale. It will tell the story of the Biennale as an event that engages with the city’s social and political contexts, while also questioning its place in the world. As the mayor of Venice, I’m quite certain that I’ll get a chance to write a journal of the Biennale, from the city’s perspective.  [1] The Biennale is published by Koninklijke Philips Nederlandsche Bank Amsterdam. The author does not hold any positions in any organisations that might have an influence on the venue of the Biennale.  [2] The Biennale has been partially funded by the European Commission and Telefónica</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part of a longer-term, ‘institutional memory’ project that became visible in the Biennale’s portfolio over many projects, including the 2016 Venice Biennale, which is ‘the last chapter’ in that history.7 The journal may be an object of memory-work, but its retrieval and repurposing raises questions about the limits of memory, the relations between the host and the artefact, and the possibility of intervention beyond those typically associated with cultural interventions. The journal may also hint at intervention outside the context of the Biennale, suggesting that the biennale itself may engage in similar kinds of cultural amelioration. That said, the journal’s widespread distribution and its proximity to the event it is commenting on suggest a more immediate involvement. That week of 11-14 June 2017 will mark the one hundred and thirty-second anniversary of the assassination of Archduke Franz Ferdinand, and its publication will come as a surprise to many</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial, and the curatorial officer directs the biennial’s exploration of its subjectivity through a series of ‘contemporary art practices’.5 Other biennial curators have sought to intervene as early as possible in the events of the week of 11-14 June, with the aim to create an ‘institutional memory’ of the event through the repetition of it in other curatorial activities.6 The main curatorial officer of the Venice Biennale, Paolo Baratta, explains that his ‘institutional memory’ of the event is the object of continual revision. Since its foundation in 1999, the Biennale has been publishing its third edition in 2017, in an attempt to ensure that it remains ‘relevant and influential’ in influencing policy and public reaction to the city’s infrastructure. It remains to be seen how the Venice Biennale can contribute to this memory-work through its journal. Its publication, he says, is part of a larger ‘curatorial’ project that aims to ‘define the event as a cultural phenomenon’ and instigate a ‘political, social and historiography of the event’. ‘Cultural[s] means cultural institutions, those that foster social formation and instigate change in the cultural landscape’, the journal reads, paraphrasing Paul de Grauwe. ‘Individual or small group action, “combined with political and social formation and determination”] can be seen as a more accurate definition of what the Biennale has in mind. But what exactly do the Biennale and its curatorial officers mean when they decree that the subject matter of art, architecture, landscape, youth and so forth should be taken up, and what counts as a cultural act in the eyes of the state? Some might argue that the biennale is part of a larger curatorial enterprise, part of a larger ‘cultural infrastructure�</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about the future. Artworks we encounter in the exhibition hall, and those that appear in the exhibition catalogue, communicate a story of the past, the future and a possible future. The act of taking these artefacts out of their natural context, of telling a story through them, is a story that relies heavily on narration, metaphor and story. It is an art of narration, metaphor and story. 	In a way, then, the ‘present’ in the Biennale is both narrativist and story-telling. It is both a narrative that serves as a marker of time and a storyteller in its own right. It establishes a stage on which art can be reckoned as contemporaneous with events that happen in the present, and in the future, so as to capture the essence of what is happening in a contemporaneous way. It establishes a kind of shared ontological threshold, beyond which no other narration can claim it. 	In the case of a ‘</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about the future. What a gift to be able to conceive of art and the biennial as historic objects from the past that now live among us in symbolic forms – artworks that tell us more about the contemporary condition, and artworks that metaphorically narrate the present. 	But perhaps the most potent narrative narrative element of the biennial is the ‘present’, which is understood by many curators and artists as encompassing multiple pasts and perspectives. The narrative of the biennial as a whole, then, is part of a ‘big picture’, and the ‘present’ is a ‘slice of the pie’. What this pie metaphorically represents is a partial and distorted view of the world, and of contemporary art in particular. What is contemporary and what is past in the contemporary world is made visible through the artefacts that are displayed, discussed, analysed and judged to be contemporary within the biennial. The ‘present’ is</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about the future. In other words, they point to the inevitable tendency for art and art history to repeat itself – from the biennial to the museum and thence to the contemporary gallery – a tendency that we should all be watching with keen interest. 	[1] The Biennale website provides more information. biannale.org, 'The Dictators of the Biennial: Venice and the Rise of the Contemporary Art Biennial’, http://www.biennaleofvalencia.org/en/stable/topic/1/116/1/116-what-s-next-venice-biennale.html, accessed 10 August 2013. [2] Interview with Jonathan Crary, Curator of Public Art at the London and New York Philharmonic, 2015. [3] Interview with Prof. Christopher Booker, Director and Curator of Public Art at the London and New York Philharmonic, 2014, in New York Journal</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about the future – about events in the contemporary world that are rendered invisible or completely unavailable to the human voice. But what distinguishes the micro-biennial from its larger biennial counterpart is that the latter builds its narrative around the exhibitionary form of the biennial itself, while the former builds its narrative around the artist-organiser, the biennial, whose curatorial choices and institutional frameworks may be considered as part of a ‘future that can’t necessarily be predicted’.[9] This latter story may or may not be true, but it is the contemporary story, and as a result it is far more accessible to the vagaries of economic, political and social change and imperialism. And so the monolithic biennial – which began as a curatorial choice in the 1980s and is still overwhelmingly a decision for the biennial – has come to dominate contemporary art’s other major exhibitionary forms, including: large-scale contemporary art shows; significant numbers of works on</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about the present. And yet they are objects of consumption, used, of which we are innocent. This is the paradox of the museum: it offers, to be sure, a particular experience of the past, but is also a repository of knowledge about the future that can only be understood by understanding its contents. In that sense, the museum is both ‘the past’ and ‘the present’.[9] The museum is both the past and the present in the modern curatorial sense. But this doesn’t mean that the museum is without meaning or that it becomes meaningless or empty or that we simply don’t want to know what it is that we don’t know. Nor does it mean that the museum should be closed or empty or that it doesn’t connect to our past, present or future. On the contrary, the museum should connect with what we mean when we say it’s a ‘past’ or a</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about the future. 	And this strategy of showing contemporary artworks as past practices, or ‘filths of humanity’, is a recurrent one. In an October 2014 interview with the artist Emily King, Foster and King recalled the 2014 Venice Biennale, in which Foster framed the act of going to Venice as an extension of her previous work, ‘where a few words are all that remain of the human race’. King asked whether she could imagine herself in the future if the demand for animalistic artworks were met in the city. She replied: ‘I can't. I had to grow up without that fantasy. I had to grow up without that.’[9] 	But this self-implication is part of the Foster-King relationship: they both see themselves as artists, intellectuals, and he understands that she must have to be an artist in order to be taken seriously. That this is not an easy thing to do is a testament</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about the present and future of the art world. And so the ‘biennial’ is a fiction created by an art institution that has also created a fictional narrative for the purposes of its business. As biennials have proliferated across the world, in different localities and with different curators, they have also proliferated in Europe, North America and Australia, taking the form of symposia, exhibitions and encyclopedias. And so the ‘biennial’ is a fiction that circumscribes the real, which is a condition that contemporary biennials seek to redress. That is, the real curatorial intervention, negotiated between art institution and artist, emerges through careful negotiation between the two. It is negotiated through negotiation between curators, art professionals and artists. And so the ‘biennial’ becomes what it is: a fiction, and a negotiation. 	But the ‘real’ does not simply become ‘ideal’.</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about the contemporary curatorial role: what kinds of relations between artist and audience are there today? How different are those relations today from those relations of engagement between artist and people? How different are the standards of living in cities like Liverpool today? How different are the standards of living in Third World countries where the biennale is not embedded? How much of the difference is due to the presence of large scale curators, such as Hirsh and Rubens, who are able to command astronomical fees today to engage with the contemporary curatorial appetite for images, and who can use the biennale to engage with the conditions of global habit and urban sprawl, while simultaneously challenging the audiences of curatorial art today? 	In her book The Biennial Condition (1986), Carol Tavris documents the conditions of the biennale in her hometown of Liverpool, as well as in other cities whose history and contemporary populations are often associated with the biennale. She argues that ‘the biennial has</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about the present and future of art. They stand in for what has been lost, and so awaken a memory of what is possible in a given geographical area or population. In this way, they function as a reminder. The image above is a fragment from a 1973 journal entry that was part of the archives of the Archaeological Survey of Egypt, and part of the writings of Prof. Hussein Topal, the curator of Ancient Egypt at the University of Sydney. 	During 1972–74, Prof. Topal worked closely with the archivist Prof. Amram Sethi at the Hebrew University in Jerusalem to sort through the rubble of the Old City and other sites that had been reclaimed following the demolition of entire neighbourhoods. These excavations were part of a wider plan to rebuild the Old City after the destruction of large parts of the Old City, as part of a broader project to create a new urban fabric around the archaeological city of Jerusalem. These projects were also part of a wider archaeological dig at the West</text>
    <text>reimagines the curation of a biennial’s future through what he calls ‘the micro-biennial’ that takes place over the course of the biennial. Micro-biennials are *part of the larger ‘biennial narrative’ that we tell through our artworks, and so they add another level of context and negotiation. 	But micro-biennialism is also a narrative that emerged in response to the biennial, and so it is ‘serving as a counterpoint to the global biennial that emerged during the 1980s and 1990s, and which was, in many ways, all too familiar: boring, monotonous and empty.’[8] And so the narrative of the biennial has reframed the modern curatorial and art-historical relationship, between the art and the biennial, and between the artist and the consumer. Artworks displayed at the Biennale are not only artefacts from the past, but also tell us something about the contemporary curatorial and art-historical relationship that exists between the two. And yet they are also artefacts that tell us something about the relationship between past and future, present and future. This is what William Shakespeare meant when he said that ‘fate plays a part in the destiny of nations: nations are the victims of their own fates.’[9] Fate, of course, is a huge theme in many of the works that we display at the Biennale, and it is this double sense of fate and tragedy that is central to the work of art and the biennial as a whole. But the way in which art is staged, represented, interpreted and distributed globally, and the extent to which that interpretation is driven by the economies of tourism and the remoteness, poverty and homelessness that characterise our contemporary world, requires a different kind of negotiation and negotiation. 	One might even agree that the art must be staged in a particular way in</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and used larger amounts of data.  These developments have put artificial intelligence at the core of many new technological paradigms, and foresee a world in which computers that can think like living things and act like language will play a greater role in the future of humanity.  In an attempt to understand how this might work, Oxford University Press published  An Intuitive Approach to Artificial Intelligence (2015) by Bernard Susskind, Arjun Appadurai, and Mukul Roy in a series of four handpicked chapters covering topics ranging from the physical to the metaphysical to consider in greater depth. The title of the book is a play on words:  infra-red  and   	intelligent artificial intelligence. It is a new kind of metaphysics that looks to the future, and the world beyond, in order to understand how such things might emerge. The essays in this collection move from the realm of biology and the biological to the realm of computer and artificial intelligence, and they implicitly or</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and use.  A deeper understanding of image recognition could one day pave the way for the creation of autonomous weapons or even fully autonomous vehicles.Deep learning is just one of many fronts in a multi-front war being waged right now across industry, academia and government. Other fronts include: urbanization (too many cars, pollution, etc); gender (use of cars for transport but also for exploring and ‘getting lost’); nationalism (standards, laws, symbols); transnational corporations (lobbyists, investors, etc); and geopolitics (international financial institutions, corporations, etc).  A quick look online suggests that many fronts are engaged in this war, with government officials and technologists keen to tell us how to behave in certain ways, to make ourselves ‘better’ or ‘better suited’ to certain environments.  One hopes that, in the future, these kinds of multitudinous philosophical and ideological quandaries will simply be historical footnote-like phenomena that</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and use.  So perhaps the conversational interface is not just a sophisticated interface; it’s also a conceptual interface that creates representations of the world in ways that can be applied to it.  Perhaps, as Carolee Lévesque remarks, the interface is not just a human interface but actively creates worlds through its surface patterns. Such is the language of the interface.  And if the human interface is the language of interface, then perhaps the augmented interface is also the language of interface…  The conversational interface is a linguistic interface that actively creates representations of the world through its surface patterns. Such is the language of the interface.  And if the human interface is the interface, then perhaps the augmented interface is also the interface… The conversational interface is a linguistic interface that actively creates representations of the world through its surface patterns. Such is the interface.  And if the human interface is the interface, then perhaps the augmented interface is the interface… A linguistic interface creates representations of</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and use.  A version of this network was used in the 1997 film Groundhog Day, in which Patrick Stewart as Bill Murray, the narrator of the poem, narrates the same passage over and over again.Deep learning is the underlying mathematics that enable this kind of manipulation, and is the underlying technology that underpins many aspects of artificial intelligence. It was originally hoped that the underlying foundations of deep learning would remain opaque, but recent developments have allowed researchers to gain access to the underlying mathematical structures and thus to begin to investigate ‘how the brain creates imagery and what kinds of ambiguities can be created in the system that allow it to produce imagery’. Deep learning allows the creation of image recognizers and caption deciders, but it is also possible to implement sophisticated image processing that produces still images, segmented images, annotated images, and so forth.  The mechanisms underpinning deep learning remain obscure, but a 2015 Nature Neuroscience article described the underlying principles as being analogous to those of</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and use.  A machine-learning algorithm is a type of programming that seeks to understand the world through processes of experience gathering and inference.  In use today at the API level by service providers and Silicon Valley startups,  	deep learning refers to a type of computer system that is fully internal and self-contained within its context. It is capable of understanding and interacting with data in many cases beyond the scope of its programming.  In other words, it does not see the world through a programmed set of rules, but through the experience of interacting with data itself. Deep learning is enabling new kinds of interaction between humans and the world around them, in much the same way that the Apple Macintosh in the 1990s was enabling new kinds of interaction between humans and the environment.  In use today by academics and research institutions across the globe, deep learning refers to computer systems that simulate the underlying neural networks that control the body’s muscle function and behaviour, as well as other physical systems and actors</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and use.  Finally, in 2017, a research team led by Prof. Ronald Pruett at Carnegie Mellon University applied Deep Learning to image processing in order to create prosthetic limbs that functioned like natural limbs, but with the added ability to sense and do things like touch.  The idea that computers can learn to do things in ways that are qualitatively similar to actual physical limbs presents researchers with unexpected limits. For one thing, the kinds of semantic rules that computers learn – rules governing how objects (objects with characteristics such as shapes or liquids) are paired together – are very different from the kinds of semantic rules that humans grow out of. Another is that objects in a computer system are objects, not ‘things’ – a distinction that computer scientists naturally make when they learn how to deal with data (rules governing how and when data is processed).  Another is that ‘things’ are containers, objects holding information about themselves, actions that occur between objects. For example, a person</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and use.  Finally, in 2017, a research team led by Oxford University’s Dr. Deepak Obhrai and based at the National University of Singapore developed  	Magneto, which they said was the most powerful object-oriented computer ever made. Although Dr. Deepak Obhrai has since become a billionaire, his group’s work in the area of super-computer processing is now focused on deep learning, an area of computer programming that focuses on the underlying mathematical mechanisms underlying the algorithmic nature of data and image processing.4  So, while deep learning continues to gain traction, it is important to contextualize its deployment in a way that properly considers the many different uses that it may play. The diversity of uses that it is deploying to date is impressive, but more needs to be done. In the foreseeable future, deep learning will likely be employed in image processing, but for now, it is being deployed in a more nuanced but still important way:</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and use.  In the journal ‘Neural Computation’, Paul Irish hypothesizes that the capacity for creativity and innovation inherent to modern science and technology may lead to cultural and societal changes driven by the application of these new tools.[8][9]  Irish imagines a society where ‘ordinary people’ can reclaim the capabilities that have been ‘converted’ into useful – instrumental – things – things like cars and homes – and things like Twitter and Facebook – not by reason of individualised epistemological manipulations, but because of the inherent creativity and imagination of modern technology. These new creative technologies, Irish suggests, are capable of freeing ‘ordinary people’ from their dependence on the things that make them human’.[10]  Whether or not this is possible with current technology, Irish nonetheless proposes that we might one day return to pre-technological origins: technology from the beginning of the universe was made manifest in the form of networks, protocols,</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and use.  In fact, in the journal article ‘Neural Networks’, Paul Graham and his team describe their version of artificial intelligence as a way of structuring recursive functions so that recursive procedures can be written in simpler forms; a version of this system could be used to write recursive instructions in the human language.  The question, then, becomes how to imbric such systems with the kinds of agency and humanity that are necessary to address the challenges of our age.  In my view, there are three ways to think about such systems: as moral agents; as emergent moral agents; and as hackers.  The first approach is to treat algorithms as if they are natural moral agents – machines that have principles and understandings that can be changed by human beings – a view shared by many computer scientists.  The second approach is to treat algorithms and data as if they are codes that have meaning beyond their execution on a particular computer. And the third approach is to treat algorithms and data</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. In the future, it may be that a machine, endowed with vast computing resources, responds to the increasing demand for data with what some have dubbed ‘deep learning’.  In other words, the language of the recurrent neural network may not merely capture and process data; it may actively create and process new data in ways that can be applied to existing images, sounds, and data. Deep learning is the application of mathematical models of image processing that harness natural language processing to identify and classify images, detect human speech, and more.  As of 2015, deep learning was employed in image processing at the University of Toronto’s Media Lab, and was reported to produce impressive results, including the ability to identify individuals in images, people in audio recordings, and text that have been digitally altered.  Furthermore, according to a 2015 Nature article, researchers at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology had created a similar kind of neural network to recognize images of living things, but was simpler to program and was able to distinguish between natural and artificial life forms.4  So, while there is still a lot of research to do on the neural network and its applications, we do know that reinforcement learning is a kind of machine learning – that is, the application of mathematical formulas to implement neural networks in software – one that is deeply rooted in the physical world. Machine learning is the merging of mathematics and physics in the service of life itself, and it is being driven by a kind of mathematical imperative. Machine learning algorithms operate on large amounts of data, constantly sampling from a massive data set, and thus constantly face new data sets and architectures that are more complex to program against. In this way, the algorithms can continually evolve and adapt to meet the evolving needs of the social web, while retaining the primacy of living things in the system at the same time.  One could ask if there is something fundamentally different about how humans relate to data, and if that is the function of mathematics or physics. I</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do things that are ‘out there’, and to infer meaning from those things. More generally, every human capacity for action is imbued with the potential to be entertained by machinery. Every thought, gesture, and action that occurs in the world is potentially predictive of the future – whether that future is friendly or not – and so every encounter between human and machine is subject to the potential that a future might be wholly different from the present. This is why so-called emergent behaviors, natural or automatic systems, generate contingency, sometimes terrible consequences for human beings, in the form of war, poverty, or other pernicious outcomes. In general, if the systems that are the products of human thought cannot be trusted to act with consistency and predictability in the future, we cannot rely on them to do so in the present. This is one reason why technological innovation and science fiction are so unnerving. They suggest otherwise-optimal futures for readers and viewers.Why are human capacities for</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do things that are ‘more natural’ than the human can. This is why so many computer programmers find themselves drawn to action-oriented programming, which embraces emergent phenomena and the unpredictable. It is also why artists, including Jan Montefiore, Noel Burch and Noel Ben-Tovim, have incorporated programming into their art. Art has many faces, but none are natural-born artists. Its natural tendency is to face the world through programmed images and sounds. In this sense, Ada Lovelace is not just saying we should all be programmers; she is saying we should all seek to understand and relate to the world through code. In this sense, Ada Coles could be considered a proto-programmer. As Ada Coles herself explains, programming is not just about programming, but ‘includes all the operations that computers perform, such as data processing, manipulation, and data encryption’.[7]Programming languages are written to automate particular tasks, and thus machines</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do things that are ‘out there’, but cannot possibly be represented or observed with language. In other words, programming enables the machine to imagine ‘things that aren’t there’.[7] And this is precisely what Turing, Goebbels and all those other pseudo-intellectual figures in between called the New Machine. It is a set of abstractions that live inside of the physical world but lack the core essence of what makes the world real. It is a metaphor that makes no sense outside of the given context. A metaphor is a metaphor that subverts the real meaning of the world around it. It exploits the ambiguity and metaphors of language to produce ever more perfect representations of things that never are ‘there’. Its power is in its ability to manipulate ambiguity and create ever more elaborate images of things that never are ‘there’.In other words, language – and in particular, the implied semantics of language – play a fundamental role</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do much more than it can express in the form of commands. More specifically, this understanding of the world as actionable objects called ‘metainterfaces’ allows the machine to understand and produce imagery – imagery that is both physical and poetic – that is unique to its environment. Such imagery is fundamentally understood as a ‘language of action’.[7] The third and final iteration of Moore’s visual poem – entitled Present Tense – documents the events of September 11th, and their evocation of the contemporaneous political situation. In this version of the poem, the events are brought to life through imagined sequences of events that occur on that fateful day in history. The actions of the participants are brought to life through imagined models of the world. The result is an imagined ‘language of action’ that is both expansive and finite, ever on the verge of becoming ambiguous and unpredictable. This is the third poem in the series, and it is a beautiful and moving poem</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do things that are ‘out there’, and thereby to act. This is why programming languages encourage users to explore ‘more than just the page’ of the platform they are given. Programs can look for patterns, collect data, make mistakes, and so forth. More generally, every programming language encourages users to ask deeper questions, to explore more worlds, and to do more with less. This last aspect of programming is what M. Butterfly López de la Torre means by when she says: programming is the enabling of the machine’s capacity to think and to understand more clearly this world beyond the page. More generally, every kind of programming invites the human programmer to expand the meaning of the programming he or she creates. Every kind of programming is ultimately a kind of play, and every programmer is a master of his or her kind of programming. (What could be more fitting, perhaps, for this article than a lament by Ada Lovelace, whose programming languages</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do things that are ‘perceivable’ within the confines of its environment. In other words, programming enables the machine to imagine and do things that are not ‘perceivable’ in the world around it. This is in sharp contrast to the rigid nature of human language, which requires that statements such as ‘this is a computer program’ be taken literally. Languages also offer a number of other powerful ways of organising complex processes and phenomena. For example, when a process such as the calculation of a stock market relies on data – the mathematical formulas underpinning the system – information is conveyed across the system in the form of electrical current. As a consequence of this phenomenon, it is possible to construct a mathematical model of the system that captures the flow of current through the system; such a model replicates the behaviour of the system as a whole. In effect, the programming of the system creates new understanding and action within the system. This kind of understanding and action is deeply embedded within</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do things that are ‘perceivable’ in the human realm. More generally, every programming is an action between subject and object (in this case, humans and computers). There are many forms of abstraction in the world of programming, but the most recognisable one is the kind that takes place within the context of the computer itself. Here, action in programming is described by Ada Lovelace’s Neural Library, or Object Oriented Paradigms, where the programmer puts her model of the world in terms of processes that evolve within the systems she or he works with. These terms capture the essence of what she calls ‘the emergent’ properties of the system: behaviour, for instance, or ‘instant properties’ that emerge from the system when it is programmed. More generally, every programming is an ontological argument between subject and object (in the strict sense of the term’s application to all living things). Here, the question is whether or not</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do things that are ‘out there’ in the world, but which are ‘out of this world’ in the context of a civilization. And, as Lovelace puts it, programming is not just about doing things, but also about the ‘enduring mystery of what is beyond the limits of human perception and understanding’.[7]In this sense, Ada Lovelace is arguing that our current obsession with the notion of the ‘enduring mystery of what is beyond the limits of human perception and understanding’] obscures much more interesting behaviour within the system that is constituting the ‘real’. In contemplating the nature of beauty, programming and artificial intelligence, she is arguing that we face a more fundamental question: what kind of relationship does language have with reality? Language is a construct – built into the very language itself – and thus questions of reality inevitably bring us to questions of language. For Ada Lovelace, the answer is a res</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do things that could not be possible in the presence of formal and symbolic rules. More specifically, this understanding of action in language is what allows the programmer to create and interpret objects and processes that are ‘alive but interpretable’[7] – capable of understanding and interacting with the world in ways that are not reducible to subject and object.Programming languages are seen as the solution to a ‘problem that cannot be solved with programming’. This is not to suggest that programmers are innocent, but is instead to question the kind of interpretation of human language that leads to the creation of autonomous agents capable of understanding and interacting with the world. This kind of ‘interpretability’ is seen as a fundamental premise of programming, and programming is seen as the solution to a problem that is not understood or resolved. This kind of internal conflictualy between subject and object is seen as an essential aspect of understanding and action in the world. In programming, subject and object are seen</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines, and extends it to all living things.] The second version of the work addresses the physical world through metaphor, or, as Ada Lovelace puts it, ‘the language of action is action in language’.[6] In other words, the physical world – the world as it is constituted and embodied by machines – butts up against an assumed future ideal of a world populated by autonomous agents capable of acting on their knowledge (how to put it crudely?). In this sense, ‘language of action’ is intimately related to the physical world – action in language is action in physical language. This is why computer programming enables machines to understand and execute complex patterns of thought – complex systems built on tacit understanding and emotion. The beauty of programming is that it is completely internal, unlike the rigid rules of human language. It is understood as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (the human subject and the machine object). Thus programming enables the machine to see and do things that are ‘nonhuman’, ‘artificial’ and even ‘technologically inhuman’. And this sense of ambiguity and unpredictable outcomes is a source of much of the power and mystery of the technological future.On a conceptual level, then, there are three versions of ‘human language’: (1) the physical human language – the set of rules, symbols and procedures that humans employ to communicate; (2) the abstract human language – the set of principles and emotions that machines employ to execute those rules; and (3) the implicit or presentational human language – the set of principles and emotions that do not incorporate rules, symbols or procedures but instead rely on the environment, habit and experience. All three versions of ‘human language’ engage with notions of author and audience, but differ in that the language of action is understood not as an entity but as a series of actions that take place between subject and object (subject and audience),</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s
    <text>curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s the adoption of an objectifying subject that comes with the job. And maybe, in the UK at large, we choose to see these objectsifying subaltern street corners as something that we can all be proud of. But when we actually do get to know these people, we see different sides to them, and we have to work through some of the complexities. I remember, years ago (around 2005), we tried to turn a blind eye to the fact that these areas of the city were being taken over by developers, because we didn’t see it as a threat to our utopian vision of a ‘City of Glass’. But then, some years later, we decided to actually look at what was happening in those neighbourhoods. We decided to start a campaign called ‘Redevelopment Matters’ and, by Redevelopment Matters, we decided to refer to areas that were in trouble, which was an effective way of bringing these neighbourhoods into the narrative. We then</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s true, but I have no evidence to support such a presumption.  The leshy is an object that represents and encapsulates a certain kind of experience: a particular kind of London street vernacular, and indeed a particular kind of urban environment. It’s a name that comes from the pamphlets that accompanied the articles, and it’s a verb that’s used to describe things that happen in the world outside of the pages that we find on a newspaper. The  Leshy is a name that comes from the pamphlets that accompanied the articles, and it’s a verb that’s used to describe things that happen in the world outside of the newspaper. The introduction to the London Street vernacular (1883–1907) begins: ‘The London Stuarts were a queer and romantic club of artists, writers, poets, and other creative people formed in 1883 by the eponymous magazine. Its six issues from March</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s the Europeanisation of the capital that’s happening, and we are part of that process.  	But what does it mean to be ‘laid back’? What does it mean to be cosmopolitan? What does it mean to be egalitarian? What does it mean to be cosmopolitan locally? What does it mean to be cosmopolitan internationally? What do we mean by ‘London’ when we talk about the UK? 	What does it mean when we speak of cosmopolitan cities? In contemporary parlance, it’s a synonym for ‘global’. And indeed, as any Londoner who has been to London will tell you, the UK’s global reputation as a city of spectacular cultural institutions and opulent residential neighbourhoods is a myth. The UK is an ‘entity’, with its own particular set of characteristics and attributes, which can neither be pinned nor claimed. It’s true that the UK</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s the way that the media represents London in its quest to be ‘global’. But what’s novel about London is that every now and then a reporter from a different newspaper will visit and find a place that reveals itself as London. They’ll find a bakery, a coffee house, a clothing shop, a jewellery shop, a melon shop, and so on. And every time they do that, they’ll find another corner shop, a supermarket or a bakery that advertises a product from that corner shop. They’ll find a bit of history relevant to the place they’re in, and they’ll learn something new about London. And every time they do that, they’ll find a new corner shop, a supermarket or a bakery that’s closed or empty.  This is what happens when you stop growing and start being consumed by the metainterface.  A reporter from the Daily Telegraph came to</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s the extent to which the machine is being fed the right vernacular.Whatever the case, the fact that we encounter it so frequently doesn’t mean that we don’t experience it. Like so many other aspects of the English Dream, it’s connected to some degree to some degree, and that’s why it’s called the English Dream. The question is, what degree of that is connected to the machine? That was a complex question to answer.First of all, there’s the misconception that you have to be alive to experience the English Dream: you can have the Dream in one of its many guises. For me, and I think for many of the people who experienced the Dream in their lifetimes, the answer is yes. But there’s a difference between life and death, between dream and waking reality. For me, waking reality meant waking up every morning and having to deal with the fact that I wasn’</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s the way of the world. But what a world it is. A world so different from the one we live in that it seems unreal, so foreign even.  And that’s what a leshy is: a thing that exists outside of our world that we can't define or put into words. A thing that we can only imagine exists.In recent years, however, we’ve begun to put together ideas that can be put into words. We have a set of words that describe what a leshy is, and what a neighbourhood is. And sometimes a set of images that illustrate that idea. A set of symbols that point to where that word or image is found. And sometimes a neighborhood is just an idea. The point is to find a way to put those ideas into words that are as accessible as possible. Without getting bogged down in the details, ideas, and figures of each neighbourhood, we can create a map that helps us find what we need,</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s the ubiquity of the newspaper that makes us forget how different it is from the city we live in. The wager that a newspaper can be found in virtually every corner of the UK reinforces the idea that it’s everywhere, yet inaccessible; the newspaper cannot be found anywhere.  Borders, indeed. But the wager is that the reader can, if he wants to, locate the newspaper nearest to where he’s located, and read the same newspaper online. The ability to find the newspaper nearest to where he’s located is the ability to read the newspaper offline. The paper is the locus of knowledge; it’s what we refer to as ‘the Common Good’. And so, the common good is policed. It’s regulated. It’s suppressed. It’s found in virtually every book published in the UK in the 1990s and early 2000s. And so the reader is placed in a situation in which</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s time to revisit that cliché. There’s a reason why tabloid journalism flourished in the 1980s and early 1990s: there was a money to be made from it. The tabloid trade was a necessary by-product of the growing economy, and the tabloid form was a way for journalists to make a bit of money from the front page of a newspaper. The tabloid journalist would publish the story on the front page of the newspaper, alongside a series of other stories that would tell similar stories. The basic idea was that the newspaper would present a different view of events from the way that the powerful organised them. This may have had some value in an economic sense: a newspaper with a story that is consistent with the prevailing economic narrative is more likely to have a voice in public life, because that’s what powerful voices in society do. But as the economy sagged, and the front page of the newspaper got smaller, the tabloid journalist’s role shifted from telling the dominant narrative to</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s the way that the media represents us. So, what does it mean to ‘lose the plot’? What does it mean to ‘wake up one day and find out that the plot has just been rewritten? How do we start to unravel the narratives that are constructed around us?What can we learn from each other? What can we learn from the past, that we can act upon and change the course of our own futures? When we learn something new, we’re making it up as we go along. What can we learn from the past, that we can act upon and change the course of our futures? Our texts below were written for and with the L.A. based LGBTQ+ community. I brought out some of the thoughts and narratives of the people I met during the journey that I produced ‘The Stages’ – the text was produced in response to the death of a character in the BBC’s Blackadder, which I co-</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] that’s reading everything that’s written, from the street, from the blog, from the magazine. It’s reading every word that comes out of that machine. If that’s not a nightmare, I don’t know what is. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a dream. When you’re in a loch, you’re in a nightmare.‘Blank’, as the saying goes.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleThere’s a misconception about what a leshy is. Most of us don’t encounter it, or perhaps we don’t care to. When we encounter it, we tend to assume that we’re dealing with a common London street vernacular that can be found in virtually every newspaper in the UK. It’s a cliché that’s too familiar; perhaps it’s time to reconsider that assumption. Leshies don’t exist in a typical British novel, nor do they have the ubiquity, globalisation, and material riches of contemporary urban centres. But they’re there, and they’re everywhere, and they’re everywhere very sensual, emotional and mysterious. The fact that they’re twentysomething women, living in underground cabarets, or in derelict buildings, or in the back of vans, or in the unglamorous but lucrative but increasingly dehumanising jobs of receptionists or cleaners, or in the vast service industries of flats and hotels, or in the higher but no less hazardous but no less glamorous professions, such as mining or banking, is all we need to know to feel that we’re part of a canonised but cosmopolitan but also highly stratified history. It’s as though the language of the leshie is some kind of universal shorthand that encompasses every</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In these new jobs and networks, people streamed into ever denser geographical range, travelling much faster than the networks could take them. And so the demand for ever more energy became ever more apparent, fuelling ever more elaborate energy resources needed to support the growth of ever denser amounts of data.For more than just the infrastructure companies and data-hungry businesses, the biennials also provided the cover image for the increased numbers who visited. The biennial’s popularity at the time was due in large part to its accessibility: it was readily apparent across borders, and the iconic image was often shared across national media. In addition, the importance of the biennial as a publicly visible event grew as the post-WWII economic miracle unfolded. More and more people were coming to see the art fairs and the biennials, and as a result the biennial count grew. At the height of this, there were six biennials in London per year, and they were followed by</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In these new jobs and networks, people traveled far more easily and more affordably. New trade routes developed connecting East and West, and new markets developed in response to regional differences in size, colour, tastes and religions. All of these factors made it possible for workers to connect with friends and family abroad, and to travel more widely.New technologies made it easier to monitor workers, and to track workers across the landscape. From the mid-1990s, when the release of the Personal Computer Operating System (Peacemaker) revolutionised corporate IT, to the arrival of satellite imagery and mapping technologies, it became possible to trace workers across the landscape in a vast number of industries, employing tens of millions of people. While this may seem like a load of rubbish now, back in the day when people lived on the fringe of society, it was quite the opposite: it signaled a shift in the balance of power between the very rich and everyone else, and it signaled the end of the age of big business</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In these new jobs, there was little concern about transport or logistics; much emphasis was placed on the glorification of workers’ bodies as animate parts capable of performing complex functions. In these jobs, the roles of humans were reduced to interchangeable parts, and the automation of tasks was the desired by creators rather than the victims of modern society.In this technological society, the distinction between producer and consumer became increasingly blurred. New technologies such as drones and robots are capable of performing tasks that would have once required highly trained workers, and can therefore be seen as disruptive in their implications. But in the age of abundance, the distinction between producer and consumer is becoming increasingly difficult to distinguish, and in an increasingly urban and information society, the distinction between productive and unproductive spaces is likely to remain ambiguous. In an increasingly information society, the autonomous individual will be able to become something like a cloud, gathering data and knowledge across multiple sites in an ever expanding web of data that will hopefully be indistinguishable from data collected by humans</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In these ways, the end of the industrial age could be seen as a point of great technological potential.Yet the end of the age of the industrial workplace did not come without cost and disruption. The growth of biotechnology, for example, brought with it a proliferation of toxic waste sites and the proliferation of non-human animals capable of being genetically engineered to be bug-eaters or energy vampires. The proliferation of these kinds of corporateised forms of life also brought with it a proliferation of surveillance and policing technologies, some of which were far more advanced and expansive than was possible at the turn of the century. The proliferation of surveillance and policing technologies means that it is no longer possible to simultaneously operate within the parameters of the workplace and simultaneously demand and carry out a wide range of destructive activities. The proliferation of drone warfare, for example, means that it is no longer possible to simultaneously employ armed personnel and that task forces now have the capabilities of an organisation. The proliferation of social networking and the connected car also</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In these new environments, the qualities that made the industrial workplace possible were put into question. What we might call the ‘knowledge economy’ has become immensely more complex, and it is this emergence that falls under the heading of technologisation. But while new technologies made it possible to employ ever larger numbers of people in ever denser geographical range, they also raised the productivity of existing workers – workers with skills that could be honed and appended to production lines, or incorporated into production processes that required greater precision and skill, through what Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel term ‘technological unemployment’.Technological unemployment meant that people without the requisite training or education could not find jobs in the knowledge economy; they either stayed home with the kids, or went to work in the factories where the robots took over. The practice of ‘hiring robots’ quickly spread throughout the global south, and now looks to exist in only a few cities in China and the Middle</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In these new contexts of abundance and surplus, the crunch came when demand failed to meet supply, or when infrastructure failed to deliver what was needed. As a consequence, people who remained in the workplace had to be rescued from their jobs in order to satisfy ever-greater consumer appetites. As industries everywhere shifted production to locations with greater economies of scale, there was a corresponding shift in the role of people in the workplace: people with skillsets to deliver the goods but no means to consume them. This is the historical trajectory of technological capitalism, and it is the historical trajectory of social destruction.In 2016, a group of young people from the Bay Area convened under the name ‘Silicon Beach Manifesto’ to protest against the loss of innocence and wonder of the era during which they were growing up. The manifesto referenced events from their privileged school years in the 1980s: the day Michael Jordan retired as a champion basketball player, the day Nintendo released its iconic green and yellow Game Boy, and</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In these ways, the production of ever more complex goods and services could be performed by anyone with access to ever more powerful tools. In the words of Isaac Asimov, ‘Any sufficiently advanced technology is indistinguishable from common sense…[and] is indistinguishable in its effects from long term storage and processing technologies that can […] replicate natural phenomena such as weather and climate […] [but] is indistinguishable from zero year nano-computers that can […] evolve […] into self-aware and responsive […] systems’.2   	In the twenty-first century, we seem to be living through a period of economic malaise. Productivity is projected to grow at an annual rate of 2.5% in 2016, far faster than in 1990, and although this is still a relatively modest rate of growth when accounting for inflation, it is faster than in any other advanced economy. Productivity is a product of many things – the value created by the interaction of people (including labor), the exchange of commodities</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In these ways, the pace of technological innovation – which could be categorised as either high-performance or ‘high-resolution’ – could be adjusted according to the changing needs and desires of the firm.New kinds of mobility were made possible by the spread of computing and communications technology. In these ways, the pace of technological innovation could be categorised as both spatial and temporal.New kinds of mobility are made possible by the spread of computing and communications technology. In these ways, the infrastructure required to support them could be categorised as either ‘high-performance’ or ‘high-resolution’ – that is, capable of meeting the demands of a rapidly expanding global economy in the age of the information explosion.And thus, in this narrative that I have been constructing since 2015, the story that I am constructing is that of the ‘Hambrecht-Weilermann Complex’ that I created in my basement in the Swiss Army Museum as a kind of temporary</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In these ways, the pace of technological innovation allowed firms to more fully engage their workforces, allowing for ever larger data collections and storage, and allowing for ever more autonomous ways of processing information.New technologies made it possible to balance people and machines, enabling workers to thrive in settings where the machines become ever more like sensors and data capture devices. As a result, there was a proliferation of automation in the workplace, which in turn bred a proliferation of autonomous technologies, which in turn bred a proliferation of possible workplace configurations. In the final analysis, there was only so much that could be done to quell the growing automation crisis before it threatened not just the resources of the planet but also its very existence.The end of the industrial age signaled a shift away from the source of much of the wealth generated in the West – namely, the production of goods and services across borders – to the production of wealth internally. The result was that much of what was valued along the peripheries of the planet was exported.</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and robotics’s potential to transform not only the workplace but also the social, economic, and cultural landscape of the planet.In their book The End of Work: Innovation, Brutality, and the Future of Employment, Nils Muiznie and Peter Weibel detail how the end of the industrial age ushered in a new era of abundance and abundance of resources, increasingly apparent to be the product of inexhaustible natural resources. As the end of production lines replaced humans in most factory settings, and as demand for goods and services increased, so too did the infrastructure required to support them. In the wake of this demand, technological innovations such as computer chips, hard drives, networking equipment, virtual private servers, telecommunication networks and data capture and transmission (for which IT companies would develop industry-standard tools) made it possible to deploy ever larger numbers of workers in ever denser geographical range (high-speed internet access and ubiquitous wireless networks were standardised in the West at the time). In these new jobs, lifestyles and networks, people could be transported anywhere on the planet in an instant, and afforded whatever facilities and rights they so desired. Yet these new jobs also demanded new modes of collective organisation capable of supporting the workers in ways that were not dependent on the resources on which they were built. New forms of social organisation were required to accommodate the millions of people now employed in the new economy of sharing, and to permit these new kinds of collective organisation to take root. In short, new forms of labour could not be expected to thrive on the pre-industrial model of the workplace, which indeed shifted ever further from the site of labour, and from the site of wealth. New forms of labour demanded a radically different kind of organisation. This kind of radical organisation lay in rebuilding the capacities of the urban and its peripheries, in rebuilding the social life of postindustrial places, and in rebuilding the planet.I N T he late 1970s and early 1980s saw a rapid proliferation of various</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a
    <text>curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a symbol of what we might like to happen: the emergence of a new breed of artists, enfranchised and empowered by the emergence of a hummingbird. The emergence of new breeders is a main theme in Margaret Atwood’s work, and she is no doubt aware that many of her readers find Atwood’s work feel a little dated. She introduces a reader to Cormac McCarthy’s On Killing Eve (1950), in which a dissident British army surgeon is cast as a surgeon practising in Vietnam. The novel is set in the year 2075, and the scene is set during the height of the Cold War. The scene takes place in the year 2142, and McCarthy is writing the screenplay for a film based on his experiences in Vietnam. The novel is set in Vermont, so we can identify with the fictional patient Mitchell and her fellow patient Aftab, both of whom are fictionalised in the film. We can also identify with the town of</text>
    <text>curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a good match for the challenges we face as an urban community. The question that arises is what order of individuals can harness the city to achieve this growth frontier? I propose that there are two levels of authority, or ‘levels’: the city as a ‘system’ and the metropolis as a ‘tribe’. The city is made up of many different levels, and different levels are nested in and embedded in the city. The level of the street, or the street level, arrives at from time to time at the city ‘tribe’ – it is a pre-conceived idea, but one that emerges from the city’s momentum. The metropolis, on the other hand, emerges from the city’s momentum, but only to a limited extent. It is made up of many different levels, and different levels inhabit different neighbourhoods. ‘Levels’ are not given places; rather, they are positions between and within</text>
    <text>curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a valuable ecological observation. We notice the sprawl happening because we have become so accustomed to it. The film then cuts to a future with a city that is becoming ever more dense and unmanaged. The film shows that the sprawl that we are witnessing is the result of a chaotic allocation of resources. Resources, by their very nature, exist in a constant quest for survival. The metropolis is losing its shape. Resources, by their very nature, cannot exist in a fixed state. Thus, we can say that the resource crunch is a by-product of the metropolis. The challenge now becomes how to structure the city in the future so that it can respond to the problem of sprawl in a way that is not a catastrophe for all of us. I believe that the answer is in the development of new modes of exchange that take into consideration the emergence of completely new economic forms and social formations. These modes of exchange do not merely accommodate the exchange of existing things, but create entirely new ways</text>
    <text>curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a visual aphrodisiac, appealing to our visual senses, capturing the magic of the night sky and the city at large. The city, in turn, harnesses the magical hummingbird to capture our attention and thereby foster growth: the more the city emits, the more it is seen as desirable, even magical. The visual aphrodisiac aspect of the hummingbird catches our fancy. We pay attention because we want to; we cannot ignore the things that attract our attention, and we are attracted to things because we recognise their similarity; something in our nature is amiss. The visual aphrodisiac aspect of the hummingbird also works against it: the more the city is managed according to a centrally planned, ‘smart growth’ narrative, the less attractive and magical the future city will be. The city will be managed according to the same set of priorities and values, but with a difference: the priorities will be based on need, and the values of the new urbanisation.</text>
    <text>curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a image that demands our immediate attention, and because it is a punctum that is both alien and familiar. We are captivated by the seemingly new element that has entered the city. We are drawn to the hummingbird because we think, ‘That thing that flies, does that thing that flies’. The film then cuts to a shot of the hummingbird in flight, and the caption, ‘That thing that flies, does that thing that flies’. We see that the hummingbird is being chased by a dinosaur, which is thought to have sharp beaks and large, black eyes. We are also shown that the hummingbird is in danger of being eaten up by the larger dinosaur, which is also thought to have sharp beaks and large, black eyes. The scene changes from raptor-like to bird-like, to before the bird even takes off, and from bird-like to dinosaur-like. We are captivated by the change. The hummingbird becomes</text>
    <text>curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a species that needs to be watched, and because it does well in the film. The hummingbird has developed a reputation as a scavenger, and the film shows how this is possible. In the film, we see how the hummingbird eats organic matter, breaking it down to supply the celluloid in its beak. As the film progresses, we learn that the humbug is not alone in her pursuit of food. Other creatures, including birds, also prey on the plant material that makes up the shell of the beak. The film concludes with a series of images that capture the humbug’s behaviour as it examines the celluloid in more detail. In each of the images, the celluloid is examined in turn, as the hummingbird makes her way through the material, eventually arriving at the part that catches her attention – the part that shows the celluloid lining the inside of the beak. In the sequence, the humbug makes a number of interesting choices, choosing to expose</text>
    <text>curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a familiar one: the city represents the excess of resources, pollution and excess of goods; in pursuit of resources and goods, hummingbirds fly past at great speeds. The movie then shows us a world in which the city represents a limit to be conquered, or better yet, to collapse.‘It’s time to draw a breath, to catch your breath, to slow down, to take stock, and then, just for a moment, to admire the beauty of a city’s growth and development’. The hummingbird appears as a metaphor for what is expected of the city: a certain amount of growth, pollution and excess, to be controlled. The control mechanism is a kind of computer, or ‘smart phone’s’ control system that continually monitors and records physical and mental activity in the city, constantly collects and sorts data and makes inferences about the world around it. The idea is that, in order to maintain a certain level of growth and development</text>
    <text>curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a powerful symbol of the inefficiency of the city and the need for action. The city is a capital trap, and individuals like yourself who are part of the system are part of the mechanism that traps the birds in cages of urban misery. But birds don’t make machines. The metropolis does.And the metropolis is not inevitable to become what it once were: beautiful, fulfilling, and rich again. The city is a capital trap and individuals like you who are part of the system are part of the mechanism that traps the birds in cages of urban misery. But birds don’t make machines. The metropolis does.Instead, the task is to reimagine the city in ways that maximize the potential of the city in ways that minimize the inefficiency of the city and the need for action. The aim of this work is to help create a public realm where the city’s inherent contradictions can be overcome. This means helping the city become what it was before the economic and</text>
    <text>curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a visual metaphor that operates at a deeper level than the specific image that appears on the screen. When we turn our attention away from the image, we can ‘see the big picture’. If the image is not sharp enough, we can ‘see the dots connected’. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a visual metaphor that operates at a deeper level than the image that appears on the screen. When we turn our attention away from the image, we can ‘see the big picture’. If the image is not sharp enough, we can ‘see the dots connected’.  So, the next time you sit down to a nice Italian restaurant, or a nice London pub, or a nice old-fashioned English pub, think of all the places that have been taken and all the jobs that have been created or lost because of urban sprawl. That sounds eerily familiar. That is, of course, the image that comes</text>
    <text>curated by a machine. The film is a kind of ‘catch-all’ for the persistent problem of city sprawl, with areas of the metropolis seen as ripe for the picking of what is often described as ‘the urban jungle’. There is no urban jungle in the true sense of the word: cities do have issues of sprawl and development, and a natural capital allocation problem plays itself out in the city. However, the film shows an interesting alternative: ‘A city that can grow without issue is a city that can grow rich and powerful’. In other words, the future city is possible, but only if the city grows rich and powerful enough to support a future growth rate that is on the order of what we would like to see in the world. There is a tension here between the ambitions of the city as a whole, and the ambitions of each of the individuals who make up the metropolis. The metaphor of the hummingbird catches our attention because it is a symbol of the future that is visible only at the moment of its emergence. The metaphor of the hummingbird itself serves another purpose here: it tells us something about the future that is not yet here. The image captures the growth of the metropolis in the image of a hummingbird, capturing its shape and its activity, its sound, and thereby its character. It is the image of growth at a very exponential rate, both visually and audibly. The metropolis becomes visible only when it has produced enough to feed itself, and then only as long as the metropolis produces more and more. ‘Speculation One: A Conversation with Rafael Cardoso of Macondo’s Unmesh Areas’, conducted by Nasser Rabbat of the Macondo Cultural Center and Rafael Cardoso of the Macondo Oil Company, conducted in English and Portuguese, 2017. Photo courtesy of Rafael Cardoso.PreviousNextFuturist Library / Futurist Library / Macondo</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what that means.When we talk about biennials, we tend to mean places that actively engage with their place in the world, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we generally mean places that actively incorporate or recreate aspects of their past, but we don’t always know what those past practices are. When we speak of ‘art’ we tend to mean socially engaged art, but we don’t always know what that means.When we talk about biennials, we tend to mean places that actively engage with their place in the world, but we don’t always know what that means. When we talk about ‘regeneration’ we tend to mean places that actively incorporate or recreate aspects of their past, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘art’ we tend</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of biennials, we usually mean places that actively engage with their place in art, but we don’t always know what those engaging with their place in art means. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively support and foster them, but we don’t always know what that means.When I began to explore the idea of the biennial in relation to the city in 2015, the idea of the biennial as a major art form, and the city in particular, came as a surprise to me. I had assumed that biennials were places where the artist was confined to allow time for her or his art to develop, and the art to be developed, into a significant work of art form. But the idea that artists were confined to allow time for their art to mature and become works of art seemed completely divorced from the actual development and maturity of art. The</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what that means.When we talk of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in the world, but we don’t always know what the boundaries are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we generally mean areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are.When we talk about biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what the boundaries are. When we talk about ‘space’ we generally mean the physical world around us, but we don’t always know what that means.When we talk about biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in the world, but we don’t always know what the boundaries are.When we talk about organisms, we generally mean life itself, but we don’t always</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what that means.When we speak of biennials, we usually mean places that actively engage with their place in the world, and actively seek to create a parallel universe to the one we live in, seeking to make it different from the one we have today.For example, the Biennale of Sydney started as a biennale, but as it turned out, aesthetically speaking, the new age of transparency and in-depth exploration of nature was already well underway. So the Biennale was already engaging with aspects of the natural world that were not natural, and these engaged with aspects of the anthropologist’s job description that were already somewhat natural, since the biennale is usually a gathering of people seeking to understand and celebrate the world in a particular way. So the Biennale’s engagement with nature came out of a place of naturalism, and it was an engagement that was realist, even though it</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in art and in culture, but we don’t always know what that means.When I started The New Inquiry in 2003, the term ‘biennial’ seemed like an oxymoron. I argued that the reason why biennials were so prevalent in the US was that they were investments in the future, in the future of humanity, in the future of the planet. The problem with this particular oxymoron was that it entailed a commitment to the future, which inevitably follows from some kind of fundamental assumption about the nature of the human condition. So the assumption about the nature of the human condition meant that we had to actively work to change the future, which inevitably entailed making painful choices now. And this is precisely what biennials did. They demanded of their audiences a future with surprises, which inevitably followed</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of biennials, we tend to mean places that actively seek to map society out of existence, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of biennial, we tend to mean places that actively seek to intervene in their local context, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we tend to mean areas that can be reclaimed whole, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of biennials, we tend to mean places that actively seek to intervene in their local context, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘regeneration’, we tend to mean areas that can be reclaimed whole, but we don’t always know what that means. 	When I started as curator of the Liverpool Biennial in 2010</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘regeneration planning’ we are generally talking about developing strategies to reclaiming areas when they are abandoned by their developers, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are.When I started in the 1970s, the idea of the biennial was significantly different. The reason was that the museum was the main outlet for artists and their ideas to be expressed. The biennial was a destination for ideas and images, and not necessarily an expression of them. Now there is a strong bias towards the image, and the biennial is the main venue for that. There are of course many other ways to engage with the present, but the biennial is the dominant one right now. The emergence of other cultural forms has stimulated a new wave of artists to engage with the present through art projects and festivals. The biennial is the rarest of institutions, and the arts are its most difficult</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with the role of art in shaping our cultural and social experience, but we don’t always know what that means.When we talk about biennials, we tend to mean places that actively engage with the role of art in shaping their geographical position, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of biennials, we tend to mean places that are able to sustain their cultural impact through the direct or indirect support of art, yet are also capable of generating additional cultural impact through investment in arts education, production and dissemination. When we speak of biennials, we tend to mean places that actively engage with their place in society through cultural tourism, but we don’t always know what that means.When we talk about biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in terms of art</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what that means.When we consider the future, we tend to imagine things better. We imagine a less violent, more sustainable world. We imagine a world in which there are no wars, in which suffering and death are replaced by something better. We tend to imagine a world in which building projects don’t happen in the middle of the night, or in the middle of the day in the middle of the city. We tend to imagine a world in which there are no epidemics or disasters.We don’t yet know whether the autonomous elements of these ideas are really the best ones, and we don’t yet know what changes in our world would happen if those autonomous elements became clear. What we do know is that in the coming years, it will be much harder to create a biennial that engages with the world as a whole, or works through a singularity, than it will be to create one that engages with specific</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines. The second is the issue of autonomy. When we speak of ‘autonomy’ we generally mean the ability to take decisions for one’s self, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of human rights, we are generally talking about the ability to draw lines and draw boundaries, but we don’t always know what those boundaries are. When we speak of self-healing materials, we are generally talking about materials that can heal themselves, but we don’t always know what that means. When we speak of ‘spaces’ we are generally talking about real areas, but we don’t always know what those areas are. When we speak of ‘regeneration’ we are generally talking about areas that can be reclaimed, but we don’t always know what those reclaimed areas are. When we speak of biennials, we generally mean places that actively engage with their place in society, but we don’t always know what those arts and cultural institutions mean.When we talk about biennials, we usually mean something that is more along the lines of collections. Collections are extremely typical of biennials. We have a general idea of what a biennial is, but we don’t always know what a collection is. For instance, the art fair that we have in Lisbon every two years, the Biennale of Modern Art, is a collection. It includes works from every possible discipline, and it is through this collection of works that the Biennale of Modern Art, itself, advances. It collects and assembles, and it does so with ever greater regularity, since, like all biennials, it is a collection first and a collection of users. It is a collection that is ever more reliant on the city as a site of circulation, and it is a collection that is ever more dependent on the financial mechanisms of art and society.</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights.
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Public Trust Doctrine and the Private Client Robert H. LivingstonToward a Theory of Intimate Partner Relations: Towards a Theory of PublicityJessy EdgarWith Love and LossSusanne Rich and the Crowded Plaza, 2010. Performance at the 2009 Venice Biennale. Courtesy of the artist and FACT.Jessica CoonJessica Coon is a partner in the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services. She joined the Justice Department in 2011. Her work has addressed topics including immigration, criminal justice reform, and the policing of protests. She received a Presidential appointment by President Barack Obama in 2014 and she served as an assistant attorney general during the administration of former President Donald J. Trump.Public Trust and the Consumer: Understanding the Impact of Art and MediaJudith Curry</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Deputy Assistant Attorney General for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice. She previously served as Deputy Assistant Attorney General for the Criminal Division at the New York and Brooklyn Supreme Courts, a civil rights and voting rights unit. Prior to</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessy EdgarJessy Edgar is a partner in the law office of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., where she advises on civil rights and employment litigation. Prior to Bolger, she worked at the Office of Legal Counsel, where she represented the Office of Federal Treaty Compliance at the US Department of the Interior, representing the Indigenous Environmental Network in a challenge to the Bureau of Indian and Tribal Affairs's jurisdiction over protected lands and waters. She also represented the Indigenous Environmental Network in a challenge to the constitutionality of the Central American Human Rights report, which was adopted by the US Commission on Historic Landmarks and Institutions, which recommended that the White House preserve the historic character of the site selected for the National Mall. She advised the Commission on Historic Landmarks and Institutions that she had the authority to</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the Law: Advancing Rationales for Exclusion (2014-present)By Tania BrugueraTania Bruguera is a writer and organizer with a particular interest in the impact of technological innovation on social structures. She is currently the Director of Research and</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Deputy Assistant Attorney General for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice. She holds a law degree from Yale Law School and is a graduate of the Criminal Division at Harvard Law School. Prior to joining the Justice Department, she worked</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the Law: The Practice of Law in TransitionJennifer Morgan 	Lawrence Lessig is Professor in the Law and Practice of Globalization at Columbia University. Her research interests include the law, constitutionality, and practices of international law; the legal regulation of wealth, poverty, and social</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.In 2005, Msgr. Sharon Steele argued before the Supreme Court on behalf of the Innocence Project in a challenge to Maryland's release of a black criminal defendant from prison on the pretrial release of a co-defendant. The Innocence Project argued that the government had overstepped its bounds in attempting to release Charles Augustus Mitchell, a nonviolent Black male, from prison on the grounds that the two were similar in terms of prior offenses and circumstances. The Court denied the Innocence Project's request and instead found that Mitchell was similarly situated to others serving lengthy sentences for non-violent drug-related offenses. It reversed the conviction and sentence of six other defendants, concluding that their constitutional rights had been violated when their convictions were affirmed on the basis of a similar showing of similarity between the Innocence Project and itself</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, Cooley, Ligonier &amp; Associates, which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the Law: Policing the CrisisCurtis LinghamCurtis Lingham is a partner in the firm of Ligonier, Bolger, Ligonier &amp; Associates, which provides civil rights and employment litigation services to the federal government. Prior</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the Law: The Intercepting of Communication Jessica Coon is a partner in the Washington office of the law firm Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services. In her current role, she is responsible for coordinating the Office of Legal Counsel and assisting</text>
    <text>developments in artificial intelligence and machine learning that will make them easier to spot, easier to link, and perhaps ultimately, more like you.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Outside the LawJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the federal government in civil rights cases including employment, civil rights, and voting rights. In addition, she was a partner in the Washington office of the law firm of Bolger, Bolger, &amp; Co., which provides civil rights and employment litigation services.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is the Justice Department's deputy solicitor general for legal affairs. Previously, she served as deputy assistant attorney general for the Criminal Division at the Department of Justice's Legal Services Corporation, a private legal aid firm. She has extensive experience representing the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to
    <text>curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to take care of ourselves. Now all we had to do was sit around and wait for the bus.’[7] A return to the pre-computer media world is suggested, where the artist’s responsibility is lessened, since there is no longer a direct line of communication with the viewer. This is also evident in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ where the group is invited to a Christmas party at the local Christmas shop. As soon as they arrive, a mysterious woman dressed as Santa Claus appears and demands that they hand over their presents. In a fit of rage, Homer resorts to cutting himself with a pair of pliers and ends up in the tree of knowledge. Moments later, a pair of angry reindeer run up to him and demand to know what’s happening. There are two main theories as to what really happens when artists are invited to perform in public spaces: either the art is suppressed or the participants participate in a kind of performative</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to take part in things that now we don’t really care about.’[7] The reference to the Great Depression is deliberate. In the episode, a group of friends gather round to discuss the passing of the vernacular. Jughead, Lisa and others in the group look on in bewilderment. ‘What did you do when you grew up?’ asks Tom. ‘Did you play sports?’[8]. 	[1] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, Part 1, Scene I. 	[2] William Shakespeare, King Henry VI, Part II, Scene II. 	[3] Tim Curry, ‘The Tree of Life: A Social History of Botany and Physiology’,  	Ensign, July, 1991, p. 10. 	[4] Lewis,  	The Fountainhead, p. 4. 	[5] K</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to “paint our own picture” with respect to the things we saw and heard. Now, however, we’re the ones subject to the things those pictures supposedly document.’[7] In other words, the technological literati view art as an art form that is constantly evolving, and thus incapable of providing the qualitative heterogeneity and political complexity that would warrant the toolkit of a political party. But this is not true of all art forms.  One could make an argument that modern art has essentially become an interactive media work, where the art has a clear and measurable impact.  One could also make an argument that contemporary art has essentially become an interactive media work, where the art has a measurable impact but also has a political impact.  That last category seems like a stretch, however, since political impact and multimedia work are inextricably linked.  And to be clear, I am not suggesting that there is not a way to connect the dots between art and</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to ‘turn on’, but not anymore.’[7] In this period, the sub-headings ‘Beauty as a Response to Postmodernism’ and ‘Postmodernism as a Response to Decay’ refer to the ongoing crisis of modernism and its discontents. Postmodernism is the answer to the question: how to live in accordance with postmodernity? The philosophy of postmodernism argues that the postmodern era is defined by a reversal of the historic social/cultural trends – which were, in Marx’s phrase, a ‘reversal of trends’ – resulting in the commodification of culture, along with a multitude of new administrative forms that impose modernity on an increasingly dispersed and urbanised planet. The emergence of new media and graphic design, along with the related rise of mass communications, ushered a new era of postmodernism. As a sub-head, ‘Postmodernity’ refers</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to take care of ourselves. Now all we had to do was sit around waiting for the world around us to change.’[7] The reference to the Great Depression is a deliberate one, and the idea that working-class people are helpless before global financial markets is a myth. Banking on such crises is the project of the ‘Greatest Generation’, and it’s this ‘project’ that’s being commissioned again this year. In an ironic twist, the commissioning of artworks by and for artists may in part be a kind of self-reflection. As the image above shows, in 2014, the Greek theatre company, Herculaneum, was one of the artists invited to develop a new kind of theatre, one in which the audience would participate through interactive media. The project was called ‘The Second Coming of the Theater’, and its theme was a mixture of apocalyptic and comic-book metaphors. In Greek, the word</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to count on you, now we don’t, and we’ll never again pretend like we have to give a damn what the papers you sit through say.’[7] (Emphasis mine).In response, the paper announces that the episode will air 'as is now a matter of state policy' – a policy that punishes those who fail to conform to the dominant forms of socialisation. As the episode draws to a close, Lisa and The Gang are confronted with the reality of the situation: the system they worked so hard to construct is coming tumbling down around them like a house of cards. The destruction they imagined never to happen is coming at them from all sides, and now they’re trapped in a kind of existential crisis. For some, this is cause for celebration, for for others unease. For the actors, it’s part of a process of self-criticism. For me, it’s the worst possible situation</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to take matters of the universe for granted. Now that’s all gone.’[7] Of course, in the age of infinite resources and in the universe suddenly existing in ‘all of our natures’, this kind of planning is impossible. But in this case, the inability to plan is experienced as something positive, as a kind of epiphany. The writers of ‘Lisa and The Gang’ clearly saw an opportunity to indulge their egos and take matters of the universe for granted in the form of anthropomorphic animals. And the episode ends with an all-powerful Homer Simpson telling the assembled writers and audience members that they’re ‘going to make things happen’. So the episode takes the form of a narrative meeting of the minds, where the assembled fragments of knowledge are put into one unified whole. The question that remained open throughout this process was what would become of the knowledge once gathered? One possible answer might have involved the return to life</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to … drive by … picket fence … punch bums in the eye of bums in line … blow raspberry slippers … break windows … kick the s*** out of bums in the back seat of a car … buy a pack of cigarettes and crack an a** for the first time … blow raspberry slippers … kick the s*** out of bums in the back seat of a car … buy a pack of cigarettes and crack an a** for the first time … blow raspberry slippers … kick the s*** out of bums in the back seat of a car … buy a pack of cigarettes and crack an a** for the first time … blow raspberry slippers … kick the s*** out of bums in the back seat of a car … buy a pack of cigarettes and crack an a** for the first time … blow raspberry slippers … kick the s*** out of bums in the back seat of a car … buy a pack of cigarettes and crack an a** for the</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to ‘turn up to the local pub and have a good time’, but now that’s gone. Instead, the television personality that is Matt Groening (the creator of The Simpsons) appears to contradict this sentiment by attempting to turn the town of Springfield into a Matt Groening-type religious utopia through the magic of pop culture. Groening’s character, Bart, is a young hippie preacher turned secular humanist. Bart’s quest is to turn ‘ordinary’ people into ‘perfect’ people through self-improvement through self-purification. To achieve this Bart leads a community of like-minded youths in a series of self-flourishing initiatives dubbed ‘The Merry Pranksters’.One of the more bizarre aspects of the episode is when Bart attempts to use his newly discovered creative-writing skills to become an artist rather than an administrator of a community arts centre. He’s given the job of</text>
    <text>curated by a machine] as a kind of trial by machine.’[6] The sub-headings ‘Art as Art’ and ‘Art as Art’ make it clear that the project is concerned with the aesthetic rather than the technical aspects of the art. For instance, the title of the first episode of ‘The Simpsons’ is a pun on the ‘Twas the Night Before Christmas’, when the town of Springfield is preparing for Christmas. Homer, played by actor, Lisa Boni, is preparing to leave Springfield and moves to a smaller town a short distance away. He’s given up on ever feeling like he has to give a speech in front of a group of people, which is why in the episode ‘Lisa and The Gang’ he resorts to writing a letter to the editor of the local newspaper. In the letter he invokes the ‘Greatest Generation’ and proclaims: ‘We used to be able to ‘turn on’, but that couldn’t be good enough anymore. We’re here to say ‘We’re not good enough, we need some more.’[7] The reference is to the 1950s television series The Simpsons, which was heavily inspired by the book The Wizard of Ostrich Farm by John Steinbeck. In the book, a wizard named L. Frank Baum created a television show with a name that sounded like a collection of obscenities: ‘The Wizard of Ostrich Farm’; ‘The Linguist’; ‘The Satire Writer’; and ‘The Satire Artist’. The name ‘Lisa Simpson’ comes from a children’s book, and the reference is deliberate. As Simpson points out in her memoirs, the nickname came from an Uncle Sam speaker who came into her classroom one day and said things like ‘You�</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level
    <text>extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level rises will make many cities uninhabitable.The second meta-narrative that came out of the Venice Biennale was a set of myths and legends surrounding the city. One of the first things that came out of the biennale's trash can was a set of three-dimensional representations of itself. In the first myth, the Biennale is a magical place full of mythical creatures and mythical goods. In the next myth, the Biennale is a place of commerce and art. In the third myth, the Biennale is a place of architecture and animals. These three myths are interwoven into a kind of unified whole, and as a result, the city becomes something other than just a set of images. The biennale changed this second narrative, and while it has some intrinsic magic about it, it has to be differentiated from the magic of other art institutions and economies. The economic narrative of the biennale was developed much further in the years that followed</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level rise and floods will become commonplace.The second factor is nongrowth, or the changing face of the planet as a result of human activity. For the past 150 years or so, the percentage of global sea-level rise prevented from happening has been caused by natural factors. However, anthropogenic greenhouse-gas emissions have steadily increased since the late 1970s, and as a result of this, the sea-level at the end of the century has now risen 415mm, or thirteen-tenths of one per cent per year. If we remove this year’s sea-level rise from our calculations, the rate of increase will remain constant at 495mm a year. This means that removing one billion barrels of oil from the global economy would allow the world’s oceans to fill with clean drinking water. This would mean levees, pumps and reservoirs everywhere, and they would form into a cohesive whole. So far, so normal. But what does that look like? In</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level rise will only make those mistakes even worse.The trajectory of sea-level rise is still unclear. Many scientists agree that the hottest parts of the world will be flooded, and some predictions suggest that as much as 90% of the Earth’s coastline could be underwater by century’s end. But even if 90% of the Earth remains underwater, the seas will still rise, and sea-level rise continues to exacerbate this situation. Even if every country on Earth doubled its coastline, this wouldn’t solve the problem, since the additional water taken from the sea would still have to be channeled into existing infrastructure. Instead, since the 1970s, countries have directed a significant share of the extra water to shore up against eroding coastline. In places, this has created what’s known as a ‘buffer zone’ along the coast. This zone covers areas where the sea levels are expected to be no higher than 5% of the pre-industrial average. In</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level rise will only make things worse.AI is changing the infrastructure of the city in profound ways. It’s not just the infrastructure of oil refineries and packaging plants, but the infrastructure of cities all over the world. It’s displacing human settlement as the planet warms. That’s why cities are so worried about flooding; it’s so we’ll have to account for displaced people and infrastructure when it rises.Sea-level rise is already beginning to impact the coasts of North America, Europe and Australia, and it’s likely to do so in the future. Even if coastal cities build seawalls and divert resources to other uses, the sea levels rising will only make matters worse. Cities will have to figure out how to live with the excess water, and cities will have to figure out how to feed their burgeoning populations when it comes time to build seawalls and divert resources. And that will mean figuring out how to buy seawalls and divert</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level rise will make coastal places uninhabitable. If we go extinct, that’s what happens. It’s a sad state of affairs, but we’re far enough into the future that we don’t need to worry about it.AI is changing everything that’s possible with regards to transportation and communications. It’s as if we've all become superhuman in some way. And in a world with more and better AI, we’re not just superhuman in the sense that we’re smarter than ever, but that we’re also more mobile and connected. This is the age of the superintelligent being, which is being encouraged by policymakers because they’re so envious of what’s happening to the world. Not only that, but these people also have a sort of primal ‘Chinese feeling’ about the world that comes across in their writing. It’s as if we’re all</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level rise will make coastal cities more vulnerable than they already are.More and more coastal cities are becoming indistinguishable from one another, and this trend is accelerating. If the United Nations is anything to go by, we’ll become indistinguishable from one another. If we follow the logic of AI, we could say that the more distinctively human-like a settlement is, the more likely it is that AI will be able to discover and employ the technologies that allow it to prosper. The question becomes whether the features of coastal cities will be able to adapt to the new kinds of heterogeneity and change that will inevitably result from the new technologies. One can only imagine what that might mean in practice, but there are already signs that some of the most prestigious scientific institutions in the world are developing ways to monitor and assess such developments.Is the question of anthropogenic global warming really about which of us is responsible? If the answer is no, then perhaps it is time to reconsider what we mean when we talk about �</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level rise will make coastal flooding inevitable.A final factor affecting the climate is net migration. Migration is a topic of considerable discussion in the open source ecosystem, and the global question of ecology and migration is of particular concern. There are of course other factors that also influence the climate, but the fact that large parts of the world now experience climatic extremes due to human activity is of particular concern. It’s as if we live among species that are collectively doing irreparable damage to the planet. We need to find new ways to live among species that are also collectively doing damage. This may involve adapting to the new forms of life that are emerging in the world. There are various ways to do this, from trying to reimagine ‘natural ecosystems’ to establishing indigenous ‘heritage ecosystems’, but the point is that we’ve all become cogs in a machine. Nature has endowed us with certain capacities, and we need to work together to create new systems that are</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level rises will become even more devastating. Furthermore, as the world warms, the landmasses that make up the North Atlantic right now are going to be particularly vulnerable. The Greenland Ice Sheet is melting faster than ever, sea-level rises are occurring at an unprecedented rate, and coastal flooding is a major issue in these coastal zones. As a result, more and more of the planet is going to be flooded, and millions will become dangerously displaced.All of these trends are fundamentally connected to the exponential expansion of artificial intelligence, or AI, as a result of decades of research into machine learning. AI is the emergent behavior of software programs that are able to learn anything, and can therefore be programmed to do anything. In other words, it’s able to replace human workers in highly specialized fields. Machine learning has been around for some time now, but it’s only recently that it has begun to gain widespread acceptance. Most AI labs don’t even have a working AI</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level rises are inevitable.But what can we do? There are currently no effective treatments or vaccines for this underlying malady. There are, however, promising candidates for the catastrophic effects of climate change. A growing number of researchers are coming to grips with the fact that the only effective way to combat rising sea levels is for all of humanity to commit fully to renewable energies. Research universities, for example, are turning to social studies courses in an effort to equip their students with the knowledge and tools necessary for a social change, but even these courses remain rudimentary. Most students remain uneducated about climate change, nor do they realize that the infrastructure necessary to support such action is already in place. For example, the electrical grid already supports the construction of seawalls and can expand those walls at will. Over the past century, global average sea-level rise was about 6.1mm, and while the seas didn’t actually rise, human activity did make a significant impact on the coastal lands that are part</text>
    <text>extends the proposition to machines as well. It’s an increasing meta-narrative that’s partly informed by the ascendance of artificial intelligence and partly by the failure of human beings to foresee the catastrophic ramifications of climate change.Human activity is the cause, but AI will also radically alter the world’s infrastructure. Large industrial ports now house semi-permanent human settlements. These ‘habitat-forming institutions’ are the site of significant amounts of oil refining and packaging, as well as major petro-chemical operations. As a result, these densely populated coastal locations host human settlements that regularly encounter one another. The proliferation of port cities around the world is the direct result of the proliferation of oil and gas reserves, and the shifting of these reserves has major anthropogenic effects. The climate is a major anthropogenic factor in the growth of these coastal cities. If we don’t change our behavior, we’ll repeat the mistakes of the past, and sea-level rise is a fact of life in many coastal locations.As a corollary, AI threatens not only the infrastructure of port cities, but also the very ecology of the planet. If these threats are not taken seriously, or worse, exacerbates existing issues, then AI could well lead to a future in which major coastal cities are submerged or submerged underwater. That would mean that coastal areas would become uninhabitable, and the seafloor would be overrun with submerged cities. In the words of Paul Davies, a co-founder of the Open Ocean Institute: ‘There is no alternative to a future with fully fledged, identifiable, and controllable AI, regardless of how much of a mess it makes in the process.’ These threats are real, and they need to be addressed. But there are other ways to think about the threat.One could look to the history of AI and how it came to be in human hands. This is a common scenario in dystopian science fiction:</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
