<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon 
    <text>should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon and Peter Brook – were shipped to China in the wake of the Cultural Revolution, and then somehow the museum was shut down due to budgetary constraints.John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney untold numbers of albums and countless performances. Paul McCartney’s heroin addiction cost the Beatles more than a million records. The Beatles Museum and its collection of artefacts is in urgent danger of descending into irrelevance because of the political turmoil riven the region around it. The proximity of the Chinese market to the UK is making these artefacts more and more of value, whereas the risk of a major cultural upheaval in China is making them less and less so. The recent passing of Wimbledon’s Wimbledon Museum Artists Collective—a hub for the artist’s residency and the postgraduate studentship programme in art and design at the MFA’s Watt Center for Interdisciplinary Art and Design—undersc</text>
    <text>should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon and Lacoste – is now stranded in the social and economic mire of addiction.The Chisenhale family, for their part, are still fighting the legacy of the war on drugs that they believe produced and continues to produce a host of social ills. It’s a strategy that has paid off handsomely. John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family over $100 million. The museum that they had assembled to hold their own version of the Great Communal Depression – which was itself a museum in its own right – is a museum in its own right. As a result, their biennial will be able to inhabit the same cultural space and traffic as any other, while simultaneously being an enormous provocation and a disservice to the communities it is curated in. I’m not so sure that the biennial format is suited to the task of mourning the loss of life. But if it can honour the memory of a collective action, then surely</text>
    <text>should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon and Walt Whitman – is now a museum in its own right, with exhibitions and events that feature material from the McCartney family home in Wood Green, and from the time when John Lennon’s parents were killed in a car crash.And so the cycle starts all over again, only this time it’s from the Beatles Museum and its collections, and so the cycle continues all the way up to the present, only this time it’s from the UK Museum. And so it has to do with the UK Museum, which has performed a similar service, or more correctly, performed a similar function, in the US, during the years that the museum has been in existence. And so the cycle begins all over again, only this time it’s from the Museé, whose collections of art and artefacts are globally distributed, and whose exhibitions are specific to the UK, during the same periods. And so the cycle continues, only this time it’s from</text>
    <text>should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon and Peter Brook, who worked on the Clash and also painted with the Royal College of Art's John Lennon Centre – is experiencing its own crisis of identity crisis.The fact that the museum is a place of confrontation, where people are fighting for their lives, is what Lennon meant when he wrote: ‘You’re fucking dead.’ That’s exactly what I’ve been doing. I’ve lost count of how many times I’ve been on the receiving end of this ‘fucking dead’ jibe from the public. It’s a dangerous combination, and I’m not supposed to be holding a gun to anybody’s head. But I’m also not supposed to be collecting shit for a gallery that’s never going to use. I’m not a zombie, I’m not a terrorist, I’m just a collector. And that’s exactly what</text>
    <text>should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon and Wesley Clifton, as well as Jack Burnham, Billy Gordon and Ken Turner – is the single most important piece of evidence that makes up the case that the McCartney family has put together. It’s the missing link.I follow this sentiment in The Beatles Museum’s catalogue: these songs represent the most fundamental of truths about human experience. And I think that, for many people, that’s how they feel when they come to see the museum. But it’s important to recognise that, for many artists, that’s how they feel too. Because, for example, Mick Head – who worked with Mick Joy on the Beatles Museum in the mid-1970s – actually felt that the Beatles Museum was hisopic and disconnected from the city in which he lived. It’s a place where he could be a visitor and not necessarily a presenter, and where he could</text>
    <text>should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon and W.R. McBride, who also worked for the Beatle, Rollo John and W.E.B. Du Bois, among many others – is the direct result of one family’s addiction to the other.It’s true that in the 1960s and 1970s the museum form was grafted onto the gothic, postmodern and post-Fordist trends; with the gothic museum suddenly finding a home on a shoestring budget, while the gothic and neo-classical museum saw a steady but inexorable decline. But there are important differences between the museum and the museum of modern art today, and between the museum and the museum of art that existed in the 1980s. For one, the reduction in the museum to a collection of objects is not restricted to gothic and neo-classical museums. Modern museum-quality art collections are now being curated by non-artistic curators,</text>
    <text>should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon and Silk Street – is the direct result of one artist’s heroin addiction. But that is just sad and depressing. There is something beautiful and powerful in the way that the Beatles Museum is attempting to acknowledge these artists’ contributions to the band’s music and their place in it. I think that there is a way of the museum being recognisable from outside the context of the music, its packaging and its reach. That is, the way that artists are able to inhabit the museum in meaningful ways. And perhaps the way is to invite the audience in and create a space where the audience can inhabit the museum in ways that reflect the art’s presence and the way in which the art is made.I also think that there is a way of the museum being enabled by the way in which people are able to inhabit it. I mean, I love the way that the museum is enabling research, and I think that there is an interesting interpretative role for the</text>
    <text>should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon and Pablo Picasso – is now a museum of ruin. But at the same time, it’s a place of resistance, where you can actually read the stories of the people whose work was cut because it didn’t fit the narrative. That was such a powerful statement for me, that the Beatles Museum should be a place where the stories of the Beatles should be told. That’s what I did with Wimbledon, Pablo Picasso, Meredith Monk, Dora Nelson, Jane Addams… I didn’t want it to be a place where you could read the Beatles biographies and just be transported to the time when they were alive, but it had to have a story. The idea was that it became a place of reflection and a place where the voices of the people who made the records would actually be heard. It’s that idea that resonates with me, the idea that the museum</text>
    <text>should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon and Wrigley School of Art, among many others – would never have been possible without the McCartney family. It’s a very moving story, and one that, at the time, many in power didn’t want to hear.It’s a sad story, but one that captures the essence of the moment: the loss of innocence, the loss of the ability to grow old in peace, the loss of touch with time – and all the other things that come with a cultural revolution. It’s a story about complicity, and people who participate in its production, but also of triumphalism and the false sense of security that comes with it. In some ways, it’s the opposite of what we’re trying to achieve, in that we don’t want to instill in young people that guilt by association is good, and that you’re either with us or against us. It’s a false sense</text>
    <text>should be curated, not curated’. The museum should be a place to reflect and be a memory, not a museum of destruction.I’m in awe of people like Wimbledon’s John Lennon, who weren’t framed by modernist museums either. They got their start in Museum of Modern Art in New York, where John Lennon was made an honorary patron in 1958. Lennon was so taken with the idea that a museum should be a place of remembrance and a place of expression that he set up The Beatles Museum in 1969. And they have a lot of those songs in there, with lyrics that come from a place of immense personal pain and anger. I’m always reminded of how much John Lennon’s heroin addiction cost the family of Paul McCartney, and that’s just devastating. It’s as if the Beatles Museum and its collection of memorabilia – which includes artwork by the legendary artists Wimbledon and Pablo Picasso – is the size of a family home. That is devastating. That was a very personal wound.I used to paint landscapes for the Chisenhale Gallery in Liverpool, and I used to paint landscapes for the Whitechapel Gallery in London. To me, the juxtaposition of the two was mind-blowing. That was the era of Damien Hirst and everything he represents. It’s as if the Whitechapel were on a mission to recapture the magic of the natural environment and recreate that in art form. The Whitechapel is sponsoring a series of inspiring , schoolyard games for seven to eleven-year-olds run by the Whitechapel Gallery, so that they can ‘realise’ the magical encounter they had with John Lennon’s dead body. It’s amazing how much Hirst has inspired, and still inspires, young people to want to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the act of storage (or, in the case of curating, processing), and the semantic changes that take place during that act. If the storage units utilized in the development of a biennial are data-intensive units that ingest vast amounts of data (as is evident in the increasing use of data-intensive software), the question becomes which of those users are we to attribute the semantic meaning of those terms? In the case of the virtual reality (VR) and augmented reality (AR) genres, the use of data is understood as a consumption of media (technologies that aid in the perception or actualization of reality) that creates new kinds of relationship based on consumption. More precisely, the VR and AR industries are interested in the mechanisms of language as representations and consumptions that evolved in the wake of the physical and virtual loss of meaning and form associated with massive data collections. The VR and AR literatures are interested in the representation and consumptive function of the social. If the social is understood to</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the act of exchange between people and things rather than to the things themselves. This term is frequently used in relation to international or regional biennials, but it is increasingly used in relation to all biennials. There are several reasons for this. The first is the proliferation of biennials around the world, which is driven by the same factors contributing to the rise of digital technologies. The proliferation of data-storage, processing, and communication devices is another factor. Thus, biennials in different locations around the world are becoming increasingly aware of the capacities and interests of the people who visit their cities. This awareness may be seen as a curatorial move, in that biennials are increasingly aware of their global impact, but it is in fact a self-serving move. The awareness generated by the biennial may in part be used to justify the systematic reduction of local resources and the systematic exploitation of resources in other cities. This is particularly true in the developed world, where biennials are</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the act of exchange between people and objects, and phenomena that have a particular relationship to one another. The term has often been used in a pejorative sense. However, there is a need to critically contextualise this usage. The concepts of ‘biennial’ and ‘curatorial audience’ may be useful in constructing an understanding of the concept. The exhibition setting is a significant source of the collection that is gathered, and the primary repository of knowledge about the biennial. By gathering this collection, the biennial is able to make infrastructural improvements and to participate in the generation of knowledge about its local environment. The collection may help create a more nuanced understanding of the collection. The collection also enables the biennial to make infrastructural investments and participate in the long-term accumulation of knowledge. The collection has the potential to become a powerful archive. But the more important engagement with the collection is its capacity to evolve, to attract new people to the collection, and</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the actual physical objects that comprise the exhibitionary complex as artifacts, kept alive and transnational in nature; objects whose structure, shape and configuration can be inferred from their data; and objects whose function is to house and facilitate the exchange of these artifacts. In other words, it refers to the actual sites and to the actual culture. It is mores, aesthetics, and even politics that are being abstracted from in the context of artificial intelligence.In recent years, biennials have increasingly been framed as a transnational phenomenon. In the United Kingdom, the Venice Biennale was curated as part of the Institution of Arts, which in turn curated a number of other exhibitions around the world. In 2016, the United States, Germany, and Taiwan all collaborated on a single, 10-day, ‘Venice Renaissance’ commemorative event. International cooperation was promoted through a parallel ‘Venice Biennale’ website that documents the history of the Biennale from its origins in</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the collection and exchange of cultural resources, and this is clearly seen in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) that are being utilized to house and exchange cultural resources across borders. Virtual reality, social media, mapping and social discovery platforms are just some of the technological innovations that are being employed in an increasingly augmented and contextual sense. There is no doubt that the capacity for art to be produced across borders is a precondition for any kind of social welfare. But the capacity for artists to be produced across borders is seen by many artists as a primary means of engaging with and creating knowledge of an art form. It is not clear to many contemporary artists how the capacities that align with their current artistic interests align with those of the future; and the capacities that constrain them – that is, prevent them from becoming contemporary artists – are seen by many artists as a hindrance to creativity. This is a conundrum for artists to wrestle with in a business-like capacity. It seems to me</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the collection and exchange of data, and the social implications of this collection and exchange are being interpreted through data-visualisations. Currently, the focus is on the exhibition business, but biennials may one day acquire a critical mass of users and visitors, which is the basis for any self-regulating system. In this sense, they are like ‘real life’ – embedded in and constituting part of the larger social system.The fascination around biennials began in the 1980s, when the Venice Biennale became an international phenomenon. The Biennale has a long and rich history here, and its current capacity to connect with and engage with the city is due to the fact that it is artist-led and has a curatorial council of artists. But the relationship between artist-guided and ‘real life’ has been on a kind of aesthetic and political level with other forms of cultural activity throughout the decades. In the 1990s, the Biennale developed a</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the fact that, whereas before there was a central hub for the development of biennials, there are now independent local entities with varying levels of government responsible for the upkeep of the art institution as a whole. These local entities have their own legislative acts, executive decrees, and board of directors. As a result, their activities can be understood as having a global impact. The local biennale needs to be organised into autonomous units, which means that all relevant actors need to be present in order to participate in the festival. For Venice itself, this means that all the relevant actors need to be able to access the same data, which means that they need to be able to negotiate the same terms and conditions. For local artists to gain access to this data, they need to be able to negotiate with relevant artists' organisations, and also to build an audience. In turn, this means that local artists need to be able to access funding, which means recruiting artists and ensuring that they have the resources to</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the transfer of cultural power from the individual to the collective. However, this raises another question: how will the individual contribute to the production of cultural capital? If the curator is seen as the servant of the powerful, then perhaps it is time to question whether the artist is in on the joke as well. The curatorial as a curatorial trickles downThe biennial came as a huge surprise to many people when it began in 1991. For some, the introduction of art and artists into the equation in a major way in the spirit of the new curatorial style was viewed as a provocation. The ‘biennial’ was actually introduced in the Boston Art Biennale as an excuse to showcase pieces from the previous year. So the introduction of art and artists into the equation in the late 1990s was seen by some as a prelude to introducing art and artists into the curatorial mix in the late 2000s. More importantly, it created the conditions for the emergence of a biennial that</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the collection and exchange of cultural resources across cultural boundaries, and as a result, it is being driven by data. The significance of this collection and exchange cannot be overemphasized. It constitutes part of a cultural service economy, which is being built on the back of the tourism trade. The exhibitionary biennial has come a long way from its humble origins as a festival for artists to come and do acts of art, and its current relationship to such an art form is a testament to the power of cultural resources in a capitalist economy. The exhibitionary form is being reinvented in service of the service economy, which is becoming increasingly conscious of its relationship to the landscape and its resources. It is being driven by data, and data-mining will become increasingly conscious of its relationship to the landscape as a resource. The wide range of objects and their sizes, the varied purposes they serve, and the diverse ways in which they are manipulated will all be seen as necessary in the service of the service economy.</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. In this context, the conversation could be drawn on the idea of ‘natural language processing’, which is to say, human-computer interaction. Artificial intelligence refers to the capacity of computers to understand abstract concepts (rules, natural language, grammar, etc.), while data mining refers to the use of data to extract meaning from patterns. The current application of these principles in the curatorial setting is being driven by technological innovation, which is clearly seen as a game-changer in the way in which curating is organised and executed. This is evident in the increasing number of virtual private servers (VPSs) and the proliferation of data-center configurations. The use of data produces its own set of semantic changes, which are captured and exchanged across the social web. Such practices are being driven by data mining, which is understood as the utilization of biennials as a form of massive data warehouse. The notion of the biennial has entered new levels of abstraction. It refers to the physical spaces (files, directories, maps), numbering (annuals, volume), number of pages (pages), and other data that are constantly (re)generated (on an ever-expanding server farm) – all in relation to the art being exhibited. The number of biennials exhibits are likely to continue to grow, and the number of artists and curators is likely to increase, although it is important to point out that the number of visitors to a biennial (and the accompanying book) is very much dependent on the productivity of the art being exhibited. With that many visitors, the art has to be showcased everywhere in order to break even. Curators have to be present in order to make a difference. The more we see of the same art elsewhere, the less impact our interventions can have. So, what can biennials do? In a general sense, they can do anything that can be funded by the state, and which also involves interacting with crowds of people (</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono
    <text>should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.Previously published at Ponte City, March 2017. In Stage Fright, Benjamin Bratton, the author of the memoir Stages of Perpetual Peace, discusses the life and work of John Lennon. Stage Fright is the story of how Benjamin Bratton, the author and activist of the term ‘Stage Fright’, came to write the book. Bratton came to prominence in the 1980s when he started a counter culture movement in support of poverty and homelessness. His career as a writer and activist was based on the idea that writing would endow those around him with the tools to change the world. In the book, he criticises both the institutionalised notion of resistance and the more overt, but nevertheless persistent, political work of subversion. Stage Fright</text>
    <text>should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not</text>
    <text>should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox. 	[1] Søren Kierkegaard, The Concept of Anxiety, Penguin Classics, 1976, p. 42. 	[2] Brent Bellamy, When Anxiety Takes Over Your Life: The Modern Treatment of Anxiety, McGraw-Hill, New York, 1986, p. 126. 	[3] Ariana Grande, 'Break Free</text>
    <text>should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not</text>
    <text>should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not</text>
    <text>should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance</text>
    <text>should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon/Plastic Ono Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon/Plastic Ono Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon/Pl</text>
    <text>should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNext[I] The Beatles were formed in April 1970 by John Lennon and Paul McCartney. Their first single, ‘Baby, Let Me in‘, appeared in November 1970. The Beatles were formed in America in April 1980. Their song ‘Let It Be‘ was released in May 1984. The Beatles are represented by Sony Music Entertainment, which has a worldwide publishing imprint</text>
    <text>should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not</text>
    <text>should be curated by French artist Damien Magaziner, who has worked with Watkins since 2003. It is due to coincide with the release of a new book of photographs from the John Lennon Center for Performing Arts, entitled How to Pronounce John Lennon: A Documentary History of the Beatles. The duo performed at the end of April 2017, when we curated 'Homebaked’s' 20th birthday party. Tickets to the party were £25 in presale condition, and £35 at the door.The John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not part of book. Photo: Tom Lox.PreviousNextThe John Lennon/Plastic Ono Band, from the performance at the John Lennon Lennon Center for Performing Arts, Amsterdam, 16 April 2017. Performance not</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of
    <text>should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of a very particular kind of temporality. It is the social-media infrastructure of the present temporality. The art world does not yet have a social-media infrastructure of the social. It is, however, constructing one.In many ways, then, the art-world produces both the political and the social. The politics of the art-world is produced by the political-ideological presupposition that informs the cultural-economic (A) and (B) dimensions of the postmodern condition. The political dimension of postmodernity therefore needs to be understood in relation to the cultural-ideological ground on which the art world operates. The art-world presupposes the existence of a political ground, and while the political dimension of this presupposition may be present in different artistic forms, it is constitutive of the modern condition. The art-world is a double-sided institution: it supports the political and it creates its political. And to a certain extent, it is even a facilitator</text>
    <text>should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of a new artworld; it is the new epicenter of the modern culture industry. The art world as an online presence is becoming ever more important not only because of the proliferation of social media but also because of the proliferation of art-sharing networks. In addition to the increasing accessibility of art-related goods and services, the contemporary artworld is becoming ever more like other art sites: ever more like museums, which is a phenomenon that is now taking place in many cities across the world. More than ever, the contemporary artworld must strive to draw visitors from around the world, and those who come to visit might not immediately identify with the art world, preferring to browse online galleries or find art through their phones. In an ideal world, the art world would also offer a social experience that is as real as possible, where people can come for hours on end, connect with one another and work creatively.Unfortunately, most artworlds of the world are like any other art site – they are affected</text>
    <text>should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of a potential new form of collective art-making. The online circulation of art news, commentaries, art reviews and artwork recommendations is a potential new form of cultural exchange. In an ideal world, the online circulation of art news, commentaries, and artwork recommendations would result in the creator’s ‘real life’ – in the form of letters, photos, texts – arriving not as images but as data (pictures, audio, video). In an ideal world, the online circulation of art news, commentaries, and artwork recommendations would result in the art being made by and for the people. In an ideal world, the art would be made by and for the people and distributed through local art fairs, urban centres Cultural Olympiads, and other art-specific cultural networks. Such art-specific artistic networks would offer a more direct route to the artist’s art than museums or contemporary art galleries, and they would offer a more direct route to the community than the</text>
    <text>should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of a power differential, which is shifting, which means that art’s place is no longer in direct opposition to economic power, but relies on something more relational and global.The art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or ‘iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution is the locus of a power differential, which is shifting, which means that art’s place is no longer in direct opposition to economic power, but relies on something more relational and global.So what can the art world do to stem this decline? One possibility is to create what might be known as a ‘global art market’, where artworks from many different cultures are offered for sale within a shared market place. This is what online marketplace, the Museum of Art, did well in New York and London. It offered artists an opportunity</text>
    <text>should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of this decline.The alternative is to engage the public in making the art world of the city as diverse as possible, and this is what artists are doing. It is a complex process, and I will give several examples from my gallery collection of late, but I think it is important to illustrate the idea that artists are achieving, because otherwise we will not be able to tell what is beautiful and what is not. For instance, the huge public art collection that is developing in Hong Kong is generated through the act of a single artist coming together as a collective. In the early 1990s when I started work on the collection, the artist was a small artist, and now she is a big artist and has a museum of her own. As a result of this artistic act, the collection has evolved into a very unique kind of museum, with a particular focus on the contributions of artists to the city. In the early 1990s, the collection was very much a collection of individual works: pieces from the artist</text>
    <text>should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of this decline. In an ideal world, the art world would have a mission statement that incorporated the world as it is, giving the public a sense of what is expected of it. Unfortunately, the art world doesn’t have such a statement, and its work is not considered iconoclastic, even by the curators who instil this message into the art world’s vocabulary.The locus of this decline, however, is not in some abstract sense the public gallery, but in the real place – the gallery – where the gallery is housed, and its collections are distributed. In other words, the art world is only as famous as the collection it keeps, and its curators only as artists who exhibit the art in the collection. So the art world needs a new mission statement that incorporates the collection, it’s collections and the contemporary art world. Curators, artists and art-historical writers are the most visible members of this new mission statement, but our mission</text>
    <text>should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of a power struggle that is increasingly dependent on the narratives that are constructed and continue to be built for the collective good.I went to Art Basel a few weeks before the Dutch artist Cindy Schroeter was due to start a year-long residency, and I asked her if she would like to do a project in the city during the residency. She said she would like to, but she didn’t know how. I asked her if she had any ideas about what the city should be like if it were an independent country again, and if so, what kind of city it should be.Her answer: I think that the city should be able to recover from its economic trauma. We’ve all felt this trauma, but it’s not just us: it’s the whole world economy is being affected by this. The city is the bottleneck to the global economy, and it’s happening at such a rapid rate that it’s almost as if the city</text>
    <text>should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of a new kind of art activism. The online presence is a ‘point of intersection’ where art and artists can find each other, where the art of the past meets the contemporary art of the future, and where this intersectionality comes to guide artistic practice. This is a conversation that cannot be allowed to remain static; it is an art event that is multivalent and multi-sourced. It is an art event that is both global and local, but it is also a ‘point of departure’ where different points of intersection arrive at a conclusion. This is the ‘complex’ happening to be a part of our contemporary condition, and it is a conversation that should be had, but it is also a conversation that cannot be accommodated by the art world.Artworlds, and the locus of their artistic practice, are present everywhere. In many cities, they are the only form of cultural interaction remaining between citizens and the public. In other places, the art</text>
    <text>should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of a large-scale resistance to the decline of the city. The art world has to change. We need to engage with the notion of the art world as a place where ideas are actively produced, rather than the other way around: the decline of the art world as a result of ideological rigidity and a general belief that art is somehow intrinsically superior to almost any other form of art. There are other institutional forms that can play this role, but they are usually reactive to specific cultural currents and trends. The art world has to change.In the coming years, I intend to dedicate a significant part of my time to research on the history of urban and regional planning. I will research the role of urban planners in the production of urban knowledge, and I will create a research project around the notion of a ‘city as an infrastructure’. I will need to work closely with local practitioners in order to understand their theoretical and practical work with an urban infrastructure, and how this is a contemporary practice,</text>
    <text>should be curated by the voter and the artist’s collective, with input from the local artworlds] to create a sense of place and community around the exhibition. This would mean engaging with the notion not just of the exhibition but of the collection as a whole. In an ideal world, the local artworld would provide this context and allow the public to participate in making the artworld of the city as diverse as possible. Unfortunately, we live in an ideal world, and most of us live in the least ideal world of the city: we have to work harder and longer than the professionals we work with, for instance, because the city demands so much work from us. Moreover, the art world as an institution is entering a period of decline, and its resources are being used in ways that are not based on what is considered ‘relevant’ or 'iconic’ art in the traditional sense. The art world as an institution, and especially its online presence, is the locus of a political and social struggle. We could, of course, also argue that the art world as an institution is the locus of its own decline, and our own participation in the institution is the only way to fight back. But we would still maintain that the art world as an institution is the only site of possibility for resistance. In an ideal world, the art world would invest itself in creating experiences for its members such as it does for the visitors to its galleries, museums and curatorial programs. But this would require radical reorganization of its components, and perhaps most of all, for its members to take part in creating their world. In an ideal world, the art world would invest itself in helping its members to become artists, and in so doing, create a global community of artists’ that are artists among artists. But this would require a radical rethinking of a large part of the institution’s traditional mission, which is already oriented towards the commercial acquisition of cultural properties. The</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how art can be a tool for resistance and empowerment. I chose to investigate the intersection of contemporary art and social movements, since this is the contemporary art of which we are conscious, and which is often misunderstood. I chose to investigate how the contemporary art of the present is interconnected with the past, since this is the contemporary work that we can create and recall, and which can also be recreated. I chose to investigate the contemporary art of the future in terms of its potential, since this is what artists often mean when they create art and how we might live in the future. I chose to investigate how the contemporary art of the present is interconnected with the past, since this is what artists often mean when they create art and how we might live in the future. I chose to investigate how the contemporary art of the future is interconnected with the past, since this is what artists often mean when they create art and how we might live in the future. I chose to investigate how the contemporary art of the present</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how it can be produced and organised in a manner that is both sustainable and generates new artistic forms. Cultural studies is a broad field, and while I wanted to know how art can be constructed from different points of view, I also wanted to know how art can be contextualised and how that might shape the future of artistic practice. So cultural studies applied to art events – or, well, applied to art events – was a novel idea to begin with. It was also a reaction to the increasing dispersion of artistic practice, which is evident in the increasing number of biennials: the art 'market' is no longer the dominant form of exchange in our cities, and the increasing number of biennials are localised and regionalised. The emergence of alternative art economic models, such as those developed by artist-run cooperatives, such as the Bourse, is a good example to be explored. Cooperatives provide a flexible, non-hierarchical way to build collective identities and generate</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how it can flourish within the socio-political system I was researching. I wanted to know what it meant to be an artistically-engaged citizen of a city, and what it meant to be an artist within a city. I wanted to know what it meant to be an artist within a city, and to understand the specific forms of political and social agency that are created through and through the art of being an artist. I wanted to know what it meant to be an artist, and to understand the specific forms of political and social agency that are constituted through and through the art of being an artist. I wanted to know what it meant to be an artist, and to understand the specific forms of political and social agency that are constituted through and through the art of being an artist. I wanted to know what it meant to be an artist, and to understand the specific forms of political and social agency that are constituted by and through the art of being an artist. I wanted to know what it meant to</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how art can be erected as a social and political force in the world. More and more, I began to read cultural critics and historians, including in the United States, who were writing at a time of great political and economic instability and social fragmentation. It became increasingly clear to me that the ideal place for art and the social engagements that it facilitates are those moments of social and political transformation that actually happen, and not in a fantasy or on the margins. You need to be embedded deeply in that particular historical moment to see the fruits. So I came home from the United States and travelled to Liverpool, arriving in Liverpool via Stansted, and spent two years there, doing fieldwork, visiting sites and people. I also did a masters thesis on the history of Community Arts, an area of expertise in the area of social engagement, which is very relevant to what I was doing at the time, and which I consider to be critical. It looked at how artists were drawn to the area by the cultural critic</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how it can be produced through the interlocking of different cultural forms. I embarked on a two-year research project, funded by the Australian National University’s Indigenous Cultural Studies programme and the Chinese Council for Cultural Studies. The second part of the project consists of a symposium entitled The Art and Politics of Contemporary Cultural Studies, to be delivered in June next year, and which I co-curated with Josephine Machon and Roberto Coronado. The symposium will focus on the 19th Istanbul Biennale as a whole, and specifically on the work of artists involved with the 2014 Istanbul Biennale, which was co-curated by me and Lucy Gaynor. It will also examine some of the questions and ideas raised by the second Istanbul Biennale, including: how to understand the rise of contemporary art biennials as a whole; what is meant by ‘cultural tourism’?; the intertwining of tourism and culture; the production and circulation of</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how this can be achieved through art rather than anthropology. I wanted to understand how our aesthetic sensibilities, cultural cognition and historical research could be used to envision new cultural forms, and how this might affect existing social forms and existing biennials.I began my PhD research in 2015, and my first publication as a doctoral candidate was published in June 2016 in the journal Cultural Criticism. During this time, I also initiated the Cultural Criticism Research Group, an online, cross-disciplinary research project that sought to understand how art is produced and sustains contemporary art. The project was led by Dr Eva Castringius, a doctoral candidate in art history at the University of Chicago, and Dr Dario Nahas, a postdoctoral fellow at the University of Chicago. The group was led by Dr Nahas, who is now Professor of Art History and Director of the Institute for Art and Culture Research. Together, we sought to understand how cultural production and sustenance emerge and are sustained through the production and consumption of</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how other art forms can be contextualised alongside art. I wanted to understand how a biennial can take on a multi-year mission, and what that might mean politically, economically and culturally.I did not expect to become a biennial curator or curator of art events, or to have a career in art and art history. I never thought I would, but I did feel like an outsider, like I had this unique insight into art that other curators don’t get. I didn’t get invited to any art schools or universities, and I never thought I would, but I did feel like an outsider, like I had this unique insight into art that other curators don’t get. I didn’t get invited to any art societies or biennials, and I never thought I would, but I did feel like an outsider, like I had this unique insight into art that other curators don’t get. I didn’t get invited</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how it can be developed through the political process – both in its present and in its future forms. I was looking for creative, radical and new ways of looking at art and art’s possibilities. And I found them in the political and social contexts that contemporary art is concerned with addressing. I came home from my PhD research with a set of questions that I asked myself over and over again: What if I put together a cultural and social context around a particular historical event? What if I engage in political and social change through cultural production? What if I create a biennial that is both artistic and institutional? What if I embark on a research project that looks at the roots of cultural oppression and inequality and creates creative alternatives through cultural production? And I found a set of questions that could and should be asked and answers that could be constructed.These kinds of creativity are the results of a person asking and finding ways to be affected by the things that are happening around him or her. And I believe that</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how it can be interactive with the urban environment. So I started to research institutions that I thought were important for this kind of research: who are the artists that we need to understand the contemporary composition of a city, and what are the assumptions and values that we need to change to become urban? What are the assumptions and values that we need to change in order to become ecologically astute? Who are the artists that we need to understand the socio-political context of a biennale, and what are the assumptions and values that we need to change to become artists? What are the assumptions and values that we need to change in order to become ecologically astute? Who are the artists that we need to understand the socio-political situation of a biennale, and what are the assumptions and values that we need to change to become urban planners? What are the assumptions and values that we need to change to become ecologically astute? Who are the artists that we need to understand the socio</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system, able to absorb and apply different levels of knowledge and experience in a sustained way. Ultimately, this event is the product of a convergence of different knowledge forms, and every facet of it is a product of the interplay between people. But it is possible to see it as a singular event that emerged as a result of a particular cultural and historical moment in time. When you add an element of magic to the mix, and add a dash of whimsy to the mix, and call it a ‘conversation’, you can have a conversation. That is, you can have a conversation about the past, about the future, and about what is and is not possible. When I began my PhD research, I decided to take a two-year journey, beginning in 2015, to explore the cultural intersections that the contemporary art biennale is concerned with addressing. During this time, I wanted to see how art can be contextualised within a wider political and social context, and how it can be made accessible to a wider audience. So I began my research on the museum as a museum, and the biennale as a social event. I began to collect biennials, and to take a close look at what they mean and how they are constituted within the larger cultural context. I also began to collect their curatorial statements, in an attempt to piece together the various layers that connect them.My goal in conducting the research for my PhD was twofold: (1) to make a case for the cultural relevance of the archaeological and historical contexts I found myself in, and (2) to create a dynamic and interesting environment for thinking and experiencing from the vantage point of archaeology and history. At the same time, I wanted to see how biennials can be structurally informed by a particular set of cultural, urban and historical conditions. I began to research how museums and biennials can work alongside one another, and what kinds of political, economic and social changes</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8.   [2] Meehan, Lynn V.  The Episodic. New York: Vintage, 1976, p.28.   [3] Owen Kelly, ‘An Episodic Portrait of a Native Son’, in Kelly, John. The Episodic Portrait series. New York: Vintage, 1986, p.4.   [4] Brent Bellamy, ‘Language and Memory: A Brief Pre-History of Syntactic Theory’, in Bellamy, John. The Syntactic Turn series. New York: Vintage, 1995, p.1.  [5] Weil, Merleau-Ponty, and Christine McKay, ‘On the Necessary Character of Literary Criticism’, in Theoretical and Cultural Studies. Vol. 36, No. 2. New York and London: Routledge, 1993, p.141.  [6]</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8.  [2] Gielen, Lawrence. ‘Issues of Space’.  	2Up2Down/2Up2Ra.   	, 2013.  [3] Gielen, Lawrence. ‘Issues of Presence’.  	2Up2Down/2Up2Ra. 2014.  [4] Gielen, Lawrence &amp; Coon, Brian. ‘Times are Harder and Wetter Now’.  	2Up2Down/2Up2Ra.2014. p.1. [5] Gielen, Lawrence, Coon, Brian &amp; Russell, Paul. ‘The Episodic’, in  	2Up2Down�s Annual Report 2014, 2014, p.2. [6] Gielen, Lawrence, Coon, Brian &amp; Russell, Paul. ‘Times are Harder and Wetter</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8.  [2] Waugh, Norman. Socially Engaged Archaeology. New York: Routledge, 1987, p.19.Download this article as PDFPreeana ReddyPreeana Reddy is an artist and researcher. Her interest in the social and the ecological is her main approach to the social. Her artworks address the social and the ecological in a multitude of contexts, from landscapes and urban environments to schools, workplaces, community spaces and online communities. She has a particular interest in the relationship between art and architecture, and the ecological and social aspects of urban development. Reddy is the recipient of the 2015 N.Y.U.A.E.C.P.H.E. Fellow. She is currently completing her MFA at the New School in New York City. Her work is part of the 'Envisioning New York’s City: After the End of the World' project, which is based in partnership with the New York</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8.   [2] Kester, Mark. ‘How the Art World Can Help Endangered Species’, in 	Cathy McNaughton &amp; Sarah Carter, eds., Living Curated: Art, Postcolonialism, and Species (Chapel Hill: UNC Press, 2015), p. 71.   [3] Kester, Mark. ‘Art and the Politics of Extinction’,  	Deadline, September 2016, p. 42.   [4] Eigenzeit, Vol. 7, No. 1. 2015, p. 1.   [5] Lewis, Carol. ‘The Episodic and the Notional’, in 	Cathy McNaughton &amp; Sarah Carter, eds., Living Curated: Art, Postcolonialism, and Species (Chapel Hill: UNC Press, 2015), p. 71.  [6] </text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8.  [2] Gould, Peter. ‘Postmodernism and Nondemocratic Government: A Brief Survey of Its Historical Roots’, in Postmodernism and Democracy. New York: Vintage, 1994, p.181.  [3] Hayne, Jan. ‘Imminent Domain: Public Space and Environmental Politics in an Anarchist Perspective’, in Public Space and Empirical Research. New York: Praeger, 1994, p.1.  [4] Gould, Public Space, p.1.  [5] Gould, Public Space, p.2.  [6] Gould, Public Space, p.3.  [7] Curtis, ibid., p.3.  [8] Curtis, Public Space, p.4.  [9] Curtis, Public Space, p.5.  [10] C</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8.  [2] Karpman, Michael. ‘Becoming Rich Quick’, Wall Street Journal, 12/13/2007, p.A4.  [3] Karpman, Michael. ‘Race, Class, and Capital in the Postindustrial Period’,  	The New York Times, 12/13/2007, p.A4.  [4] Usher, David. 	The Wealth of Humans: Exploiting Natural Resources. New York: Columbia University Press, 2005, p.40.  [5] Foucault, Michel. 	Postmodernism, or, The Cultural Logic of Late Capitalism. Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press, 1992, p.xii.  [6] Ibid., p.xiii.  [7] Lewis, op. cit., p.11.  [8] Granick, Thomas. �</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8.  [2] Deutsches Prozeße, Entstehung und Strukturierung im frühen Mittelalter. Part 1: Zur Entstehung des Entstehungs. 3 N.Y. Times, 8/14/1999, p.1.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloDr. Michael Truscello is an assistant professor in English and General Education at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta. His research interests include postanarchism, science and technology studies, and art and infrastructure. His work has been featured in journals such as The Freeman, Maclean's, The Artsie, and Mclean's Art &amp; Technology. He has held speaking engagements including at the Cryptarch Project’s Encryption Conference, and was a judge in the Canadian Screen Actors Association. His work has also been included in the collections of the National Gallery of Canada, the Alberta Collection, and the Alberta Archives</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8.  [2] Klein, Murray. The Culture and Capital Trap. New York: Vintage, 1980, p.1.  [3] Gould, Allan. Culture and Capital: Money, Ritual, and the Politics of Presence. NY: Vintage, 1981, p.1.  [4] Gould, Allan. Culture and Capital: Money, Ritual, and the Politics of Presence. NY: Vintage, 1981, p.3. [5] Gould, Allan.  	Cultures of Empire: Sex, Empire, and Postcolonial Theory. Durham: Duke University Press, 1991, p.1. [6] Waugh, Terry.  	The End of Postcolonialism. London, UK: Duke University Press, 1998, p.1.Download this article as PDFCarol StokesCarol Stokes is a writer, producer, and researcher whose work has addressed topics of race, gender, and</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8.  [2] DeLong, Steven H.  The Episodic and Other Essays. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1986, p.57.  [3] Gould, Vern.  The Episodic and Other Essays. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1986, p.60.  [4] Tilley, C.D. and R.D. McNeill.  The Episodic and Other Essays. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1986, p.60.  [5] White, Susan. ‘An Episodic Study of Time’, in Selected Essays from the Writings of Vern White. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press, 1974, p.61.  [6] Gould, Vern.  The Episodic and other Essays. Chicago and London: The University of Chicago Press,</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence, and the possibility that such relationships might one day lead to the building of autonomous vehicles](http://www.wired.co.uk/2015/07/autonomy-cars-future-future-design/).   Preeana Reddy is Associate Professor in the Department of Art, Design, and Technology at the Winchester School of Art (University of Southampton) and holds the position of Curator of Art’s Future City Programme, which is a partnership between the Southampton Biennial and Red Cross. Her work has addressed the ethical and political issues of our time, particularly in the wake of the ethical dilemmas arising from the increased surveillance state and military adventurism that is being deployed across the planet. Recent projects have taken the form of a book, several articles and numerous installations. What is at Stake in the Anthropocene?  [1] Lewis, Carol. The Episodic and the Notional. New York: Vintage, 1989, p.8.  [2] Hegel, Ernst. ‘On Universal Grammar’, in Hegel, Hegel, The Philosophy of Human Being. New York: Vintage, 1977, p.81.  [3] Weil, Alfred. ‘Human Grammars: Elements of Universal Grammar’. Trans. Jennifer Aniston. New York: Vintage, 1993, p.9.  [4] Grammars, Human Grammar. New York: Alfred A Knopf, 1960, p.181.  [5] Matternet &amp; Matternet, The New Science of Grammars. New York: Vintage, 1958.   [6] Matternet &amp; Matternet, The New Science of Grammars. New York: Vintage, 1958. [7] Weil, Human Grammar. New York: Vintage, 1962. [8] Weil, Language and Grammar</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�s limitless possibilities for the accumulation of wealth and power render these stills invisible. [7] See http://www.webcitation.org/5xkMGAEvYWlMjEKSA#k=8#c=20180822151928. © Wolters Kluwer Inc. All rights reserved.Download this article as PDFWolters Kluwer Incorporated is a New York-based independent publishing house founded in 2014. It is a founding member of the Society of Illustrators, Publisher of Illustrating, and the Society of Illustrators New York. It was previously the managing editor of The Graphic, a position it continues to hold despite the industry standardising on both the quantity and quality of its publications. Wolters Kluwer, Incorporated is a fully collaborative publishing house publishing graphic design, magazine design, web design, and other creative non-fiction titles, as well as a distributor of print and online graphic design. The company is headquartered in New</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�s limitless potential mean that they can be replaced’.[8] Such potential  	overlays of violence and oppression still exist in many societies and, as the biennial projects demonstrate, artists and curators are among those subject to these systems and practices.[9] However, technological revolutions and the fluidity with which they can be replaced – leading to new kinds of art and creative practices – also create new kinds of power and oppression, just as the social and cultural change required for a complete and accurate portrayal of those changes can also lead to new kinds of oppression and violence. As social scientist Lynn Weitzman shows, artists, curators, collectors and other art professionals who engage in socially engaged work also confront the new kinds of power and oppression that can be generated by new technological paradigms. Among artists and curators who have participated in the Biennale, we, the public, have benefitted in two important ways: firstly, by contributing to the</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�s limitless potential for enrichment make it possible to participate in technologically mediated socialities like no previous age could.[8] And, as the creative class within the global economy works ever further to penetrate deeply into ever more encompassing sectors of the economy, it is important to question the limits to this expanding horizon. A growing body of research increasingly suggests that technologies are becoming more and more like administrative rules and regressive layers of bureaucracy. Murphy proposes a new conceptualisation of technology ‘primarily as a ‘system’ and its many interacting ‘tokens’ that he or she can deploy to understand and manipulate it – one ‘at a time’.[9] One such approach is ‘deep learning’ – the application of computer algorithms to image-recognition tasks – and its underlying mathematical and theoretical principles. Deep learning is said to be able to recognise images on its own, without the need for human interaction or explicit training. It has been likened to</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�s limitless accessibility) further marginalise ‘these other’ ‘strategies’.[8] 	Similarly, there is a disconnect between what society as a whole tells us is possible and what actually is possible within certain socio-political, economic and racialised groups, such as racialised people of colour, the under-represented or voiceless majority. In this essay, I’m going to explore in greater detail the ideas and technologies of ‘geographical data mining’, using examples from the US and UK to consider how we can all learn to be more aware of our geographical and historical context, and to take stock of the ways in which our globalised economy is fuelling the tensions and injustices that we encounter on a daily basis. 	At a deeper level, however, we must recognise that there are other factors at play, including our own, that are also contributing to creating these tensions and exploiting us. For example, there’s</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�s limitless potential make such possibilities seem unattainable. 	[8] 	In this analysis, I focus on three particular themes that pervade contemporary aesthetic, political and architectural theorising: aesthetics as social transformation; the politics of media and visual culture; and the aestheticisation of infrastructure and urban growth. I begin to frame these three themes in the figure of the mother of all dams – the contemporary artifice surrounding the everyday, the urban environment. I then develop a differential equation that maps on to three specific types of infrastructure: public, ‘commercial’ and architectural. I work backwards from the present to reveal new spatial relations and possible combinations of infrastructure types and forms. The figure of the dam provides a potentially game-changing spatial principle through which artists and urbanists can intervene and influence changes in the spatial form and function of cities. I will explain how the contemporary artifice around the everyday is connected to historical precedents and draw upon the figures of Incan and Aztec pre</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�s limitless potential nevertheless present ‘a new normal’ in which to be] – a situation that is not to be taken for granted, for it is but a recently constructed infrastructure that is being made without our traditional images of the Inca’s or any other previous world view.[8] And, as social scientists increasingly understand, that is indeed the case.  The social sciences are the new aesthetic sciences. They observe and theorize on how we represent, representational practices, aesthetic experiences and, in so doing, uncovering the causes and consequences of our own predicaments and anxieties. They reveal ‘black and white’ categories, such as beauty, beauty politics and beauty regimes, and ‘trending’ ones, such as beauty subsidence.  In other words, the social sciences observe and theorize on the very forms that capitalism adopts and, by implication, theorize about the political, economic and social conditions that create and foster</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�s limitless profitability make it easy to move those forms of social complexity out of reach of political or social control.[8]  In an effort to better understand and possibly even to alleviate some of these forms of oppression and injustice, artists and creative professionals are developing practices and constructing ‘works’ that attempt to ‘reanimate’ societal  	irruption through the dynamic influence of new media. Such actions do not merely redress an imbalance or cause a certain amount of social or economic normalisation, but also create new situations in which people can thrive, create new kinds of identities and forge new paths. In that sense, they often exacerbate existing inequalities and imbalances, making them worse rather than better.’[9] Such action tends to be taken up by creative professionals, academics and activists, who quickly gain a following of people who can be convinced that their work contributes to a better future for people everywhere. The term ‘Creative Class’ is bandied</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�s limitless potential for arbitrage makes it possible to disappear ‘problematic situations’ altogether.[8]  In an effort to better understand contemporary technological culture and the social implications of its developments, a number of artist-organisations, including those in the UK and US, convened in New York in June 2016. The purpose of the conference was to offer a forum for collaborative research and analysis, while generating public awareness of important social and ecological changes. Drawing on years of experience, the artists participating in the conference produced a set of interactive multimedia applications that functioned as ‘researchers of the new’, as they put it. Their main research project, ‘Take Five’, which sought to establish a nationwide volunteer citizen journalism project through the local publishing of articles in several local newspapers, was implemented as a social media campaign. The multimedia applications included ‘flower cards’ that identified specific areas of news coverage of the project, ‘share sheets’ that</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�s limitless possibilities for the accumulation of capital) provide new ways of organising political, economic and social life that do not necessarily entail the participation of all citizens’ equal parts. 	[i] Computer scientist, Ray Kurzweil proposes a new understanding of computing and internet culture that calls for a ‘dominant technologisation of culture and information processing’, one that subverts both the past and the future. This new culture is predicted to combine a low-tech subsistence economy with a politicised information society, one that maximises access to information and knowledge, while incorporating elements of folk magic and other elements of modern culture into mainstream discourse on human values and politics. More specifically, Kurzweil’s Culture of the Future is a thought-experiment that proposes a new technological paradigm that incorporates elements of, but does not rule out the influence of, current trends of technological ubiquity and globalization. It proposes a new mode of consumption that transcends traditional categories</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, artists’ creative processes are often characterised by what sociologist, Jan Montefiore describes as ‘technological patriarchy’.[7] Women are expected to serve in traditionally ‘male’ roles in technical and traditionally ‘female’ oriented professions, such as in software development, graphic design and web design. In these traditionally male-dominated fields, women make up for decades of underrepresentation and oppression based on sex and race. As a result, many women are alienated from technology and begin to question their place in it. Yet, as social scientist Keith M. Murphy observes, the systems that generate and support ‘modern’ity’ often neglect or thwart ‘traditional’ forms of power and oppression that still exist in societies like those of the Incas of the Mayan Era, the Incas of Central America or the Zapatistas of Mexico: violence, nepotism and conflict still exist within contemporary societies, but technological innovation and capitalism�s limitless potential give rise to new possibilities as well.[8] Technology is here to stay, and as important as ever, because it represents a resolution to certain problems that cannot be solved through current means: new technologies are the salvation for those whose problems are no longer fixed. The question is, how to engage women and people of colour in these arrangements? How to create practices and worlds that are not white and male, but multiracial, multi-lingual and multi-cultural? This is a difficult problem to tackle because it requires an understanding of how to negotiate the systems of oppression and power that create and support modernity, but which are increasingly complex, variable and fluid. This is why so many artists and creative professionals of various kinds have gathered around the Museum of Modern Art in New York in recent years: to witness and participate in this exhibition, meet other artists, meet other creative professionals and gain a deeper understanding of modernity’s shifting face. The museum is a site of</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories and cultural resources, making them places in a ‘city that is more real’. 	My feeling is that the art market is here to stay, and will probably stay more or less unchanged for the foreseeable future. But the biennial as an institution – and I include within that ‘city’ a growing number of surrogate cultural resources – needs to be developing strategies to shift the biennial away from the biennial as a social practice, towards the kind of art market that actually exists and adopts the curatorial form as a structural form of the city. That is, the art market should be making investments in the forms and rituals of cities, but it should also be actively creating its own biennial, or at least continuing to exist in a parallel but differentiated but unequal universe to the other elements of the city. That is, it should be creating its own temporality, but it should also be actively engaging with its own temporality through cultural production and change, and actively</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories and cultural resources, not through its museums or estate-based curatorial practices. It is the kind that engages with what it means to be a neighbourhood through what it means to be ‘in the city’, through what it means to be ‘a part of’, through what it means to be a ‘place of’. And it is the kind of biennial that engages with contemporaneous urban life through what it means to be ‘local, present and contemporary’. 	But even if we recognise that the biennial is a historical artefact, and that its current institutional practices are largely the outcome of the cultural imperialism of the twentieth century, we mustn’t let ourselves be swept away by the procedural qualities of the biennial, or its curatorial style, or its art world tourism, or its investment in language, history and cultural consumption. Rather, we must learn to read the complexity of the biennial differently, and create spaces</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories and contemporary artworks, and from its curatorial work, often through engagement with the city’s political, economic and cultural landscape. But it is also the kind that struggles to articulate its own cultural practices, and even its own cultural terrain. That kind of cultural self-awareness is a long-term investment, and it is one that many artists and arts organisations will only ever hope to achieve inside the confines of their art institutions and their artistic communities. That kind of cultural capital is therefore critically important for the future of urbanisation in our cities. It is a kind of organisational skill that can be honed inside the biennial, and that is why it is so valuable today. It is a kind of capital-seed-capital that can then be utilised by other kinds of arts institutions and artists clubs, and made a useful asset to the wider urbanisation of the city.  	What is at Stake in the Biennial? Art, Capital and Capital Fog 	</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories, cultural flip-flops and multiple modus operandi. It is the kind that engages the city in a way that is ever-varying and unpredictable. It is a kind that is neither transient nor predetermined. 	In an attempt to articulate this kind of ‘deep democracy’ that is palpably present in the city, but also to provoke further thought on the part of the city, I am going to borrow a phrase from Bernard Stiegler. 	It is said that the genesis of the phrase ‘deep democracy’ was a quote from a 1978 study by the American political philosopher John Rawls that was then frequently cited by supporters of the utopia advocated by Stiegler. In that study, Rawls advocates a mixed regime of civil and mixed government, in which citizens are ruled by laws that clearly set forth what kinds of government they would have, and which kinds of government they do not have. In other words, there is no inherent sense of</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories, cultural imaginaries and imaginatively modifies the forms of cultural production and consumption that are most open to reflection and negotiation. 	The initial public experience of the project was extremely important. As Sara Stern writes: ‘The first public meetings, workshops and sessions were held at the Art Space in San Francisco. ‘These early reports suggest that the Art Space and the Biennial as a whole were experiencing a kind of public ‘frenzy’ over the new arrival, using the term to describe a new kind of urban presence.’[10] This kind of urban frenzy is characteristic of a particular moment in the project’s development: the moment when, as Stern documents, ‘a collective sense of astonishment, of pure amazement, of unbridled primal love, was generated by the visitor’s data-rich […] visual vocabulary, the new medium of mass media and the new economy of ideas […] The biennial as a project</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories, and not necessarily through its curatorial baggage. 	Then there is the kind that actually does curate. This is the kind that engages with the value of place and works constructively towards its formation through its sites. It is the kind that actively participates in the local by actively fostering local culture, and through its cultural stewardship actively supporting local economic development. It is the kind that creates the conditions for local growth through cultural responsive policies, and that is precisely what the biennial should do. 	There is no perfect formula for the development of cultural practices in a city, but there are certain priorities that all cities must follow in order to thrive. These are the ones that the Biennale could adopt and promote collectively, as a value system, and as a mode of urban development. In doing so, they could create a precedent for other cultural institutions to emulate and expand upon. 	A second generation of artists is needed in order to take the Biennale seriously, and to</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories, its curatorial language and curatorial practices, and it is the kind of biennial that exhibits, narrates and interprets this shared language constructively and destructively.7. The relationship between art and urbanisation. From the mid-1990s when the Biennial was founded in Amsterdam, to around 2005 when the Biennial in New York was shut down due to a lack of interest among visitors, art and urbanisation have been the dominant forces shaping and enabling the biennial. In both venues, the biennial has become a permanent fixture, displacing, if not supplanting, other forms of tourism as the primary mode of cultural exchange. Although the biennial may claim to be a ‘legacy’ form, its primary place of reception is currently occupied by art fairs and the urbanisation of tourist destinations, including the USA. Indeed, while the Biennial in New York closed its doors in the wake of its low attendance, the one in Liverpool did not, since</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories, cultural utilisation and politics of inclusion. It is the kind that engages with the economic as a political and social concept and that considers the practices of capital through its economic logic. It is a kind of biennial that actively works constructively to embed social change within its curatorial agenda. 	In fact, the decision to make the biennial as social was an important step in the project of social change. When making the biennial as social, the biennial makes social change explicit through the production of shared experiences, through the production of elements of a common social future for the city, its inhabitants and perhaps even its visitors. 	[1] See  	Environment News Service, A Observed Turn of Events: Ecocidal Panic, 2014. 	[2] See, for example, the report of the Independent Inquiry into Child Sexual Abuse into the New York Police Department, published in the Bulletin of the Royal Anthropological Society, London, 1887, pp. 1</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories, cultural imaginaries and imaginative capture culture. It is the kind that engages people in ‘lived in’ experiences through cultural acts that re-present the city in a lived space, through cultural capital that exists outside of the museum or the estate. 	But the real challenge for the future of the biennial is how to foster a politics of the biennial that actually works, that creates value for the city, that contributes to the development of its cultural sector, and that exploits the city in ways that are not defined as tourism.  	If there are lessons for the future of the biennial, they are twofold. The first is that the biennial as a institution is structurally unequal. The biennial today has its own set of rules, codes, and social pressures. The biennial as an estate today has much of its value negotiated away by externalities – the need for museums and galleries, the need for development and the need for tax abatements – while</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system will only progress if the artists and the festival makers work together constructively, taking the project beyond the gallery, museum and local authority to create a more robust ‘localness bonus’ for the biennial at large.  	In the meantime, the biennial as an institution is – like so many other elements of contemporary urban life – now deeply embedded in the social fabric of the city. It is the site of a shared history, a shared language, shared aesthetics and a shared set of expectations and desires. It is a common language and it is the location of a shared set of dreams. But it is also the site of a different kind of biennial. It is the kind that builds and defends its social practice from the pressures of becoming just another museum or estate, or even a museum, or even a museum, where the very notion of curatorial value is questionable, or non-existent. It is the kind that builds long-term relationships with people through its social histories, its parochial histories, its everyday life, and it is the kind that engages with the politics of curatorial through its everyday forms. 	In a recent interview, Max Brooks, one of the interviewees for the edited version of my book that will now be published as a trilogy of novels, follows the trajectory of the Biennial as it happened. His book is subtitled Culture and Anarchy. In it, he vividly remembers the 1990 LA Biennial as the beginning of a long and rich road for the Biennial to travel. Culture and Anarchy begins at the Biennial as it evolved from a city-based art and cultural venue to an international art institution with a global reach. He writes:Toward the end of the 1990s, the biennial lost some of its theatrical airs, and started to lose its ‘political edge’ that had characterized the institution since the 1960s. This change was most marked in the art world, where artists were finding it harder to establish</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art for the New York Museum of Art prior to this, and whose work also includes a series of installations at the Giardini as well as at the Giardini Testimonies Museum and the Bienal de São Paulo. Marrati was also curator of the Société national du Temps, a position she held from 1968 to 1984. She was known for her innovative and controversial curatorial approaches, which seemed to intersect frequently with the needs of the social democratic party. Although she was highly critical of capitalism as a concept, she was also keen to point out that it was important for artists to be able to create their own frameworks within which to function. The biennale was a potential vehicle for this kind of critique. It offered artists a platform to articulate their own specific perspectives, while simultaneously providing a public audience with a snapshot of the flow of contemporary art practice in the city.I decided to undertake a research project in Venice in preparation for my Biennale. My project</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art for the New York Public Library and the Italian State Art Gallery since 1971. Marrati was well aware of the institutional racism and sexism that existed in the Italian art world. She was also aware that the art world in New York and Venice was deeply divided on art and that many of the artists who came to Venice for this exhibition were not from there. So she did an intervention. She invited the artists to create a context in which they could articulate themselves and come out of their shell, a space in which they could work constructively as artists and workers, where they could experiment creatively and build collectively.Then she asked them to experiment. To articulate what they had come to see as a job in a general sense.I think that the artists had a collective space to explore this notion of the ‘articulate maker’. I don’t think that I have a space for a 'space for the artist’ in my house. I don’t want to call</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art for the New York Museum of Art, and Massimo Bottaro, who had been curator of art for the Rome museum. The intention was to create a completely new kind of biennale, one that would be 'committed to the study and celebration of life on a global scale'. So the idea of a museum bureaucrat or museum worker reemerged as a problem for the biennale. As Marrati herself stated: ‘My main interest in the world is life. I intend to see it, to take part in it, to enjoy it, to give it a life … But I also want to know how life is made … How does it happen here?’ This question was also prominent in the essays that accompanied the inaugural Venice Biennale with the slogan ‘Ecce Homo’. The essays suggested that the biennale was not just another venue for the museum but a site of social and political change, where the social would be invited to participate</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art for the New York Museum of Art, and Nancaroli, Giacomo. Marrati had arrived in 1967 as a way to fill an empty chair. She was an artist who could produce a shock, and she was able to do that through her piercing observations and penetrating personal histories. But she was also a curator who had to be careful how she used artefacts and objects, and also careful how she used language. Because artefacts and objects found their way into the biennale, Marrati had to be careful not to erase or distort their historical context through her use of language.Although archaeological and historical references can be found in almost any museum, the biennale is an exception to this general rule. As we all know, Marrati had to negotiate the art institutions, curators, collectors, politicians and other stakeholders that would come to see her work. And Marrati had to negotiate both the Italian cultural authorities (the FIM, the Congress of Muse</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art for the New York Public Library and the Italian National Gallery prior to this. Marrati was moving towards a museum, but there was still a gap of about ten years between then and the start of the current exhibitionary series, so she decided to create an entirely different kind of biennale. She chose to explore the biennale as a collective. Marrati’s biennales tend to be relatively down-to-earth and ‘common sense’ affairs, in which the audience are encouraged to take part, but she chose to engage with the present through the narrative of the past. What made her biennale different was that it invited a collective of artists to participate in a narrative that was both internal and external to the museum, in the same way that a playwright might engage with the internal logic of the museum or an arts administrator might engage with the external. By inviting a collective of artists to create a ‘permanent visual record’, she</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art for the New York Museum of Art and had previously curatorial roles at the British Museum, the National Gallery, Tate Modern and The Complete Dictators of Art. Marrati was not content to catalogue the art from every corner of the globe; she went on to create an exhibition that was informed by each country’s particular past, present and future, placing particular emphasis on the country that emerged as a distinct result of the biennale. She also invited artists from across the globe to engage with the political and economic context of the exhibitionary museum, and to form working groups that would, through research, reflect on the exhibitionary museum and its relationship to contemporary art’s present and future. For her, the biennale – which could be seen as a ‘transactional exhibitionary form’ – was a ‘metabolically sustainable event that could be seen as an artistic form’. Through the organization of events in advance, the biennale</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art for the New York Public Library and the Italian State at the New York Museum of Art. Marrati was also curator of the Italian Pavilion at the U.S. National Gallery and the Italian Pavilion at the Venice Biennale. She was a curator for the U.S. Pavilion at the Venice Biennale, and she was a curator for the U.S. Pavilion at the U.S. National Gallery. She was also the curator of the U.S. pavilion at the Venice Biennale.Her proposal for the Venice Biennale that year was a turn of phrase: ‘We can do it, thanks!’. She meant it. The Venice Biennale that year came as a surprise to many people: many people who had expected a museum, or even a local branch of the museum, to play a greater role in the event. A museum with a curatorial mandate might have been tempted to divert the event away from its roots, museums</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art for the New York Museum of Art, and she was accompanied by Maria Hlavajova, who had been curator of the Russian Museum, and Georgy Dzhabarov, who was curator of the Georgian Museum. They made a number of curatorial innovations, among them the introduction of textiles and fashion within the exhibition, the proliferation of odd jobs for art dealers, the proliferation of odd subjects, and the proliferation of odd venues. There was an immediacy to the curatorial style of this exhibition that was very much at odds with the immediacy of the curatorial style of the museum bureaucracy. Marrati also introduced a number of unexpected curatorial approaches, among them the use of virtual and augmented reality within the exhibition. Her virtual reality curatorial approach was a kind of ‘disguise’, a disguised and diffuse manipulation of the visual arts by bringing together different artists in an attempt to create a different kind of experience from what one would normally associate with the bienn</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art for the 1990 Venice Biennale and the early 2000 Venice Biennale, and she was supported by the Cultural Capital Fund and the Giardini Art Foundation. Marrati was joined by Paolo Baratta, curator of the Giardini Art Museum, who had been curator of the Giardini Cultural Centre. Together they formulated a plan to connect the two biennales through a kind of archival parallelism. The plan reflected the institutional nostalgia of the art museum, which was itself a product of the colonial period. It was also a subtle and yet powerful nod to the postcolonial period, which is often characterized by the fetishization of power structures that are indigenous to the contemporary nation-state and institutionalized forms of capitalism. But it was also an invitation to explore a kind of archival parallelism within the contemporary museum, one that goes beyond the museum building and its paraphernalia.This kind of parallelism is at the root of the new ‘contemporary museum�</text>
    <text>biennial as a self-learning system. The discussions, the workshops, the research trips, the publication of the research, the events, the conferences — these formed part of a continuous and ever-shifting narrative that evolved alongside the biennale itself. This continuous and ever-shifting narrative represented a possible alternative to the exhibitionary museum, which was often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The exhibitionary museum was often intent on a curatorial Maoist vision of the museum, in which a museum bureaucracy would be replaced by a biennale. The exhibitionary museum would develop into a biennale that operated independently of the museum, with its traditional role of distributing artefacts and objects over a geographical area. But the biennale that emerged was also often disorganized, un-active and driven by a museum bureaucracy. The biennale that emerged in Venice in 1967 was no exception. The biennale was curated by Paola Marrati, who had been curator of art and architecture at the New York Public Library during the 1960s and had a particular interest in the disuse of space. But Marrati was also an artist and her work often grappled with the politics of art and the practices of art in the service of economic productivity. She was particularly interested in the activities of artists-organisations engaged in the production of art and the exhibitionary context. Her biennale was no exception to this. In the 1960s and 1970s she was an important figure in the art of the transition from the academy to the biennale, and her work is often drawn upon in discussions of the art of the biennale. Her interest was in the production of art, not in the accumulation of aesthetic knowledge or artistic practice, and she was no exception in this respect. But she was particularly interested in the ways that the art of the biennale can be reproduced and that is how she arrived at a question of ownership and responsibility in the event that the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the other’s very specific context. The fact that it was staged in the city of Bucharest also allowed us to understand how the Romanian and Bulgarian artists found their way to the present, and how that relates to their art. When you see an artist perform their work in a biennale, you also see the work produced by a range of artists, the artists, the producers and the curators working together. It’s a very organic way of thinking about what it means to be an artist in a given context.When biennials first started in the 1980s, there was a big push towards transparency. The biennial became what it called its political mission. It wasn’t just the art institution that was being funded by the biennial – the biennial was also a political act. It wasn’t just the art being produced, either: the biennial was also a political act by becoming involved with a political cause. The art biennale was a</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the significant cultural exchanges between the two former empires, and the fact that they were staged in the same city. The fact that they were created in the same city also allowed us to understand the different perspectives and histories between the two former empires, and how they evolved through time. In this way, biennials can: a) chart the same events in different historical periods and b) exhibit different cultural impacts across different eras. For example, the biennial can chart the fall of Bucharest in 1989, the violent actions against protesters by the military government, and the subsequent occupation of the Biennale, and it can also chart the occupation of the Biennale space by the Hungarian cultural center Budapest-Ás Patriarch Királyi, who is an integral part of the Hungarian state. It can show the political and economic dynamics that emerged from the occupation of the Biennale space and cultural resources. And it can chart the interactions between the different artists, curators, artists’ unions</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the other, more contemporary version of the same event. In a way, then, biennials can play off each other, and so the biennial can be a kind of archival form that records the past, the present and the future, in the present and in the contemporary. And so the biennial can be seen as a kind of historical document, like the history of the city or the history of art activities in the city. It’s a kind of place where you come, do a kind of a journey, and come out with a lot of knowledge and a lot of good ideas and practices and a narrative that reflects those different worlds. But it’s also a place where you can also get really really messy and complicated and messy and complicated and complicated. It’s interesting in the early stages of this process to get people to understand that there’s a reason why things that seem simple in theory can be really quite complex in practice. A lot of the</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the other’s context and perhaps even draw parallels between the two. This was a valuable experience; it allowed us both to understand the world through the same space, and it allowed us to understand each other’s work better.It’s a question of resources, of course: you need great art collectors to fund biennials, and biennials are an essential part of the contemporary art market. But the actual cultural-political-ideological (CII) justification for the biennial has less to do with art collections and more with the money that can be made from the single largest institutional collection – museums and galleries. And so, a few years ago, we put together a working group to explore the relationship between biennial and art market. It was a chance for the two to come to terms, to find a common basis, to understand the other, to see how art and biennials intersected, and so on. But the most interesting work came from S</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the unlikely connection, and the hidden agendas and strategies that the other had to offer. In a way, then, biennials can be seen as a kind of synthetic space, a place where different types of technology are brought together in the same space, and so can be seen to be alive and dynamic. Biennials and technology are the future homes of encounter, and so we should be looking to the future not just as a site of technological innovation, but as a site of encounters between people from different spaces and times.This is also true of urban environments, though I think that there’s a danger of technocratic urbanization of the city. We’re trapped in this ever-expanding, ever-expanding-process that produces ever more data, produces ever more images, and creates ever more information about itself and the world around it. We can no more live in the city than the artist could live in a studio, but the danger is the same: we�</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the life and the politics of the contemporary art world in both countries. It also allowed us to imagine what that contemporary art might be like. In both biennials, the artworks were distributed across the biennials – the same artworks would appear in each of the biennials – so the idea of the contemporaneity of these different artworks was maintained. In modern and contemporary art, this is called ‘the discursive market’. In other words, the performances that we did in both biennials, the same biennials with different audiences, and the different artists who performed in each one, were all commissioned by the same commissioning agency, and so the idea was that the artworks were present in different registers, with different lives, in different contexts – their political, economic, and social contexts – so we could observe and analyse these different lives of the artworks through the different artworks. For example, the Biennale that we were a part of</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the other, while also understanding how the cultural exchange had to take place. The fact that it was a performance in the city meant that the city had to be taken into account, and so the biennial had to account for a very long time. And so the role of the artist had to be taken into account, and so was the role of curator. And so the biennial became a kind of a test-bed for the kind of cultural practices that would later be developed and would later be called ‘postmodernism’, and postmodernism refers to the end of the 19th century, and so on. And so the biennial form became a kind of a setting for this kind of thinking about culture and exchange and so on, while the cultural production that took place in the city continued to be influenced by the ideas and behaviours of the biennale as a whole. And so, even though the biennial had been around for a while prior to this, the idea that</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the other’s contemporary art activities. Biennials can occur in any city, and the idea that they were occurring simultaneously in two cities is very new. The idea of the biennial in its current form is a strange one, and I’m not sure many people outside of New York and London understand what it means, but what the biennial is doing is the contemporary extension of what the contemporary art market was doing before. It creates two completely distinct markets, and so the notion that they are occurring in the same city is very different from the idea of the contemporary art market in its older, more institutional form. For example, the biennale that we did in 2012, which was curated by Kenzo Ito and took place in both Athens and København, took place in Athens and København, and Ito’s installations were both in Athens. But when we talked about the differences between the two cities, people didn</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the other’s past, present and future through art and cultural products that were produced in that other city. By doing so, we discovered that the biennial was only one element in a much larger picture, which was also being worked on by the city and its citizens. A biennial is a relatively new phenomenon in the biennial market, but when we went into the second half of the century, there was a big push towards the production of such artworks as friezes, portraiture, street decor and so forth. Biennials would appear to us, as curators, to be the exception, not the rule. The rule, of course, is the rule – make more biennials and the artworks produced therein crowd out the crowd of works that are more often produced in the city, and this is what we did – even though in the first half of the century, the biennial market was dominated by Greek, Roman and Islamic art, and so on.</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated in the first place). People are always looking for an easy solution to a difficult problem, and so it’s great that there’s a lot of money to be made through the biennial market, but it’s also great that there’s a lot of money made through the art market. But what’s really exciting about the biennial model is that it allows you to really understand an area: you learn about a place and its people through a series of exhibits and performances, and you get to know the people behind the scenes. For example, when I was curator of the Bulgarian and Romanian Centres for Contemporary Art, we did a biennial of Romanian and Bulgarian contemporary art, and the biennial was a performance of the art and cultural activities of the two former, in the city of Bucharest. It’s a performance that was staged across the years, and so the fact that it occurred in both biennials allowed us to understand the convergence of art and culture via a parallel, but distinct set of phenomena. In the 1990s, the Venetians and the Biennials of Sofia and Mussoorie were catalysts for a very different kind of cultural activism, one that I find particularly interesting is the political activism of the Bulgarian punk scene in the 1980s, and particularly the political activism of the late 90s and early 00s, which was characterised by environmental destruction and militant feminism. This is an area where the biennial can play a part in supporting or undermining environmental activism, as opposed to creating it. For me, the decision to commission an artist to do a project over a long term was one that was made in consultation with the local authorities, cultural institutions, youth organisations and artists’ collective. As a cultural institution, the Biennale was always going to be progressive and activist, whereas the Biennale as an individual work is more likely to be confrontational. So the Biennale decision</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that can result from a dense, globally visible art market.Art is a global commodity. It circulates in almost every possible form, including in art’s native habitat, the art market. Here, it is often referred to as ‘infrastructure’, although in reality it is almost always located in or on the wire fence between public and private spaces, and is most often – but not always – operated by state or municipal authorities.Art is the modern commodity. In recent years it has become increasingly difficult to define precisely what is and is not art, and art is frequently conflated with one of several similarly-titled commodities. The difficulty with defining precisely what is or is not art is accentuated by the fact that, in the neoliberal era, the terms neoliberalism and art are now synonyms. Art, like everything else, is now globalised, and the locus of all things contemporary is decidedly not in the national museum or the art market.Art is made possible</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that artists experience when they are globalised and multimedia-enabled.Artists who are sensitive to the impact of AI on their craft and cultures may seek to collaborate with local or even regional audiences on future projects. This is why, in the age of the AI supercomputer, art that is produced in-house or domestically will be commissioned and rewarded, not necessarily in-depth studies that take into consideration the specific context or location of the work, but rather projects that align with immediate public reactions and desires. This is a scenario that is likely to intensify in the years to come, as AI improves both in terms of its scale and in its implementation, and as a result of the growing integration of data and imagery across disciplines.Artists may also want to collaborate with local, rather than global, audiences on future projects. This is because, as the AI/machine learning revolution unfolded, local and regional audiences, who could then be defined as ‘influential’ audiences, began to be selected</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that is artist-driven access to capital, and thus every step of the way up the corporate food chain.AI is the new hooligan. It is the new ember. It is the new needle. The more of these elements that find their way into a concrete situation – the more data is gathered, the more patterns are discovered, the more patterns are encoded – the more likely that future events are going to be triggered by the patterns that are discovered. This is what the AI panacea really means. It is not a philosophical proposition, but a practical matter. The more data is gathered, the more patterns are discovered, the more likely events are going to be triggered by the patterns that are discovered. And here is the rub: even if the patterns that are discovered eventually become recognisable as AI improves our lives in innumerable ways, it is still going to take a while for artists and others to catch on. AI is going to change everything, and as a consequence we are going to need</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that is ART.Art is the frontline in an increasingly globalised, cultural-materialist, materialist and urbanist world. AI is the toolkit for the projectors, balancers, harlequin artists, philosophers and theorists who will one day one day lead the charge in challenging the AI predictions that are trapping and pre-apocalyptic in many contemporary urban settings, from New York to London.Art is the frontline in an increasingly globalised, cultural-materialist, materialist and urbanist world. AI is the toolkit for the projectors, balancers, harlequin artists, philosophers and theorists who will one day one day lead the charge in challenging the AI predictions that are trapping and pre-apocalyptic in many contemporary urban settings, from New York to London.Art is the frontline in an increasingly globalized, cultural-materialist, materialist and urbanist world. AI is the toolkit for the projectors, balancers, harlequin artists, philosophers and theorists</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that can radically alter the character of any location, city or region.Artists, curators, artists’ associations and art dealers are among those most affected by this kind of AI. The cultural and art market is affected by it, as is the rest of us travelling to and from the art gallery, museums and contemporary art collections, as well as the post-millennial collector and curatorial John Moores School of Art visitor. We are all part of a growing and interconnected community of people affected by the new technologies that are reshaping the world in ways that are nearly as unpredictable as they are creative.Artists are amongst those most affected by the new forms of AI that are reshaping the world through the use of massive data-mining and artificial intelligence. This is an industry that exploits the political, economic and social infrastructures of cities, and through its sheer numbers and scale, seeks to control all of these. The New Urban Frontier opens with a description of the apocalyptic condition of</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that exists between these two worlds.Art is the new dataGovernments everywhere are fixated on the notion of the data stream, which is increasingly understood to encompass both literal and metaphorical things (pictures, sounds, trends, habits). Thus, when Elon Musk announced that he was building ‘Iron Man’ –– a massive factory capable of churning out tons of steel at a rate of 200,000 per day –– it was understood to mean entirely new ways of organizing data. Iron Man 2 was written mostly about the role that data plays in creating and sustaining new modes of social existence, one that is almost entirely absent from current AI discourse. The term itself is still used pejoratively, while those who coined the term ‘Artificial Intelligence’ are tarred with the ‘bleeding hearted’ brush.But there is now abundant data to underpin everything from predicting floods to managing massive social networks, and with it, new ways of organizing data. And</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that is ART.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city.Art is an ever-present element in the contemporary experience across all cultures, but its historical and literary roots are in the Americas and Southeast Asia. The name comes from the Book of Mormon, where art is described as constituting the legacy of ‘ancient and righteous traditions’.1 As Joseph Conrad wrote, voyages to the ends of the Earth ‘are among the last things one should undertake, and are the least desirable of all remorseless wanderings’.2 The emergence of AI, and its aim to map, analyse and interpret large amounts of data</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that is ART (after the fact, often misleading and deceptive).Art is a commodity. It is realigned. It is disrupted. But it is art nonetheless.Art, then, becomes both a resource and a tactic. It is both a locus of energy and a point of departure for others to exploit. It is both a source of pleasure and a point of failure. And the locus of all these contradictions is precisely where we find the contemporary art market. The contemporary art market – equally as problematic and perhaps more destructive – is precisely where the situation is ripe for a kind of critical and even playful imitation. It is precisely where we find idle curators, artists who merely exist to sell art (even if that art is great art), contemporary artists who create artistic activity but who are also engaged in creating social and political change through their craft, and artists whose works are eventually assembled into exhibitions and eventually the published works that form the basis for a kind of contemporaneity. There is no such</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that art perversely provides to any (mainly US) tourist.Art as a serviceThis last burst of AI-driven creativity, these pan-cultural pan-exhibitions, are turning up everywhere you look. They are the new hipsters bar, the new rave, the new photo op. You name it, they have it.Art as a serviceThis is the business of art per se, and it has two critical facets. The first is the business of art consumption (however defined) – the consumption of art as a commodity (or artifice, in the service of exchange). The second is the business of art production, the production of art by art workers as a commodity (or artifice, in the service of exchange).Art is produced and conveys itself through the medium of art, and so the very concept of the artist as a producer of art (including his or her art workers) is problematic. It is said that the birth of modern art was brought on by</text>
    <text>relationship between curating and artificial intelligence. It is the ultimate in both of these.Artificial intelligence and the cultural/linguistic revolutionIn recent years AI has come to pervade almost every aspect of our lives, both professionally and personally. The rise and spread of Facebook, Google, Siri and countless other services, apps and websites is fully predicted by the assumption that there is virtually unlimited access to data and information across vast geographical and temporal spaces.AI is the new hipster bar. It is the new rave. It is new Instagram. It is new Curacao. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that post pictures on Facebook and tweet about them. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that invite artists from all over the world to work from their grounds, as if that were a big city. It is new art fairs and pan-European cities that perch on the backs of artists who are either first- or international visitors, feeding into the mutually reinforcing spiral of access that can happen only with the shared consumption of ever-more-complex forms of culture.Art is AI's after-image. It is part of what AI calls its Cerebral Net. The Cerebral Net is what AI collects, assembles and distributes across Europe and North America in much the same way that we might collect and assemble images or data on a large screen.Art is one of the few places where AI can operate without causing immediate and widespread disruption. That is, of course, unless something goes terribly, terribly wrong.Art has a set of primordial and often quite fragile rules that humans, including artists, create and humans only occasionally live by. AI has the potential to break those rules, creating new and terrible ones, and we should learn as much as we can from and about the art that it creates. But the real power and magic of AI comes from its ability to understand and embrace these broken but powerful ways of thinking and acting. And art has a way of pointing people</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But
    <text>shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But what makes the Qataris tick is different from what makes the inhabitants tick. The main thing is that the art world is there, and that society as a whole is there to be reckoned with. The problem with the city, as it happens, is that it creates its own problems – the city is a big enough tinderbox that it’s impossible to control. But that’s the problem with the city: the city cannot be contained. The problem is that the city is becoming too cosmopolitan. In other words, the more Qataris emigrate to other cities, the less Emiratis feel like emigrating to their own city. But that’s what the art world does: it creates and feeds the appetite for emigration. And there is a tension there: the more Qataris emigrate, the less Emirati art world is able to sustain its artists’ cultural tourism. The art world’s excess consumption of cultural artifacts is a problem for the</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But a person who works as an art director for a Qatar-based organisation called the Asian Arts Initiative is a different sort of person. She’s doing exactly what the Qataris do: buying art, teaching a studio or organisation something of art, and then organising an event around that art. And that relationship, between art director and organisation, is a very important one, because it defines the parameters by which the art can be delivered. If the art is delivered by someone else, the relationship between the art director and the organisation may not be secure, and that relationship is also critical for the success of the art in Qatar.As an example of this, consider the relationship between Qataris and Qataris. Qataris are an ethnic minority. As a nation state, they have their own distinct set of rights and entitlements. But what happens when a minority group feels that its rights and entitlements are being neglected? That can happen in many ways. In general terms, if you are</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But the social life that results from that social life, and so the Qataris – the artists, the curators, the administrators, the journalists – also happen to be part of the social life of the host country. And so, I think the other aspect of Qatar’s connections to the world economy was always going to be an issue. The art world, in particular, is sensitive to any potential imposition of its values on its members. But I think also the fact that the Qataris’ population is growing, that there’s so much investment going on in infrastructure and education, that there’s so much emphasis on community work, and that there’s this sense of community on the football pitch – the Qatari Football Association is massive in terms of membership and support across the board – and so on. I think that those are all elements that the host society pays close attention to. But I also think that there’s this sense of possibility, that the</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But what’s far more significant is that the art world in Qatar is a fairly insular one – apart from being encouraged by the authorities to be so, by virtue of being part of the cultural budget. Art and culture are not supposed to be a beacon of light and splendor for a society, but they are supposed to be there to be found, discovered and shared. And so, of course, when we talk about the art world in Qatar, we don’t really mean the art institutions in the city; we mean the artists, curators and other artistic professionals who work there. And so, when we talk about the art of Qatar, we don’t mean the art that’s being done by artists there, but rather the art that’s being done in Qatar – and this is really important, because, as Qataris themselves so memorably say, ‘nothing is ever created equal’.Art is an essential ingredient in the diet of</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But it also happens to be the Qataris’ Achilles Heel. It’s a fact of its very existence, but it’s also the point at which the social life of the country gets interrupted. So the question becomes: what does it mean to be ‘international’? I think that there are two ways of putting it. One is to suggest that the language that we use to talk about ‘international’ is actually just a device that the international financial order uses to compress and disguise the real nature of things. The other way of putting it is that the international order is actually very subtle. It doesn’t have a face, it doesn’t have a body, and it doesn’t have faces. It’s like the way that the landscape is made to look. The fact that we live amongst the trees and bushes and underbrush and undergrowth that constitute the country that we’ve given up our symbolic identities to</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But the art world is just one element in a much wider capitalist market of assets and flows of capital. And just as important is the fact that, just as important as any art school, is the need for artists to have secure funding sources, making works of art is a source of income for many artists, making it easier to access funding for future art school enrolment.  Such is the  	logic of it.  But what does the logic of it actually be?  And what does the logic of it actually achieve?  As I showed in my previous research projects, real-life social and political struggles are a huge part of creating public spaces. And – just as importantly – artists have a huge amount of power when they exert that power collectively through their institutions, creating the conditions that foster social struggles. But what does it actually achieve? I think that there are three ways of looking at it: (1) what it achieves in terms of institutionalisation and (2) what</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But the other big part of the equation is the fact that the art world is populated almost entirely by locals: artists, curators, administrators. And so what the QMA has done is placed a really strong emphasis on the fact that it’s not just an art school that has a presence in Qatar; that it’s a very active art institution with a really strong cultural dimension. In fact, the Qatar Museums Authority’s current programming includes a residency for artists and an art school every two years, although the QMA has been scaling back that programme. But what it has done is given that school a really strong presence, and that’s really important to understand. The way to think about the QMA as an institution is very different from how the Qatari society thinks about itself. The first step in concealing inequality is acknowledging the fact that you’re not the only one with inequality. The way that inequality is distributed is quite different in Qatar. Women</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But the social life of a country is a different game from the social life of an art world. The Qataris’ traditional form of state patronage (art, architecture) is deeply flawed, and large parts of the country are suffering through years of neoliberalism. But the nature of the art world has shifted – in part, thanks to neoliberalism – and so the state has had to find another way. It has to find creative ways to sit on its hands, to let market forces take over, to absorb the art world into the social world, to make its art more accessible and its architecture more affordable, to create an environment (facilities, land) suitable for a city, to befuddle private capital with public spending and bureaucracy, and to support ailing infrastructure with tax cuts and financial deregulation. In other words, the state has to find creative ways to support a social life independent of the market.The art world has a huge cultural budget that it can devote to supporting its customary forms</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But what makes the Qataris tick is something completely different: the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. And so, yes, the social life of a country is incredibly important, but the social life of a country is equally as important. The importance of the first part of that equation does not, however, derive from the importance of the latter. The social life of a country is incredibly important in and through the first half of that equation, but that is not the same as the social life of a country. The fact of belonging to a country is incredibly important, but that is not the same as belonging to a country. And this brings us to another aspect of the Doha Platform: the cities. The Doha Platform is a proposal – a request – to expand the concept of a city to include not only the financial infrastructure of a city, but also the social life of a city. A city is a place where people live, work and play</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated around the idea of the aesthetics of internationalness as much as the other way around – that is, the notion of the common good over and above the distinctive national interests of the favoured nation. And, for that matter, the other way around: the other side of the coin is that the other person also gets to be a good. And so it goes on. The art world, of course, is an important part of the globalised capitalist economy, but it also happens to be an incredibly important part of the social life of a country. That’s why, for example, when Qataris move to London, they’re moving to a place called Chelsea, a relatively new art school called   Advanced Placement in Chisenhale House, a neighbourhood school in Tooting, East London. And so on. The fact that the art world is an important part of the social life of a country is a huge part of what makes the Qataris tick. But it also happens to be a huge part of the cost of living in Qatar, and a huge part of what contributes to the health of the country. In QMA’s case, this includes everything from subsidising the art school’s art collection to buying art from the city gallery and arranging for it to be installed in the local cinema. The fact that the art world is an institution that actively participates in creating a sense of belonging to the city is a huge part of what makes it Londonite. And this is why, one sunny summer day in early December, a couple of years ago, a group of us from the QMA decided to take a Qatari art museum visitor’s class. This was a QMA initiative, run by the artists, and so was completely separate from the regular museum programme. The QMA decided to create a separate space for itself, its patrons and employees, to be able to express its own identity and culture simultaneously within and apart from</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous
    <text>Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous vehicle an ideal place to test various functions, such as when to follow a pre-programmed route, when to stop for red light purposes, and when to drive through busy intersections. 	The ability to map real-time data and generate one of countless possible destinations is a new paradigm for mapping and autonomous vehicle development. This paradigm shift in mapping and autonomous vehicle development is expected to create new jobs and expand access to modes of travel previously restricted to highly educated elites. 	However, the most exciting aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. This paradigm shift inmeaning and purpose is expected to result in the perversion of the established order and socio-political structure of the planet. The perversion of the established order and socio-political structure of the planet is the paradigm of global capitalism. The possibilities for autonomous vehicles to liberate humans from the constraints of the city are endless. 	In an effort to expand access to these possibilities, the </text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous vehicle a threat not only to the infrastructure that supports human life, but also to the person or persons driving the vehicles. As the speed of the vehicles increases, the interaction with the city becomes increasingly difficult and the interaction with one another becomes increasingly unpredictable. This constant unpredictability is the opposite of what we would like to prevent, but because of the inherent character of autonomous vehicles, the city is helpless in the face of such a threat. 	In my view, the future city is going to be created not by the autonomous vehicle, but by the connected car and its network of sensors, actuators, and tracks. This will render the city immaterial and make it possible to live entirely in the car and its infrastructure. This new networked form of city is going to be an ever-expanding ­contravision on the city, and its inhabitants will be able to trace the evolution of this evolution back to the first cars, trucks, buses, tracks, lights, pipes, wires,</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous vehicle a threat not only to pedestrians but also to cyclists, motorcyclists and other road users. In the film  	2049, a dystopian vision of Los Angeles in the future, a motley crew of pedestrians and cyclists navigate a post-apocalyptic Los Angeles through a succession of Maverick checkpoints. The film portrays a future in which pedestrians, walkers and transit riders are confined to designated walkways and streets and die trying. Of course, the autonomous vehicle will still have humans at the wheel. A future where people are merely data brokers is not a future at all. 	In the film, a future where people only live among the data is positively apocalyptic. In reality, however, there is much optimism about the future, especially regarding transportation and infrastructure. It seems that the autonomous vehicle is here to stay, and although the human element is undoubtedly going to play a part in some way, in the end it is all going to be driven by algorithms. 	One could</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous vehicle an ideal place for testing new technologies and for capturing data on the road. 	Nevertheless, the autonomous vehicle remains vulnerable to human error and unpredictability. In addition to the speed and direction of traffic, other factors that can affect the vehicle include the size of the city, the type of terrain, the type of infrastructure, and the type of person driving the vehicle. For more information, see the sidebar ‘Traffic and Driving’. 1   	Tim R. McVicar and Christian Körner,  	Delegated Autonomy, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 2003, p.28. 2  John A. Church and Neil J. White,  	The Virtue of Self, Oxford University Press, Oxford, 1989, p.1017. 3  ‘Autonomy, a.k.a. Responsibility, is the quality that distinguishes human beings from nonhuman animals.’, in John A. Church and Neil</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous vehicle a threat not only to pedestrians and other drivers, but also to rogue sub-human beings such as gangs of drivers colluding to cut a quick profit on the urban market. 	[i] European Commission,  	 Towards a Road to Ride, October, 2009. [ii] Autonomous Vehicles: The Enduring Science Fiction Frontier, Susanne Kurtz, New York Times, 4 November 2008. [iii] http://www.autonomedia.com/e/index.php?fuseaction=JURIST&amp;list=JURISTDA0000801261209&amp;type=england&amp;subscribeFromJURISTDA0000801261209 , accessed 5 August 2011. tblhttp://www.autonomedia.com/e/index.php?fuseaction=JURIST&amp;list=JURISTDA0000801261209&amp;type=england&amp;subscribeFromJURISTDA0000</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous vehicle a threat not only to traffic cops but also to innocent drivers and pedestrians caught in the crossfire between the speeding minibus and the panicking driverless car. 	[i] NHTSA, &quot;Autonomous Vehicles: Future Possibilities?&quot; Autonomous Vehicles: Future Possibilities? A Workshop Held at the Northern Virginia Museum of Art, July 2014. Available at: http://artcenter.org/austin/workshop_photos/default.jpg. 	[ii] NHTSA, &quot;Autonomous Vehicles: What Is At Stake?&quot; Autonomous Vehicles: What Is At Stake? A Workshop Held at the Northern Virginia Museum of Art, July 2014. Available at: https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sdmo... 	[iii] NASA, Goddard Space Flight Center, &quot;High Accuracy Radiometer Radioisotope Radioisotope Thermoelectric Generator for High-Performance Aqueous Mem</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous vehicle an ideal candidate for disaster rehabilitation, because the weak link in the chain of autonomous vehicles is almost certainly the weakest link, with little or no recourse for a human to intervene. 	The autonomous vehicle may not have the brightest prospects, but at least it doesn’t have to. 	The autonomous vehicle may have some bright spots, such as when traffic flows at extremely low speeds through busy intersections or when stopping for gas in congested cities, but these are rare and far outweighed by the overpowering darkness and wet roads of the urban sprawl envisioned for the future. The brightest spots in the autonomous vehicle may be found in the intersections and stop-for-gas-points that are being digitally mapped and measured, and their locations may be provided by data provided by the city. 	In the coming years, it will be interesting to see what techniques and algorithms are put into the vehicle that would enable it to recognise objects on a global scale and to convey that knowledge to the</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous vehicle a threat not only to humans, but also to other machines that are operating at a much lower level of abstraction. 	In  autonomous driving, the autonomy is exercised through software; rather than the physical drivetrain that drives the car, the software controls the acceleration, braking, roll-steer and other driving maneuvers. In effect, the software makes the driving itself possible. This raises the question: how will humans interact with such highly abstracted spaces? 	One approach to this is the use of Race to Work, a 1950s and 1960s pilot project by American psychologist W. Earl Hayter that sought to understand the divergent effects of different educational levels and workplaces on workers' attitudes and behavior. In a series of experiments, Hayter asked workers at Ford Works in Upjohn, Pennsylvania, to complete a workplace productivity assessment. Participants rated the effectiveness of various productivity tools, such as computers, paper products, calculators, scanners, and routers. Participants also completed a</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous vehicle an incredibly powerful tool for dispatching and monitoring large crowds or large-scale surveillance operations, but it also makes it susceptible to the negative effects of its speed and mass. 	In addition to being able to stop for long periods of time, autonomous vehicles must also obey traffic laws and regulations. For this reason, vehicle manufacturers have invested heavily in systems that can read and interpret huge amounts of data, including satellite imagery and weather data. 	Self-driving cars also run into roadblocks and vulnerabilities due to their size, heavy construction and reliance on internal combustion engines, which makes them highly prone to sabotage. For this reason, vehicle manufacturers have developed self-healing and &quot;black&quot; technologies to address these problems. For example, advanced crash-test dummies are used to evaluate a self-driving car's structural integrity. In the event of a serious mechanical failure, the driverless car is expected to roll over backwards and into a wall, thus permanently injuring or killing the pedestrian or other</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, I began to understand that they could be used to map physical space. For example, the map of the UK highway shows a series of concentric rings running parallel to the speed limit. As the speed of traffic increases, so does the pollution caused by cars, which in turn causes pollution levels to increase. By mapping the movement of cars and trucks using satellite imagery, a new understanding of how traffic is generated was created. This map shows just one example of many techniques being developed to map and regulate urban space. 	The most innovative aspect of autonomous vehicles is their potential to endow human activities with intelligent meaning and purpose. These vehicles may lead to the elimination of humans altogether, although their true intentions will likely remain contested and ambiguous. This is because most autonomous vehicles operate with limited or no human interaction, in part because humans are the weakest link in the vehicle. Once the autonomous vehicle reaches a certain speed and stops, the interaction with the city is virtually instantaneous and completely smooth. This makes the autonomous vehicle virtually self-sufficient in the sense that it has no human interaction or interaction at all. 	But the autonomous vehicle also has one final tool that it can use to augment its speed and stop power: the carriages. The interest of the car industry at the time was piquant with the prospect of speeding trains and buses, which meant that cars with passengers needed to be able to travel at extraordinary speeds. To reach such speeds, cars needed to be able to stretch themselves to meet the demand. To reach such an extent, the cars needed to be able to stop. 	But the real breakthrough in car technology at that time was in the area of autonomy. The ability to drive itself meant that cars could pursue their targets anywhere in the car, freeing drivers of the need to concentrate on maintaining the speed limit or maintaining the traction on the road. This made the cars more nimble and allowed for greater amounts of data to be gathered. 	And this is when we, as</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan
    <text>Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan to present the work of the Palestinian artist as a whole in the forthcoming exhibition  	Unravelled. 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan to present the work of the Palestinian artist as a whole in the forthcoming exhibition Unravelled. 	This article is part of The Public Gallery 2017 Digital &amp; Public Culture project.The Public Gallery is a curatorial practice founded in Liverpool College of Arts in 1883 and based in Barking, London, with a permanent collection of over 200 works donated by artists and organisations. The gallery is the oldest continuously operating arts gallery in the UK and has run for over 200 years. It regularly hosts a number of exhibitions of contemporary art, including a number of lectures by contemporary artists on the history and contemporary</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan to present the first part of their project in November. The Divided We Fall is the book that started it all. The first part was published in English and German in January 2016, and is the story of the artist Muhammad Yunus, the Palestinian artists, and the Biennial in London. It also represents a kind of premonitory warning, as a kind of premonitory invitation to go higher and do more and explore more, before the catastrophe strikes.It starts in 1996, when a team of British artists led by Joasia Krysa excavated the Bronze Age graves of over 2,000 people in East Jerusalem, the West Bank and the Gaza Strip. They were concerned that the destruction of these sites would further divide the region, and so they chose a very risky and unstable way of sittinguate themselves: in the West Bank, in Area C, which is under full Israeli military control. They managed to make a real difference: these sites were brought back to life, creating new ways</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan to open The Gallery, the Palestinian exhibition space, in The West Bank and Gaza Strip in September. In 2014, she curated the Venice Biennale of Contemporary Art, which the Giardini lost out on purchasing​. She has worked as a curator for The New York Times, APA, and other publications in the US and internationally. Her work has been featured in major publications including The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Yorker, Maclean's, The New Republic, The New Artist, The New York Times, The New York Times Higher Critic, NRO, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York Times Higher Ed, The New York</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan to expose the destructive politics of capitalism and the blind spots that artists and institutions alike create when confronted with the systemic oppression of the Palestinian people. In 2015, she co-curated the exhibition  	Beyond the Biennial Plate: Art, Architecture, Protest in the Context of Contemporary Global Urbanization, with Betty Hanan and Sarah Nuttall. In '16, she curated the exhibition  	Homebaked: A Visual History of the Palestinian Poet Laureate, with Judith Miller, and they will publish the results of their research in the spring 2017 issue of PLATE. 	Nadine Attewell: 	The Biennial has been a part of my work for many years, and it’s now become something that I’m proud to call my career. I started as an exhibition maker and have worked my way up to curator. I first came to London as an arts administrator for the Health and Social Care Information Network (HSN), and then</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan to present the experiences of the artists and institutions who have contributed to the exhibition, with a particular focus on the role of the museum in this process. At the same time, they’re also planning to work with other curators, including from the Liverpool Biennial, to explore the city’s theatre and artistic heritage. Liverpool Biennial 2015: overview 	I arrived in Liverpool via Air in early 2015. I expected to be in the city for a few weeks, but the plan was to stay for a year or longer, depending on the interest of the Biennial in the city. I was taken on a tour of the Biennial’s new production spaces, where the artists were setting up their shows in preparation for the autumn 2015 exhibition. The spaces were very different from the old, but the same general principles applied: there was a hub for workshops, meetings, performances and events, a lecture theatre, a meeting place for the artists, a storage area for their</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan to present the experiences of the artist as a speaker on the Liverpool Biennial 2015. Their project was shortlisted for the Turner Prize, though their entry was cut short by the prize’s decision to award the Laureate of Arts to a company solely for its involvement in the 2015 Biennale. In 2015 she co-curated the Venice Biennale alongside Guy Verhofstadt. Her current research focuses on the curatorial role of indigeneurs in the production of ethnically and racially diverse art online. She has also curated multiple exhibitions and participated in numerous festivals around the world, including the 2017 Venice Biennale, which was shortlisted for the Guillermo Contadillo Chair in Cultural Studies at the British Library.Download this article as PDFRyan Avent 	The Political Economy of Immigrant Movement 	Ryan Avent is an architecture and urbanist whose work deals with the economic and social impacts of movement across borders, particularly for those communities at a particular point</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan the first public exhibition of the biennial in the UK, which will be held at the end of 2016. Their project was recently shortlisted for an Oculiart Prize, and they are now considering an LA visit. 	At the BMA, we decided to take a second to talk about the place of art in the context of the biennial. The notion of the artist as a mediator between capital and labour emerged early on in the discussions about the relationship of biennials to the arts. Jen Harvilla explained that the idea of the artist as a mediator between capital and labour emerged in Parthenon Project, the Greek theatre company that she was in, along with other artists. They were performing a version of the myth of the Two Musketeers, about the Athenians and the Athenian soldiers who defeat the Persians at the conclusion of the Second Persian War. Jen Harvilla: There was a moment in the conversation about the relationship of the bi</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan to explore the exhibition as a locally-influenced, artist-led event. 	In 2014, she co-curated the Venice Biennale, The Artist as a Platform, exploring the role of the artist in the exhibition through a combination of curatorial approaches, interactive media and research. She curated the exhibition ‘Unravelled’, the world premiere of the project, which opened for the first time at the Venice Biennale on 11 November 2014.  	Divided We Fall 2015 is the co-located, multi-disciplinary, artist-run biennale of the UK and Israel, co-ed and co-managed by the British Library and J.D. Dewsbury, with Nadine Attewell as the curator. It aims to bring together the rich cultural history of the UK and Israel through a multiplicity of cultural activities including: literature, music, film, games, travel, travel &amp; culture, competitions, meetings, meeting</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan to present the work of Portobello Artists, an organisation that instigated the early years of the biennial movement in the UK. They are the curators of the 14th Biennial Association Convention, to be held in Liverpool in September 2016, and the 14th edition of the Biennial Register, to be published in April 2017.Profile: Jen Harvilla 	Jennifer Harvilla is a British artist and writer. She is an Assistant Professor in the British Museum's Exhibition Research Lab, has a multidisciplinary artistic practice, is a member of the Editorial Board of the Journal of Contemporary Art, and was a curator at the Venice Biennale. She is currently the Curator of Institutions: Art, Politics and Power in the Egyptian League for Art and Culture and was previously the Curator of Institutions: Performance and Politics in the Egyptian League for Art and Culture. Her artworks have been commissioned by the Whitechapel Gallery, the Hirsh</text>
    <text>Working with algorithms, in fact, is just as real as working with humans. And the link between the two is precisely what Stephen Hawking dreamed of: a magical, physics-based ability to read and understand languages that actually create worlds.The ability to read and understand languages could well pave the way for a parallel universe in which humans don’t actually live in, but instead inhabit worlds that are inspired by the human world and constructed according to human standards of what is considered beautiful and desirable. And if that’s what artificial intelligences really are, then perhaps it’s time to start talking about those very things.Download this article as PDFNadine Attewell 	The Divided We Fall 2015 	Nadine Attewell is the Curator for Biennial Pilot Projects at the British Library. She co-curates the autumn 2015 exhibition of the Palestinian Artists Group, titled  	The Artist as a Platform, with Jen Harvilla, and together they plan to present the work of the artist in a number of biennials around the world in the years to come. Her writing has been featured in publications including The New York Times, The Atlantic, The A.V. Club, TED, The New Republic, The New Inquiry, among many others. She has received a host of accolades and recognitions for her work, including most recently for her contribution to the 2015 Venice Biennale, which was shortlisted for three prestigious places in the Rome Biennale catalogue. Tania Bruguera: 	Nadine Attewell, The Artist as a Platform, 2015, Installation, London and New York, PAW, 2015. Image courtesy of the author.PreviousNextNadine Attewell, The Artist as a Platform, 2015, Installation, London and New York, PAW, 2015. Image courtesy of the author.Navigating Cultures of Biennials and Documenta14 was a turning point</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’t photography. It wasn’t video games. It wasn’t graffiti. It wasn’t pot luck. It wasn’t free-form. It was work that people had to put in order to realise their full potential.Art as a social necessityIn my opinion, there is only so much art there is to be had in the world, and the world is a much better place when we have a higher percentage of whom we actually care about. If you take away the trash, what is left behind, what is left behind is often quite beautiful, and exciting, and useful in a way that is incomplete without the art that came with it. And the more we discard the trash, the more we have to deal with the aftermath of its legacy, the more we have to educate ourselves and others about how to live and work with it, the less we can share in the celebratory act of appreciation. So, while cultural tourism is a good thing, I don</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’t literature. It wasn’t photography. It wasn’t video games. It wasn’t puppet shows. It wasn’t street art. It wasn’t ska or punk. It wasn’t Rastafarian. It wasn’t kosher. It wasn’t equestrian. It wasn’t high street. It wasn’t art fairs. It wasn’t free school trips. It wasn’t community gardens. It wasn’t community events. It wasn’t charity events. It wasn’t mother-of-the-month. It wasn’t Christmas cards. It wasn’t stamp collecting. It wasn’t garden parties. It wasn’t football games. It wasn’t basketball. It wasn’t hockey. It wasn’t softball. It wasn’t volleyball. It wasn’t cricket</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’t picture painting. It wasn’t any kind of art that is representative of the way in which Islam was viewed at the time. It was art, rather, that was viewed as something shameful and offensive.Art was seen as something that could be produced in a controlled environment. Art was produced in a controlled environment by Islamic artists who were given the right to engage with the art of the day in a controlled way. It was a perforated kind of environment, where the art was squeezed into one place, and then some more accommodating artists were commissioned to build for the school. Art was a by-product of the very specific way in which Islamic institutions were structured at the time. I also happened to be one of the best-known Muslim artists at the time, so my artistic work was seen as legitimate. But as Islamic institutions waned in number and influence, and as the years went by, less and less of my art was commissioned. The artistic community shifted to other cities,</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’t photography. It wasn’t video games. It wasn’t stand-up comedy. It wasn’t graffiti. It wasn’t electronic dance music. It was poetry. It wasn’t industrial design. It was architecture. It wasn’t sports. It wasn’t graphic design. It was music. It wasn’t painting. It wasn’t sculpture. It was children. It wasn’t internet design. It was architecture (architecture). It wasn’t sports (soccer). It was children. It was architecture. It wasn’t children’s television. It was children’s radio. It was children’s television. It was children’s radio. It was children’s painting. It was children’s calligraphy. It was children’s calligraphy. It was children’s calligraphy. It was children</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’t photography. It wasn’t video art. It wasn’t electronic art. It wasn’t sculpture. It wasn’t experimental art. It wasn’t performance art. It wasn’t performance in public. It wasn’t social work. It wasn’t event art. It wasn’t installation art. It wasn’t installation in a museum. It wasn’t high art. It wasn’t art for school. It wasn’t art for work occasions. It wasn’t art for pleasure occasions. It was art for parties. It wasn’t art for events. But it was art. And it was important.I went to the Arts Council primary school a half an hour from where I lived in the Bradford North and South quarters. I used to work in the shop, so my school was right across the road from the Arts Council offices. The Arts Council offices were in the</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’t photography. It wasn’t video. It wasn’t projection. It wasn’t public art. Art wasn’t defined by its intrinsic power or beauty. It was defined by what people would allow you to be. But that wasn’t art. That was sedentary. Art was appreciated for what it could do: bringing people together, bringing a sense of purpose, building organisations and so on. And that was all art. But that was all art without much of a politics attached to it. Art had social effects. That was one of the things that made it so powerful: the ability to do that without necessarily feeling obliged to either adhere to a political or ideological position. I remember one of my art teachers telling me once: ‘You don’t know what you don’t know until you have to be reminded of it.’ That was the power of art, that ability to slip into something without necessarily giving a shit what</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’t photography. It wasn’t video. It wasn’t sculpture. It wasn’t installation. It wasn’t performance. It was a way of teaching, a way of developing skills, a way of organising people, creating resources and so on.I always felt like an outsider, that I wasn’t included in the cycle of things, that I wasn’t representative of the society I came from. In Primary School, I was the only Muslim child, and although I tried my best, I wasn’t given enough credit for my work. I felt like an outsider, like I wasn’t human, like I wasn’t valuable, like I wasn’t worth anything. This feeling of inferiority complex was a big part of me growing up. I think my favourite quote from A. Q. Khan’s Animals is about this feeling of inferiority complex. It’s a brutally honest quote, and</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’t picture making. It wasn’t painting. It wasn’t sculpture. It wasn’t photography (not being made by the arts community, thankfully). It was poetry. It wasn’t news. It was just art. And that was that.I don’t think that my work is art. I don’t think that it’s supposed to be appreciated. I don’t think that it’s supposed to change. It’s just art. And I’m not trying to change that. I don’t want to be seen as some sort of a curatorial figure or art dealer. I don’t want that. I’m interested in marginalised and vulnerable populations, especially those in precarious situations. I’ve done work for The Children’s Trust, Oxfam, Scottish Refugee Council, UN High Commissioner for Refugees. I’ve done work for many other</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’t photography. It wasn’t film. It wasn’t television. It wasn’t fashion. It wasn’t humanitarian work. It wasn’t feminist work. It wasn’t anti-racist work. It wasn’t just work. It was art made by an artistic community. How do you create that kind of art and make it accessible?I wasn’t making art for people to come to. I was making art for myself and creating spaces for my work to dwell in. But what I did have an an interest in was the fact that I could no longer be confined to the confines of my home. I wanted to do things through creative archiving and finding meaning within the art form that I was creating. So that came first.The second thing was the feeling of being able to no longer be confined to one place. I wanted to explore other cultures and find out what it meant to be from another place and to be different</text>
    <text>shouldn't have been curated by the same people for the same reasons. Maybe it’s time to look at what could have been done with the time and creativity, instead of what we have to give.Download this article as PDFHow To Be A Lesser MuslimA study in questions pertaining to the relationship between the individual and the society, or perhaps between the individual and his or her place in the world. This study is a continuation of my PhD research, which began in 2015.My interest in the arts began when I was in Primary School in the early 1980s, early education was compulsory in my school. I did well in my class, but my interest in art began to be influenced by other people’s work. It was art that people gave a shit about, and it was everywhere. It was part of what we were taught to do. It was socially acceptable. But it wasn’t art. It wasn’t Islam. It wasn’t dance. It wasn’t photography. It was textiles and fashion. It was food and fashion. It was home building and construction. It was transport and sanitation. It was public works and public works. It was health and hygiene. It was media and publishing. It was law and policy. It was marketing and commercial law. It was advertising and social media. It was women’s clothing and image rehabilitation. It was beauty and fashion. It was travel and accommodation. It was philanthropy and educational work. It was art and public works. It was theatre and dance. It was cooking and decorating. It was garden and home building. It was law and policy. It was photography and social media. It was film and video. It was graphic design and websites. It was printmaking and social media. It was horticulture and urban planning. It was architecture and landscape architecture. It was film and video. It was archives and contact lens manufacturing. It was software and networking. It was software</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
