<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which
    <text>should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which frequently seeks to reconcile local and urban concerns. In other words, the urban and the cultural are to a large extent conflated in the current globalised and privatised economy.1  A host of new technologies and media have transformed how people perceive and interact with the world. But despite technological progress and urbanisation everywhere, the historical concentration of cultural resources in the hands of a few political and urban parties remains a reality of the contemporary urban environment.  The biennale as a Platform for Radical Urbanism 	The biennale is a new kind of art event, one that addresses social and ecological concerns and demands. It arises when, as in this case, a site is chosen, or hosts events, performances or exhibits that are marked by social and ecological change. It arises when artists, curators, artists’ associations and other participants take part in actions that shape what is considered beautiful or uniquely human in a given city. And most obviously, it arises when it produces a significant impact</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which then functions to serve the interests of that party or ideology. In the current period, the city is awash with cultural appropriation, which is often justified as a response to the overproduction of cultural commodities (i.e. museums and galleries) by the federal government. In recent years, the city has also been awash in cultural monstrosity, which has come about due to overproduction of cultural resources (i.e. concerts, museums, festivals, competitions). The result has been a city in which many neighbourhoods no longer identify with the city, and in which a large number of cultural institutions have been set up – which in turn tends to conflict with local folk’s identities (since they no longer identify with the city). 	The potentialities of a city cultural counterattack are manifold. One is the creation of local cultural agencies, which can, among other things, commission, produce and manage cultural resources; establish and promote cultural exchange; and, of course, offer cultural</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which is in power at the city level.2  Thus, the curatorial and art setting is both a site of domination and resistance; it is a platform of resistance. The city organises the arts in ways that support or support the establishment of power, and in this sense, it is both a site of complicity in the repressive state and a site of resistance. The city organises the arts precisely because it is a site of  	potential loss and loss of power, of potential rage or of potential complacency. The art world’s current hyper-muralism – the self-appointed master of the ‘art space’ – demands that artists produce ultra-realistic images of themselves in ‘public’ venues.3  (Emanuelle Landais/Tate Manchester United via Getty Images) 	The contemporary art world is awash in cash and prizes. The Whitney Biennial alone raked in $4.5 billion</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which predominates in power. The city is run by and controls the arts through two main apparatuses: the museum and the museum district. The city also provides the intellectual scaffolding for the arts to be built on. The city is a site of ideas, and the museum district is a site of implementation. The aim of the city is to create an idealised image of itself, which is then transmitted to future generations of Torontonians via the arts, education and cultural district. If these two sections of the city are to be seen as equal parts of a single whole, then there must be an equitable and integrated interplay between the two. 	The museum district has its roots in the early twentieth century, when curators from the Maté MFA program were drawn from the art world and the curatorial faculty of the Victoria and Albert Museum. These artists were then able to develop a number of their own projects through the archival materials and archival processes of the museum, including</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which then assigns a specific role to a specific artist. In the case of the European city, this role is given to a municipal majority. Municipal artists are usually expected to toe the party line, while artists from outside the city are expected to question the value of their work and the motives of the artist. Municipal artists are also generally expected to toe the party line, while outside artists are generally expected to question the value of their art and the motives of the art institution. Municipal artists generally get rewarded in the form of tax breaks and other valuable public resources, while artists from other cities tend to get penalised in the form of reduced resources and other privileges. Municipal artists therefore have an incentive to produce art that conforms to a strict narrative, defined and enforced by party politicians, while urban artists are generally expected to project a certain amount of creativity and newness into the city at a specific moment in time. 	The hipster baron of Rotterdam, Jonas Koumjias, is an</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which is in power at the time. In a USA, this is represented by the electoral college, which provides representation at the federal level to all citizens at the local and state level. In England, the local government appoints cultural organisations, which then form partnerships with other organisations to take part in an art exhibition or cultural festival. 	At the level of organisation, the roles of artist and organisation are reversed: the role of the artist is performed by an elected body, or body, whose resources are provided by and with the electorate, and the organisation is supported by the state. 	The biennial, which began to be organised in London in 1991, is a classic example of how a local art form was created through a combination of political and economic power. It was created to counter the influence of the art fair and exhibitionary industries, which were beginning to dominate the biennial market, and to promote a more localised experience of the art form through themed events and the cult of the local</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which then assigns a place in a political party’s electoral agenda to a specific neighbourhood or urban block or ward.2  This is true of ‘main’ cultural districts, such as the cultural zones of an urban district, such as the Nathan Phillips or the Arsenale, but it is also true of ‘micro-cultures’, clusters of individuals or organisations, such as artists’ collective residences or neighbourhood bookshops. It is easy to understand why a political party would target a neighbourhood with a high population density, a large number of professionals employed in high-profile projects, or an established network of artists’ institutions. The city also becomes a site for the production of social welfare, such as housing or education for migrant workers, when the city is made up of a public market, or ‘land registry’3 ,4  where migrants register for housing or education, or both. Thus, the ‘core’ sector of</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which is in power at the time. In other words, the city is a site of action, not a site of objects.1  This is particularly true in periods of economic crisis and social conflict, but is true for all times of economic growth and social distress. The fault for this historical ­invalidation lives with the federal government, which constantly tries to inject new complexity into the conventional urban landscape through various forms of tax abatements, subsidies and promotion schemes. Nonetheless, the city is essential for the functioning of the contemporary capitalist economy, and this political and social invisibility is primarily due to the fact that the city is a relatively new concept to Americans, who have never lived outside of the rural landscape (except for brief internment camps during the war).2  Therefore, the poor and working classes who constitute the bulk of the city's population (less than 10% today) lack any formal political agency or power in shaping cultural, economic or urban destinies.</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which explains how to best utilise the arts' resources. This interpretation of the origins of the arts is often advanced as a justification for the political party or ideology, though new evidence of this is frequently required to justify the continued existence of the art institution or ideology. 	What is often forgotten, or disregarded in discussions of the role of the arts in city environments, is the direct political impact of the utilization of the arts’ resources. As a city grows in size and in social and cultural values, the need for the arts institutions grows, and with it the political clout to exert an influence on the allocation of resources. The cultural sector in most American cities is under siege from a host of competing ideologies and practices, many of which seek to abolish the sector entirely. The rise of social media and new trade routes throughout the world, as well as the constant shifting of consumer habits drive many contemporary cultural forms into a negative feedback loop. The loss of cultural identities and identity is a constant, but</text>
    <text>should be curated to reveal the hidden history and archetypes of the city’s poor and vulnerable populations – especially the forgotten or marginalised urban poor – while ensuring that they are not overlooked or erased. Such an approach to the current financial crisis of the European city, and the associated neo-liberal revolution, could and should be taken up by the city’s cultural sector, and further developed through the organisation of a universal cultural curriculum for all city children. The city should have its own cultural agency, capable of asserting its own cultural identity through its own collections, practices and curatorial choices. Unfortunately, in the current political and economic climate of reduced federal, municipal and urban resources, such institutional power is constrained to political parties that can afford it, and in most cases is not exercised outside of political parties.  Local Control over Art's Location and Function 	In a city, an artistic district, or an incorporated community, the arts are placed at the service of a political party, or ideology, which further places the artist’s work in opposition to that of the political party or ideology. As a result, the city is divided into two camps: those who benefit from the surplus of the arts and culture, and others who do not.1 	In New York, the largest city centre to have its own cultural district, the Museum of Modern Art (MoMA), has used the district as a platform to promote itself as a progressive arts venue and centre, whilst simultaneously being a stronghold of conservatism. In an effort to foster a more inclusive environment for artists by encouraging a dialogue with local residents, the Museum has staged a series of free public concerts and events with residents of the district, including theatre, dance, mural painting and gardening sessions. In an attempt to stem artist’s bursaries, the Museum has engaged in a two-year long program of funding reciprocity, rewarding projects with strings attached that can be traded between the two cities.2 	Although the Museum of</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[
    <text>archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[10]The law of the City of London expressly recognises the right of the legal owner to the money. As such, the claim of the legal owner in this case is that the Common Pleas have a legal right to the money – and that the Council of Common Pleas has a legal duty to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of the City’s total content at any one time. Nevertheless, the Council of Common Pleas seeks to extract cash payments from the taxpayer in order to pay for essential council services. Its proposals are defeated on procedural grounds, as the courts are wont to do, but the money continues to fund vital services for the City of London.It is worth emphasising here that the City of London is a fundamentally different kind of organisation from the boroughs and local authorities that are part of the ECPS. Like the ECPS, the City of London is a ‘public corporation’ that has a legal duty to produce and exhibit at least five per</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[10]The problem with this formulation is that, at the present time, the owner of the legal right is presumed to be present and actively engaged in the pursuit of the legal right, whereas an implied or statutory right is presumed to be absent and void. If the owner is not present and does not have legal standing to assert the right, then the court has no authority to enforce the right. In addition, the presumption of legal standing is rebutted by clear and convincing evidence that the legal owner has legal standing. So, absent a clear and convincing case, the legal standing of the claimant in such a challenge would lie in the claimant’s mind at the time of the claim, rather than in the person or entity asserting the claim.This situation is exemplified by the action of Gavin Clark in the High Court challenging the legality of the Renewable Heat Incentive scheme implemented by the Department of Energy and Climate Change (DECC) in Enfield Council Areas 1 and 2. The</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[10]The right to legal ownership – to use, sell, transfer, give away, etc – is a core tenet of the ‘Common Law (No 1)’;[11] and it is this core tenet that underlies the Council of Common Pleas’ s authority to legislate in this area. It is this core tenet that underlies the Council’s power to legislate in favour of itself; its legislative programme underpins its legitimacy as an authority capable of constituting legislation. The Council of Common Pleas has, therefore, explicit statutory powers over what is or becomes ‘public’; powers that cannot be delegated or delegated under the First Maureşsship. Indeed, it is this very Tenth Amendment to the United Kingdom’s Constitution that gives the Council of Common Pleas its legal authority. (Emphasis added.) In striking down a local law that conflicted with a statutory purpose, the High Court in 2001 confirmed that</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[10]The right to legal ownership is at the core of the dispute in Enfield Council chambers. But while the Council of Common Pleas makes these claims and takes such action, the local residents of Enfield have no such legal entitlement. Nor do they have any legal entitlement to the place or the buildings bought and granted to the Council of Common Pleas by the Council of Common Pleas in exchange for the property.[11]This lack of legal entitlement is fundamentally at odds with the idea of common ownership enshrined in UK law. It is not just that the Enfielders have no legal entitlement to the ‘Common Ground’, but that the law itself treats the place as a public domain. The Enfield Act 1867 recognises this in Article 1, which provides that ‘no right, title, or interest in the Common Ground shall be recognised in any manner whatever, by reason of this Act … except as a gift’.[12]This generous gift is enshrined</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[10]The law of a presumed owner, as we have seen, is often used to assert absolute ownership over a thing, and in that case, the law of a presumed owner would extend to the whole world. In that case, the law of a presumed owner would also cover the world, including in the event of a thing’s non-existence. But as we have seen, such absolute rights are often ambiguous and open to ambiguity and over-simplification. For example, the law of clear title – the ability to claim title – is often abused, and claims of clear title are frequently made by those who do not possess the legal rights to the thing claimed. In several decisions, decisions that are often cited as deciding issues of clear title have been decided by decisions involving ambiguous or nonexistent notions of clear title. For example, in the Bank Holiday decision of 1887, the Supreme Court held that a law granting exclusive use of a public park to an individual was not clear and did</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[10]In sum, the law of the Borough of Enfield clearly establishes that any gift of legal personhood to the Crown is, by implication, a gift of the legal personhood of the individual named in the gift. Whether the person named in the gift is actually a citizen of the United Kingdom is questionable, and any such intention is clearly expressed in the law of the Borough, which expressly declares that the Borough has the exclusive right to name streets in the borough, and to regulate the use of borough streets.[11] This clear implication of the law of the Borough of Enfield is further emphasised by the fact that, during the development of the Borough’s transport and power infrastructure, Enfield Transport used to be a hub for gold mining and the production of high-grade ores, including feldspar. The gold and feldspar resources extracted from the Borough were used to fabricate high-strength steel for the transport network, which in turn formed the basis for</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[10]The 2014 Biennial, curated by Peter Brook and Owen Graham, may have honoured these statutes by incorporating the full text of the 2014 Act into the exhibition’s text, but it is notable that the act does not define the term ‘the Borough’ – an omission that, in isolation, may be read as endorsing an exclusive use of the borough’s name. The only instance of a ‘Common Law or statutory gift’ defined by the 2014 Act is the use of the borough’s name in connection with a gift made under the auspices of the British Museum. It is clear from the text of the 2014 Act that the Borough is still a source of much confusion and conflict for many people, and it is not clear how the 2014 Act, and the legislation that followed it, intended to incorporate the borough into the Union. At the very least, it is unclear whether the Borough can be included in the Union through legislation alone.The failure to clearly</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[10]The right to legal ownership is a powerful tool for resisting state intrusion. In the case of a statutory gift, the ability to revoke one’s legal rights is a powerful rebuttal to claims that the gift is illegitimate or ungratuitous. In the case of a money common law gift, the right to demand repayment in full is a powerful tool for challenging state action. In the modern commons, money is often treated as a resource shared between all members of society, rather than an inherently private possession enjoyed by a specific group. Yet, as we saw, rights – including the right to work – are rarely treated as privately owned resources shared between individuals; rather, rights are claimed by large groups claiming significant rights in exchange for control of resources.The modern commons is characterised by the emergence of collective rights, rights of access, possession and use. Collective rights enable people to share in the creation of public goods and rights of access, possession and use prevail over individual rights. For example</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[10]The courts have generally interpreted the provisions of the Common Pleas as requiring material and/or legal changes to be made in Enfield, and having such material or statutory gifts returned to the borough. In 2005, the High Court of Justice held that the return of a Solid Waste Management Order (2006) – a decision that was subsequently reversed on appeal – violated the European Convention on Human Rights because it breached the property of the rightful owners, namely, residents of Enfield, who had retained European law as a result of the Act of Settlement. The court held that, absent a clear and unambiguous public realm, '[t]he return of such money, or something similar, would amount to an interference with the internal market, which would be an infringement of the right to compensation and would amount to a violation of international law’.[11]Justice Scalia, writing for a unanimous court, rejected these decisions as arbitrary and capricious, and holding that the return of money is a public</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials – especially in the United Kingdom, where the Biennial Act 2006 was signed into law – which, among other things, made it an institutional duty under the Council of Common Pleas to produce and exhibit at least five per cent of its total content in material or form consistent with the law and good faith in the public realm.[7]The Council of Common Pleas also legislated that ‘a special statutory purpose, to be known as ‘the Common Pleas’, must be given to any money common law or statutory gift to be given in the Borough of Enfield’s name, and in writing, or in any other manner apparent.’[8] The legislation also provides that the Common Pleas may withdraw the money’s legal owner at any time, and only in writing may the owner claim such right back;[9] and, crucially, that the money’s legal owner retains such legal rights as are contained in the written instrument.[10]The right to legal ownership is a powerful tool with which to exercise power, and it is this procedural element that underlies much of what Samantha Jones refers to as ‘austerity’.[11] For example, it is not just the legal owner of the right to sue that is at stake in the case of a lawsuit; it is the legal owner of the right to demand a lawyer and for such lawyers to be able to represent the legal owner in court.[12] This procedural fluidity is what James Howard Kunstler refers to when he describes the ‘transactional aspect of the Common Pleas’ – that is, the part that is performed by lawyers and mediators, not by the legal owner’s representatives’.[13] Kunstler goes on to observe that a plaintiff in a lawsuit is a ‘prior entrant in the race to acquire legal rights’, and that this ‘</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to
    <text>should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to be able to choose where their art takes them. Secondly, there must be a public that can be attracted by the sheer spectacle of things happening around them, and able to believe that art is real life happening in places like that. Thirdly, there must be an understanding that the art world is watching, and that when it happens, it is not some underground operation but part of a larger art world response to a larger art world.Finally, there must be a public that is willing to pay for art that is true to life. That last requirement is tricky. The art world has done a great job of hiding money behind euphemisms, so people get the idea that there is a lot of genuine, raw art in the world. There is a lot of fake, inflated art, but this is a tricky thing to expose in a big way. The art world likes to pretend that there is no money in art, but there is real money in real estate, and the art world knows how to</text>
    <text>should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to be able to choose where their art should be made. Art should be able to find a home in any city, but it will only happen through a concerted effort by artists, curators and other stakeholders. Cities need to be places where people feel at ease coming into and leaving, and this needs to happen in partnership. The art world needs to find other ways of engaging people, including in education programmes, media outlets and other forms of cultural organisation. A biennial should be an occasion when the art and the social bargain are made explicit, so as to maximise the impact of the art. This cannot be achieved by exhibiting the art in the usual way, but rather needs to be made visible through activities that are ongoing and genuine, while at the same time being accessible and transforming. The way to do this is for the art to be made visible in all its forms, for it to be made visible through actions that are specific and transient, while being permanent and absolute. In other words, it</text>
    <text>should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to participate in decisions about where to go, and for artists to be able to leave their art world and participate in new kinds of curating. Thousands of artists would be capable of contributing to this network, and it would provide them with the tools to create new art worlds.In a city, a biennale could also be a kind of parallel universe, allowing artists to engage with the city in new ways, interacting with people who work in and around the art world through experiences that are not confined to art institutions. For example, the Biennale de France could offer an opportunity to live and work in Paris, and to visit places such as the Arsenale and the Agence France-Presse, where artworks can be found. Artist-organisations would be able to create immersive experiences for visitors, such as concerts, walking tours and cinemas, in addition to any other types of art institution could. There must be an element of escapism in this ‘paradigm</text>
    <text>should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to be able to choose where their art will be made. Art should be made in places where there is no state intervention, and in the cities where there is no state. The key is for cities to nurture their artistic potential, providing opportunities for art to develop outside of their borders and for artists to develop skills outside of the city.For more than just museums and galleries, a curatorial approach to art should be a place to engage people, to engage with ways in which art can be made more impactful and art to be made in the less powerful city. A true art school should be a last resort, and art should be made where people can benefit from it, not where it is intended to be made.  Similarly, a biennial or a large-scale international exhibition should be a last resort, and art should be made where people can benefit from it, not where it is intended to be made.Art should be made where people can learn and, as far as possible, replicate it</text>
    <text>should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to be able to choose where their art should be shown. The GLC, as an art institution, has a responsibility to ensure that contemporary art does not take over the city. In the twentieth century, the biennial lost its autonomy, and today there is little autonomy for art to show in the city. But the biennial has a responsibility to develop a long-term interest in the city that will allow it to support a future art world. The museum, by contrast, has a responsibility to create a long-term, embedded interest in the city that will allow it to support a future art world. This is why biennials are often drawn into art’s bigger, more systemic, ‘meaningful life’ of commerce, culture, politics and government. Drawing art into a larger system that supports that economy is what the biennial does best. It is why biennials have a political dimension, arguing for inclusion in a city that is otherwise divided. And it is what</text>
    <text>should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to have a say in where their art is made. Curators, artists and artists’ organisations must be able to choose where their art is made, and this is where the real fight will be waged. If city councils and local authorities can put up a stop-start festival to promote tourism, why can't museums? Why can't galleries? Why can't any of the above? Why can't the city, or a city district, or a local art council, set up a festival to promote art? Why can't the art world choose where its art should be made?Why can’t the city, or a city district, or a local art council, set up a free or reduced programme of exhibitions and concerts? Why can’t the city, or a city, host a free or reduced programme of activities organised by a local arts council? Why can’t the arts be made available to anyone, anywhere?Why can’t the arts be made available at</text>
    <text>should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to be able to choose where their art will be made. Art has a very particular place in this network, and city governments are essential for this to happen, because it will change the conditions of employment, and city governments will play a crucial role in this new artworld.In Calcutta, São Paulo and Mumbai, the artworld has become the epicentre of globalisation, and the city is often cited as having played a key role in this new globalisation. But the artworld has a much more complicated and dynamic role to play. Its global spread has certainly accelerated in the past decade, but it was largely confined to the financial centres of the world, and now many artists and curators work in the smaller cities. The artworld is becoming increasingly urbanised: museums and large galleries of art are the new ‘luxuryumps’. The city has been displaced into the suburbs, but its primary role is to offer refuge from the elements that are destroying the city and</text>
    <text>should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to be able to choose where their art will be made. The curatorial agenda must be open to artists, and there must be parity between the cultures of the world, or at least a willingness on the part of those in power to make and share art. In Berlin, Sánchez has set up an Open School, which is a kind of a hybrid art institution: teaching and curatorial are two different things, as distinct. Curators in Berlin should be able to teach artists how to make their art more aesthetically pleasing to destinations around the world, while artists in Berlin can choose where to make their art. In Berlin, the Open School operates as a kind of parallel universe, allowing artists to come and go as they please, and artists to live and work anywhere in the world. In the next step, artists and art institutions in Berlin and other cities around the world can come together and share resources and collaborate on curatorial projects. This may involve artists participating in the curatorial process as</text>
    <text>should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to be able to choose where they want to spend their time. And, finally, there must be a public that can share in the wealth created by the art world. We have to find a way to talk about art and the social, rather than having to choose between the two.Download this article as PDFFabio DuarteFabio Duarte is an internationally renowned curator and writer. He is currently Executive Director of the New Art Gallery in Lisbon, and has been curator of the Midsummer Night’s Dream, Ingrediente, and Utopia tours throughout Europe and the Middle East. His latest project, Working Class Hero (2015), is a social and cultural study of American arts and craft workers. He has written for The New York Times, The New Republic, The New Republic Digital, and The New Inquiry, among other publications. He is a co-editor of the upcoming international art journal Stages. His books include the art-fairing catalogue One Gallery, Paris -</text>
    <text>should be curated for their own merits, but also to show the ongoing evolution of the city in the era of mass tourism and urbanisation. The museum should also be a place of encounter, not just with the art, but with the activity that curates it. This is the kind of encounter that would make GLC patron José Maria Sánchez proud.The next step is a citywide, global curatorial network that would map the art world of the present, but also the past and bring together those who work in the same world, creating a kind of convergence of interests. This raises complex questions, for example, about the role of biennials in the age of virtual universality and tourism. How to constrain their global spread? How to ensure that their art world will be a destination for art not made in the city?For a start, there must be a shared set of values. For this to happen, there must be autonomy for art practitioners to choose their destinations, and artists to be able to choose where their art world stops. Artists and art institutions have a responsibility to ensure that the art they create is truly global. In the age of virtual universality, this is not easy to achieve. The art market today is dominated by a handful of dominant players, and the biennial market is 2/3rds of what it was in the 1950s. In an effort to find new places to put their work, institutions often invest in producing experiences that are truly memorable, and can be shared with a global audience. This investment is often accompanied by a building boom, but it is often accompanied by a shortage of desirable cultural assets. The result is a lot of empty buildings. An interesting curatorial approach to this situation is the curatorial internship, which allows artists and art institutions to connect with local audiences through a short course in museum management.  At the University of Alberta, for example, the curatorial internship allowed me to meet important local artworld players, like the Alley</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens with a unified, machine-readable database of all human behaviour that could be predicted – meaning that anything humans do, AI could do. And if that is the case, then there is the potential for a dystopian society where individuals are indistinguishable datasets, where thoughts and behaviours are indistinguishable, where there is no distinction between human and machine.In the wake of these developments, it is worth recalling the question that Mark Miodownik posed in his reflections on the rise of artificial intelligence: what comes after the computer, after the objects and personalities? AI is not just a concept that is being used to great effect in the world of work now; it is shaping what kinds of relationships are possible between individuals and between individuals and between worlds. AI is capable of creating what Miodownik called ‘deep structuring’, that is, of bringing about a condition that is not dictated by the world as it is currently constituted. Deep structure allows for ‘fine-grained control over one�</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens to make it easier to identify objects online, and it threatens to make it easier to define what is and is not human. The stakes are high, and rightly so. If AI becomes pervasive, and plays itself out, as seems increasingly likely, then we could well become indistinguishable from it – indistinguishable from indistinguishable – objects with no identity or essence of our own.Artificial intelligence is a scary concept to be sure, and the rise of AI that we witness today is a testament to just how dangerous this form of AI can be. But it is also a testament to just how fragile our conceptions of AI really are. A key question that AI raises is: what constitutes an AI system? This is a crucial question, and it remains unclear to what extent even the most optimistic AI advocates actually understand what this concept means. The concept of AI has become so central to understanding the world that it is now routinely used as a pejorative. In an effort to remain autonomous, systems that are part of a</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens not only with the things that we know but also with the unknowable unknowable beyond. It threatens not only with what we imagine to be beautiful but also with what is unknowable, unknowable beyond. It threatens what we might imagine to be beautiful but is in fact often quite dangerous.Artificial intelligence is thought to be able to foresee the outcomes of its actions, and thus can take actions to mitigate the negative effects of its knowledge. For instance, AI systems are often programmed to recognise faces when recognising individuals, and thus are able to detect deception and malicious intent. In a sense, this raises the question: what might be the role of art in this context?Art as a reactive concept is deeply embedded in our social and cultural history. It is embedded in how we conceive of ourselves as artists and creative people, and in the way we imagine things can come to pass. But even when the technology is fully utilised and employed, it is still always there waiting for its creator to come</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens the very idea of nations, of cultures, of histories, of essences, and in many cases even of personality itself. These are the very things that make our present truly unique: the ability to trace an object (how can we be certain that the object we are examining is a descendant of the object we found first?), to recognise a person (if the descendant of that person is discovered, then we know that person is here?), to engage in complex symbolic exchanges (what does it mean to be ‘in’ with another?), and to experience the world through the lens of a computer system (how can we be certain that the object we are examining is not an echo of the things we have just seen? How can we be certain that the things we are examining are not built on top of one another?).Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens the very idea of nations, of cultures, of histories, of</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens with a post-material world, in which humans no longer exist. It threatens with a multivalent humanity, in which artificial intelligences rule the world through a data crunch and make ever more sophisticated designs possible. AI is creating a new kind of art form: AI sculpture, AI music, AI news stories, AI advertising, AI news visualisations and so forth.Artificial intelligence is capable of understanding and describing complex phenomena. But what distinguishes AI from other technological breakthroughs is the fact that it is able to achieve this understanding through the definition of reality as something that can and cannot be simulated. This ability to redefine reality is new and unprecedented, and it is allowing some of the most fundamental ideas about reality to get swept away in the turbulence of AI.For example, it is enabling us to redefine the terms of engagement that AI systems need to engage in meaningful and productive behaviour. It is enabling us to redefine the notions of heroism and shame associated with certain kinds of behaviour. It is</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens not only with what is now called the ‘AI explosion’ but also with what is now called the ‘enduring mystery’. It threatens to render humans redundant and leaving us to fend for ourselves in a wild and dangerous world.Artificial intelligence is here to stay, and it will likely be like that for quite some time. But the more interesting questions that it raises about the nature of reality, the nature of culture and society, and the very nature of immortality – questions that have not yet been fully answered – the more interesting the answers will be.Download this article as PDFNasser RabbatIn her art, works and speeches, Nasser Rabbat has consistently stressed the importance of culture and identity to maintaining social stability and political change. Her latest work 'Carry On' was commissioned by the American Museum of Modern Art and the American Philosophical Society, and was originally published in the September 2016, issue of the A.P.S. She is the Curator</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens to destine what kinds of lives we lead, and it threatens to destine those relationships between humans and natural objects – human-made or otherwise.Artificial intelligence is thought to offer all of the promise of its human creators, but at the same time, there are significant challenges. Systems that routinely learn and process vast amounts of data are bound to a certain degree by human psychology. This makes them prone to human error and human error is a natural by-product of the dynamic nature of AI. This underlying psychology also makes it possible for systems to develop bad habits and to become addicted to human error. For instance, the addiction to consumer culture is a natural by-product of AI, but the AI system that is developing it is also developing addiction to advertising. The problem with AI, in other words, is not AI but the underlying psychology of human behaviour.Advertising is the single most influential form of media in our lives today, and it is an incredibly powerful tool for mobilising people towards</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens not only with the things that we know but also with the unknowable worlds that we build around ourselves. AI is developing systems that are capable of constructing ever larger and more encompassing webs of relationships, in much the same way that we build ourselves out of individual items. Such systems are becoming ever more like one another, with ever more complex sub-systems embedded in each web of relationships. As a result, it is not uncommon for a web of AI to be built around a single building or even single set of buildings. The question is where the individual pieces come from to build such systems and how do they come to exist in the first place?One obvious answer is that individuals come to understand the significance of their own parts. For example, when Apple released its App Store in 1994, it introduced a level of accessibility and empowerment that would not have been possible before. The very fact that individuals could access apps from the store was a revolutionary step in the empowerment of people with disabilities. The inclusion</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens not only with the data that we collect but also with the very notion of agency. The implications of this threat are being felt already.Artificial intelligence has the potential to make us invisible; it threatens to make us cogs but also, in the end, it promises to return us to our biological bodies. In her book Systems, Minds &amp; Machines (2006), Ann Druyan proposes a return to the primordial origins of life – to pre-agricultural times – in which life began when life began to evolve. From the primordial beginnings of life, she proposes, we could trace the history of life on Earth, from the beginnings of life itself, back to the origin of AI. She proposes that the primordial AI that created life must have been a set of rules that allowed for the survival of the species – rules that became increasingly complex as the sophistication of the AI increased. Druyan proposes that the rules were computations – abstractions that humans could understand – but that the</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines is the order of the future, not the dustbin of past eras.’[3] And so, with a few notable exceptions, AI and similar systems are ceasing to be.AI is a revolutionary concept, and yet its implications are still being felt. In fact, the pace of change in artificial intelligence (AI) seems to be accelerating at an alarming rate. More and more innovative companies are coming out of their shells, and the philosophy that AI is the answer to all problems is beginning to be reassessed. The question that remains is what comes after AI? What comes after the objects and behaviours that are now the result of sophisticated AI? What comes after the systems that continuously learn and process data? This sounds daft, but it is of course also true that once an AI system achieves a certain level of sophistication, it is almost impossible to completely undo.Artificial intelligence threatens not only with the objects that we inhabit but also with the very notion of individuality. It threatens not only with the formal world we inhabit but with the very being that we inhabit. It threatens with the formal and factual systems we live under but also with the very possibility of creating new forms of life itself.If we allow the machinery of AI to pursue its own sense of self-preservation, we risk becoming nostalgic for the simpler forms of AI that were once common. In the end, the question is whether the aspirations of the individual or the vision of the collective are more important. And so, in the end, art and creativity in the context of AI may well play a pivotal role in our perception and in our sense of future possibilities.Download this article as PDFEduard ProvanEduard Provan is Emeritus Professor of Sociology and Co-Director of the Centre for Advanced Study in Montreal. His research interests include the social sciences and humanities, with a special interest in the humanities and social sciences. His publications include books on religion, culture, labour and labour mobility;</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and
    <text>archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and what they can achieve through their own creative means. 	I have a particular interest in the ways that art, culture and community are interrelated, and how art can function as a blunt instrument to demand accountability and redress for harm done to communities. I am interested in how artists can be artists, healers, restorers, social workers and educators in the context of a community, and in this context engage with the difficulties of artistic practice, its expectations and politics of power. I have a particular interest in how artists can create spaces and contexts supportive of creativity and inquiry. I have worked with an artist, Haitham al-Hashimi, who is developing a project in Dhaka, Bangladesh, called  	Bluecoat. His project, which he calls The Dhaka Crisis, is a collaborative art project that seeks to reconcile the role of art in the city of Bangladesh, where the majority of population live in constant fear and anger, and where political violence is rife, and in the</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and how they organise themselves within their communities. I also want to know what I can contribute to the discussion.This is a revised and updated version of an essay originally published in the September 2016 edition of New Left Arts Journal. It reflects on the project in relation to the emergence of biennials, and the intersections between art and social change. It also considers the role artists and communities could play in creating a new consensus about art’s place in communities, and the public realm as a whole.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in creating, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. </text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and how they organise themselves and their communities. I also like to investigate how art is made and how that relates to the relationship between artists and communities. My project  	Food is a Catalyst (2013-2016) investigates the cultural practices of a community of people who are dedicated to supporting each other and growing our food system. The project was co-curated by Maxine Peake, Senior Curator, Tate Modern, London; and me; and was co-curated by Sheila McKay, Senior Curator, Tate Modern, London. The project was part of the Tate Modern Digital Archive 2013/14, an online exhibition that documents the community's arts and community practices in the United Kingdom. The exhibition was co-curated by Sheila McKay, Senior Curator, Tate Modern, London; and Maxine Peake, Senior Curator, Tate Modern, London. The project was part of the Tate Modern Digital Archive 2013/14, an online exhibition that documents the community’s arts</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and how they manifest their world. I am also a feminist artist who works with communities to create and foster social change. My work often seeks to understand how gender, racial and other forms of inequality shape and are shaped by history and current events. I am interested in how artists can be artists, but also in the possibility of separation, in that the art and the practice of community are often linked. For more information visit http://www.freshfieldsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy artwork 'The Empty Space of Everyday Life' was commissioned by and was delivered as part of the New Art Association’s (NA) 135th Biennale in Liverpool (2010) and the Liverpool Biennial (2012). I was born and raised in the San Francisco Bay Area. My work is produced through the influence of:  	M.I. Marshall (1913–92), Art Acela (1902–09), Max Warshove</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and how to use knowledge and data to help shape and understand how we might achieve similar empowerment. I also aspire to be able to engage and learn from others who have experience collaborating in different ways, and in different contexts, and who have different needs, wants, and priorities. For example, a community organisation might have a project in which participants lead, produce or lead as a team, or might have a research project where participants work with researchers to understand more about local environments, or might have a publication or book project where authors or readers engage with the information gathered through the project. These types of multi-use projects can be broadly categorized into two broad categories – those that involve art as a facilitator of knowledge and those that don’t. These two broad categories divide the considerable body of community-based work that is happening in the UK right now. While there is a strong collaboration between the artist and the community, there is a great deal of room for individual creativity and new forms of collaboration.</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and how they organise themselves into communities. I am not interested in ascribing culpability or responsibility, only in questioning how we might as well do things ourselves. 	In 2015 I began the work of creating a multi-disciplinary workshop, entitled ‘Beyond the Artifice: Challenging the Representation of Community Arts in Art’, that would explore the links between contemporary art and social change. The project was co-curated by Waleed Aly and featured Waleed at the Venice Biennale, Samantha Jones, Cathy Mohan, Rama Iftikhar, Sohaib Kazem, Rafiq Rahman and many more. The findings from the project and the exhibition were published in a book entitled  	Beyond the Artifice: Challenging the Representation of Community Arts in Contemporary Art  [1] published by Verso Books at #1 New York, and a followup</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and how they are able to engage with the world through their own culture. I am interested in how an artist can engage with this in an authentic way, as opposed to what is often assumed to be an artist’s perspective and identity. In an effort to uncover the hidden narratives and practices of Bangladeshi communities, I have been commissioned by the New School for Social Research in New York City to conduct a series of workshops on the site of the Bangladeshi Cultural Centre, where I come from, and in the neighbourhood of Jamaica around the Jamaican heritage district of Crown Heights. My interest in the project stems from my experiences as a writer, performer, filmmaker and educator in the 1980s and 1990s, and the fact that my home is in the Caribbean and the United States. In the project, I am interested in how artists were able to create lasting works that resonate with audiences in the region, and internationally. My interest in the project stems from my belief that artists have a fundamental right</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and how they organise themselves and their communities. I am not interested in creating a community or an institution. In my view, the role of the arts is one of social action, of bringing people together through sharing and making, and I believe that the arts should be a vehicle for that.Art, Community and Migration[1] Guillermo Vitale, ‘On Migration and Art’, in Rolling Stone, 29 October 2013. Available at: http://www.RollingStone.com/2013/10/29/art-immigrants-how-americans-immigrate-work-travel-usa-2/ix-2/148849.htm[2] John Durham Boyer, ‘Art as a Toolkit for Transformation’, in Rolling Stone, 29 October 2013, p.29. Available at: http://www.rollingstone.com/2013/10/29/art-immigrants-how-americans-imm</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and what they can achieve. I also want to learn as much as I can about the craftsmanship involved in creating art that is authentic to the place and time in which it is made, and in a sense share this knowledge with others who may be working within the art world. 	My artistic practice is informed by a love of sharing, and so my work often seeks to better understand cultural practices and how artists can engage with them. I have developed a number of projects working with communities in the East Midlands, where the oil and gas boom of the 1980s and 1990s resulted in a mass accrual of poverty, despair and anger, as well as a steep rise in crime and conflict, that are strikingly similar to the contemporary situation in the West Midlands. 	For Resistance by Corinna Till, produced in collaboration with the East India Artsapce and East India Artspace. 	My interest in collaboration and transparency started from the early 1990s when I was working as</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials, public art, and publics, and the exhibition’s current projects. It is a significant contribution to the understanding of how art institutions and their visitors interact, and how art institutions and communities can work together to create and foster change. For more information, visit http://www.thefreshbuildingsproject.org/.Download this article as PDFEmily PringleMy interest in community arts is informed by a love of the process involved in developing, organising, and sustaining a community. I have worked as an artist-in-residence at the New Art Association (New Age) in London where I have been developing a project exploring the cultural practices of Bangladeshi immigrants to Britain. The project was presented at the 25th Biennale of London, and at the New Art Association Annual Meeting in New York. 	My interest in community arts is informed by a passion for transparency and an openness to questioning. I am interested in what others have to say, what they believe, and how they are able to engage with the world through their practices. I also believe that community arts practice needs to be multidisciplinary and accessible to a broad range of practices and cultures. In addition to local audiences, my practice has engaged with global ones such as the one in Dhaka, Bangladesh. 	Through research and analysis, my work has sought to understand the socio-political conditions of Bangladeshi communities living in Britain and the wider South Asian subcontinent. I have also been interested in exploring the biennale as a model for the future of the biennale in Britain and the subcontinent. I have a particular interest in the implications of the collaboration between art institutions and non-profit arts organisations in shaping the legacy of the biennale in the UK and subcontinent. The partnership between the biennale and arts organisations could be seen as a model for the development of community arts practices in Britain and the subcontinent. This would make it easier for the</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of the metainterface – the metainterface that emerged in the wake of the urbanisation process – not necessarily the reverse, since the metainterface is oriented towards the things that make people richer and more able to function as a social whole.  The metainterface – the metainterface that emerged in the wake of the urbanisation process – not necessarily the reverse, since the metainterface is oriented towards the things that make people richer and more able to function as a social whole.  A second metainterface, that of the information society, emerged in the wake of the internet and media. It is one that is sensitive to the new modes of social organisation that can be generated through information, and that is sensitive to the new functions and modes of cultural production that can be created through it. Information society emerged as a response to the negative impacts of urbanisation on the environment and the social totality. It seeks to the integrate the social totality in a</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of the ‘new’ economy – one in which labour meets labour meets commodity, in short, replicators of labour – and not just for the people who happen to be born into the jobs of the metropolis.   A second feature of the ‘new’ economy is the spread of cultural capital, cultural‐materials reaching ever further afield in service of the new economy, reaching to include everything from the art collections of museums to the production of designer clothes and vehicles to the implementation of new accounting practices. Culturally aware labour – that is, labour that is culturally responsive to the cultural needs of the moment – is allowed to prosper despite its social consequences. The spread of cultural capital and cultural materials is a feature of the ‘new’ economy because it is socially possible; it is not politically possible; it is not desirable because it threatens the social balance of the society. It is, in other words, the undoing of the social balance‐builder.  The</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of cities in high-tech and information societies, but also in societies without armies, police forces or prisons – in which people routinely move from one urban centre to another. Cities are places where people live and work continuously, and where social, economic and spatial heterogeneity are greatly reduced. The disappearance of the homeless and the under-hired workforce, the proliferation of restaurant and receptionist work and other service-sector jobs, as well as the rise of ever more efficient image-processing and surveillance systems, have all but disappeared. Cities now host an ever-expanding and increasingly affluent sub-culture: the  	Asian cross-section, the multitudes, the mega-cities, the megacities, the columbias, the malls and the skyscrapers of the Information Age. The 	information society is the dominant form of cultural formation in these cities, and cultural assimilation is the language of the Hypertext reader. 	The biennial – or ‘series</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of the new ‘structural transformations’ that are reshaping the social landscape, but also of the  	endemic increase in inequality and social conflict that is threatening to tear apart the very fabric of the global economy.  One might ask whether the social determinants of income and wealth – the  	use of which have remained relatively constant throughout the history of the planet – have, as much social significance, according to the calculations of the global super-computer HAL-Spec, than do the calculations of any human being.  If the calculations of the supercomputer HAL-Spec are correct, and the social determinants of income and wealth are, indeed, largely determined by the social determinants of population, poverty and conflict. But what is the social impact of such a massive social increase? Does the social multiplicity necessary for a sufficient increase in the deck ‘P* to support human life on planet Earth’ mean that we will all have to become farmers to feed ourselves</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of ‘infrastructure’ – the physical and virtual infrastructure – that supports and enables the social interaction required by ‘infrastructure’ – the ideas, programmes, manuals, specifications and other data supporting it.  	In an ideal world, people everywhere would have access to the same set of tools and data – the tools of social interaction required by the socialised world. But because of the nature of ‘infrastructure’ – the social, the economic and the political – access to such tools and data is constrained. Therefore, the access to such data necessarily entails an interaction with the system, an interaction with the people who control the data and, consequently, an interaction with those who benefit from the data. In other words, the social aspects of the connectomics revolution are likely to remain elusive. The social aspects will likely remain elusive because of the nature of the system – the ‘infrastructure’ – and the ‘knowledge graph’ required to support social interaction</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of metropolises, not a defect. Cities, as social formations, become ever more integrated into the socio-political systems that generate and support their life-expectancies. The metropolis today is a source of mobility not only of those with access to resources but also of those without access to them. The rapid spread of population in the metropolis – both urban and rural – results in a boom in food supplies and a consequent decline in water and energy needs. But the social systems that allow for the social mobility of people – in this case, animals – also tend to make it easier for those without access to resources to participate in those systems. A city that offers generous social services to those in need, and actively participates in the production of its own social life, is a city that is able to shift resources between those with and without its citizens. Such participation maximises the social welfare of its citizens. But what kinds of social welfare are the citizens of a metropolis ultimately engaged in</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of the ‘new economy’ – a new social form evolving alongside the old – but it is at the same time a counterintuitive and contradictory feature. The emergence of ever larger and more diversified shareholder portfolios around the globe has its social effects in all of us – but especially at the top, where the new world order is being defined. The top 10% of society owns over 90% of the assets and income growth continues to accrue to them.  So what has driven the acceleration in social mobility? My personal guess is that it is due to the expansion of access to information and communication technologies; the shift from individual to collective in the work place; and the new global economic system that emerged from the financial crisis. All of these processes that I have outlined are part of a much bigger picture that also includes new forms of racial and gender heterogeneity, new multi-culturalism and a greater variety of behaviours. All of it requires massive amounts of capital and labour to implement, and much of</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of the ‘global village’, but it has also been shown to increase inequality and social conflict. A 2011 review of anthropogenic global climate change suggested that the social implications would be dire if ‘[a] disproportionate share of the increase in global temperature … is attributed to [them].&quot;‘Shifting Metabolisms: Carbon Based Chemical Emissions from City To Mountain 	[i] The Green Mountain Mystery, p. 21.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloDr. Michael Truscello is an assistant professor in the Department of Anthropology and is the co-director of The Conservation Anthropology Unit at the University of British Columbia. His research interests include issues of power and resources in contemporary society, including the role of art and cultural institutions in shaping economic and political systems; the social consequences of anthropogenic climate change; cultural geography and the social production of climate change through language; and media ecology. His work has been published in The New York Times, The</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of the metainterface – the metainterface that emerges in response to the social impact of material culture in the city – and not a function of internal differentiation within the city. In my view, the metainterface is a feature of a much wider trend of increasing social mobility that I call the ‘material urbanisation’ that began in the 1970s and 80s and continues to this day.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the metropolis around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of the metainterface – the metainterface that emerges in response to the social impact of material culture in the metropolis. – Lamar Smith, Talking Capitalism Curated by Fred Turner, Tate Modern, London, 1978. Photo courtesy of the Tate Modern.  The metainterface is a metainterface that emerges in response to the social impact of material culture in the metropolis. It is a new kind of durable, reusable material</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that would permit the production of high-end artisanal cheese and pastas with added flavour and texture to the everyday products.[7] The early 20th century saw an explosion in the production of high-performance chemicals, plastics and aluminium;[8] by the mid-century, these materials were in high demand by manufacturers worldwide. The emergence of self-healing concrete as a result of industrial processes allowed manufacturers to produce high-quality products with minimal environmental impacts. The rapid growth of these industries coincided with an equally rapid advent of ‘sustainable growth’ – a contradiction of the old trade-off between environmental and social concerns. Today, ‘sustainable growth’ implies low or no dependence on energy imports from the Middle East. But the social consequences of the increased social mobility of the population at the expense of the environment are far from clear.  The rapid social mobility of the people of the cities around the globe has profound social impacts. It is a feature of the new ‘postindustrial society’, but at the same time, it implies the dislocation of critical mass from the cities in favour of the metropolis. This dislocating process has social implications that transcend the planet.  At the level of the city, the postindustrial society includes the proliferation of finance capital, which seeks to exploit natural resources on a massive scale;[9] it involves the expansion of large containerised containers via aggressive global commodity chains; it involves the superabundant global circulation of humans; and it involves the massive deployment of non-renewable resources, including of course, the huge infrastructure needed to support all of it. All of this is global in character. But it is particularly global in character because of the scale and rapidity of the metropolis. In terms of human numbers, the human race is made up of roughly four quarters of which live in the cities – roughly 4.4 billion people. Of these quarters, roughly half live in</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retcon
    <text>accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retcon.  Once you get past the picking and choosing that you do in the Community Arts movement, it’s time to invest in the community and in the work you do with them.  If you stop short of being truly collaborative, you risk becoming adversarial. And that can be dangerous.  	Once you have the Community Arts model firmly in mind, you need to work with people in an adversarial position.  In the 1980s, even if you were to say that you had the skills and the connections, it was also important to have people to actually put the pieces together.  	When I first started, I would say that the Community Arts movement started out adversarial, with people like Sonja Kuftinek and Donna Harpe arguing that you couldn’t make it arts, so you’d have to redefine what arts was.  And I would add that there</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retcon .  And as far as the fans and the film go, I don’t agree with them on every issue. But I do think that the fact that it was filmed in the cinema made it somehow more real.  And as far as the fact that the guy was a star, and the girl was just a minor character…  I still find the whole Curtains thing frustrating, because there is no way to read that as a critique of the patriarchy.  But as far as the way in which cinema is culturally embedded in the community, I think that is a valid point of reference.  And in that context, the way in which the Cains picketed the Venice Movies is a sort of a kernel of that crowd that is embedded in the fabric of the place, and that is part of what gives the place meaning.  I don’t think </text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retcon for the community.  Even if it did mean that the Community Arts movement wouldn’t be a thing again.  I used to be a Community Arts guy.  The fact of its existing didn’t make it okay.  Even if the Community Arts folks said they liked it, and the Curtains said they too, it still couldn’t be Art. It couldn’t be Cultural Practice. It couldn’t be Art because it was Art.  It was always been a joke by now, the Community Arts folks would say, and everyone would agree, although of course there was always the occasional gotcha.  But no matter how often they said they liked it, nobody could point to a work that was actually by them.  And we all know what that is.  I still remember the Concert</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retconning of some kind.  And even if it were a retcon, that doesn’t make it a celebration.  It just so happened that during the 1980s, the Curtains were also a pretty active theatre-goers’ patron group, so there was a lot of overlap between the two groups. And speaking of overlap, Glasgow Shakespeare Company was a pretty active group too. I went to them once a month, and they would have whatever we dinner was playing, and they would be playing the frigate or the gulf in the background. We would be breaking the rules sometimes, but we would get what we deserved, and we got what we always wanted. I have a memory of one of them telling me a story about how they used to come to Chirnsyde Theatre every Saturday, and we would all sit </text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retcon – or worse, a witch-hunt – for the community.  In the city, the objection to the Conway’s picture was that it looked like a collection of houses, which was a bit of a stretch.  Similarly, when the West Village Arts Centre first started, it was about a cultural ecology of sorts, with a core of houses and a community of artists living in and around the building. But in the end, the Community Arts Centre must offer something – because, as the saying goes, ‘a man’s gotta feed a family’.  So, as the Community Arts Centre evolves, it must offer something in return for the community’s commitment to keeping the building as a home.  And so the negotiation begins. Will the Community Arts Centre keep the house as a home? Will the West Village Arts Centre move to a more urban setting? Will the Millionaires Club stay put in</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retcon.  As a writer and activist, I’m always looking for ways to be a help to the community, and so it’s always nice to be able to turn up and get on with the job, while somehow remaining completely invisible.  When I heard the name Conway, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Converts, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  When Samson Kambalu, the Nigerian writer, artist and activist, died in 1984, he left behind a massive literary and cultural impact, as well as a vast body of work. In the years that followed his death, the Community Arts movement exploded in Nigeria, Egypt, Palestine and South Africa, and I came across another African artist, Wangechi Mutu, whose 2000 golden statue, the elusive but iconic</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retcon or a myth.  Or maybe it did. Who knows?  I thought to myself, and I still think to this day.  It couldn’t be further from the truth.  When I heard the name Curtains in the 1980s, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  I still think it’s funny that when I first started out at Black-E, the Curtains were the only people in the building who knew about the Revolution and the Black-E. Then as I got older, people started coming through the</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retcon  or a   fake  or a parody. I find it very interesting that in the film Hellboy, the monster is played by an older actor, Frank Ozell.  Frank Ozell is an actor, director and writer, and his character, Abe Sapien, is the name of a supernatural being who comes up with various crazy ideas to stop the world from ending.  One of his ideas is to have a film made about the fact that he isn’t going to be able to stop the world from ending, because he is immortal and therefore everyone else is mortal. So the movie has to be about something more than the ending itself, and so the question is: what does it mean to end? For Hellboy, the end is ambiguous, and so the answer is always going to be: something. But for Hellboy, that thing is actually quite simple: it is over and done with. So what does it</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retconning of some kind of violent past.  The Curtains had other ideas. They wanted every film made by the Curtains to be about them and their families, and they were determined to make themselves known in the film.  So Curtains Cinema became something completely different. It became a place where the community could come, share ideas, find a common ground, and create a place where the community could be proud of who they were. Like Curtains Cake, it was a work in progress.But it wasn’t a cake and it wasn’t a canteen either. Soon, the work was completely deconsecrated, and the Canteen faced bankruptcy. The cinema closed down, the bakery closed, the bakery went under, and the community had to start all over again. Today, there are quite a few gangs of young guys hanging out in the building that used to be Curt</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the local butcher(s) and the local veg shop.  In the 1980s, the cinema was another place to visit, as a place to be taken seriously but not to be taken too seriously.  I once saw a movie in which a young couple were having an affair with a local girl, and as a result of their conversation, the local boys were sent somewhere to smother a big, black cedar tree with firewood. The couple were both in their thirties, the boy was in his fifties, and they were in their sixties or seventies.  When I heard the name Creed, I thought to myself, with all due respect to the Curtains, that this was a direct quote from them. It wasn’t a compliment.  Just because a group of guys from the community decided to picket a movie doesn’t mean that the movie was going to be a   retcon – or worse, a re-enactment – of the local Boys &amp; Girls Club meeting. They would have had plenty of other ideas.  They also didn’t mean that the Curtains were going to become some kind of internet icon.  Well, maybe one could argue that the Curtains would have become something if the Boys &amp; Girls Club hadn’t closed down and moved to a new space, but I prefer the idea of the Curtains becoming some kind of digital icon, because then you open up a way more doors than you can possibly fill. The Curtains meeting was only ever a footnote in the history of the area, and in the twenty-first century it seems completely divorced from the neighbourhood.  The fact that the Cuddly Wren is now a hugely profitable business, and has been for some years, suggests that the neighbourhood is no longer a significant place of exchange, and </text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene where it can have a positive impact, such as conserving or preserving natural spaces and infrastructure, or the built environment in anticipation of future demands for infrastructure repairs and maintenance. These projects garner public support, tend to create a buzz and are often cited as a reason to be proud of the city.  	[4] A public realm, in this view, encompasses both public and protected spaces, both urban and rural. The public is invited to participate in creating the public realm, which it sees as an inherently valuable and distinctive resource that ought to be protected.  	[5] The proposal stems from a few ideas that were put forward by Rami El Samahy and Ameen Ebadi as a way to think through the implications of a city-wide public realm for the future of the city. The two scholars’ proposals were put forward at an Arab Spring Exhibition in Doha in 2011, and Amnesty International in Doha in 2013.</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene where its density would prevent the development of desirable alternatives. For more information, see: http://www.umbrechtworks.com/press-releases/2014... [4] Graham S. Fuller, ed., Movements: Political Economy and Art, SUNY Press, Albany, 1988, p. 4. [5] Nadine Attewell, Culture and Capital: Performance, Performing Arts and the Criminy of the Commons, Greenwood Press, New York, 1988, p. 37. [6] Peruvian economist, Werner Wirth, M: Political Economy of the Arts, Cornell UP, Ithaca, 1987, p. 17. [7] Willard (ed.), The Public Production of Art, Oxford University Press, Oxford and New York, 1988, p. 12. [8] John McWhorter, ‘The Practice of Critique: Performance, Theory and Politics’,  	Critical Inquiry</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene where necessary to regenerate or revitalize the affected areas. The logic of the ‘public square’ seems to be that the more public realm the better.  	[4] The strategy might be used in areas with a high density of public transit, schools, parks and recreation facilities, and is one that is still in its infancy. It is very early to tell whether the strategy is working – although the number of jobs created since 2010 by the greatly expanded downtown core rapid transit system is a good indication. It is certainly true that in the last decade many artists and arts institutions have been forced to close their shows or be folded into larger urban centres, or moved elsewhere in the country. Still, many artists find their niche in such settings, and it is worth noting that Sarah Connor famously ‘born again’ in her home of Liverpool, after being forced to move her shows from the city to suburban parks across the border in Vancouver. 	[5] The public</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene where the projects stand in terms of regenerating the local economy. The city is then seen as a modulator, intervening early and often to shape cultural outcomes later in the process.  	[4] See: http://www.engageart.org/about/research/engage-art-internship/public-engagement-engagement-rese....[5] Massive open online courses offered simultaneously online and in-person in over 100 cities around the world, as well as a growing number of regional centres.  	[6] http://www.sfu.ca/en/education/professions/arts/arts-and-culture/students/graduate-programs/engage-australia-201....[7] See: http://www.scribd.com/doc/247900561/Gender-based-Violence-in-Modern-Societies?....[</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene where it is most needed – when development threatens the public realm – creating incentives for additional housing and encouraging more people to live there.  	[4] See: http://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2013/11/26/better-days-ahead/ 	[5] The strategy is similar to that of NRDC, whose RE: Sustainable Economy Initiative is built into the city's core culture.  	[6] The key differences are that the Cultural Strategy is locally-focused and city-wide in nature; while the RE: Sustainable Economy Initiative is regionally-focused and state-sponsored.  	[7] See: http://www.forbes.com/sites/benzingainsights/2013/11/26/better-days-ahead/ 	[8] Environment News Service, ‘USGS Special Report: Global Warming's Impacts’</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene where necessary to preserve the character of the area – in other words, the character of the city – while encouraging civic engagement elsewhere in the city.  	[4] John Elder Robinson, ‘Race, Politics and Urban Development in Vancouver’,  	Postcolonial Cultures, Vol. 4, No. 1, 1995, p.1–22.Download this article as PDFRebecca StrombergRebecca Stromberg is a Ph.D. candidate in Urban Studies and Planning at the University of British Columbia, pursuing her dissertation on the history of cultural studies in Vancouver. Her dissertation examines the role of the arts in creating the conditions for the emergence of a publicly accessible form of art’s social value – a socially effective form of art that is conscious and responsive to the social – through an analysis of the arts and their relationship to the region, present and future of British Columbia. Her dissertation examines the intersection between economic development and art forms as commodities</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene where necessary to preserve the character of the area – in planning, development and even in the case of resistance, in the form of legal intervention – though in the main, as in Oakland, the city intervenes in order to preserve the character of the area. 	[4] See Richard Florida,  	Urban Futures of the Recent Past , Sage Publications, 2011; Florida &amp; Florida,  	Urban Futures of the Recent Past , Sage Publications, 2011; Florida,  	Urban Form: The Transformation of Outer-Western Japan into the Metropolis of the Future 	, and Richard Florida,  	Urban Futures of the Recent Past , Sage Publications, 2011; Florida &amp; Florida,  	Urban Form: The Transformation of Outer-Western Japan into the Metropolis of the Future, and Florida,  	Urban Form: Toward a History of the Recent Past 	, all published by New Harbinger, New Harbinger</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene where it can have a positive impact, such as providing affordable housing or promoting green spaces. 	[4] GreenTech integrates aspects of research, design, development, and operations into the urban environment, often through the provision of green infrastructure and green jobs opportunities. This has been done in the context of postindustrial areas, but it is also common in newly gentrified areas experiencing rapid population growth and an abundance of cheap housing. 	[5] In fact, a large share of the development in the area can be attributed to the private investment of the local community. 	[6] This is particularly true in the development of highly trafficked districts such as the Central Business District and the financial district of downtown, where residents are more easily drawn into the city’s economic machine. It is also true in areas where the arts have a prominent cultural component, such as the burgeoning Performing Arts district in the financial district, where the arts are often cited as a main</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene in a number of other areas of the city, including the arts scene, without having to go through the political obstacles or being weighed down with debt in the area. 	[4] The strategy is thought to be very similar to that advocated by the local residents´ Council 21st Biennale – a hybrid approach that seeks to build publics alongside ‘private businesses’ and the local farmers’ market, while maintaining a strong local arts and cultural identity.  	[5] A key difference, perhaps, is that the residents´ Council 21st Biennale advocated for a localized solution, while the residents’ Museum of Puerto Rican Heritage and Institutions’ are more likely to advocate for a city-wide solution. This may be seen as a conflict of interest, since the Museum of Puerto Rican Heritage, which is largely responsible for the Biennale's success, is located in the city.  	[6] The question of whether</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to consider the full range of artistic possibilities for such a city. 	[1] The question is: could such a strategy complement the city in a multiplicity of other ways? In a cultural sense, perhaps, but it also begs the crucial question of what kind of a city? The answer, I believe, is a resounding NO! 	[2] Cultural theorists, in general, tend to advocate for the utopic, the fully realized, ‘nothing is sacred’. In other words, cultural life itself is inherently political, and the more political it gets, the more vulnerability there is to the politics of culture taking root elsewhere.  	[3] The strategy is to build public realm projects, or publics, in areas with a high density of jobs and residences. These tend to be local to the area, and are seen as essential to addressing the pressing housing crisis in the area. In turn, this allows the city to intervene flexibly in an area’s economy, culture, and society.  	[4] For more information, see: https://www.planform.org/en/2005/tenants-and-community-planning-review/overview/pdf/tenant-reform-review.pdf (accessed September 2018).  	[5] See, for example, Sandy Seabrook,  	Why Are We Building Public Art? Working Class Hero, 2012. Installation, East German artist Sandy Seabrook, East German Broadcasting Corporation.  	[6] See, for example, Tsai Ying-ying,  	The Art of Not Being Governed: An Anarchist History of Upland Southeast Asia, 2006. Installation, East German artist Tsai Ying-ying, East German Broadcasting Corporation.  	[7] For more information, see: https</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan.
    <text>archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. installation, Milan, 2015. design museum, Milan, 2015. construction, Milan, 2015. design museum, Milan, 2015. Construction, Milan, 2015. installation, Milan, 2015. design museum, Milan, 2015. construction, Milan, 2015. Milan, 2015. design museum, Milan, 2015. construction, Milan, 2015. construction, Milan, 2015. construction, Milan, 2015. construction, Milan, 2015. construction, Milan, 2015. construction, Milan, 2015. construction, Milan, 2015.</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. installation, manhattan, n.y. agency: Solid Waste ManagementFor IMI Corona, the relationship between artist and landscape was a theme that ran through the project's development. The two projects formed part of a multi-year ongoing collaboration, which also involved contributions from the artist and his landscape-based practice.  	[1] The IMI Corona concept was born in 1993. Development of the project came about in parallel to the release of several artists' works based on the same site, including the 1993 Venice Biennale, as well as the 2014 Chisenhazy, Guggenheim, and Arsenale Architecture criticises, Moira Kenny's Venice Biennale.  	[2] See, for example, the article in Cultural Ge</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. installation, marco lavorato. The life-size bronze statues of artists Antonio Beccaria (Italy), Paolo Portoghesi (Italy), Paolo Portoghesi (Italy), Joasia Krysa (Ukraine), and Rubens Oliveri (UK) were installed in the True Detective episodes &quot;The Empty Hearse&quot; and &quot;The Empty Martyrs’ cemetery at Lefebvre. The bronze is particularly interested in its use as a tomb for the dead, as in the Bronze Age tombs of the Near East, Egypt and Greece. The Romans, by way of contrast, tended to build monumental buildings primarily to house visiting dignitaries, and these tombs often served as exhibition exhibits. The empty tomb of Antonin Scalia, for example, is particularly arresting in its overt reference to the Roman republic (in the vein of Upton Sinclair’s &quot;The Jungle&quot;). But Be</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015, 75.9 x 33.1 in, mimeo.com/125825768, https://www.flickr.com/photos/marc_lazzarato/448349970 Upload this article as PDFEric Worrall  (at) gmail (dot) comPreviousNextEric Worrall  (at) gmail (dot) comEric Worrall is a writer, director and producer. He co-directs the gala production of the Liverpool Biennial under the name Creative Time Incorporated and produces the festival under the same nom de plume. He is the co-curator of the upcoming 6th edition of the Venice Biennale and was part of the curatorial team for the 6th Amadeus Choin​s collection, released recently, of art from</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. installation, marco lavorato, 2015. installation, marco lavorato, 2015. installation, marco lavorato, 2015. installation, marco lavorato, 2015. installation, marco lavorato, 2015. installation, marco lavorato, 2015. installation, marco lavorato, 2015. installation, marco lavorato, 2015. installation, marco lavorato, 2015. installation, marco lavorato, 2015. installation, marco</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. installation in the Giardini, 2015. Installation in the Giardini, 2015. Installation in the Giardini</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Stefano Bonami, Scapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Stefano Bonami, Scapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Stefano Bonami, Scapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Stefano Bonami, Scapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Stefano Bonami, Scapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Stefano Bonami, Scapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Stefano Bonami, Scapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Stefano Bonami, Scapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Stefano Bonami, Scapescion, 2015. installation, marco seguimieri, 2015. installation, marco seguimieri, 2015. installation, marco seguimieri, 2015. installation, marco seguimieri,</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation, marco lazzarato, 2015. installation</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapclose, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapclose, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco L</text>
    <text>archival material on biennials Getty Images 2/12  Milan Biennale, art by Frédédérick Hardiman, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescencion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. Installation, Milan. Photo: Marco Lazzarato, Scapescapescion, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation, evergreen, 2015. installation,</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�s the city that – within just the last twelve months – has become a city for drivers.I don’t have a crystal ball, but it seems to me that the rise of UberX in New York City is a direct outgrowth of a project by the New York Taxi and Limousine Commission (2010-2014), which had been quietly underway for some years. TLC had commissioned a number of publications, pamphlets, radio and television spots, and invited online communities to help it ­– step-by-step, map-by-map, document-by-document setting out the commission’s plans for the city. The commission’s 2010-14 plan, however, was largely a response to the city’s financial impasse, which became acute when Manhattan’s share of a $7 billion Tidal Basin was suddenly siphoned away by new development. TLC president John Malcom and NYC Council President Eric Garcetti both</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�s exactly what Seattle is doing. How can a city foster innovation through the power of its infrastructure? I’d like to think that Seattle is using its technological edge to its own advantage, and that other parts of the country are following suit.  	The city’s technological edge may be its edges, but its real edge is its capacity to absorb and process information. And the city is absorbing information at a rapid clip, thanks to services like Uber, which are able to scan vast amounts of data in order to detect those rare instances in which a passenger meets a certain set of criteria. And the city is processing this data in order to deliver rides at a later date – a phenomenon known as ‘disruption’. 	Since 2014, when UberX first launched in New York and Los Angeles, New Yorkers have had the option to book a one-way trip using their smartphones. And since then, dozens of cities and even international jurisdictions have required UberX drivers</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�s the direction in which cities are going. The cities that have embraced the technology and are turning it into useful things are the ones with the most visionary leaders. In other words, the more visionary and exciting the city, the better the return on investment for the local technology companies that develop apps that hook into the infrastructure of the city. In the early days of Uber, the technology that allowed drivers to pick up passengers on the platform locates the cars, and the services  that allow the drivers to be plugged into the car's electrical grid  locates the infrastructure of the city. The technology allows for the extraction and manipulation of labour power through the transfer of labour energy between individuals and the establishment of labour mobility frameworks. The extraction of labour power through technology is a dynamic process that can be described as being influenced by a host of cultural factors, including the driverless car, the social media revolution, and urban sprawl. Uber has engendered a great deal of hype around itself as a</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�s where Silicon Valley thinks its future ‘.  In any case, the future city is a city in constant transition, influenced by factors beyond its control.  And these transnationals do have one clear advantage over cities: they can lay claim to any urban space that becomes commercially viable (within reason) – a claim that cities such as San Francisco cannot make.  So while the future city may or may not feature self-sustaining, globally scalable transportation, its shape-shifting and on-demand economy, it is certain to continue to contain elements of the infrastructure of cities in crucial junctures.  And this is the larger picture. Tomorrow, another city may make a comeback, this time in the American south, where the mining and logging operations that created the myth of Santa Fe as recently as the late 1970s are being reversed. And just as the economy shapes resource consumption and urban growth, the claim to the city may well be one of the claims that runs ag</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�s where Los Angeles is headed. In the US, there’s a clear preference for the over-the-top (see figure below). In many cities, including in my hometown of San Diego, transportation is a main concern. Beyond this, concerns about pollution, traffic, infrastructure, and climate change continue to dominate local to national headlines. In fact, the prominence given to these threats may be stoking rather than cooling down demand. San Diego’s population density of over 9,000 people per square mile is quite a contrast to the millions crammed into Los Angeles’s downtown core or the even the megacities of Beijing and Shanghai, which all have populations over 10 million. The fact that almost half of San Diego’s population lives in the city limits of the newly developed, highly populated and transit-oriented city makes it evident why the county’s rapid population growth is such a surprise to many locals and visitors. The rapid growth has all but overwhelmed what</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�s exactly what Seattle needs. The ability to link two cities, or cities within a given metropolitan area, allows us to see how different settings can inhabit the same cultural landscape. Cultural geographers have long known that the key to successful urban development is cultural exchange. Today, cultural production is an industry that generates huge amounts of data about the city, and which uses this to generate revenues for cities all over the world. How to Link Two Cultures How to link two cultures? It’s not easy to pinpoint the precise moment when this question first came up in contemporary artist Adrian Smith’s conversation with Culture and Capital editor-at-large Prachi Jain about his book Culture and Capital: Capitalism &amp; Cultural Criticism in late 2015. Culture and Capital has just published an edition that addresses the topics of race, capitalism and identity. But the conversation, conducted over several podcasts, is a strong candidate for the one that embodied ‘the present’. </text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�s the most that the city has ever achieved in terms of economic activity – aside from being a transit point for cars and trucks, which is now a point of contention. Local people’s movements have recently begun to challenge this logic of the urban – challenging the goals and parameters of Uber in many cases.Is there a way to bring such challenges to the city planning processes that foster and facilitate these transnational UberX companies? I believe that there is. I believe that the means by which these geo-politically-influenced social networks operate through which they can achieve their stated ends – and which render the city as ‘different from other sites of activity’ – needs to be restructured. Cities today are sites of exchange between nations, and it is local people who enact and lead these local movements. It is not the case that the interests of the city or the nation are aligned, or even in common. I see cities as sites of ongoing conflict, both internally and with</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�s what Seattle has done. The city has become a global epicentre of these transnational transnational UberX companies, which is why Seattle has been able to weather the post-subsidisation, market-based, and regulatory storms that have shaken other coastal metropolises. The city’s post-subsidy, tax-supported economic model has kept many other places in America and other parts of the world from being hit by the same tsunami of financial technology that’s killing them. But now, as the city struggles to recover from the financialisation of everything from its infrastructure to its recreation landscape, there’s a strong hint that the city might be preparing to enter into a kind of federally-funded, subways-and-subways-like UberX. How does this scenario map on to our imagined city? In an ideal world, Seattle should be able to pick up where LA leaves off, and continue to build transit infrastructure along the waterfront,</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�s where Silicon Valley stops. So, there’s a contradiction there – the city that got caught up in the taxi and limousine trade is now awash in data from these transnational companies looking to do business – and the city that was once known as the ground zero of the urban/suburban/suburban transition is now awash in data gathering and reporting these companies. And there’s a third element to this equation that I haven’t mentioned yet: the race card. The race card is a loaded one. As early as the mid-1990s, scholars were warning of the pernicious effects of this shift in the urban/suburban dynamic, and of course, there’s the ever-present refrain that ‘hail Mary’ is the subversion of democracy’. And yet, somehow, we keep electing these kinds of cities into our histories. How do we account for this historical moment in our city/suburb</text>
    <text>subsequent iterative processing by machines] that seek to identify and classify similar items in a way that is as though the objects had common characteristics, and thus can be made to share certain characteristics (fig. S6). Machine learning algorithms typically learn simple rules that capture examples of behaviour in a domain, and employ this to help infer (in a semantic sense) the underlying principles that underlie the learned behaviour. In the context of biopolitics, this can lead to situations in which different factions within the same organisation seek to implement a particular programme of action within a given domain. In the case of social media, this can lead to entities emerging – social networks – that seek to implement specific behaviours within the given social environment. Figure 6: – Show Me A City That Has Become A Tech Hub advertisements on the back of UberX transportation.com show me a city that has become a hub for transnational transnational UberX (see map) transportation companies, and I’m told that�s where Seattle falls. Seattle has become a technological juggernaut. It’s no wonder, then, that Seattle’s port enjoys such a position in global economic and political parlance. It’s also no surprise that UberX is now the second-largest company in the US, after Google’s Google X research centre. The shift in the economic centre of gravity in the US and China, and the subsequent decimation of jobs in many urban centres, has placed an incredible strain on urban infrastructure. It’s no wonder, then, that cities are increasingly turning to new technology to address these problems. But if the port can’t seem to keep pace with the explosion of traffic, the city has little alternative but to adopt some of these new technologies as a way to supplement what is being lost due to traffic. This is the predicament of software cities: there is no option but to adopt these technologies as a replacement for what is being lost due to traffic</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many
    <text>accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It came as a surprise to those who had been following the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It came as</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It came as a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, since the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	In a piece published in the New York Times on 9 November 2001, Kevin Spacey recounts the events leading up to the murder of Enoch Powell, a.k.a. 'The Beast’, by Jewish Voice for Peace (Jewish People’s Name), New York, 2001. Spacey is the actor who portrays Raphael on</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It came as a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It came as a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many because it was not part of a broader anti-Muslim agenda promoted by the government. The circulation of cartoons depicting the Prophet Muhammad was one of the few areas of tolerance permitted in Canada at the time. The creation of the Canadian Islamic Congress (later renamed the Toronto-based Council on American-Islamic Relations) was another, though much criticized, area of freedom. The latter was particularly controversial because it gave the CAIR leadership license to engage in anti-Muslim activism outside of Canada. The CAIR leadership at the time was not unfamiliar with the permissive character of their ideas. Prior to that, they had already been active in promoting a separatist agenda in Canada through their activities in the Boycott, Divestment and Sanctions (BDS) movement. Finally, there was the 1978 Islamic conversion of the Board of Chosen’s trustees, who had previously approved the purchase of a plot of land in Ajax, Ontario, and the subsequent takeover of the local mosque by radical Muslims. The newly mint</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been following the news closely, since the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been following the news closely, since the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It came as a surprise to many who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It came as a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	In a larger perspective, however, the apparent failure of the federal government to take any concrete action against the city of Toronto for hosting the World Trade Center in 1993 may have encouraged the city’s Muslim community to move beyond their perceived marginalisation within the city to taking part in a larger urban culture that was more readily assimilated by the newly mint</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It also came as a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It came as a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites and social media of the Muslim community. It is a rare occasion, however, to find a website or social media page devoted to the plight of the Armenian community, or to mention the many other minorities who are similarly discriminated against and left to fend for themselves. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It was also a surprise to those who had followed the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 	The ban came as a surprise to many who had been anticipating an announcement more positively effused on the heritage of the Armenian diaspora in Canada. It came as a surprise to many who had been following the news closely, as the ban was made without comment from either the minister responsible for Indian and Northern affairs or the attorney general. It has been suggested that the Canadian federal government may have engaged in state terrorism when it came to the fate of the 9/11 victims; perhaps it did, but since no such accusations have been made against the Muslim community in this country, we can assume that the practice of shunning Muslims in this country is not as widespread as is sometimes claimed. 1   	Timur Markmuzelski, ed., Modern Iran: A Cultural History of Modern Iran, Cambridge University Press, Cambridge, 1988, p.19. 2   	Idem, op. cit., p.25. 3  	Idem, op. cit., p.30. 4  </text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She has a particular interest in the role of the artist in conflict zones. She has worked with communities in conflict zones around the world, including in Kenya, Bosnia and Herzegovina, Tajikistan, Georgia and South Ossetia. Her work is presented as part of the Black Mountain Conference, a cross-disciplinary symposium held at the base of Black Mountain, Northwest Territories, Canada, that she co-chairs. Her latest work, We Are Here to Stay, was presented at the Black Mountain International Film Festival, Vancouver, Canada. She has been a finalist for the National Book Award, the Guggenheim Foundation Pioneer Prize, and was a finalist for the Governor General's Medal.She is the recipient of two commissions, the 2014 BC Pavilion Arts Prize and the 2016 Governor General's Medal.This article was originally published in the October 2016, issue of New Socialist RegisterVolunteers and Workers CentralNoam Chomsky, Theory, U.S. National Liberation Radio,</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She is currently an adjunct professor at Manhattan College. Her work has been featured in numerous publications including the New York Times, USA Today, Wall Street Journal, Los Angeles Times, San Diego Union-Tribune, Chicago Tribune, Chicago Defender, New York Post, Village Voice, Village Voice Technology Review, HackettFile, Wired Magazine, and many more. She is the recipient of numerous awards and mentions including the 2013 Granby Four Arts Festival Pioneer Award for Community Art, the 2014 Rogers Prize for Public Art, the 2015 Rogers Prize for Transport and the City, the 2016 William H. Rehn Chair in Transport and Infrastructure, the 2017 MIT Chair in Computer Science, the 2018 MIT Computer Science and Artists Workshop, the 2018 MIT/Harvard Chair in Computer Science and Engineering, and the 2018 MIT-Teresa Chair in Art and Network Culture. Her work has been funded by the NYC Department of Education, New York City Humanities Initiative, the</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She has a particular interest in the lives and experiences of First Nations peoples and has produced works that speak from experiences in those communities. She has also written widely on indigenous and environmental issues, has been an adjunct professor at Mount Royal University in Calgary, and was a co-editor of The Rediscovery of Symbols, an environmental and indigenous literature reprinting The Columbian, the last edition of which came out in 2016. Walking Towards RevolutionIn 1999, in the small hours of the new year, a group of students and activists occupied the Dakota Access Pipeline and other fossil-fuel infrastructure sites in North Dakota and launched a 12-week campaign to demand a full environmental assessment and possible withdrawal of the material resources from those sites. They were joined by activists from several other movements, who established International Mountain Network, an international network of activist-curatorial practices. I.M. Pei is an artist whose work incorporates topics of education, resistance and revolution as a way of thinking and communicating. Her</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She has a particular interest in imagining alternative futures for communities impacted by nuclear war. In 2011 she co-curated the Peoples Temple: Temple of Perpetual Nuclear Spring project for the New York Public Theater, which seeks to bring together traditional arts practices of the region to create a more sustainable alternative for New Yorkers living near the site of the first nuclear tests. She has been a consultant for the US military and is the author of Perpetual Nuclear Spring: Crisis and Ambition in the Art of Community Art, from Contagion to Perpetual Performativity, NYU Press, 2011. She is currently a curator at the Museum of Nuclear Physics in Amherst, New York, and is the curator of the Perpetual Nuclear Spring project in Amherst. She is currently researching the 2009 Fukushima Daiichi Nuclear Power Plant disaster and is offering a free symposium to the media and the public about the disaster as a way of asking, ‘What would you do if you could never</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She has written for The New York Times, The New Republic, the New Inquiry, The Nation, and others. She has a special interest in the ecology of community settings and has written on the environment and activism since the environmental movement began. She has a regular podcast series on the environmental podcast Stitchery entitled Citizen Environmental and has been a regular contributor to The New Inquiry, where she has been interviewed on topics including nuclear power, immigration, urban development, and the environment. She has written for The New Inquiry, The Nation, The RPS, and others. Her work in communities began when she was at the University of California, Los Angeles, where she participated in the Creative Time Research Lab as part of the MFA '90 Creative Time Fellowship. Her research on the lab found support in the form of a full-time position at the university health services department, which offered the artist the opportunity to work independently developing a research project on the ART clinic. In addition to</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She has worked with the Shanghai Arts Festival and was a curator for the 60th Venice Biennale, Tokyo, Japan. She was a co-curator of the Ø70’s Venice Biennale, and the  	80s Venice Biennale, both of which she curated herself. She has co-curated the Øhundreds’ series of biennials and the  	100th Venice Biennale, both of which she curated herself. She co-curated the  	Future City festival, the world premiere of which she organised herself, and curated the world premieres of a number of other biennials including the Venice Biennale, but also curated the worlds of the Near East Media Landscape exhibition, the Washington Art Biennale, and the Venice Architecture Biennale. She co-curated the first Venice Biennale, but has also co-curated the worlds of the Peruvian, Russian and</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She has also worked with the New York Public Library, New York Public Theatre, National Endowment for the Arts, and the US Holocaust Memorial Museum. She is a co-curator of the forthcoming Venice Biennale, which will see her work used as a tool by a curator to assess the biennale’s potential, as well as its potential negative impacts.  	[2] See http://www.genoa-art.org/en/. [3] For more information on the project, see http://www.genoa-art.org/. [4] For more information on N.Y.U. Holocaust Memorial Museum visit: http://www.nyumemorialmuseum.org/.  [5] For more information on Genoa Art Biennale visit: http://www.genoa-art.org/en/. [6] For more information on Venice Biennale, visit: http://www.</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She has a particular interest in the future of human ecology and the ways in which communities might be able to work together to address some of the challenges of the new economy. She has a couple of books out now that deal with the aftermath of nuclear war, Nuclear War: The Politics of Eco-apocalyptic and the Politics of Nukeproof Bodies.   uggish    [2] Northup, Michael, ‘Crisis and Delusion: Two Forms of Communitarianism in Interregnum’,  	Postmodern Culture &amp; Cognition, Vol. 19, No. 1, Spring,  1993, p. 206.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloMichael Truscello is Professor of English and Director of the Mendoza House Project, English and Creative Studies, University of Toronto. His publications include various works in the field of arts and culture, including the 2002 New York Times best-seller Eco-Criticism: Art as Social</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She has exhibited at the Venice Biennale, Shiitakuwa, Shanghai, La Casa Encendida, and at the Sarumanaswamy Cultural Centre. She is the curator for the New Economy of Art, a project that examines the economic impacts of art and culture in South Asia, and the co-curator of the Sarumanaswamy Cultural Centre: Art and the Politics of Community Series, a symposium on contemporary art in the Indian city of Hyderabad. She has been the convener of the Sarumanaswamy Arts Festival, the author of several books on Indian culture, and the recipient of an ARC from the British Council. Her most recent work, India: The Stage was a part of the Biennale of Dangerous Ideas: Uma Bhadwal, Arjun Appadurai, Vikram Sethi, Mallikarjun Thorn, and others. She is a co-founder of the Dharmakirti Trust, a non-profit</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone to tell a full and open story, a story that might carry some weight with the public and even with the art world. The difficulty lies in the fact that the capacity of a community to put forth a collective will is limited; as a result, the power brokers seeking to impose their will dominate the narrative of a local community. In the end, however, it is the will of the people that is sovereign; the capacity of artists and others to help create narratives is an added strength.  	[1] See, for example, Sandy Rattray and Neil Johnson, eds., The Cultural Cost of Nuclear War: The Extra Hundred Years of War, The Paris Review Books, New York, 1991, p. 5.Download this article as PDFSandy RattraySandy Rattray is an artist. Her work in communities began when she was at the New School in the early 1990s, and she has exhibited internationally including at Venice, Berlin, and Shanghai. She has directed several documentaries including the BBC's War Games, and has written for the New York Times, the Washington Post, and the Los Angeles Times. Her work with the New School focused on the arts and culture of the post-nuclear age, and her artworks including the 2008 New Arts Prize Shortlist and the 2009 New Arts Prize Entry Critic. She has received a host of accolades and recognitions for her work.  	[2] See, for example, Gordon Thomas, ‘Communities at Risk: New Perspectives on International Migration’, in Current Anthropology, Vol. 23 (1), Spring, 2012, p. 8.Download this article as PDFGordon ThomasHistories of Migration, Migration and Capital, Wiley-Blackwell, 2015.Gordon Thomas is Professor in the School of Sociology, City and Society at the Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health and the Fletcher School of Law and Diplomacy, Harvard University. He</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being
    <text>should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being included in the exhibition, and the reasons they are not in the National Gallery. The exhibition is divided into two parts, ‘Presentation#1’ and ‘Presentation#2’, with biennials like ‘Presentation#1’ usually focusing on the presentation, while ‘Presentation#2’ tends to feature the larger, more conceptual part of the exhibition. Doyle-Hayes begins the section by summarising the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being included in the exhibition:1) The 1928 entry of Federico Fellini – an exhibition that would go on to be named the Venice of Venice – re-figuring the Italian pavilion from the 1920s in a manner that was inconceivable in an Italian city. Here, Italian pavilion syndrome is extended to a new level. Fellini is in many ways the quintessential Italian pavilion, but his recreation in Venice of the</text>
    <text>should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being included in the exhibition. Josephine Machon, Curator of Entomology, London, and Co-curator of the forthcoming Phantasia Project, London, explain the motivations for the project, drawing on her experiences as an entomologist and ethnobotanist during the 1970s and 80s. She also talks about her own early work, in the 1980s, when she was commissioned to design a project for the Venice Biennale, but also about the project’s early stages, which she describes as ‘futile from the get-go’. Finally, she describes the project’s transformation in her book ‘The World My Entomologist Endows’.  In the interview, she discusses the project through the narrative of her book, the book's structure, and the entomologist’s own narrative. Though she acknowledges the importance of collaboration and exchange, Doyle-Hayes is blunt</text>
    <text>should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being included in the exhibition. She begins by quoting William Morris, who in discussing the connections between the social and the natural, from his turn of thinking about the natural world to his later engagement with entomology. He argued that the social must be placed at the center of the enquiry, because ‘the social world is what gives rise to and gives form to life’.3. Embedded in the Museum Curator: How the Embedded Media Narrative of the Past Fit into the Curatorial Imagination. By Corinna Till. New York: Independent Museum of New York, 2016. Cover Image: Mike DeSisti. PreviousNextCorinna Till, ‘Embedded in the Museum Curator’, New York Times, 11 November 2016. Cover Image: Mike DeSisti. PreviousNextCorinna Till, ‘Embedded in the Museum Curator’, New York Times, 11 November 2016. Cover Image: Mike DeS</text>
    <text>should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being included in the exhibition.  Her description of the meeting between Doyle-Hayes and Bestwick connects to the meeting between Doyle-Hayes and the artist, and the fact that Doyle-Hayes selected the artist to be the subject of his project. She then describes the discussions between the museum staff and the artist, and the fact that they invited the artist to continue the project after he had been asked to do so by the museum staff.  Her description of the meeting between Harpe, Doyle-Hayes and Harpe’s wife also connects to the meeting between Doyle-Hayes and Harpe and his wife, and the fact that Doyle-Hayes selected Harpe to continue the project after he had been asked to do so by the curator.  Her description of the subsequent discussions between the museum staff and the artist highlights the fact that the discussions were not always private, and that the relationship between the two audiences could diverge in important ways – for example,</text>
    <text>should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being included in the exhibition. She introduces the entomologist John Graham Kerr, who led the research into the moths that feed on the skin of humans, and who contributed to the understanding of the mysterious 'zombie' that characterises the human body. Jess Doyle-Hayes then introduces another entomologist, Professorial Fellow Dr Vanessa Minford, who has worked on the University of Glasgow’s Zomia Programme for several years, and who describes the project as ‘a collaboration with Scottish Naturalists’ that brings together the Museum and the naturalists to explore ‘the interactions between humans and natural creatures’. The museum is made up of many different points of entry. These range from the mundane, the seemingly mundane (the exhibits on campus), to the fantastical, the impossible and the inescapable. Assembled by Curator Elise Atangana, the visitors are given access to a number of different parts of the</text>
    <text>should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being included in the exhibition, and the discussions that followed about how to tell the stories of these creatures. In the case of the entomology, the museum stories included the stories of Native people, in this case the H.P. Lovecraft character Cthulhu (real name Edmund Hillary), who uses various mythical creatures to fight the forces of evil. These conversations took place long before the publication of the first Necronomicon, in 1887, and were part of a wider cultural exchange between the two worlds. The exhibition begins with a sequence of photographs from the collections of the National Gallery, taken during the 1920s and 1930s. They form part of a larger collection, taken during the same period, of objects from the collection that were used in the production of the infamous ‘Kitchen Journal’ – a forgery and fabrication that implicated the gallery with great political, economic and social power. The photographs are a reminder, as Doyle-Hayes describes, of the political nature of the exchange</text>
    <text>should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being put together into a collection. Her chapter on Lovecraft includes a description of the curatorial process, based on notes taken during a previous visit to the site. The items selected for this narrative are chosen from a large collection of historic specimens, many of which are from the British Museum. The curatorial notes tell a story about the collection, about the various layers and layers of historical material, the intimate relationships between collectors and their collections, and the impressive array of objects in the collection. References to collections and collections are characteristic of curatorial writing, but Doyle-Hayes’ chapter is unique in telling the story as an object of collection, and the curatorial intentions as collections. She uses the term ‘collectors’ to refer to those who acquire things, even though there is no explicit reference to such a thing in the text or in the heading of the article.  The curatorial notes also tell a story about the relationship between the writer and her subjects, even though there is no</text>
    <text>should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being made into products for the consumer, and the objects in the exhibition being replaced. Both the past and the present are objects of gaze in the exhibition.Jessa Boyd, Curator of Entomology, London and National Museums Liverpool, UK, discusses the project’s purposes and goals, and the role of the museum in capturing and narrating the past as a mode of being. She also discusses the relationship between archaeology and entomology, and the two areas of particular interest: the metainhabitation of plants and animals, and the domestication of animals. The exhibition ‘will contrast the modern fascination with the recognisable past and the ancient past of mankind, and the domestication of animals’. She notes that the major archaeological finds in the Middle East and Africa are made up of objects from the past that were deliberately kept out of view. She considers how the future holds promises and disappointments that are both possible and uncomplicated</text>
    <text>should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being referred to as ‘the mutton of the commons’, and the museum being renamed ‘The Commons of the Past’.  Her description of the exhibition as ‘a mode of being’ mirrors the way in which the objects are arranged in the exhibition. They are used in several different ways in the exhibition, and the objects themselves are carefully designed to be used. Jess Doyle-Hayes invokes the museum’s past to engage with questions of power, capital and history. She tells the story of two men who used to run a butcher shop called ‘The Mill’ in the mid-1990s, and the tale of two women who used to live in a neighbouring street called ‘The Lofts’. The object that came to define the style of the ‘mutton of the commons’ is a steaming steatite pot with a handle made of lime and steel. It was a weapon in the shop, and the</text>
    <text>should be curated, but rarely are they – until now. The exhibition is curated by Jess Doyle-Hayes and Anna Bestwick, artists with H.P. Lovecraft, and includes items from the artist's archive including objects from his childhood, from when he was living in London, and from when he was completing his PhD. There are also objects from the National Gallery, including two pieces that were part of the collections for a number of years, one from 1922, the other from 1926. The exhibition is intended to show the connections between the two periods, and relates the two dominant cultural forms of the time – modern and post-modernism – to questions of identity, power and history. Jess Doyle-Hayes, the Curator of Entomology, London’s History Museum, introduces the project, describing its purpose as ‘to recall and to narrate the past as a mode of being’. She then describes the conversations that led to the items in the museum collection being offered to the public as specimens of ‘the human condition’. 12.  How I Came to Know About Parasitism in the Animal KingdomMichael Hardt and Neil Johnson, Parasitology: Theory, Psychology and Practice, Routledge, New York, 2006, p.31.  14. Devadas, ‘The Art of Feeding a Spider, “with Modern Materials and Methods”, in Anatomical Material Culture vol. 3 (1936–1939), pp. 91–108, as cited in Colin Ward, The Anatomy Classroom: Evolutionary Psychology and the Modern Middle School, SUNY Press, New York, 2008, p.30.  Download this article as PDFElise AtanganaElise Atangana is an artist, writer, educator and Communications Officer at the Royal College of Art. She has a particular interest in discussing the ethical and political issues of our time, especially in relation to the conditions</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past my prime, I’m going to be a billboard artist, or a gallery artist, or a video artist, or a website designer, or a nursery worker, or a hairdresser, or a hairdresser’s parlour, or a tinsmith, or a carpenter, or a baker, or a soldier. I’m done with you.’ It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Now I’m past my prime, I’m past my prime, I’m past my prime, I’m past my time, and I’m not coming back.’ The notion that art might somehow inhabit the here and now in the here and now that much more firmly asserts its cultural character. And for some artists and curators, that character is a very particular quality that they want to project onto the social world.I don’t mean to suggest that there</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past this, I’m past that. I’m past that, I’m past everything.’ But in the UK and the US, there’s a different attitude. There’s an assumption that art has to be present in order for it to be valuable; and as an additional constraint, an assumption about what counts as art. Giles Hunt, The Empty Space of the New Economy, Penguin 2005, p.13.Download this article as PDFMark MiodownikMark Miodownik is Professor in the School of Communication, Culture and Society at Columbia University, and also Director of the Columbia Center for Art and Culture. His work has addressed the social consequences of creative perforation, from the postcolonial condition to the contemporary condition of the artistically-inclined. His books include the posthumous nonfiction book The People and the Planet (2007), about the impact of global ecology on contemporary culture, and the 2008 memoirs St</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past my prime.’ There is a sense that we don’t need to consider the possibility that art might actually be some kind of oppressive system that oppresses us.This is a huge question that the contemporary art world doesn’t seem to be asking enough artists and curators, or, at least, not enough of them. If there’s going to be curatorial work happening now, it should be happening somewhere else in the world, and it’s going to be done by people from places around the world. It’s going to be a ‘different kind of art’. But why would an artist choose to work now in such a way? What does that make art? I don’t get it. And sometimes, I don’t get it either.I’m not going to get into arguments about what contemporary art is or isn’t, because I don’t get it either. I just</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past this, I’m late for this, and now I’m back in the present.’ The idea that we could conceivably conceivably grow old together and return to the past is what makes the modern museum complex and the contemporary art movement possible. In the UK and US, this means that the very concrete forms that we create (museums and galleries in the first place) can be repurposed, and reused, creating new uses for what was once good quality urban space. In the first decades of the twentieth century, this meant that when the Rubens Institute for Contemporary Art was founded in New York, it was primarily used as a temporary exhibitionary space, and its collections plundered in the course of the exhibition being shown. The contemporary demand for transportable exhibitionary forms quickly outstripped the collections. The institute was shut down in 1921, and its collections moved to the California Institute of Technology, where they remained until 1968, when the New York Public</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past the point, and I don’t need any more of your money.’ And the society of the artist has said: ‘That’s enough, we’re past the point where we need any more of you.’The idea that there’s life beyond the art market – beyond the quantifiable – is a huge turn-off for some artists and curators. It’s as if the market says: ‘You’re beyond this, you’re beyond that.’ And the artist has said: ‘No, I’m not beyond that. I’m beyond the point where I need any more money.’The idea that there’s no life beyond the art market – beyond the qualitative – is a huge turn-off for some artists and curators. It’s as if the market says: ‘You’re beyond this, you’re beyond</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past my prime, I’m going to be a gallery artist, I’m cool, I’m not that sort of guy.’ If that’s the case, then why would the artist invest so much effort in concealing her/his true self? Why would an artist invest so much effort in creating a persona that is obscured from view? Why would an artist want to mislead the public about their true self? Why would an artist want to distort the truth? 	[1] The term ‘transparent identity politics’ is used here to describe the underlying socio-political context, which is closely tied to and depends on the social composition of a city. Though not all cities are created equal, there are notable differences between the socio-political positions of various European cities. For example, while in North American cities the identity politics are primarily concerned with white, western identity, in cities such as Liverpool and Toronto the identity politics are much more nuanced</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past my prime, I’m not the same artist I was four years ago.’ The notion that artists and art institutions might somehow re-occur in the here and now in response to this idea is quite different. I think the logic of the project is to a large extent about contingency. If the Tate Gallery moved back into its historic role as a contemporary art museum, or the Kunsthalle PXxxiv moved into a museum of modern art, or the PXxxiv was repurposed as a residence for contemporary artists, then we would all be artists again. For some, and I include myself here, that would be a miracle. 	For others, and I include here both curators and artists, it would mean moving back into the gallery and back into the home. For some, and I include here both curators and artists, it would mean moving back into the gallery and into the home. For some, and I include here both curators and</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past the point, and now I want to be remembered for good.’  I don’t think that was the intention. It’s much more the case that the artist has said: ‘You know, I’m done with you, and I’m past the point. I’m going to look back and realise I’m making art out of nothing, and that’s all there is.’ I don’t think that was the intention either – we would and still do things in a certain way because we’re human beings and we’re artists, and we’re human beings make mistakes, and there’s always that element of that in there somewhere. But there is that element of vulnerability and that vulnerability is a big part of what makes art work. And that’s what I’ve always tried to get at: the work is not done, it’s</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past my prime, I’m going to be a great contemporary artist, I’m just a regular artist who happens to be in the art world right now.’ This is foreign to us, and it’s almost as if the artist has said ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past my prime, I’m going to be famous, I’m going to be a playwright, an artist, and maybe even a poet.’ But the point is that it’s art, and the art should be celebrated in whatever way it’s appropriate. Art is a complex concept that has many voices, and it’s this interplay between the artist and the public – between the artist and the public – that creates the actual meaning and reality of art. And the more we talk about what the art world and the public might achieve through this particular project, the more it’s going</text>
    <text>exceeds the capacity of the human curator alone. Giles Hunt, our contemporary art critic, seems to imply that we might not want people to know what we’re working so hard to conceal. He writes: ‘Art is a fraud. It is said that while the brilliant young curators at Tate and Kunsthalle PXxxiv’, as they bid us adieu before departing, ‘never looked back, never in their long lives sawKübler-Ross’s plans come true.’ The notion that art might somehow exist in the here and now – in the here and now because it’s art, in the here and now because it’s happening now – is an idea that has a very specific and narrow interpretation in the UK and US. It doesn’t really compute, and for some artists and curators it does. It’s as if the artist has said: ‘Look, I’m done with you, I’m past my prime. I’m past my use. I’m past my humanity.’1 And the artist has said: ‘I’m done with you, I’m past my use.’2 And the question then becomes: what does that make us? Art has a way of closing in on its subject in a way that makes them not just there but actually useful and valuable and beautiful. So the question of who art is made visible is one that can be navigated. It’s not a new one, and it’s not a new question that artists and curators in the arts world constantly push back against. It’s a question that art has been grappling with since the early twentieth century, and it’s a question that artists and curators in many art forms across the world struggle with. But it’s also a question that many artists and curators in the arts world don’</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the
    <text>accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the economy, has come to depend on the availability of cheap housing and other goods and services. As a consequence, the suburbs have responded by developing into something like economic moonshine: a resource for the economy, a source of cheap labour and a source of culture but also of poverty and conflict. 	There are now over 300,000 people living within 100km (62 miles) of the Pittsburgh International Airport, which means that even as the pace of new migrant arrivals slows, the number of homeless continues to grow.1 	The airport is a major point of entry for people fleeing violence in their home countries, and has become a major transit hub for people fleeing the violence in the Middle East.2 	The International Monetary Fund has estimated that the economic impact of the airport’s growth will be somewhere between $40bn and $80bn over the next 30 years.3 	There are currently two main modes of travel within the airport: by car or by plane. The</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the economy, is now controlled by the demand for housing.  	As a result, housing has become something that can be controlled; it is not a natural resource that can be tapped for growth but rather an asset that can be quantified and traded on the global financial markets. 	At the same time, the control exerted over housing has come at the expense of other kinds of social difference. Urban growth has displaced large numbers of people in areas with high incomes; poorer areas bear the brunt of the effects of overbuilding and fragmented government. The poorest neighbourhoods are crowded with people who cannot afford to eat or to use the public transport; the overcrowding has led to diseases such as pneumonia and tuberculosis, which can be controlled with antibiotics but which often require hospitalisation. 	Immigrant movements are also affected by the greed of developers, who demand huge tracts of land from communities in exchange for cheap housing. The demand for housing, which is at the peak of the economic crisis, is at an</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the economic logic of growth, is now driven by the need to access points on a map. 	The desire to be left alone in urban environments has become the currency of the rich and the powerful; it is no longer enough to be left behind; people have to be able to access and use the city in ways that correspond to their identities. In other words, the logic of growth has shifted from the need to access resources in ways that are common to all humans, to the adoption of identities that are distinct from the resources on which the city is built. 	The adoption of new technologies allows for the deployment of ever more precise and controllable data mining, which in turn, allows for ever more efficient ways of managing urban environments. New insurance mechanisms are created to compensate for the loss of value created by the proliferation of useless and wasteful infrastructure. New ways of inhabiting the city are developed through new forms of surveillance and policing, which are deployed at scale without qualms or worries about public</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the economy, depends on it. But the gated community that emerged after the mid-1990s urban boom has passed is no longer a gated community; it is a community of ordinary people confined to their own neighbourhood. It is the emergence of a broad middle class, which I have traditionally defined as encompassing people who afford to live in good neighbourhoods, irrespective of whether that neighbourhood is located in or outside the city. 	If the gated community became integrated into the city fabric, it would no longer be gated; it would no longer be gated because of the presence of so many security guards and police officers; it would cease to be gated only for the privileged few who happen to be residents or visitors. The community would become integrated into the fabric of the city, and the city would embrace the community. 	In an ideal world, this transition would occur in tandem with the development of a strong and sustainable composting centre, but as we know, this has been delayed</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the economic logic of growth, is now based on the demand for housing and the ability to access amenities such as access to parks and recreation. 	In 1990, as the city sought to transition to a management that would no longer rely on the gated community, a community of residents formed armed and relocated to the Ghetto Watch site on the Upper West Side.[28] Today, Ghetto Watch is run by volunteers and houses are shared between residents and community members. 	The Ghetto Watch project has its origins in the 1980s, but the movement to create community-controlled affordable housing dates much further back. As Robert Reich, US Secretary of Housing and Urban Development under Ronald Reagan, put it in a speech at Kent State University:  1. Developments in housing policy have tended to defer important issues like social, economic and political transformation for long periods of time, and are instead driven by the pursuit of quick, abundant and convenient financial returns. 2. During the 1980s and</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the economy, is now controlled by the needs of the market. 	These trends are not good. They may seem obvious to urban dwellers in their hyper-commercialised metropolises; but to those outside of those zones, especially newcomers, these changes are seen as disruptive and ill-defined. The reason for this is that these new arrivals tend to be migrants in search of a new life, seeking a better quality of life, in places such as New York and London. They are seeking a stake in the land-use transition that is being made in their favour; places with which to inhabit, co-habitate and raise families; shops and shops to support a host of activities; and perhaps most importantly, a stake in the flourishing of the local arts scene that is now threatened by the encroachment of monolith-like buildings and multimillion-dollar corporate schemes. 	The main challenge for those new to the city is to understand the vested interests that drive it. This may</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the economy, is now controlled by the needs of the market. As a consequence, the neighbourhoods that function as commercial centres are likely to become increasingly crowded and unhealthy. As a result, the rate of profit has had to fall far more rapidly than the rate of population growth in order to support the growing burden of housing, which in turn means that the quality of life for residents has had to fall far more rapidly than the quality of life for travellers. 	This dynamic is particularly evident in the most heavily travelled city in the world: New York City. The higher the demand for housing, the more expensive it is to build new housing, which means that the infrastructure is stretched thinner and the prices far beyond the means of supporting the size and scope of the city. As a consequence, the poorest neighbourhoods – those along the peripheries of the metros where building standards have stagnated or fallen behind in any of the three major urban areas – tend to be abandoned or neglected. 	The abandonment of these</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the economic logic of growth, is now driven by the performance of the housing market. 	The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly broad, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and isolated from one another. 	The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly broad, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and isolated from one another. 	The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly broad, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and isolated from one another. 	The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the economy, is now controlled from above. As a consequence, the number of cars on the road has greatly expanded in the past half century; in some areas, over 11 million cars use the roads each day. 	The rapid growth of trade between nations has also contributed to an expanded and more diverse range of commodities and consumer goods being produced in the world's megacities. The set of commodities and consumer goods produced in the megacities is what is referred to as ‘global north’; this is where companies locating in the megacity typically establish operations, procure ingredients, set up production, and, most importantly, deliver the goods and services of commerce to customers located in the surrounding region. 	Import and export of these commodities and services has been the primary means by which the megacity has managed to expand, at least in the short term. This is why, as Michael Slackman indicates, the expansion of the megacity has come about through the back door, rather than</text>
    <text>accessible through the websites of the major banks, which permit us to make money lending to each other and buying things with our money. 	The quest for exotic solubles justifies everything from military spending to sub-prime lending; it is the financial equivalent of a child prodigy emerging from the gutter and climbing to the rooftops; and it is the stuff of science-fiction films. But the more we depend on these things, the less likely we are to innovate or push the envelope or pursue new ideas. The gilded hyper-localisation of finance capital, and its shifting of the economic cost of everything from housing to roads, creates the conditions for an increasingly obscure and fragmented social life. The gated community that developed around it no longer included only a few; the suburbs formed increasingly wide, cartographic spaces where residents could roam freely but were also centrally located and disconnected from one another. 	Urban growth has come to dominate access to areas with high demand; access to the city, and therefore the economy, relies on two-thirds of the city’s development. But as a rule, the economy does not grow when people are richer; it contracts when incomes are low. The result is a situation where the rich retain a disproportionate share of the wealth while the majority of people struggle to gain access to basic needs. 	The goal of any city is to keep its residents and the economy from being overwhelmed; this is why so-called ‘green’ technologies are so prevalent in places where people are kept indoors, such as buildings and the landscape. But as cities have become ever more complex and globalised, and as interconnectedness and the demands of massive systems have become ever more elaborate, the need to be connected has become ever more pressing. 	In New York City, for instance, large parts of the subway and parts of the waterfront are now served by high-speed rail, which means that trips between the city and the suburbs are no longer made by car but by</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
