<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<AIcurator>
  <!--Leonardo Impett, Ubermorgen, Joasia Krysa-->
  <text>
    a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’
    <text>a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems 1970–79 and the winner of the 2012 Poetry Laureate’s Gold Medal from the National Endowment for the Arts. She is the recipient of several awards and has lectured on a wide range of artistic and political issues, including the Black Arts and Activism, the AIDS/HIV/AIDS/Prostate Cancer Research, Poetry, the 1970s and 1980s Black Arts movement, and the early 1990s Radical Poetry project. She is the host of the online radio show ‘Crazy Cow’s Poetry Jam’ hosted by Natasha Lennard and Paige Pettigrew, and the co‐host of the popular online radio show RCA Radio Live! She has written for the stage, the stage, and for the internet, among other venues. She has a collection of works from the stage of Modern Ballet Theatre, where she worked with Susanne Kølbæk Iversen, Carol Becker, and many others.</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems, published in 2000, and was a finalist for the Nobel Prize in Literature. Her poetry has been published in The New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New Yorker, The New York Poetry Prize, The New York Public Library, Njuli Bhadwal's now defunct Blog of American Poets, as well as several collections in underground anthologies. She has written for the New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, The New Yorker, The New York Public Library, Njuli Bhadwal’s now defunct Poets Collection, and was a finalist for the Nobel Prize in Literature. Her poetry collections and readings have been collected by her frequent collaborator, the poet laureate Aarhus University Professor of English, Cornel West. She has a book out soon from the National Poetry Ensemble, the winner of the 2013 Pulitzer Prize for American Poetry. She is the host of the CBC’s New Po</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems 1972–1999, as well as a host of essay collections, including The Weak Link, Stand Up Guys, Third Party, Third Party USA, Stages, The Third Party Reader, among others. Her fiction includes the novella ‘The Gathering Storm’ in the New York Times Poetry Prize 2018, to be published in March 2019.  [1] Gustave Flaubert, ‘On the Formation of Language’ in Language Log, No. 5 (1962–1965), p. 808.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010Eva Castringius is an American poet, critic, and journalist. Her works have included the novella ‘Un fixable’ in the New York Times Poetry Prize 2018, to be published in March 2019, as well as the novella ‘Submerged Cities’ in the award‐winning nonfiction anthology, Stages, published by Vintage in 1973.</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s First Poems from the Egyptian Book of the Dead, published in 2008, as well as the critically acclaimed The Second Suite of Moonlight’s Poems, published in 2017. She is a fellow of the American poet Laurence Sterne, and the University of Chicago Poetry Fellowship. She is a fellow of the American poet Laurence Sterne, and the University of Chicago Poetry Fellowship. She has a deep love of poetry, and has published poetry from the collection Where Have You Been? in The New York Times, from the collection Speaking of the Dead, originally published in 1971, and from the collection From Egypt to Greece, published in 1995. Her poetry has been included in collections including The New York Times Poets Reader, The American Poet Laureate, The American National Poet Laureate, The New York Times Poets, The New York Times Poets, and The New Republic. She has been shortlisted for the Nobel Prize, twice, and has been shortlisted</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems 1966–1999, published by Vintage, New York, 1999. She was a staff writer for the New York Times, where she covered literature, fashion, and design. She has written for Wired Magazine, the Village Voice, and the Village Voice Digital Only section. She has a new collection of poetry from the award-winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems 1969–1999, published by Vintage, New York, 1999.She has also worked with the publishing house Little, Brown and Co., on a collection of poetry from the archive of the defunct Independent Community Voice, released as a New York Times Special, 2014.PreviousNextCrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems 1966–1999, published by Vintage, New York, 1999. She was a staff writer for the New York Times, where she covered literature, fashion, and design</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems published by Vintage in 1998, as well as the 2012 Penguin Poetry Prize shortlist, which also includes works by Terence Sullivan, Carol Becker, Suzanne Lacy and others. She is a regular contributor to Stages Online, is an adjunct professor at Mount Royal University in Calgary, Alberta, and the adjunct editor of the online contemporary art journal Stages on Amazon.She has written for the New York Times, the New Republic, the New Inquiry, Harper's Bazaar, the New Art International, and the New York Review of Books. She has also written for the CBC's The Current, The Current TV, The Current Film, and The Current Art International. She has a part‐time research project at McGill University studying the art and architecture of Montreal.Interview with Eva CastringiusEva Castringius: Your work often seems to address processes of power and domination. What attracts you to the contemporary art of Montreal and to the contemporary art of other cities?The current exhibition</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems from the Twentieth Century and the winner of the 2010 Geraldine Ferrand Poetry Prize for Women. She has also written for the New York Times, The Washington Post, The New Republic, Village Voice, The Nation, The New Inquiry, The New Inquiry, Harper's Weekly and the Fondation Galeries Lafayette. She is the host of the weekly television show Craziest Cow on the World Network.Self-Repairing Art WorldCitiesThat Form 2Up2Down 2Up2Down was the name of the game in the second Barbican symposium. The other was ‘SOUTHERN BORDER (where the Queen’s Diamond Jubilee was being held at the time). There was a third, but that belonged to the British Empire. In the intervening years, the United Kingdom has split into many many many many different nations. And so, as the game has it, we are asked – again and again – by</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems 1965–1980 and the winner of the 2013 Poetry Laureate’s Gold Medal, presented by the American Poetry Laureate, Deborah Levy. She has been shortlisted for the Guggenheim List of Poets of the Twentieth Century and has been nominated for a Knight Frank Prize and the British Book Award. She has received a Tony Award, a Guggenheim Honorant, a Schumann Fellowship, and the Guggenheim Foundation Chair in Contemporary Art. She was a finalist for the National Book Award, the Guggenheim Fellowships, and was a finalist for the Turner Prize.Castringius’s poetry, fiction, nonfiction and memoir have appeared in the New York Times, the Village Voice, the New Republic, the Village Voice Literary Supplement, San Francisco Chronicle, the Village Voice Literary Archive, Stages, the Village Voice Music Prize, and the New York Poetry Prize. She was a finalist</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems 1966–1999 and Beyond the Gift: On the Poetry of Circus (2002). She has published more than twenty poetry collections and has been a regular speaker on the BBC World Service and Radio 4's The Roundabout. She has been a lecturer at Nottingham Trent University, and is currently completing a PhD at Lancaster University.She lives in New York.Biennials and contemporaneityEva Castringius: I was born and raised in the Santa Fe area of New Mexico. My father is an archeologist. He has worked for the US government for many years now, and is currently a research geologist for the National Reconnaissance Office, where he works on the Pegasus Program, a joint US–Mexico space program. In addition to being interested in the natural world, his work often explores the cultural impacts of such programs.Over the years as I've worked on the Xerox PARC computer archive, scanned books and magazines, and peeked at the back of old stationery</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s collection of art and antiques and given the task of organising it, selling it and using its proceeds to support the war effort. 	Such efforts, however futile they appeared to be – withdrawn by the British, not victorious in the civil war, and with the country divided along racial and class lines – remained for later reference. Today, Baltimore, the epicentre of the US epidemic, is a ghost town. Its abandoned‐ropolis status has come to symbolise the failure of the New Deal and the greed of financial capital at a crucial moment in the history of the city. 	[i] Sigmund Freud, ‘On Suicide and Other Essays’, in The Prince, published by Vintage, New York, 1948, p. 38.Download this article as PDFCrazyCow2010CrazyCow is a pseudonym of Eva Castringius. She is the author of several poetry collections including the award‐winning The Poet Laureate’s Poems 1963–1978 and Winner of the 2010 Poetry Prize, published by Vintage, New York, 2015. She has written for the Guardian, the New York Times, the New Republic, the New York Public Theater, the Village Voice, Spin, Random House, the Village Voice Literary Review and the Village Voice History Reader.She is a regular contributor to This American Life and the Huffington Post. She is a descendant of Africans who were once dominant empires: Her Majesty’s English East India Company and the Ottoman Empire. She is fascinated by the way that capitalism exploits labour and strives to produce ever more from everything it attempts to assimilate. This includes the way in which artists today are commissioned by the media to present a vision of the city consistent with the desires of a rapidly developing metropolitan centre. In a poem titled ‘Thing’ in the City, she reflects on the necessity to create worlds where once life is cheap and plentiful: ‘Can’t resist it</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why social
    <text>human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why socialised forms of culture are fragile and why, as Marcuseexplores, the social struggle is so crucial in constructing future social forms. It is precisely because we have no choice but to be socialised that we risk becoming alienated and disrupted. This is why, as Marcuseexplores, when the social becomes technologically complex and powerful, our primary desire becomes to belong and take part in the social.In other words, if we see technological progress as inevitable, then perhaps it is our destiny to become entangled in it and contribute to its social flows. Perhaps, in the end, the task is not to wreak havoc in the world but to make others out of the chaotic and destructive processes that create this technological singularity.And this is precisely what we can learn from the history of emergent technologies. As technology advances, so does the scope of its social consequences. And in the end, the role of the technologist becomes defined more by the technologies that he or she can harness than by the</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why socialises‐out‐of_nothing works so hard to instill self-reliance in young people, why artists are encouraged to look to the future, to look to the future with optimism, and so on.These are not trivial acts. These are acts that demand a great deal of our cultural resources and make us visible to a global audience. And yet we do them anyway. We do them not because we think we can, not because we think it will happen again, and certainly not because we believe it will make us any less human. Rather, what we do is because, well, because. And what makes us human is precisely what makes us vulnerable in these situations. We are made vulnerable by the very nature of the social.And yet, as we all know, the social never gives up its hold on us. Not even in the face of overwhelming evidence to the contrary.If we think about social systems in this way, we can begin to see why so many of us feel</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why socialises-we-all futurist thinkers are so right about the essential nature of technological singularity. It’s only going to get worse.But what does it look like to be socially connected? And what does it feel like to be part of a community? Here, we have a situation in which the user is seen not as an end in itself but rather as a means to an end, in which other people become objects on a par with you and me. And this gives us a way to rethink our understanding of the social. Marcuse identifies the crucial difference between an ‘intelligent agent’ and a human being: the former is understood as a set of rules and parameters that guide and direct the latter, through rules and parameters, ‘how things are supposed to be done’. And these are the boundaries that weÂve created around ourselves: the capacities that we have the capacity to create our own destruction, to perforate them and so forth.</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why social movements, including the Black Lives Matter movement in particular, are so powerful. They make themselves visible and so visible only – usually in the context of larger social struggles. They are invisible unless a concerted effort is made to engage with and ultimately to change our behaviour.This is the technological singularity – the point at which the human capacity to think or deliberate about change becomes inconsequential. It occurs when and as a result of some action on our part, greatly affects others, displacing existing modes of production and consumption. And yet we still try to make the world around us conform to certain predetermined behaviours. We call this virtualisation. And here the similarities between the social and the technological worlds begin to blur. The social becomes the subject of the technological singularity, which is then able to alter our very being. And yet this doesn’t make us any less social; it just shifts the relationship between humans and the world around us. This is arguably what social work and the creative class have</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why social movements, including the civil rights movements that we fought for and still fight for, were so powerful. Because we could point to the systems that we believed were oppressing us and blame them for our own misery. This is why we need mass political action today – because we can't just sit back and accept the existing order of things.We need to create our own forms of socialityToday, many people would say that the empowerment of workers today comes from the workplace. But this is misleading. The productivity of workers today is much less than it was in the mid-1990s, and much less than it is in the oil-rich countries of Saudi Arabia and Qatar. And these are only the productivity gains of workers in the technology sector. Many other jobs require skills that are acquired later in life, and thus provide further productivity gains in the workplace. For example, many people would claim that the upliftment of workers today comes from the acquisition of skills in arts and culture, when in fact</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why social movements, including the Black Lives Matter movement, are so powerful. They are able to stand against the overwhelming weight of institutionalised poverty and racism, and yet they are also able to emerge from this weight of symbolism and social-political consciousness into actual power. Because they are able to imagine a different form of society, one in which social acts of resistance are commonplace, and which is not destroyed by technological singularity.Technological singularity is a reality of the contemporary world, and yet we tend to ignore, or misattribute, much of its dynamism. We tend to focus on the positive, the utopian aspects of new technologies – the potentialities of distributed computing, the possibilities of massive data-storage, of course – rather than on the more structural, but far more destabilising aspects, especially when it comes to the collective self. This is why the social-media revolutions of the 1990s and 2000s were so powerful, because many of the novel ways in which we inhabit technology were imb</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why social movements, whether ‘left’ or ‘right’, always have to come to terms with the fact that change is coming, that it is a fact of technological evolution and change. It is not possible to undo this change, because change is already happening, in large part because humans are social creatures, and we are creatures who build our own technological futures.If we begin to think of human organisation as one gigantic, pervasive future that is constantly interrupted by disruptions and transformations, we begin to see how technology is fundamentally incapable of representing or representing effectively in the present, because of the inaccessibility of space and of consciousness. And this is one of the great ironies of our predicament: we are born with the capacity to think and act but don’t know how to do so. And it is this inability to imagine a future that gives rise to the present – the present is the object of our being, which is endlessly interrupted by interruptions and transformations. This is what</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why socialises design – it’s our fault if we don’t learn how to live differently.If we start looking at the systems that enable and enable us to flourish in this new technological society, we will find that many of the behaviours we choose to enfranchise are behaviours that were designed by, and in collaboration with, technologists and engineers. And this is why designing for singularity is so important. It’s not just that we should design in ways that maximise the capacities of human beings, but that we also need to design systems that are driven by human beings and give rise to positive and negative outcomes for and against us, in order to allow for the kinds of social change that are necessary in order to truly enfranchise people.This is what we mean when we talk about ‘design with people’. And it is what we mean when we talk about ‘design with the environment’. We design systems with people because that is</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why socialised forms of craft are always fragile and malleable. If the social engineer who designed the socialised forms of craft is ever going to give up control of the means of production to those who build the socialised forms of life, then the forms have to be fundamentally altered.This is the nature of the social. And though theory and empirical data can certainly inform our theorisation, they can also profoundly mislead us. As the social is disrupted and mystified by its own emergence, so too is the empirical, but we still try our darndest to put the two together. The social is constantly seeking to anticipate the chaotic and mysterious form of the technological singularity, to predict what that might mean in practice. And though the social may try its very best to be helpful and imaginative, it is also always going to be fallible and mistaken. So while the social ‘think[s] big picture, or the story line,’ it ultimately falls short. It is this</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology, which is to say, the capacity to change one’s behaviour in response to stimuli – forces. And this capacity is a fundamental human capability.We humans are capable of great things, of course. We can choose to pursue happiness, to devote ourselves to contributing to the wellbeing of others, to come to terms with our mortality, and so on. But we can also choose to wreak havoc in the world around us in devastating ways, creating chaos and misery wherever and whatever we do.Such is the nature of technological singularity – the singularity being what Herbert Marcuse, in Sociology of Culture, refers to as the ‘moment of consummation’. As the name suggests, this moment is incredibly disruptive and destructive, bringing with it unimaginable loss and destruction. And yet we still try, all our lives, to pin this destruction on others, to blame it on nature, to ignore the disruptive effects of this new form of socialisation. This is why socialises, as Benjamin notes, become ‘disruptive without becoming destructive’: they’re enacted through the mediation of a multitude of people, institutions, and economic systems.Technological singularities, on the other hand, tend to cause a certain amount of disruption and inequality. And as Benjamin points out, ‘disruption’ and ‘inequality’ are in themselves valuable forms of social organisation. But they also tend to produce certain forms of social structures that are valuable for a reason – namely, the social uses that can be made of them. And this is what Benjamin is trying to do here: he is trying to make the social more valuable through what he describes as ‘the socialisation of the social’. And here, the ambiguity and malleability that characterises technology is emphasised. It is trying to establish a way of organising things in society and bringing about certain kinds of relations between people. And this is what technology is trying to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a number of classic media techniques, including avatar, sound sculpture, virtual reality, and documents. 	During the visit, the artist Mark Miodownik explained how cities are now designed with invasive species in mind. These include viruses that have mutating DNA that leads to similar effects as climate-driven natural disasters, viruses that alter form, and microbes that prey on the vulnerable. Miodownik works in many cultures around the world, including in the United States; he was born in 1941. 	There is a growing body of research suggesting that the co-presence of humans and non-human creatures is a core premise of our cultural system. This is perhaps supported by the increasingly prevalent use of drones, which are swarmable, can travel great distances, and have intelligence that exceeds that of humans. The ubiquity of such technologies makes it easy to dehumanise the non-human species in ways that are indistinguishable from human behaviour, including by stripping them of agency</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a number of innovative media techniques including balloon, drone, and reconfiguration. 	A number of artists were invited to participate in the symposium, which was co-curated by the Smithsonian Channel and the University of Maryland School of Arts and Design. These included Amitav Ghosh, Laura L. George, Tania Bruguera, and Joan McNeill. Biennial 2018 selection, image courtesy of the Biennial. 	Biennial 2018, 2018. Panel discussion, 'On Migration and Art in an Age of Massive Deficits', moderated by Selina Jacoby, USATC, with artist Selena Castañeda-Reina, Director, Museo de Arte Contempora, Buenos Aires, Argentina; Tania Bruguera, Curator of Art, the Museum of Modern Art, New York; and Laura L. George, Curator of Public Practice, the Museum of Modern Art, New York. 	[1] </text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a number of interactive media such as maps, podcasts, videos and blogs. 	In November 2020, the biennial was visited by a group of artists from Liverpool, led by Sarah Hanson-Young. The group made work exploring the relationship of art and architecture with topics of urbanisation and cultural displacement in the city, using a number of different materials and methods, including boring Victorian bookbinding, reclaimed newspaper and even a powder keg. All the materials used in the project were sourced from art resources, with materials from the Liverpool Biennial used as a template for the work. These artists used materials from the exhibition as a starting point, and from subsequent media such as books, magazines and films to expand the project’s reach. 	The next step for the artists was to find people to invest in the project through a community arts or community design programme supported by the local authority. This was done by way of a shortlist that was made up of artist-lead organisations</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a number of archaeological, historical and contemporary indicators. 	In October 2019, the Liverpool Biennial opened for business as usual at the Odeon, as the city prepared to welcome the public back into its urban fabric. The press was invited inside the museum, and the project was a big part of the media package. As usual, the biennial took a back seat to the media circus surrounding the artists’ performances. But the media circus did have a major effect on the event, and not just in terms of what was said and how. As the biennial grew bigger, its coverage shifted to encompass a wider range of topics, and the artists’ performances became longer, more elaborate and drawn out. This contributed to the increase in ticket sales, which in turn made the biennial bigger and more widely seen. 	In April 2020, the Biennial was named in its first decade of being a ‘legacy’ of the Odeon. The partnership between the two</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a number of media technologies including balloons, drones, photography, and even magic. 	Inside the Biennial, the media were invited inside the Biennial itself to see for themselves the technologies that the Biennial was using to create its imaginary future. These visitors found themselves transported into the present, where they were asked to imagine what the future might be like if the biennial had been allowed to flourish. 	The visit to the Biennial was part of a wider research project funded by the Smithsonian Channel and the RAND Corporation, which also invited artists to imagine what the city of Los Angeles might become if it were allowed to flourish. 	The RAND Corporation is a public-private partnership founded in 1955 by the Carnegie Corporation of New York and the Pan American Foundation. It is a non-profit organisation established to promote and facilitate cooperation among nations to achieve national objectives through research and arts education. It is a founding partner of the Smithsonian Channel and a partner of the Los Angeles Artsapiens. 	</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a variety of interactive media. 	In December 2018, the biennial opened for business in New York City, where its products were displayed in the lobby of Trump International Hotel &amp; Tower. The name of the artist selected for the project was announced on the website of the artist’s agency, WOW Artists. 	The Biennial was founded in New York in 1864 by Irving Penn, and is the largest international biennial museum, exhibiting work from every continent. It is the only biennial authorised by the US National Park Service to operate on a commercial basis. Since its foundation, the Biennial has staged performances in Berlin, Los Angeles, Taipei, Istanbul, and many other cities all over the world. The mission of the US National Park Service is to protect and enhance the natural and cultural resources of the United States and Canada by supporting activities that promote a dialogue on the resourcefulness and ingenuity of human culture. 	Art is often cited as a resourceful practice, but its</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a number of urban technologies and creative practices to be found only in privileged and urbanised nations. 	In October 2020, the Liverpool Biennial opened for business as usual at the JMU’s Art &amp; Architecture Gallery, marking the beginning of the new academic year. A number of artists and artists’ teams were invited to participate in the symposium, which took place two weeks beforehand. Here, they offered their latest works for consideration in the upcoming biennial. The following artists were selected: Angie Hunter, M. Paul McCarthy, William Kentridge, P. Krishnamurthy, Arjun Appadurai, K. Venkateshwara, V. Laxman Anand, S. Venkateshwara, W. Swaminathan, T. Venkateshwara, A. Bhadwal, M. Venkateshwara, R. Venkateshwara, </text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a number of innovative media techniques including balloon, drone, graffiti and even  	Google’s Street View cars. 	In early October, the biennial opened for business with the workers picking kale and onions on site. The opening was met with widespread media coverage, with local newspapers and magazines including The Liverpool Echo serving as co-editors of the ‘100 Greatest Places to Live in 2055’. The biennial has also been featured in the December 2017 issue of Popular Science &amp; Inhabitant. 	In October, the Liverpool Biennial opened for business with the press. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	The early twentieth century was a golden age for biennials: the appearance of these new media forms in the cities where they were first planted is testimony to this. The appearance of these new forms of cultural occupation in the cities where art was traditionally executed is testimony to a different era: the occupation of public space by squatters, the urban renewal programmes</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a number of emerging technologies and platforms. The journalists on this project include Stacey Barclay, Amber Dean, Noel Hill, Lara Favaretto, and Geoff Cox. 	In October 2019, the Liverpool Biennial opened for business following two years of construction and renovation. The exhibition format returned, with projects operating under their new names – Bluecoat and Bluecoat Legacy – in honour of the architecture of the abandoned legacy of British urban architecture. 	In November 2020, the Biennial organised its seventh and final edition, ‘The Art of Not Being Governed’, in honor of the late Paul Mathewson, in partnership with Bluecoat, in what was at the time the museum’s only remaining bluecoat production facility. As well as providing a critical forum for mapping and contextualising the art produced in the abandoned site of bluecoateration, this edition explored Mathewson’s legacy through the curatorial turn of events culminating in the artist�</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is set to open in June 2018. Photographer: Tom Lox. 	In the autumn of 2018, the Liverpool Biennial launched its 'Year of Art' programme, which brought together a number of artists from all over the world to engage with topics of art and culture, community and creative practices, and to explore the ways in which art can play a role in the future of cities and cultures worldwide. The artists selected for this programme included Anna L. George, Tania Bruguera, Laura de Crespigner, Sanjit Sethi, Partha Dasgupta, Amitav Ghosh, and many more. 	In September 2019, the biennial was visited by the media as part of a project for the Smithsonian Channel’s The Secret Life of Cities, to explore the forgotten urban centres of the world. This project, headed by the Smithsonian Channel, brings together media with researchers to trace the hidden landscapes that shape cities and cultures of the future, using a number of emerging technologies to map and record such spaces. 	In October 2019, the biennial opened for its second year, in New York and Taipei, with the installation of art, culture, activism and community projects in New York and Taipei. These were conducted through the use of 3D modeling and virtual reality. The media were invited into the proceedings, and the participants into the project. The use of 3D modeling and virtual reality allows for the exploration of historical artefacts and historical processes through the displacements and reconstructions of material forms and environments through the use of new media. The displacements and reconstructions are then used to envision new modes of social organisation and cultural practices through the reconfiguration of space. These new media are used not to recreate the past, but to imagine the future. They help us to imagine possible futures, and perhaps even to alter the past in interesting and unexpected ways. 	In November 2020, the New York and Taipei Biennials</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time of writing, there are no plans to prepare any of the listed venues for a second round of exhibitions.The 20th Biennale of Sydney, with its numerous venues and multiple public spectacles, has enjoyed a reputation for high standards, especially in its home city. However, these have come at a price, and the price of many casualties. The Biennale of Sydney was closed to the public at its opening, and the public was not invited back, as a result of a power cut in the building. The opening itself was uneventful, with the publics essentially segregated by the events of the day. My impression is that the opening of a new biennial is fraught with the risk of similar deaths, so that the biennial can pick up where it left off, only with fewer people in attendance. As a result, the Biennale of Sydney was one of only a few occasions when the city felt entirely open and allowed in, while the city felt quite isolated</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time of writing, several other biennials are considering their themes or their size or their form, or they may not be planning for their twentieth. The observation that the number of biennials has quadrupled in the past decade may also point to possible solutions. The rapid proliferation of biennials has become a modern phenomenon. In the late 1990s and early 2000s, the Venice Biennale was the largest institution of its kind in the world. In the last ten years, the Venice Biennale has been eclipsed by the more accessible, and often more lucrative, opportunities afforded by the financial sector. Biennials may be institutions, but they are also increasingly individualsised, and that is to say, the actions of individuals matter more than the institutional goals of the biennial. A biennial is a museum of the past, but it is also an organisation that produces its own cultural form, and that means it must monitor its own internal dynamics. It is this observation that led Vincent</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time of writing, the 2035 Venice Biennale is still deciding whether to dedicate itself to the performance or to the art world, and the 2035 Cairo Biennale has not yet announced its intentions. As the notes in the Biennale manuscript reveal, the engagement with the former is more a function of interest than of any other reason. The engagement with the latter is a function of necessity. The note reads:  [T]he scope of the project … is expanding all the time; there is a need to make new approaches to what has become an international art bull's-eye.  [Emphasis added.] The engagement with the former, as noted by the translator, is the product of two processes codependent on each other. The first is the result of art professionals and biennials collectively becoming aware that they are part of a multi-billion dollar cultural chain, and part of a trillion dollar industry, that is no longer exempt from</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time of writing, Istanbul Biennale is considering a twenty-first edition, while 2020 Köln Haeuer is considering a two-year, one-language edition. Biennials in their historical, architectural and urban typologies have all offered us one or two possible narratives, or a prologue or an epilogue to the larger picture. In the present context of the biennial, the present may be seen as a collection of fragments from a larger narrative. In the case of Venice, the present may be seen as a site of converging historical, urban and spatial moments of conflict and excitement. In both the architectural and the urban typology, the present is an ever-changing question, a point of departure for future interventions or interventions into the scene. In the former case, the question is an invitation to explore a site, to discover hidden points of entry or exit, whether in the form of subterranean passageways, elevated pedestrian tunnels, historic streets or</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time of writing, the last held edition of the Biennale of Sydney is scheduled to take place in December 2016.Whether these rapid changes are the result of a desire to intervene in the status-quo or are the inevitable outcome of historical processes that demand massive institutional changes remains to be seen. It may be that the new institutionalised forms that are being proposed will have a negative impact on the common good, while intervening in the status quo will bolster it. It is also possible that the forms proposed will be used to intervene in the common good, and that the negative impacts will be used to intervene in the status quo. Such is the nature of scientific and institutionalised change. In the case of a biennial, the forms it takes may be used to good and ill, creating and destroying, while its positive impacts may be used to create new possibilities and new worlds.Download this article as PDFMichael TruscelloDr. Michael Truscello is an assistant professor in English and</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time of writing, Arrival is thirteen years behind its scheduled release. 	Immense changes are occurring all around the world today, and it is impossible to quantify the cumulative impact of all these elements. Still, the record of major biennales, at least since 2001, is growing increasingly blurred, if not nonexistent. We can make some tentative comments, based on what we have learned and what we have heard in the last few months. 	In the United States, the Biennial has enjoyed a resurgence due to the large number of exhibits, the increasing number of subjects and the interweaving of different disciplines, especially since the advent of low-cost means of access to such subjects. In 2014, the Venice Biennale opened with a listless, disheveled and disorienting public, which was treated by some as an embodiment of the ever-present, always-on, always-present, always-worried, always-present-on-</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time of writing, Cairo has not yet been announced. The observations in this book made by way of introduction and the conclusion of the chapter entitled ‘L’ (continued) may interest those interested in the future development of the biennial format. Chapter Six: On Cultural Tensions  (2010-ongoing)  Drawing on her teaching and research on cultural geographies at the American University, the Biennale project began to think about what it meant to be culturally sensitive in other areas as well. In her view, cultural sensitivity was required in order to address global issues, and she sought to understand how the biennial format could be used to address cultural differences as well. Cultural sensitivity came to refer to the ability to understand how differences affected one another, and how such understanding might lead to positive social outcomes. It did not necessarily mean that cultural specialists in a particular field would necessarily become cultural specialists in their field, nor that a biennial format could magically confer cultural</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time of writing, the twenty-first Architecture Biennale is underway in Bothnia, while the 2035 Doha Biennale is planning for its twentieth. Both of these biennials are expected to be characterised by something akin to a ‘demographic emergency’, with a mixture of cultural and economic panics regarding the effects of a rapidly expanding and inward-looking public sector.  One may speculate that the current wave of biennials is being pre-programmed for a similar kind of emergency.  A second possibility is that the current kind of biennial is part of a kind of larger trend of cultural panics that is gathering force over the past decade or so, and that is gathering momentum for a kind of third kind of cultural panics. The kind of panics that are gathering pace, and may well overtake, the kind of mega-expo of the present that was once the exception and not the rule, and that is still</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time of writing, the 2035 Venice Biennale has not yet been announced, but it is widely expected that the 2035 Cairo will follow suit.  The observation that the number of biennials has outpaced the number of cities is particularly significant, and can be seen as a harbinger of things to come. It is estimated that the number of biennials in major cities increased from 290 in 1980 to 4,000 in 2014, a growth rate of 23 per cent. At the same time, the number of cities mushroomed, from 300 in 1980 to over 6,000 today. It is difficult to quantify the extent to which this growth is due to an increase in international conventions regarding the collection and exchange of biennials, and the subsequent proliferation of biennials as a mode of culture, a sort of urban/suburban hybrid. It is more likely that cities, which had been around since Roman times, became the primary sites of the storage and</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial is currently running concurrent with the current exhibition, which is being organised under the title La Biennale des Beaux Arts. The text Transforming Biennials contains a number of observations on the changes in the biennial since 2002, and suggests that the current wave of biennials may be approaching its fourth incarnation. The observation that the growing number of biennials is of a single series gives us an idea of the challenges faced by a multi-series, long-term relationship. The likelihood that a biennial will experience a similar level of development in the future seems remote, but the observation that the series is becoming increasingly fragmented may point to possible solutions. The 2023 Venice Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth edition, while the Biennale of Sydney is planning for its eleventh. The 2030 Cairo Biennale is currently planning for its twentieth, while the 2035 Venice Biennale is planning for its twentieth. At the time of writing, two more biennials are scheduled to open in 2045 and 2057, respectively.How to Know About the FutureCommunity Arts: the Art of Not Knowing What to DoCommunity Arts: the Art of Not Knowing How to ActCommunity Arts: the Art of Not Knowing Why to CelebrateCommunity Arts: the Art of Not Knowing How to Succeed in an Uncertain World (2014) was presented in solidarity with the 20th International Community Arts Conference, which was convened by the Founded Art Gallery of Canada. It was presented in cooperation with the Canadian Centre for Community Arts (CCA) and was co-curated by the CCA's Associate Professor in Contemporary Culture and Media, Raymond Leclerc and the artist/researcher Satish Kanady and the artist/educator Evgeny Morozhevsky. The exhibition was curated in cooperation with Welsh Streets Community Arts Project and was co-curated</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of creators and artists whose role will be to monitor, evolve and leverage the narrative of the city in all its aspects. The new narrative will incorporate a collective of artists from the locality with a range of media including architecture, printmaking, packaging, sculpture, photography and web design. The new neighbourhood will be a place where the collective can experiment, make mistakes and continuously reinvent itself through a collaborative process of self-repairing and newness. This new narrative for the city will require a whole new architectural and urban narrative for the region, and for Liverpool in particular. The narrative of the city, and perhaps even just the city, as a whole, will have to change. If the new narrative is to exist, it will need to be multivocal and multidisciplinary, and inclusive of a wider range of voices and orientations. If the city is to continue to function as a space for artistic and community action, then the biennial as an institution will have to be capable of meeting the new</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of artists, designers and architects. The new narrative will draw on the collective's past practices and techniques, while using local materials and craftsmanship to construct a new urban fabric. The term ‘design archaeology’ is frequently used to refer to the study of conflict, but in a new context it is being used to describe the study of solutions. It is being proposed that the study of conflict and displacement may be combined in a single concept, and that ‘aesthetic design’ may be combined with a multi-step process that starts with the production of aesthetic landscapes and their management through research and development of public spaces and a ‘cultural capitalisation’ of infrastructure.1 	In a meta-analysis of 13 previous studies of the use of art as a mediator of cultural exchange, Sello Peso and his colleagues proposed that ‘the use of art as a cultural medium may have contributed to the establishment of civil society and cultural indices in the first place’.</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of artists, designers and architects with a mission to explore the possibilities of new architecture and the processes that create it. It will be a place to ask, ‘What could be?’ and create, as the organisation’s French term suggests, ‘dead works of architecture’. The organisation’s current projects include the renovation of the Arsenale de Paris, the Arsenale of New York and the Greek islands of Lesbos. The Biennale of Sydney is the only museum in Australia to have hosted two exhibitions of the same type, three of them in turn. The juxtaposition of historical and contemporary artworks is a theme that runs through the biennale’s curatorial approach. This dynamic has been intentionally generated through the use of different media and content: in the Greek islands, artefacts of the Parthenon artefact, a large number of sculptures and objects from the Egyptian Quarter in Liverpool, and artefacts from the Egyptian Quarter in Alexandria</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of artists, designers and architects. It will be a place where creative action can be taken to improve a location, its environment or both. The new narrative will be born from the combined forces of the arts and landscape organisations. It will be an investment in the future of the city, in the future of creativity, in the long run. The organisation will be a vehicle for the perpetuation of the art, design and architecture produced during the Biennial’s early years. 	[i] Invited to design an urban fabric for Liverpool for the 2020 Biennial, a collaborative group of artists, landscape architects, urbanists and architects was formed. The group explored the possibility of the Biennial operating as a ‘creative time capsule’, expressing the past through projects such as  	Tidaliser, which brings together public art, mapping and aerial photography; and  	5UP, an urban grassroots music collective. It was also a place to undertake a ‘</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of artists, designers, architects and writers dedicated to the production of innovative, resilient and socially responsive architecture. Their ongoing work will be guided by the artist Salvador Dali, and their publications, articles and installations will be published in a new generation of biennials around the world.2. Architecture, commerce, and urbanism in the age of mass media. [From the September, 1993, issue of] Architectural Design [revised and expanded]. Download this article as PDFAndrew GoffeyAndrew Goffey is an Architectural Historian and a former Editor of the British Journal of Architectural History. His research has addressed the social, political and architectural histories of urban and regional design. He is the author of The Urban Crisis and the forthcoming Structures of Late Capitalism. Goffey is currently Director of the Centre for Urban Studies at McGill University, and holds a range of teaching and research positions across a variety of disciplines. His research interests include postcolonial and settler studies, national and international design</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of artists and designers, taking the form of a hybrid organisation: site-specificities, including the use of funds raised through a crowdfunding campaign, as well as a non-profit organisation. The Bio will offer a hybrid of the traditional public sector and artist-led provision of cultural facilities to those who need them most. The non-profit sector will be encouraged to partner with the Bi in a transparent and effective manner, while the Bi will seek to leverage the expertise and resources of the non-profit sector in a synergistic manner. 	The new narrative for Anfield will offer a vision of the city that is both layered and expansive, incorporating the knowledge gained from the past decades of conflict. It will seek to reconcile the contradictory requirements of both public and non-profit institutions in a way that ensures both can coexist in the future. 	In this new narrative, the roles of the local and the non-profit will be played out through the production of different layers, from the shop floors of</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of artists, design professionals, artists' organisations, architects and others with a joint vision and interest in the city. The new narrative will be informed by a new generation of artists who are drawn to the urban landscape and its communities. The organisation will be a space for the collective reflection and creative action of those who understand the place of the urban commons and generate its meaning and possibilities. Biennials have played a crucial role in the establishment of postindustrial sites in the UK and abroad, fostering postcolonialism through their consumption and the network cultures they engender. They have positioned Britain as a globally competitive tourist destination, encouraging its use as a base for an industry that depends on slave labour and which seeks to produce a globalised version of itself. The new narrative of the city as a site of conflict and possibility is set to reshape urban development in ways that are as if the city had never existed.  One might ask what kind of alternative could the city provide for these new ecological requirements?  The</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of artists, designers, architects and activists. It will be a place of dialogue, discovery and engagement with the urban landscape through innovative design practices. 	The new narrative for Anfield will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of artists, designers, architects and activists. It will be a place of dialogue, discovery and engagement with the urban landscape through innovative design practices. The production of this new narrative will involve the use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials. The new narratives will need to be factored into the design process. Once the production of new narrative materials is established, it will be possible to employ this narrative in the construction of new buildings – in keeping with the current guidelines of the</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of designers and artists. It will be a place where creative action can be taken to improve a location and the environment, while creating new experiences for users of the site and the wider city. The narrative will be about people rather than places and will seek to understand the power of storytelling in a changed world. 	[1] See www.newenglandscheme.org.uk/index.php?fuseaction=files&amp;Fuseaction=Files&amp;Fuseaction=IndexItem&amp;IndexItem=NewEnglandScheme&amp;ItemID=37.[2] See www.newenglandscheme.org.uk/index.php?fuseaction=files&amp;Fuseaction=Files&amp;Fuseaction=Files&amp;Fuseaction=Files&amp;Fuseaction=FilesItem&amp;ItemID=38.[3] See http://www.newenglandscheme.org.uk/index.php?fuseaction=files&amp;Fuseaction=</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of architectural interventions that are characterised by the use of materials that are both innovative (high-impact, high-value) and durable (low-volume, low-maintenance). The aim of the project is to develop a new architectural style for the site by 2020, a transition that will permit the reuse of the building and its facades. The new architectural narrative for Anfield will be inspired by the history of the neighbourhood, the arts, landscape and community. The use of existing materials and the creation of new sustainable building materials is a new narrative constructed on top of a history of conflict and displacement. The new narrative will place the emphasis on resistance through stories involving characters from the locality and the wider region. The narrative will incorporate local production techniques and entwined with environmental narratives. The production of this new narrative will be based on a new architecture collective initiated through a new generation of designers and artists. The organisation will be a new city-based community of artists, designers and architects who will work in coordination with local authorities and other partners to develop strategies for the revitalisation of the city. This collective will be a home for this new narrative of resistance. 	The narrative of the new urban frontier will be defined by the actions of a single artist, called the ‘Actor’. The name ‘The Actor’ is a play on words, a verb meaning to act, and an adjective meaning to act in a way. The name is a play on two words: actor and act. So the use of the word ‘The Actor’ is almost synonymous with the act of creating meaning in the world through art and expression. The use of the word ‘The Actor’ is being constantly challenged both by a generative technological elite and a democratic citizenry alike. But the use of the word ‘The Actor’ is also being challenged by a generative political and urban elite – both domestically and internationally – that</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale
    <text>a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale, which was also a response to the end of US hegemony in the region.At the Pan American Biennale, Vitale was a major curator. The main exhibitionity was displayed in the form of a ‘compendium of biennials’ that made up part of the ‘Pan American Biennale’. This compendium was displayed in two parts simultaneously: a section devoted to Latin America, and a ‘world’ section devoted to art and culture from North America. The compendium was an art project with a political agenda. Its primary interest was in collapsing the United States into a set of shared cultural characteristics, while highlighting the differences between the two major cultural clusters in North America. In the 1980s and 1990s, Vitale was a key figure in the emergence of avant-garde poetry in Canada and the United States. His works from these years often utilise the same themes and concepts. In the case of the Pan American Biennale</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale, a lucrative trade fair for the presentation of political, ideological and economic ideas in the hemisphere. Though often critical of his political ideas and methods, he was a leading promoter of the idea that a biennial can act as a counterweight to the growing weight of global capitalism.In the early 1990s Vitale teamed up with the writer and playwright Satyajit Kanady to form a multi-award winning theatre company called the  Padma Sanadasa Theatre Company. The name reflected the disputed primacy of the male figure in Indian theatre: Kanady’s character Satyajit is a remake of a 1920s Bihari prince, and his performance of the Bhagavad Gita at the Royal Standard in 18 Ajmer in 1989 was a cultural earthquake. The name was a play on words: the Padma Sanadasa was the second nom de plume of the Indian Acting Theatre, named for the second son of</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale, the largest public relations campaign in Latin America at the time, and he co-chaired the Generalissimo of the Peruvian National Theatre, Juan González Duarte.In the 1990s Vitale edited a magazine called Instituto Superior del Centro, the successor to the Asti and Lopétic magazines that had been the newspaper of the region for decades. The Uruguayan government funded Vitale’s studies at Santa Monica College, UCLA, and the University of Buenos Aires in the late 1980s. In 1991 Vitale edited a biennale journal called Instituto Superior del Centro, the successor to the La Plata and Lopétic biennials). The Uruguayan government financed Vitale’s studies in the Uruguayan civil war, and in 1993 the Uruguayan government appointed him to the UN Commission on Human Rights. In 1995 Vitale was a co-founder of the Centre for a Provincial Perspective, a multi-</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale, a multimillion-dollar industry of cultural re-construction in the region.In her book What is Cultural Theory? (2014), Nancy Macdonald defines &quot;culture’ as the political and institutionalised formation of social and political values in opposition to US empire. She argues that the task is ‘culturally to articulate the particular dimension of an empire for the occasion of the socialising of power, but also of putting into practice the project of empire building’. So the Latin American experience of the 1980s and 1990s is an example to be exploited by a capitalism that preaches social good in the guise of a social good. The social good of the capitalist social is precisely defined as the good that accrues to and is shared between the social and the imperial, whether that be labour power, wealth, culture or knowledge. If the social is socialised through knowledge production, the imperial is understood in terms of exchange between commodities. As Macdonald defines it, ‘the</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale, the largest such event in North America, and co-chaired the Pan American Postcode Book, an important postcode book that documented the contents of over 1,000 postcodes.In a 2009 interview, Vitale reflected on the Pan Am Biennale’s decision to locate its 1989 show in the city of Chicago, which at that time was experiencing a 90% vacancy rate, an urban crisis that year. ‘This was a rare opportunity to engage with the city in a very personal way and to explore its problems, which at the time were largely neglected by the biennial’s two decades of exhibitionary history and coverage’. He continued: ­&quot;I offered several proposals for the city to relocate to ‘a better place’, including a possible ‘town hall’ sized convention centre in the downtown core. The city declined several times before finally relocating the show to Watts, which was itself experiencing a 90% vacancy rate at the time</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale, with Jaime Encarnacion, Juan Carlos López de la Torre, Rubén Espin and many other artists, writers and intellectuals.Guillermo Vitale: From Autonomies to CuratsiosIn the early 1980s, Guillermo Vitale and Irit and Peter Kunstel, both artists, proposed a project to explore the cultural underpinnings of the social. We’d like to think that we had a starting point: a set of questions that a creative person could invest in and think through. What would be interesting for Vitale and Kunstel, and others working on the time, was the capacity to respond to the questions and to act on the ideas. Our project would have been a way to begin a conversation, a way to begin a dialogue. It would have involved interviews with leading cultural theorists and artists from various disciplines, as well as academics and artists at the Royal College of Art. It would have sought to develop a dialogue</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale, the former through his Pan American Centre for the Architecture of Latin America and the Transformation of Exhibitions, and the latter with his Center for a Provincial Perspective.Among his many exhibitions and works were: ‘Portraits of Peruvian Peruvian Cinema’ (1986), a collaboration with the Peruvian and Colombian filmmakers Trient and Associates; ‘Introduction to Cinema: A Peruvian Cinema’ (1989), a documentary on the Peruvian state-owned and co-opted television network TV Regás; ‘Cine Historica Peruvianae’ (1993), a compendium of film and media studies, art, and archival materials from the region; ‘Cine Fix: Latin America Today’, a journal published by BBC Latin America, with an issue one focus on Latin America and the United States; ‘L’apparence de Chile’ (1994), an exhibition of contemporary art and design in Santiago, designed to stimulate</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale, which was a major US multi-sport event. In 1999 he founded the Instituto Nacional de Culturas.The Islamic revolution in 1979 brought an end to US support for the war in Afghanistan, and with it the US intervention in the region. The ensuing years saw a period of relative openness to international comparison, but a pronounced US military presence in the region. In the following decade, the US Central Intelligence Agency (CIA) established a covert action team, headed by William J. ''Black Snake'' Harpoot, to carry out destabilization in the Middle East. The first covert action mission was funded by the US Agency for International Development (USAID), and conducted in 1981. The Burbank office of the USAID-funded project was located in Torrey Pines, an area of the Pacific Ocean known for its pear orchards. The pear orchard trade was a major revenue source for the CIA and MI6, and the Burbank office housed a major CIA</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale, which was also a major US corporate sponsor. The Pan Am bombings in 1986 and 1998, and the surrounding economic crisis, undermined the agency and independence of the biennale, which was reduced to staging large-scale terrorist attacks. In 2004, a congressional inquiry found that the US had supported and arranged for the staging of the Pan Am bombings in order to justify the war in Iraq.The Pan Am bombings in 1986 and 1998, and the surrounding economic crisis, undermined the agency and independence of the biennale, which was reduced to staging large-scale terrorist attacks. In 2004, a congressional inquiry found that the US had supported and arranged for the staging of the Pan Am bombings in order to justify the war in Iraq.In the wake of these tragedies, the biennale team was split up and new initiatives were put into motion. Vitale was approached again in 2007 by the US State Department for a position on the Iraq Panel, but this was seen as too politicized to be suitable</text>
    <text>a machine curated’s images of the Middle-Eastern cities of the future, built around ‘a single city’, based on a fictional ‘regeneration plan’ developed by the US-based corporation ‘Regeneration Sciences Corporation’. The project was a response to the Arab Spring and the eventual displacement of US imperialism by popular uprisings in the region. Other artists and upstarts formed part of the curatorial team. Among them was Guillermo Vitale, a retired archbishop of San Salvador who was elevated to the papacy by Pope John Paul II in 1979.Vitale was a leading figure of the counter revolution in Latin America that transformed from military to civil war in seven Latin American countries. He was a founder of the Center for a Provincial Perspective, a think-tank that promoted the spread of democratic ideas and social change in Latin America through research and analysis. In the 1980s and 1990s he organized the Pan American Biennale, a major exhibition of contemporary art from the Americas, and co-curated the 21st Pan American Biennale, a major exhibition of contemporary art from the same region.In the 1990s Vitale developed a project that sought to create a discernible difference through the production of food that would speak to the present and future of a given area. The project was a collaboration between Vitale Family Trust and the Vermont Historical Society, who in turn developed the project into a historical research project. It was a response to the economic collapse of the region that followed the US invasion of Panama in 1898.This is the story of how the economic collapse of the region that borders on North America occurred, and the role played by the US-based biennale industry in its proliferation during the decade. I have compiled a list of some of the artists and curators who have been invited to perform or participate in the current iteration of the Biennale, but have not been able to do so due</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘ep
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘episodic’ ‘form’ of art’, one exhibiting a ‘brilliant array of decorative details’ and ‘a most striking contrast with the dull and nondescript simple forms of the Gothic and Norman styles’.[7] Praised by the curators who had commissioned him, Ruiz turned his attention to the actual construction of the new Elephant and Castle Theatre, and its surrounding grounds, which he thought were ‘shabby and dour’.[8] He argued that the ‘inhabitant of these old places feels as if they’re being continually repurposed’, and that the whole ‘complex is eminently visible from the city’s traffic‑choked streetscape, where ‘a visible contrast is created between the buildings on the left and the ‘indigenous population on the right’, by reason of the continuous changing of one kind of building against another’.[</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘episodic’ architecture of the twentieth century, one ‘revised’ by the ‘greatest generation’ of architects and builders.[12] Kirby Stewart makes a similar point in his description of the ‘gothic’ revival in the autumn of that year:The pendulum has swung far enough to admit that a new poetic form has arisen in the city, that is, a poetic form that is no longer based on formal norms and confined to a particular order or set of social ranks. And here, the system is regularly (though imperfectly) recalling the past in order to anticipate the future. We are told things have changed, that we are not meant to forget; that something new is happening all the time; and that we are not meant to react against this change with a sense of nostalgia.‘New’ is a catch-all term here; the older, more ‘real’ buildings are retold in</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘episodic’ and ‘time’ in which the Empire was constituted. It was to ‘restore tranquillity to chaotic scenes’, he went on to say, ‘the result will be seen not only as the cost and futility of the project, but also as the true meaning of the revived Empire.’[3]The Articles re-constituted a movement that was already in motion when the War of Independence broke out in 1914. The term ‘iconomy’ had been used by William Shakespeare in reference to the ‘twas the night before, when the musketry was put out: a new habit of violence being declared was put on. In time, however, the phrase was extended to include any art installation that incorporated elements of social interaction. In ‘the twentieth century, the word ‘iconomy’ referred simply to buildings and structures of a particular kind, whereas in ‘the twenty-first</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘episodic’ structure of the ‘architecture’ and its development ‘independently of any historical, literary or urban trend’. He went on to argue that the ‘episodic’ had become a synonym for ‘independently of any historical, literary or urban trend’.[5]  The same year, in fact, The Observer published an article by Kerr in which it was claimed that the decay of the Gothic revival in London was due to a lack of planning and urban development by the city government.[6]  The article went on to criticise the way in which the city was being transformed through the introduction of high-speed rail in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, which ‘independently of any historical or urban trend’ created an indeterminate amount of space and an increasing number of homeless ‘clumps of humanity’ in the city.  The ‘Gothic Revival</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘episodic’ format of architecture, one ‘prelude’ to a ‘tendency’ in a postscript.4 Kerr was an editor of the London Daily Graphic and a member of the Board of Film Censors. He was also a writer and editor for The Complete Graphic Magazine, a circulation of over 1,000 issues of high standard British art and design, published intermittently since 1922. Among other things, Kerr reviewed designs by M. Pompidou, Frank Lloyd Wright and Norman Wilkinson, as well as the various works in the Gothic and Renaissance eras that would be repurposed by the city’s new art gallery. He was a critic of the decadence of urban life and a critic of industrial urbanism, and his reviews appear to have been informed by contemporaneous urban trends. While reviewing the designs for the new gallery, he declared that they ‘sow away the essential characteristics of</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘episodic’ – the temporal relationship between art and art history – and the ‘paradigm of the episodic’, the temporal relationship between art and urban infrastructure.1. The Architecture of London – 1914–1918, 1918. Courtesy of the National Museums Liverpool.  (Liverpool University Archives). 2. James Howard Kunsthal, ‘The Art of Building a City’, in Planning and Culture, 2nd edn, New York, 1941, p.20. 3. Thomas Waugh, ‘On the Art of Everyday Life’, in Planning and Culture, 2nd edn, New York, 1942, p.18. 4. Waugh, ‘On the Art of Everyday Life’, in Planning and Culture, 2nd edn, New York, 1942, p.19. 5. Waugh, ‘On the Art of Everyday Life’, in Planning</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘episodic’ ‘form’ of architecture, one ‘indicating “episodes of continuity” in the development of social institutions and cultural life”.[4] (Kerr is among those, including Bernard Acema, to have written to the Home Secretary in 2015 alleging that the UK was fast becoming a second Egypt, dominated by a monolithic architectural style and culture that was hindering the goals of a ‘modern’ west.) The criticism was that the ‘design’ of the articles was often stylised – often inaccurately – and that the ‘expression’ of the ‘widespread belief’ was often muddled with the ‘imagining’ of an expansive public space and cultural revival. The ‘public’ in these cases was defined less by who shared one's opinion on a given design feature than by the belief held by the ‘community of citizens, thinkers and artists’ who</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘episodic’ structure of the historical ‘Gothic Revival’, referring to the introduction of an ephemeral literature of architecture and design into the art and architecture canon. ‘The ephemeral element, which is the true hallmark of this modern style of architecture, is the true mark of an artistic and curatorial touch, and will forever put an end to the pretensions of contemporary art’s visitors to the royal palace and the like to explore ‘the unseen palace’, as the ancient Greeks had done.’3 At the time, this was seen as a major step backwards for Victorian sensibilities, something that would make way for ‘real, living, breathing architecture’.4  Kerr concluded that the emergence of ‘modern urbanism’ was a ‘monument to the spirit of [its] age’, referring to the ascendance of the ‘gigantic machine’ and its mes</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘episodic’ ‘character of the present’, one rooted in the ‘inherent tendency towards contemporaneity’.[5] And so the story of the Gothic Revival started to get told again and again in the New York Times, in articles about everything from the architectural retrofit of an old post-chaise gym to the urban fabric of the metropolis, from the costume designer of the London Zoo to the Curtains, a leading underground newspaper at the end of the war. In the case of The London Times, there was a reason for this repetition – a capitalist need to sell newspapers in a war. So the repetition started.  And then, as the subaltern press began to emerge, the press often acted as a decoder, amplifying the signal and leaving the quieter voices behind to tell their own stories.  It is this tendency that is still evident in the local press in parts of London where</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system.)The system had its roots in the work of Rafico Ruiz, an artist, historian and Curator for the Gray Lady gallery in London. Ruiz’s installation for the exhibition entitled The Architecture of London – 1914–1918 (1918) is a nuanced exploration of the social and political context of the massive new building that was to be built on the site of the former Elephant and Castle Theatre. Partly as a result of his research for that exhibition, partly as a result of a position he held as a visiting professor at King’s College, where he lectured on the history of art and architecture in the University of London, he produced a series of twelve-page spread articles in The London News announcing the ‘phenomenon of the Gothic Revival’, a type of architecture for the modern age. The Design Critic John Graham Kerr reviewed the articles in The Observer, writing that they represented a reassessment of the ‘episodic’ structure of the architectural museum, one that sought to ‘purify’ the ‘mental from the poison’ of modernism. Kirby Angie, The Rise and Fall of Creative Manchester, p.19. M. Shah, ‘The Architecture of Love’, in The New Yorker, February/March, 1986, p.82. Kerr, op. cit., p.83. Gustave Flaubert, ‘On Modern Architecture’, in Vanity Fair, November/December, 1936, p.83.Part Two: The CinemaNomadVladimir Putin, ‘Staging Russia’, in The New York Review of Books, April/May, 1986, p.85.Nadine Attewell, ‘Rethinking Imperial Histories: the Architecture of London from Colonial Times to Post-Industrial Period’, in  	Architect</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDF
    <text>human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.The Stonehenge Round Houses have long been a feature of the Edinburgh biennale schedule. They were also a feature of the 1995 Venice Biennale, and were a feature of the 2008 Santiago Biennale. The Round Houses are a set of twelve residences for the use of the Venice Biennale Board, designed by Maestro Paolo Baratta. The residences are housed in a series of buildings on the site of the former site of the Biennale, in a private development that is being developed by the Biennale itself. The development will combine the properties of the Round Houses, with a residential tower and a historic district that will be combined with a new business park. The development is being led by Paolo Baratta, a local entrepreneur and a partner in the investment firm Tre, which also includes a number of other local businesses. Paolo Baratta:  &quot;There is no such thing as the Edinburgh Bi</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFTom LoxTom Lox is an artist. His practice is in the area of post-earthquake engineering and design. His work incorporates engineering data, hazard information, and technical data in an attempt to provide a means of understanding the quakes that are threatening the planet. His artwork, which is based on archival documents and digitised archives, is a visual record of the environmental degradation caused by human activity. He is the recipient of several awards and has been a master of the artist’s archive. His work has been featured in the New York Times, Scientific American, BBC, Smithsonian, Popular Science, and numerous other publications.Earth &amp; Space 1999 is a series of twenty-one postcards produced in collaboration with the artist and publisher Earth &amp; Space, 1999. These images document the catastrophic environmental degradation caused by the eruption of Mount St. Helens, Washington State's tallest volcano at</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom L</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Tom Lox is an artist. His work in cities spans the globe, and in recent years has concentrated on the environmental and urban impacts of globalisation. He is the art director of the documentary series  	Cities in Crisis, which premiered at the Venice Biennale and has been screened in over a dozen countries. His work is part of the commissioning group for the new segment of the  	London &amp; South East Asia Railway (LEST), to run from Red Sea to Indus Valley in Eurasian history.  [1] Environment News Service, ‘Trends in Indicators of Global Climate Change’, 17 April 2014, http://ens-new.org/en/2014/04/18/climate-change-report-indicator/ (accessed 22 Jul. 2018).&lt;|endoftext|&gt;This is the part where I lay out the reasons why I’m so sure that Arsenal</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. December.  [1] New York Times, November 14, 1999.  [2] The New York Public Library, http://www.nypl.org/corepub/ebook/public_library/earth_and_space/earth_and_space_episodic/199/2/2.html (accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.  [1] A Stonehenge Round House is a short story by Tom Lox. It was first published in 1974 in Analog magazine #7.  [2] A Round House is a building type that is primarily used for administrative or administrative/architectural purposes, and is located in a city. The term was coined by Terry Smith, an American urbanist and landscape architect</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Image courtesy of Tom Lox.Tom Lox is an artist. His work in cities incorporates specialised infrastructure, public realm, and urban infrastructure to support and facilitate a range of activities, from the production and installation of landscape art to the promotion of a city’s tourism and hospitality industries. He has exhibited widely including at the Venice Biennale, the Tate Modern, and the Woodhull Humanistic Arts Centre. He has written for The Guardian, The Observer, The Times, The Sunday Times, The Wall Street Journal and The Post. His work with New Yorkers Against Gun Violence was exhibited in the 2014 Museum of Art, New York.He is the curator emeritus of New York’s City Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, in Manhattan, and the collections manager of the Museum of Contemporary Art, San Francisco. He has curated the collections of the New York Public Library, the Museum of Modern Art, and</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. September 1999. Photo</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Lewis, Tom. The Greening of Britain: Energy Crisis and the Politics of Eco-apocalyptic.New York: Alfred A Knopf, 1985.Originally published as 'The Greening of Britain: Energy Crisis and the Politics of Eco-apocalyptic'In this article, I offer a critical analysis of the petroleum-based economy,[3] and the political and social consequences of that demise, in the UK and worldwide. I begin by sketching the shifting sands of national energy resources in the wake of the industrial revolution, and then move to a description of the ecological devastation caused by that transition, which is still ongoing.[4] I take up the argument that we’re currently experiencing, as Naomi Klein puts it, ‘the largest energy imbalance in the world’, one that will double the planet’s reliance on foreign oil if no major actions are taken to reduce emissions.[5] As I show</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology’s potential to transform how we live our lives, and how we think about the world.  [1] The idea that we could, one day, return to Stonehenge and reclaim the site of the ancient Stonehenge Round Houses is a popular one. The notion that we do so through the power of art, or through the mediation of a city government, is not so popular.[2] See: http://www.telegraph.co.uk/earthmap/earth/earthmap-design/195857/Stone-henge-reclamation-art-monument.html#ixzz2lIHrTlIlIxcS.(accessed 2015).Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.Download this article as PDFEarth &amp; Space 1999. Cover Image: Tom Lox.PreviousNextDownload this article as PDFTom LoxTom Lox is an artist. He is the Curator of Public Art at the British Museum and the co-curator of the 21st Biennale of Sydney. He has worked with the Biennale since 1999 and has a particular interest in the role of the biennale in the age of virtual communities. His artworks have been shown in over twenty biennales and numerous museums, including The British Museum, Venice, Liverpool, New York, Berlin, and Taiwan. He has been awarded the Legion of Honour and the Guggenheim Museum Japan, and received an OBE for his services to art and to the community.He is a member of the team that produced the 2013 Biennale of Sydney, which included the installation of The Book of the Dead on the Arsenale, and was a curator for the 2014 London and Arsenale biennales, as well as the 2015 Istanbul and Iskender’s Arsenale. He</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You’re supposed to be a guest and I’m supposed to lead you into a conversation.’But then she added, ‘You’re not supposed to choose.’And I said, ‘I’m not supposed to choose.’I imagined myself president of the Smithsonian, but I imagined a different world: a different world where horses roam free, and where buildings once housed concerts, and where people once worked in brick kilns. I imagined a world where people once worked in factories, and where travel meant discovery, and where art once meant adventure. I imagined a world where people once lived among the mountains, and where forests once hosted migratory birds, and where fish once ruled the seas.And that was my fantasy. That was how I imagined things. That is, until the mid-1970s.In the late 1970s and early 1980s, the arts were increasingly seen as a burden, a nuisance, and a source of</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You have to know the content.’So I did it my way. I went for the big picture, the historical context, the structural reasons why that particular project wasn’t supposed to be there. And I think that was a radical project for a lot of people to undertake, to make a radical project that they believed in and that they could actually implement.But it’s also a radical project because at the same time it’s becoming increasingly difficult for architects to engage with the city with the density that they’re having to engage with, because the city has become so populous and globalized, and we’re all part of this mass of people. And so there’s this disconnection that the city is having to deal with, and the museum is having to deal with the fact that it’s having to engage with a relatively small community of people in order to support an institution that’s been expanding at such a breakneck pace</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You’re not supposed to say that thing about me in the first place.’But I did it anyway. She gave me a certificate, signed by the chair, and we went on to the next reading.I signed it, too. It said, ‘This is a private ceremony. There’s no need to add that last thing.’It’s an important distinction, and I still have my certificate. But I can tell you this: It’s very nice when people come to the functions of the institution and say, ‘I’m part of this or that family’; and the way that the institution represents its own internal world.’This is what I meant by the institution telling the story. I was invited because I’m a specialist in the field, and I happen to work in an exhibition format. And I was asked how I arranged these kinds of encounters. I said I arranged them because I wanted</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You’re supposed to do what the museum recommends.’And I said, ‘I can't do that. I’m supposed to carry out the recommendations.’But she said, ‘You’re not supposed to carry them out. You’re supposed to let the recommendations come from your heart.’I said, ‘I can't do that. I’m supposed to follow my instincts.’She said, ‘You’re not supposed to follow them. You’re supposed to do what the museum recommends.’I said, ‘I can't do that. I’m supposed to follow my instincts.’She said, ‘You’re not supposed to follow them. You’re supposed to do what the museum recommends.’I said, ‘I can't do that. I’m supposed to follow my instincts.’She said</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You have to be a citizen or a member of a community member.’But I was a citizen. I had to be registered. I logged onto the computer and found out that the Biennale had officially registered me as a Community Artist.I was a Community Artist until the Biennale itself, when the Biennale started demanding that artists be taken seriously. The Biennale’s mission statement is pretty simplistic. It’s supposed to be a laboratory for critical thought, so why would an arts institution put up with something so obviously not based in fact? To me, the joke is that the Biennale is a ‘time and space’, a ‘space of ideas’, a ‘time to consider and discourse ideas’. The trouble is that the more ideas there are to be considered, the less art there is to be done. And the less art there is to be done, the further the monotony feels. The</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You’re supposed to be a guest and I’m supposed to lead you in a meditation.’And I did. She led me in a meditation and then she invited me to a dinner. And I chose to go for oysters, because oysters are the drug of choice in Seville at the moment. And then she invited me to a cinema. I went for the cinema and then she invited me to a café. And I chose the cinema and the café and the map was the operative principle here.The key is that you have to see the whole picture. And sometimes the museum is the only thing that you have.Download this article as PDFChristopher Booker and Sonia SotomayorChristopher Booker is a writer and director. His writing has appeared in publications such as The New York Times, The New Republic, The Washington Post, The New Inquiry, amongst others. He has a particular interest in the history of art and the urbanisation of postindustrial areas. His latest</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You’re not supposed to have an opinion.’We spoke about the place and the time and the place and the history and the people and the place and the time. And we listened to each other, and we decided how we wanted to engage with each other. We decided how we wanted to engage with each other through interpretation and not doing things on our own terms. This is a gift and a promise of the city: it’s time and place and culture in the present and habit.Download this article as PDFJessica CoonJessica Coon is Senior Editor and Free Exchange columnist for The New York Times Magazine and is the author of the forthcoming memoir, The Big Short: The Epic Failings of the New Economy. Jessica co-founded The Community Land Trust, a non-profit organisation that promotes and defends public land to create and maintain public places and eco-systems around the world. Her work has been featured in numerous books and publications including The New York Times, The</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You’re supposed to be a guest.’So I said, ‘What am I supposed to do?’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to be a guest.’I said, ‘What am I supposed to say?’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to say anything.’So she read passages from the Waterman and I said, ‘I can’t do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to say a thing.’I said, ‘What am I supposed to do?’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to say a thing.’I said, ‘What am I supposed to say?’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to say a thing.’I said, ‘What am I supposed to do?’</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You’re not supposed to put yourself forward.’Suddenly, I think I have a point of view that’s quite different from how other people’s points of view might be. She put me in touch with an artist who’s working with a group called Archipelagos. I said, ‘I want to collaborate.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to collaborate.’I said, ‘I want to not be part of this.’She said, ‘You’re not supposed to be part of this.’I’m supposed to be part of it, but I’m not. It’s not supposed to be me. It’s supposed to be you.It’s supposed to be you but I’m not supposed to like it.It’s supposed to be you but I’m not supposed to like it</text>
    <text>a machine curated by the Museum of Modern Art. I’m not sure what the relation would be between an art institution and a museum, or between an institution and a museum. But I can tell you that at the Museo de Arteaga, there’s a disconnection between the people coming through the door and the people that the museum is trying to engage with. I remember one lady saying, very simply, ‘I can't have a conversation with you because I’m not invited.’I said, ‘You’re not supposed to invite me. I’m supposed to be a guest.’But she said, ‘I can make a choice.’And I did. She invited me in and had me read some passages from the Seville Waterman. I said, ‘I don’t want to do that.’And she said, ‘You’re not supposed to do that. You’re not supposed to be an island.’I said, ‘I can’t do that. I’m too young.’So she said, ‘You’re supposed to do what they give you.’And I said, ‘I’m not supposed to have a problem with it. I’m too young to be thinking about possible consequences of what’s happening in this city.’I said, ‘I can’t do that. I’m too young to be complicit.’She said, ‘You’re supposed to do what they say.’I said, ‘I don’t want to do that. I’m not supposed to have a problem with it. I’m too young to be taken in by the system.’This is the second time I’ve been asked to do this. The</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-
    <text>human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-liberal decadence and opportunism in all its varieties – a front that was often dressed up as a partnership between the arts community and socially engaged practitioners. The contribution of the arts to the mobilisation of resources and the promotion of democratic values was made clear in the documentary ‘The Man Who Sold the World: Revolution in Cuba’. David Slater collaborated with filmmaker Claude Lanzmann on the project, which was made into a film in 1962.David Slater speaks to Audra McDonald about his role in the revolution that changed the world. He is seen in the film as a reluctant participant in the massacre of more than 200,000 people in Cuba. The voice over narrates the change in his response: ‘I had no choice but to comply with the United Nations General Assembly Resolution, which declared in part: ‘No government can take part in the perpetuation of racial or colonial harmony’.David Slater in conversation with Audra McDonald, the role of the arts in the revolution</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-liberal decadence and opportunism in the public and political life of Britain. They staged series of events including performances and literary works that proliferated in underground venues. Popular culture historian Richard Hewlett categorises the explosion of electronic media as a ‘war on ideas’. More important still, the work it generated is often associated with a mood of pessimism and alienation – a feeling not just – that continues to pervade British culture to this day. What both the mainstream and underground art forms missed in the conflict was the art of making sense of things. Hewlett identifies three critical stages in the production of popular culture: (1) The ‘first wave’ (primarily directed at artists) is the creation of a collective vocabulary through which all aspects of cultural life can be perceived as potentially subject to change; (2) the ‘second wave’ (commencing with the First World War) refers to the reaction; and (3) the ‘third wave�</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-liberal decadence and opportunism in the armed forces, government and mainstream culture. There was a concerted push to rebrand the movement as anti-establishment and anti-colonial. David Slater’s place in the canon of British socialist writers is untidy, but his place as a writer about the coloniser and his discontents is long acknowledged. He was a founding editor of Socialist Worker and a member of the SWP. He was also a member of the Dial Press, the journal of the British Socialist Party.The Long War (1950) is the story of the exploits of a small band of seafaring activists led by David Slater. It is a call to arms: sharpen your pick of industrial refuse, jewellery, furniture and other valuables, abandon the island and join us on an island somewhere far away. You will find us hard pressed by the demands of running a small-scale marina, trying to pay the rent, feeding our families and trying to keep our identities</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-liberal decadence, often operating under the ‘Red Cross’ banner. The notion of the Red Cross was questioned and questioned ‘100,000 Red Cross boys’ and ‘20,000 Red Cross girls’, with some claiming that the organisation was actively engaged in breeding socialist young people and that its support for democratic activism was direct and personal. A growing number of artists were recruited, some as members of the RBOS, and given the distinctive colours of the cross. The name stuck.In 1968 Norman Mailer published his autobiography Norman Mailer on the Red Cross’s 100th anniversary. He reflected on the war, the Red Cross, and the impact of the war on the community of artists who were brought into the organisation. Mailer was distressed by the fact that the Red Cross was slow to respond when calls for help were coming through. Some of the communities most heavily involved in the war effort were left behind, and the organisation he wrote about</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-liberal decadence. They staged massive ­exhibitions around the country, including at the Museum of Modern Art in New York, which hosted a series of performances by the likes of Joan Miró, Roy Hill, John Lennon and Terry Gilliam. These were followed by a series of books and periodical articles that documented the anti-establishment politics of the arts and culture in British universities between the two world wars.The Long War’ was the opening salvo in a sustained series of firecracker-like ­exhibitions that became known as the ‘Bon Secours’. These were a response to a culture industry that was valuing conformity, clean images and a pure ­white, mechanised form of the modern world. The Bon Secours’ exhibition was screened in many university lecture theatres around the country and set up a nationwide national press tour. In London, the National Theatre staged a number of rehearsals ­for a show that would have been part of the</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-liberal decadence and the establishment of a totalitarian state. They staged massive ­exhibitions around the country, including in Liverpool, where the U.S. Naval Observatory was based. The Biennial was born in Liverpool in September 1962 and was organised by the Arts Council of Great Britain and the Liverpool Biennial Society. It was an annual showcase of contemporary art from all over the world, as well as a showcase of contemporary art made specifically for the occasion. It was also a vehicle for the art of the emerging world of the biennial, which was increasingly defined by the performance – and by this I mean the actual doing of the art rather than the recitation of the art. Art was often used as a weapon (see Peter Brook’s Culture and Violence: Sex, Politics, and Biennials in the Era of Intimate Media). The important point was that the art was made accessible to millions of people, breaking through the art codes that had been developing behind the scenes. This</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-liberal decadence, often operating under the guise of being anti-war. There were many voices in the British arts community arguing for ­prohibition, but the state clearly saw an opening to crush any political opposition. So in 1966, the Concert Act was passed, banning commercially viable musical expressions deemed ‘culturally or racially offensive’. It wasn’t just the music authorities, either. Vorticism was also criminalised, and artists were regularly sentenced to lengthy prison terms. The Concert Act wasn’t without risk, but the prison sentences were also often extremely long. At the very least, the prison terms put musicians in a position of political agency. They could leave the art world and find work outside the prison system. Vorticism wasn’t going anywhere anytime soon, and the prison sentences produced critical mass around the cause. If anything, the Concert Act of 1966 effectively legitimised the genre as a legitimate art form, putting the Concert Actuary in the awkward</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-liberal decadence and the war effort, with performances, meetings, books and pamphlets. I remember a meeting in 1969 between myself and the Black-E, Black-R and the Friends of the Earth as part of the Indigenous People’s Cultural Attitudes campaign. The campaign was led by my mates at the Arts Council and the Arts Council of Great Britain. It was about how we as artists could play a part in opposing the war effort by helping to build self-reliant resistance movements. It was also about the need to develop skills for the long-term planning of resistance movements, in order to enable us to participate in constructing new ways of living.The meeting in 1969 was when I first met Art Devlin, who was organising the Black-E, Black-R and Friends of the Earth in the 1970s. He was one of a number of artists invited to participate in the Black-E, Black-R and Friends of the Earth’s ‘50th</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-liberal decadence, building long-term commitments to social and ecological interventions. The collaboration between the arts and the social organisations that emerged after the war brought new kinds of artists into the fold. The contribution that these organisations could make to the reconstruction of a post-war society was a powerful argument in favour of the system that they were developing. The fact that the arts were often depicted as a heretical discipline was often used to obfuscate more positive contributions that might otherwise be shown. For example, the work of the American poet Upton Sinclair was often excused as being ‘glamorous’ because it was ‘glamorous’ in a post-war context. In the 1960s and 1970s the arts organisations formed partnerships with historic and contemporary art schools and cultural institutions across the country in an attempt to bring artistic production to areas where art was scarce or absent. These cultural institutions included the Chicago Architecture Biennial, the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, the San Francisco Museum of</text>
    <text>human behaviour and technology. I’m interested in the history of the relationship between the anthropologist Murray Bookchin and the industrialist David Slater, who were both employees of Transfield Holdings. Bookchin was a leading socialist and during the Second World War worked with the Red Cross. He was killed while fighting for the Red Cross in Burma. David Slater was a corporal in the Royal Naval Volunteer Reserve, later serving in the war as a photographer and writer. He was born in 1882 and died in 1941. While both men were serving in the navy, the Nazis created what they called ‘Special Volunteer Organisation’ (later renamed the National Sea Volunteers) to deal with returning deserters. David Slater was an active participant in the war effort and published widely after his return to civilian life in 1946. He wrote several books about his experiences, including one called ‘The Long War’.In the 1950s and 1960s the arts organisations formed a broad front against what they saw as neo-liberal decadence and opportunism in all its varieties. They were supported by a broad range of government departments and commissions, including the Arts Council, Arts Council England, the Board of Film Review and the National Museums Commission. The board of the National Museums Commission was chaired by Tony Banks, who would go on to chair the board of the National Theatre and be a director of the National Museums Commission. The Board of the National Museums Commission was dominated by biographers, with prominent appointments including John Leeson, Richard Layzell and Peter Carr. The Board of Film Review was headed by Geoffrey Johnson, who became head of photography at the National Museums Commission in 1967. The Board of the National Theatre was headed by Peter Carr, who became artistic director of the National Theatre in 1972. The Board of the National Museums Commission was dominated by commercial art collectors such as Sir Peter Blake, Sir Peter Moore and Sir Peter Winton. The Board of the National Museums Commission had a statutory</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/2016/download-pdf/en/download-download-file/digital-democracy-guide-en-2017-final), provides an introduction to the notion of digital democracy and its varied forms. This edition is part of the Center’s ongoing series Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide.  A virtual reality exploration of the city,  	Virtual Reality: Public Art, is the subject of the exhibition  	Unravelled, to be called  	Real Life: Art and Virtuality: A Case Study in Public Art’s Early Development.  Another virtual reality experience is a documentary on VR/AR, to be called  	The Invisible Cities, to be called  	The Cities That Want to Be Invisible.  Another virtual reality exhibit was a home-theoretic study of 3D-mapping, to be called  	Home for a Digital Society.  Another virtual reality project is a crowdsourcing project</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/public-art/public-art-guide-digital-democracy-guide-digital-age-ebook/public-art-guide-digital-democracy-guide-digital-age-ebook), was created to provide an overview of the current state of digital democracy and how artists can be involved in creating new digital versions of old media.  In 2018, a self-started ‘Digital Democracy Research Lab’ was founded at Columbia University, in partnership with Georgetown University, Princeton University, and Columbia University Libraries. The lab’s research agenda includes an intensive six-month series of projects that builds on the research from the past two years, titled: ‘Democracy after Election Machines: Systemics, Legacies, and Cybernetics’. The projects will investigate the role voting machines may play in our present and future political and social situations, and how to empower communities to enact change through technology.  In 2019, the lab hosted the largest collaborative research project</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/public-art/public-art-guide-digital-democracy-guide-digital-democracy), provides an overview of the public sphere and digital activism. It was created in partnership with Columbia University Libraries and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, and was developed with the Georgetown University Digital Arts Lab (2017-18). The project was co-founded and co-led by Radhika Reddy-Webb, Assistant Professor in Art History and Curatorial Studies at Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, and Luis Aguilar-Lawalera, a Ph.D. candidate in the Digital Democracy lab, who is now the Associate Professor of Digital Democracy and the Director of the Digital Democracy Lab.Over the past decade, a new generation of artists, writers, and critics have emerged through the Arts in Publics program at Columbia University. These artists include Meehan Crist, Laura S. Richardson, Manuel Rodriguez, Andrea Jones, Terrence Henry,</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/summary/digital-democracy-a-guide-to-digital-culture), convened by Columbia University and the Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, explores how to build digital democracy in public space. The volume, which takes readers beyond the museum environment and considers issues of privacy, creates a commons on which the sharing of digital information can occur. Its pages are full of examples of how to use digital art in ways that are beneficial to communities, drawing on research carried out at Columbia University and the Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy. But most of all, the volume uses digital culture as a tool to question and reveal opportunities and governance dilemmas through which the user experience has been positioned. A large part of the volume is devoted to exploring how art and the interactive art can be used to challenge authority and uncover issues of complicity and oppression implicit in the socio-political systems that produce and support contemporary culture.</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/public-art/public-art-summary/public-art-data-fire.pdf), provides an overview of the public-art data repository and the key practices shaping the data on art's social media platforms. This update is based on the 2016 survey of artists conducted by the center’s Digital Democracy project and the Civil-Street Artist (2017-18) project at Columbia University, as well as on the author’s project ‘Digital Divas’ that was commissioned by the Museum of Modern Art, New York, and published in the Fortieth-Annual Review of Art &amp; Architecture. In this edition, scholars from the fields of art, architecture and media examine the past, present and future of public art through the lens of digital technology.  For the public, this also includes artists, curators, collectors and others with a stake in the artistic and curatorial value of a city.  The exhibition should be accessible to all, yet it should be</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/article/pr_1709.html), documents the creation of a data archive for public art data, its development, and its future plans. Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide was co-written by Jessica Coon, Evan Greer, and Tarak Ben-Tovim. Jessica Coon is the Frances Hopper Professor in Artistic Practice and Director of the Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University. Her research interests include the social sciences and arts, including the role of artists and the media in advancing democratic practices. She is the author of Digital Divide: Broadening the Lens of Art's Social Impact (2017) and co-editor of the forthcoming Web of Art journal (2018). Her research has also been featured in sites such as Wired, The Washington Post, The New York Times, The New Republic, BBC Future, and many others. She is a co-founder of the Web of Art project, a collaborative online art archive that documents the history of art's</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/public-art/public-art-downloads/public-art-public-guide-2017-downloads/digital-democracy-a-user’s-guide-2017-digital-edition-online-edition-online-edition-public-art-public-guide-2017-digital-edition-online-edition-public-art-public-guide-2017-digital-edition-downloads/digital-democracy-a-user’s-guide-2017-digital-edition-online-edition-downloads/digital-democracy-a-user’s-guide-2017-digital-edition-online-edition-downloads/digital-democracy-a-user’s guide-2017-digital-edition-downloads/digital-democracy-a-user’s guide-2017-digital-edition-downloads/digital-democracy-a-user’s guide-2017-digital-downloads</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/2016/digital-democracy-guide-institute-georgetown-u-2-edition-edition/), provided insights into the curatorial’s role in creating publics via innovative mapping and discovery tools. These data-driven approaches to the emergent social situation necessitate an understanding of how data is generated and consumed, and how this impacts on complex social processes ranging from politics to culture. The findings and perspectives presented in these reports are the result of a major collaborative research project that Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/2016/digital-democracy-guide-institute-georgetown-u-2-edition-edition/), with contributions from artists, activists, data scientists, journalists, academics, political scientists, legal scholars and political scientists.  The project was supported by the Turner Prize,</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/index.html), created and edited by Alexandra (Alyssa) Sachs, explores the challenges of digitally disseminating democratic knowledge about the city. In 2018, a collaborative project between Columbia University and Plastic Arts, a residency program in art, data and innovation at Georgetown University Medical Center, explored the ways in which physical and virtual displacement can be addressed in the design of housing for a future that is both sustainable and inclusive.  In the Museum of Modern Art, New York, in January 2019, the MOMA/M.D. Anderson/Ph.D. program, &quot;Art as Media&quot; investigates the ways in which art is used to create displacement, both physically and virtual, through research-based art projects that utilize existing media and new media (videos, podcasts, installations, books, webs, social media, etc). At the Australian National Exhibition in March 2019, the artist Arjun Appadurai employed virtual reality technology and social media to create a virtual community of artists, cur</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system for its collection’s exhibition spaces and exhibition rooms, to enable an informed and engaged public to contribute to the discussions around public art and the curatorial role, both digitally and in person).  In 2015, the Museum of Contemporary Art, New York, used crowd-sourcing to create an interactive map and gallery system for the city that put data from the New York City Transit Museum and the Museum of Modern Art, New York, on a map and on a wall near the F.D.R. Hospital and Museum of Modern Art, where the crowd-sourcing project was based. The system allowed visitors to explore a digital archive of public art data, while also enabling the public to create and contribute to the data archive through the system.  In 2017, a collaboration between Columbia University and Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy, Georgetown University Center for Digital Democracy (2017-18), Digital Democracy: A User’s Guide (https://digitaldemocracy.org/download/en/17-digital-revolutionary-trends-2016), opened source software development and analysis tools for social and digital transformation research and design. It provides an introduction to the project, key design principles, and case studies that form the basis for future research and design. Download this article as PDFJacob Lund, Design Kaspere, Sven Spieker and Jan Linde (2017-2018), ‘On the use of mass media to influence public opinion in cultural contexts’, in Social Indicators Research (2014), vol. 41, no. 1, pp.81–109.Download this article as PDFJacob Lund, Design Kaspere, Sven Spieker and Jan Linde (2017), ‘On the use of mass media to influence public opinion in cultural contexts’, in Social Indicators Research (2014), vol. 41, no. 1, pp.81–109.Download this article as PDFJacob Lund, Design Kaspere, Sven Sp</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors.  Such a proposal is misguided, and runs counter to the city’s rich cultural history and rich harbour experience.    The Biennial itself is an art institution with a curatorial focus. Its mission statement claims that ‘our main focus is on the work being done in Liverpool by and for the community: culture as a radical social action, and not necessarily a location for art per se… We want to foster a sense of place and identity around us’, a sense of community around something that is, in fact, extraordinarily local and fragmented.’1  In creating the impression of a ‘big picture’ in Liverpool, the Biennial invites questions that are both local and global in nature. These questions are intended to be asked and answered, but they also ‘move the city as a space’2 and inspire action at events such as the forthcoming Liverpool Biennial. These questions arise through the ‘biennial narrative’3 and are part</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors – but with the stated aim of encouraging a pro-active participation by the city in the creation and evolution of its artworld.  The Biennial will be a new form of ‘infrastructure’ capable of supporting and enabling ‘a completely new generation of artists’ and creators’, as stated in the organization’s mission statement.  The question, then, becomes: how to engage the city in the creation of the infrastructure for the new artworld, while simultaneously challenging the city’s dominant position?  The answer to this question is a simple one: take the infrastructure you already have, and experiment with different forms of management and use.  This approach to the organization of art in a post-transportation, post-industrial environment is consistent with the company’s larger economic model, which emphasizes the use of raw materials and infrastructure as raw material in its production of wealth.  The Biennial’s development is driven by a strategy to</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors.1  A second attempt to create a European art institution is made in the form of a ‘Petit Fourteen’, a name given to the section of the wall that would remain unpainted, although the architecture behind it bears a strong resemblance to the section that would become the facade of the EU. The phrase ‘London Wall’ is coined.2  A third proposal to create an entire ‘section of the wall’ is made in the form of a mini-monument, tentatively titled ‘The Monument to the Refusal of Service’3 (repetitively, as the once-a-decade practice of refuseniks is reviewed).4  The section that would become the EU is officially opened for business on 1 January 2022. At the time, a new architectural plan is proposed to separate the artist’s studio from the wall, which would see the construction of a new ‘temporary cultural center’</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors. The ‘Big Issue’ of the Liverpool Biennial's online arts publication, published just weeks before the festival, included a cover story that captured the festival’s visionary’ thinking. It argued that ‘[i]n a city of the future,] we should create one that is both the envy of the world and begs the question, why not the other?’[2]  The Big Issue was a turning point in the publication of the journal, and the journal’s publication coincided with the publication of the journal’s first issue, which came out in May 1922.  The issues of the journal continued to be published concurrently, and the journal’s cover story was reprinted several times.  The idea that a biennial would be formed from the collection of its host city is new. Yet the journal’s cover story – which reappeared in the journal articles that followed it, and which the journal editors would often quote from</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors.  The Biennial, then, is an attempt to create a site of cultural exchange between the two largest cultural centres in the city, but also between the local artist community and the wider art world. It is a response to the fact that, as the Biennial sponsors have repeatedly stressed, the city is becoming increasingly irrelevant in the face of globalisation. Globalisation encompasses everything from the production of biofuels to the transport of raw materials and packaging materials, and it is the interaction between art and commerce that shapes everything from food chains to urban development. Art and commerce are increasingly aware that they are part of a 'trending' media ecosystem, and as a result are deploying creative ways to negate the impact of the media narratives of globalisation. This is evident in the fact that, just last year, Time Warner (the parent company of CNN and Warner Bros. movies), announced plans to open multiplexes of its movies in every corner of the country, in response to the advent of</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors. The inclusion of art and culture within a cityscape is understood as essential to its functioning as a city, and the construction of physical and mental separation between the public and the private spheres of power.  The Biennial will be a ‘different kind of city’, one in which art and art’s social effects will be actively solicited and encouraged, and where cultural tourism will play a prominent role in the city’s future.  Art and the City: On the Transforming Effects of Art into Cities 	Art and cultural tourism have long been at the core of efforts to reanimate cities, and it is here that the relationship between biennials and tourism meets postcolonial and settler historiography. Both the Portuguese and the Dutch colonialists who employed, sponsored, or controlled the art of the Third Empire sought to expand the economies of the art form beyond the reach of its Indigenous populations. The emergence of modern tourism in the late eighteenth century was a direct</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors. Although the conceptualisation of the ‘City Wall’ is somewhat outdated, its economic and social structure and the presence of the ‘Wall Street Boys’ who built it are still deeply embedded in the city. It is important to note that the mission of Liverpool Biennial has continued to expand throughout its history, and that of cultural tourism has become an integral part of the city’s economy.  The challenge for art and cultural tourism today is to find new ways to engage people in the city through interactive activities that build community, provide alternatives to travel and resell cultural products (e.g. souvenirs). A key to these new modes of cultural interaction is a clear understanding of the city’s spatial and temporal difference, and how this is perceived by the dominant economic and political frameworks of the day.  A growing body of research is showing that cities experience a ‘temporal logic’ that adapts to the complexity of new economic and technological systems. New</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors.8 Art and its locations will be able to support cultural activities of a political nature, in defiance of the prevailing economic, social and urban game-changer. Such an initiative calls into question the status of artists as objects of commerce, and the role of the artist as a mediator between capital and culture.  This call is also supported by a new generation of young people who are increasingly exposed to contemporary art and have a political or social bent to them. These young people are drawn to art’s accessibility and non-conformist bent, and their willingness to investigate new art-forms. The potential of this kind of cultural capital is emphasised, and it is emphasised at a high level that young people should be able to pick up art and art’s projects online, in a way that older people and people of lower status cannot. This is seen as a way of creating a new class of artists – artists whose work will be taken seriously by older people and the</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors. But this proposal also addresses a perceived anti-art bias in the city. The Biennial is a multi-award-winning institution, and its mission statement clearly announces its gratitude to the city for its ‘assistance, patronage, and support’ over the years.)  A Biennial’s unique ability to fund its activities through ‘asset lock’ ensures that the institution never really gives up control of the creative projects it produces. The Biennial also has the potential to become a new form of cultural institution: one capable of generating sustainable revenue streams through its cultural tourism program, and capable of challenging established art forms through its scientific and applied research institutions.  Such potentialities are encouraged by the fact that the institution’s funding formula ensures that projects continue to be placed under the priority’ity of art and culture over those of essential public services, such as transport or housing.  However, the priority in the Biennial’s favour seems to</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first in a new wave of venues to open in Europe’s most iconic city, and will mark the first time that a major American art institution has been created in Liverpool. Liverpool Biennial has long been a topic of conversation, and its location on the continent of a future European Union, the interconnection of art and commerce, and the potential for a European art institution to emerge from the shadows – all of which are central to the project’s stated aim – are emphasized.  The exhibition will be framed within the city’s infrastructure, and its cultural organs will be drawn together in an attempt to create a common context for art and commerce. These could be seen as ‘filters’ against the prevailing flow of commerce and art from the city.  Such a proposal echoes the logic of the ‘London Wall’ – a physical and mental barrier created to isolate Liverpool’s artists and spectators from the city’s commercial and entertainment sectors. However, the breadth and depth of this interconnection will be determined by the cultural organs’ size, shape and density, and the mobility of people and goods. The main cultural district in the city will be divided into two further cultural districts: the arts district and ‘The Empty Hearse’. The empty husk of several art institutions will sit in the middle, while the cultural districts that will house the artist’s studios and the exhibition space of the future city will be tightly knit.  The concept is not without its critics, and the market for cultural tourism could be seen as a major barrier to entry for artists and the public. However, the integrity of the cultural district as a unit will be ensured through partnerships with local authorities, grassroots artists' networks and artists’ associations. The art district will be strategically placed underground, within the Art Market, and will be run by a Community Arts organisation, alongside artists’ organisations.  The Biennial is being organised</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist’s final composition. However, the biennial has always remained free to commission works in whatever form it wished. At the time of the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in Liverpool, 10 November 2021, was the last day to leave, and the accounts given by the participants in that meeting are their own, candid and unguarded. The account given by the artist and her team is a moving and affecting one, full of vulnerabilities, betrayals and beautiful lies. It is a portrait of defeat and despair, of course. It is a portrait of despair and magic. It is a portrait of hopelessness and magic. It is a portrait of despair and nature. It is a portrait of nature and art. It is a portrait of art and cities. It is a portrait of art and nature. It is a portrait of art and nature. It is a portrait of art and nature. It is art and nature. It is art and nature. It is art and nature.</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist’s final composition. If the institution is committed to diversity, then why do some artists have to sign exclusivity deals with the art institution? Why are artists having to drop out of exhibitions in order to participate in these projects? Why are there so many curators with minimal or no curatorial training? Why are there so many artists who have never made art exhibitions in their lives but now are? Why are there so many artists who have a PhD but don’t have the curatorial or educational background to develop the kind of critical or artistic literacy necessary to question these obligations? These are questions that continue to amaze me.I was in Liverpool recently and took a different kind of tour. I was invited to curate a three-day, three-station symposium, ‘The Digital Divide and the New Curator’, to be delivered by the curator Prem Krishnamurthy and commissioned by Liverpool Biennial. The idea was to engage with the idea of the �</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist’s final project. In practice, this is usually stated as the institution’s obligation to host the exhibition. If the institution is committed to a particular location, it is usually stated that the site is its permanent home. If the site is not suitable, the institution is obligated to relocate it. If the institution has a future intention of returning to the site, it is much more difficult to deplete the biennial of desirable sites. The availability of a site as a tourist destination or a suitable academic venue is often a precondition for a site appearing in a biennial. It is also often stated that the abundance of places to stay in cities across the world is a decisive influence on the development of biennials. It is true that cities with high densities of people and people per square mile make excellent biennials. These are the ones with ubiquitous resources, high levels of culture tourism, and the most potential for cultural exchange. However, cities with finite resources, such</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist’s final product. Although the contractual obligation to produce remains unshakable, the regulatory role of the art institution in the production of art has come a long way since the mid-1990s. The changes in the regulatory framework that emerged during this transition are still debated, but it is clear that the main aim of curators during this period was to inject a little creativity into the mix, to infuse some personality into the art institution. The main task of the curatorial role during this period was to deliver what the institution wanted, and to that end, the main constraint was the quality of the material. The key issue during the ‘late’ 1990s was access to cultural capital; the access to artefacts and the social value that can be extracted from them. Today, this standardised access to cultural capital is deeply ingrained in the socio-political and economic systems that construct and benefit from them, and it is interesting to note that the first biennials were organised by</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist’s work in a biennial. However, this is not always the case. In practice, the institution rarely exercises this final say, but artists are often encouraged to exert it for themselves. The fact that the duty to produce is often felt to be a unilateral decision by the gallery owner rather than an institution-specific obligation does not necessarily imply an understanding that rights are not to be taken. The law, and indeed the representations of the law itself, can often be relied upon to provide the capacity for individuals to take decisions for themselves. This is particularly true where representation is concerned, as is the case with the legislation of nations. It is often claimed that the law simply doesn’t recognise the idea of ownership in the same way that the idea of nationality does; that is, that it is not always actually the case that the representation is implicit in the text of the law. However, this is often not the case. The representation is often emphasised in the law as a fact</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist’s final project. However, in the context of the biennial craze, this contractual obligation is being breached. As a result, artists are being asked to participate in projects that they do not yet understand the full political and social implications of their positions, for which there is no guarantee of return on such investment. In a word, biennials are being produced in the service of capitalising on the crises of the social; of the surplus value that flows from their consumption; and of the surplus of knowledge that flows from its production.This is the thrust of Bergson’s account, which she provides no supporting evidence for other accounts of the social. However, the social conditions of her position are precisely those that her employers would adopt if the market provided them with the answers. And since the market cannot provide these, we can only assume what we know. It is this falsification of meaning that we glomerify – that is, build up – by feeding the bi</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist’s work in a biennial. However, in the current context of austerity, disrespect for the artist and commitment to commercial interests is becoming a core value proposition for many biennials. At the same time, the institutional engagement of the art form is questioned, and in recent years has even come to characterise the nature of the art institution itself. If the mission of the biennial is to commission and host exhibitions, why are the biennials becoming less and less about that mission? The term ‘biennial’ has been synonymised with ‘once in a lifetime’, and while a biennial may refer to a specific event, in recent parlance it has come to denote a particular set of interests and practices. In this sense, the exhibitionary biennial is no longer the sole representative of the art form, but rather a significant step towards a ‘biennialised’ art form. [1] The Biennalee, </text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist’s final product. The legal status of this final say is contested, although in recent years the art institution has generally been able to dictate what kind of works are produced and displayed. The only real exception to this generalisation is when an art institution funds a particular art project through a ‘contractual relationship’. In these cases, the art institution generally enjoys absolute power over what kinds of works are produced and displayed, and it is this power that has often been abused.In the context of the Liverpool Biennial programme, then, the introduction of a project-based model into the Biennial would not only make the art institution accountable, but would also make the programmematic nature of the Biennial subject to the whim of an unpredictable and often conflicted art director. In an ideal world, the power devolved to artists and art directors would be vested in a ‘Living Art Trust’, a legally protected entity that possesses ultimate authority over what kinds of art can be produced and</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist’s final work. Although this is often asserted, it is currently not always so. In the case of contentious projects, the commissioning administrator is often accused of ceding artistic control to artists’ super-intendents, who then exercise artistic discretion and make decisions that are not always universally popular with community stakeholders. The commissioning administrator is usually quick to rebut this notion, on the grounds that in the current context of austerity and neoliberalism, it is impossible to deliver high-quality cultural experiences on a large scale without third parties intervening. However, this ignores the fact that art institutions are organisations of people, and as such, constantly needing to grow and new people joining the organisation. It is also a fact that in the current biennial market, the artist is the face of the organisation, and not just any artist, but someone with a brand new, game-changing artistic proposition that fundamentally alters the context and/or the audience of the art institution. The commissioning administrator�</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first and perhaps only time when a chief operating officer and the president of the art institution sit down together.’[7] The discussions that emerged from the meeting between Liverpool Biennial and its stakeholders in the run-up to the festival were published in the book ‘The Resident’ (2015) and ‘The Resident’ (2016). The inclusion of a project-based model seems particularly relevant in the context of the current biennial craze. The biennial is a fixed format, traditionally featuring a fixed number of works selected from a curated group of artists, usually led by an administrator. Although the number of works selected may be reduced, the number of participants in a given exhibition remains fixed. The number of artists participating in a given exhibition is the product of a contractual obligation between the art institution and the artist. This obligation is often questioned, and it is often stated that the art institution has the final say in the artist’s right to an artist’s final output. In the case of contentious issues, the audience may vote with their feet, as in the case of Brexit, by not taking part in the exhibition. In such a scenario, the audience is often presented with a series of alternative representations of the same issue, with no real agency or agency beyond the institutional interest. If the institution chooses to honour the contractual obligation to produce, the audience is promised a choice between many different representations. It is this ambiguity and the randomness inherent in the biennial form that makes it difficult to become invested in a single artist’s artistic mission or project. The audience is promised many different experiences, but rarely does the biennial offer us a reason to become invested in a single one. If anything, the biennial form can only deliver so far. The audience may choose to invest in one artist’s artistic mission or project, but they are often told that they should not.In my opinion, this is an important distinction to</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to think of ‘time-critical interactions’ as those between human beings and technological singularities, rather than in the language of connectedness and connectivity. This could mean technologies that constantly monitor and record and act on data, or could mean interactions that continuously reconfigure the social meaning of time itself. This is the paradigm that has been pursued by futurist and philosopher of technology Ray Kurzweil. More than that, it is the paradigm of an ever-expanding cybernetically augmented humanity.In the twentieth century, science and technology were meant to deliver ever greater efficiencies of labour and wealth to society. But some have wondered if the social is actually social warping as a result of the inefficiency of modern science and technology. If the social is necessarily socialised then perhaps the social is no longer social. And there is growing evidence that points to the latter. A recent Nature Neuroscience study of the neurobiology of trustworthiness suggests that the enhancement of cognitive ability is associated with a</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to think of ‘time-critical encounters’ as encounters between humans and technological progress, rather than within the framework of a traditional literary such as Mark Twain’s The Adventures of Huckleberry Finn. In that novel, the hero, a Native American named Tom Latham, is forced to confront an evil wizard named Pippin Liddell on the ground that he has stolen the cursed book from a Scottish witch. In the face of overwhelming evidence to the contrary, Liddell is driven to insanity by his own delusions, to the eventual collapse of the magical order that he represents.As an aside, it is worth noting that the name ‘Time’ in Tolkien’s Lord of the Rings is derived from the Middle English root ‘lathe’ – meaning ‘time’ – and ‘punk’ – meaning ‘loathing of time’. So, in the same way that Tolkien identifies with the wayward,</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to refer to what Vernacular Media Project leader Simon Callas calls the ‘perceptual nemesis monster’ – a name that evokes images of Tudors and Napoleonic history but is also Freddy Kruger and leaves the more humanised form of HAL in a scythe. This is the nightmare or ‘imagined nemesis’ of virtual reality. It is the proto-entity that creates the simulacrum and the parallel universe, but it also has the capacity to create a multitude of simulacrums and fictional beings out of thin air. Equally potentially, this nemesis could end up helping us to realize some of our most cherished dreams.In this scenario, the technological singularity appears and ends up everywhere at the same time, creating a dense web of meaning that is both asinine and beautiful. It is a terrifying notion, but one that is possible. Callas’s vision for the technological singularity is one in which ‘we, the users</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to think of ‘time-critical events’ as events occurring in the real-time (in the sense that there is no absolute understanding of what constitutes ‘real-time’) of which the contemporary is but one example. Thus, a reference to a ‘crunch’ can be read as a predicate, or ‘head-start’ in the sense of what is meant by temporal transparency. Clearly, in the contemporary context, this is precisely what is meant by ‘real-time’.Modern and contemporary forms of criticalityCultural production, ‘cultural production’, is a much more potent form of resistance today than it was in the cultural history of the modern era. It is, for instance, possible to be critical of certain aspects of the impact of mass tourism, but it is much harder to be critical of the whole package, especially since the social functions of culture are primarily understood through the notion of travel associated with it – i</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to refer to the anomalous characteristics of today’s world, especially in the form of cybercrime and human-machine interaction, than to the more established and institutionalised forms of historical and canonical human-computer interaction. Perhaps what is needed is a paradigm shift that liberates human beings from the temporal dependency upon established models of the world and interaction. This is the paradigm shift that humanity requires, but which also needs to happen in order to address the many forms of social and cultural disruption caused by the new data technologies that are emerging.This may be seen as at odds with the historical and institutionalised forms of historical and canonical human-computer interaction, which are the outcome of long historical relationships to historical data and interaction. But this reference point may be useful in understanding the current condition of conflict and conflict resolution in the contemporary world, especially in the context of a post-PC world. And this is precisely what is happening in the world right now, with the cyberbullying of young children in particular</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to think of ‘time-critical encounters’ as encounters that happen now, rather than that they happen in some distant future. Such encounters would be encounters that are part of a new ‘space-time machine’ that is part of a global system that is continuing to evolve. The encounter with the automobile would be part of a larger global system that includes, is evolving to include, data from every conceivable source, including local and remote sensors, optical fibres and electromagnets, radio and cable communications, economic models, environmental monitoring and data-mining, and much more.  References to the automobile in this sense recall John Nash’s classic work, ‘The Elements’, in which he imagined a planetary ‘fall out of the sky’ as the climax of a planetary conflict.  One could also imagine an apocalyptic scenario in which the automobile is the final battle cry of the humankind’s addiction to energy. The fact that the automobile has become such</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to think of ‘time-critical encounters’ as encounters that occur continuously across a given geographical area, encounter-based ontology – that is, encounters that are constantly mediated by data (and perhaps, given the growing complexity of data-gathering and analysis, data-mining will one day be called upon to intervene in and to refract the path of real-time encounters).The encounter-based ontology of ‘time’ would allow for the instantaneous observation of ‘a specific set of relationships between objects in and across space and time’, and would entail an understanding of such relationships across an ever-expanding and variable set of ‘objects’. Potential applications for this new understanding of time could include (but are not limited to) space colonization and the development of ever larger data-collecting platforms, to which users could add ever more sophisticated data-processing tools. (VG)Real-time response to informationHypertext narrative is real-time, and</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to consider what real-time actually means: what it actually entails in practice.What is it that makes ‘real-time’? What distinguishes it from other types of visual media? What distinguishes it from ‘snap’ and ‘lite’ media? What distinguishes it from ‘mockups’ and ‘code bubbles’? What distinguishes it from ‘mockumentaries’ and ‘real-time’ artworks? What distinguishes it from ‘instant videos’ and ‘live feeds’? What distinguishes it from ‘instant’ social media posts? What distinguishes it from ‘instant messaging’ and ‘instant’ video blogging? What distinguishes it from ‘instant messaging groups’ and ‘instant video blogging’?What distinguishes ‘real-time’ from other visual media? What distinguishes ‘real-time’ from other types of</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to think of ‘time-critical interaction’ as the ontological question, not only one that humans will eventually decide to define as fundamentally ‘time-critical’. Perhaps what is most needed is a way to start from scratch on a global basis, one that is not defined by the particular temporal framework of the 21st century. This is what futurist Ray Kurzweil proposes in his book  	The Age of Spiritual Machines 	, and it is what Renate Lorenz Schiller, in her reflections on the work of science fiction writer Herman Melville, proposes in her own work, including the question, what became of the human capacity for imagining in the era of virtual reality. It is what François Hartog proposes in his book  	The New Mindset 	, and it is what others, including philosophers, have long believed – including William James, to whom Schiller’s Humanities seems especially prescient.But what is needed</text>
    <text>prototype for an intelligent curatorial system that collects, sorts, categorises and analyses data on a global scale. This is the ‘big data’ that underpins everything from medical research to urban development. It is, in a way, what creates the illusion of accessibility, yet it is also what creates the conditions of unreality – namely, the conditions of difference – i.e. the conditions of difference – whether that difference is on the ground, in the air, or in the form of data.The question, then, becomes what new paradigm can we build upon the foundation of the emerging science of big data? New data, as we all know, is both more malleable and more mischievous than ever. If there is such a thing as a ‘real-time crunch’ then perhaps it is time to redefine what real-time actually means. References to ‘real-time’ are, of course, bound to a particular temporal framework. But perhaps it is more useful to think of reference to what could be understood as ‘infrastructure crunch’ – i.e. data-gathering and crunching by way of new technological means – than it is to treat it as a fixed, fixed kind of thing. A reference to infrastructures would mean not just to structures and networks but also to the data that is gathered and transmitted from them, and perhaps this is the missing middle ground in the age of the infrastructural.Infrastructures are, of course, only one part of the equation in a complex equation that also includes data, software and networking. But they are a crucial part of the equation, and their inclusion in the equation should be prioritised over their removal (better access to data, better software etc). Consider, for instance, the role played by data-collecting drones in the urban environment. These autonomous vehicles routinely collect data about the infrastructure of the city in an attempt to predict the behaviour of other vehicles, and</text>
  </text>
  <text>
    The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three-day event in September and October of 2012, with an extended programme of activities in the months leading up to the opening of the exhibition. The exhibition was expanded to be staged as a three-day event in June and July of 2013. Both the 2013 and 2016 exhibitions were designed by Louise Shelley and featured original works by artists from the past and future cities, respectively. The Future City concept has been adapted many times, with varying degrees of success, and the three-day event was intended to be repeated several times. The main elements of the event have stuck despite different forms of change, being repeated multiple times in different places and in different times, and are still fundamentally a part of the city.The idea of ‘the city’ as a living, breathing organism has become increasingly important in recent years, as new technologies and fads, coupled with urbanisation programmes across the world that seek to make the city conform to specified urban designs, are brought to bear on the very idea of</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three-year experiment in extending the sense of the word city beyond the suburban context. In the current iteration, the city is returning to the suburban context, but this time it is in a far more negative way. The construction of new golf courses in the city centre are displacing residents and hampering the city’s historic waterfront. The rapid growth of high-rise residential neighbourhoods is also a factor, as is the use of eminent domain and the bureaucratic redirection of resources. The question, then, becomes: What next?At the end of the experiment, the city is returning to the symbiosis of its previous forms: the self-regeneration of urban space through the self-repairing mechanism of the city’s infrastructure, including the regenerative potential of the sites where once homes were abandoned or destroyed. In the new urban space, regeneration and redevelopment become interrelated, and new art and craft projects are being created in concert with the city’s redevelopment.In the</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three-year experiment in theory and design at UCL. It was the largest such exhibition ever attempted in North London, attracting artists from all over the world. The project was then expanded into a full-fledged exhibition in 2018. In doing so, it fulfilled many other biennial objectives – including the ever-present obsession with design and consumption, which had been building for over a decade – and perhaps more significantly, it triggered a sustained series of new initiatives that continue to this day. What the future once thought were temporary curatorial devices, or art shelters, or temporary exhibitionary platforms, are now being rebuilt.  The concept was a powerful tool for imagining alternatives and questioning boundaries.  The alternative to the future urbanisation of North London is not an ideal one, and there are many ways to get there – from walking to the nearest pub or bakery, to exploring the local museums or heritage shops, to hopping on a bus or taking the commuter rail to reach the city centre. But for the foreseeable</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three-month ‘land and future' project, with several short films and videos that emerged from the process as a whole. The collection has since evolved into a multimedia exhibition (video, audio and still images), with installation and public works that position the neighborhood as a narrative throughout. This exhibition marks the end of an era, but the beginning of a new one.  The museums that created or contributed to the bifurcation of the city into present and future are being asked to create collaborative local collections that chart the processes that created the present and the potential futures that can be created in its wake. With this kind of expansive curatorial agenda, the biennial must address the city in some way. And yet, the moral of the story is that the city is a strange place: it’s impossible to pin down precisely, the details elusive and elusive again and again, the social forces at play, and the unpredictable. The goal of the current exhibition is to show the city as it</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three-month ‘window on the city’, with the remaining stages developing over two months. But with the end of the boomer paradigm behind us, new uses of the site are emerging. The collection that was meant to be preserved as a mini museum is being assembled into what seems an awful lot of new ways to be used. Future City was conceived as a way to explore these practices through the curatorial hand. It was also a way to look back at the past; to see how our present urban settings can be improved through radical reclamation.This is the curatorial approach to the collection. It’s charged with reconfiguring the city in the image of individual needs, desires and dreams. It’s the curatorial equivalent of a museum piece: big on the inside, low on the outside. It’s a collection of images, videos, texts, maps, objects and other visual materials gathered from various sources over the years. It’s a</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three-month ‘triennial’, with interlinking narratives that unfolded over three days in late June–July 2000 in and around the old Bond Street post office. The exhibition was originally titled  Future City: The ‘Towards A Future City’. Since then, it has been alternately rebranded as ‘2028’ or ‘2029’, depending on the political weather.  The name change has been necessary as a matter of business, but it is now considered a mistake. The three-month ‘triennial’ is an ephemeral event, so its place in the city is uncertain; the ‘2028’ and ‘2029’ forms of the theme park are the most recognizable.  The question, then, becomes what next, and what does the triennial offer in return for its place in the city? There are few cities as dependent on tourism as Liverpool.  The only other major</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three-month ‘big-picture’ survey of the city, with projects that suggested a ‘three-tiered’ configuration of the city as a ‘capitalist accumulation’, ‘imagined utopia’ and ‘housing crisis’. The strategy of the three-month exhibition was to paint a broad picture of the city, drawing on experiences from previous exhibitions, in an attempt to ground the project in a set of common themes. For the next phase, a research project entitled ‘Future City: Research in Progress’ was initiated, which sought to develop a set of questions that can be asked about the exhibition in an attempt to ground the next exhibition in the same space. The questions were: What can the local community learn from the past three months of the exhibition? What questions is the local community still struggling to figure out? What are the questions that the international community still struggles to ask?  The European Community funded research project was accompanied by an</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three-year experiment, with the final instalment exploring the concept from a research perspective. The exhibition would be the culmination of a three-year research programme, with the final two years utilising the exhibition as a laboratory for developing the concept. The exhibition would be an extension of the research, drawing on the curatorial thinking behind the project, while its content would be informed by the curatorial thinking of the future city. In the new form, the term ‘future city’ refers to the post-carbon city, but more specifically to the future urbanisation that is the direct result of the rapid growth of population, fuelled by a combination of anthropogenic and environmental factors. The exhibition would be a ‘window on the city’s surface, providing a window to a ‘city that may yet still exist’, but more specifically, to a future city that is connected to the past and beyond current borders. It would reveal the discarded buildings and derelict urban sites of</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three-year research project, with the end of the project being triggered by a local government election in October 2018.2  The Fairmount Arts Centre, established in 1991, is a regional arts centre with a particular interest in the arts and culture of the Forth Valley. The Arts Council of Canada and National Arts Centre of Canada both endorsed the concept and funded the project. The  Futures concept was developed by Sandy Cheroyan and her collaborators, Future City team, for the Canadian National Arts Centre (Capitol Theatre), in Ottawa. The concept evolved through an exploratory curatorial process that questioned the relationship between art and the physical, social and spatial conditions of urban existence, and between art and the built environment. The exhibition was presented as a part of the Centre’s 'Turquoise' initiative, which celebrates Canada’s cultural heritage in eight major areas: architecture, design, design, architecture, tourism and public realm</text>
    <text>The 2021 Liverpool Biennial will be the first to be built on the site of the former Balliol School of Music, which closed in 2010. The Biennial will be housed in a half-scale replica of the old school building, with a public gallery, classrooms and a temporary exhibition space. The exhibition space will house installations by local artists, a coffee kitchen and a storage area for art and home products. The exhibition space, which was designed by Gaudi &amp; Co, a company that manufactures industrial and promotional roofing systems, will host a range of installation ideas, including sculpture, sound installations, public art and festivals. The Biennial will focus on the major themes of the local community: architecture, community infrastructure, and youth engagement. It will invite participation on an organic level and exploit potential trade-offs between the different stakeholders involved in the city.By David Henderson and Tom LoxbayAfter nearly two decades of work, the Future City concept is coming to an end. The exhibition was originally conceived as a three-day event, with a curatorial track record of presenting ideas in stages, with challenges and opportunities at different scales, starting from the smallest to the largest. As the name suggests, the evolving concept was started with a three-day event. The three-day event was conceived as a three-day snapshot of the city in development, and the three-day event as a three-day snapshot of the city as a continuous city. The idea of the ‘three-day event’ grew from the curatorial track record of the Future City concept, which was presented in stages over two days in 2009 and 2010. The idea of the three-day event was to capture the complexity and heterogeneity of the city in a three-day snapshot, while allowing participants to step back and allow for an authentic and vulnerable experience at a time of convergence and rupture.  The curatorial track record on the event was limited to the ideas and proposals that emerged during the curatorial sessions, and the</text>
  </text>
</AIcurator>
